<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY robintp SYSTEM "robin02.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY ill1 SYSTEM "robin03.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY ill2 SYSTEM "robin04.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY ill3 SYSTEM "robin05.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY ill4 SYSTEM "robin06.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY ill5 SYSTEM "robin07.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY ill6 SYSTEM "robin08.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY ill7 SYSTEM "robin09.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY ill8 SYSTEM "robin10.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY ill9 SYSTEM "robin11.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY robinfp SYSTEM "robin01.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY ill13 SYSTEM "robin15.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY ill10 SYSTEM "robin12.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY ill11 SYSTEM "robin13.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY ill12 SYSTEM "robin14.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY ill14 SYSTEM "robin16.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>From Log Cabin to the Pulpit, or, Fifteen Years in Slavery:
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>William H. Robinson (b. 1848)</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="tch">Teresa Church</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by</resp>
          <name id="ns">Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1997.</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca. 300K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1997.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note anchored="yes">Call number E444 .R635 1913</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>From Log Cabin to the Pulpit, or, Fifteen Years in Slavery</title>
          <author>William H. Robinson</author>
          <imprint>
            <pubPlace>Eau Claire, Wis.</pubPlace>
            <publisher>James H. Tifft</publisher>
            <date>1913</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South, or,  The Southern Experience in 
19th-century America.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
        <p>All the illustrations from the original may be accessed at http://sunsite.unc.edu/docsouth/autobiog.html or at http://sunsite.unc.edu/docsouth/narratives.html.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell checkers.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings,</title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Robinson, William H., b. 1848.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- North Carolina.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- North Carolina -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves' writings, American -- North Carolina.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>1997-02-25, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project editor, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1996-11-15, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Teresa Church </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="frontispiece image">
        <p>
          <figure id="frontis" entity="robinfp">
            <p>OLD GLORY!</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="title page image">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="robintp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">From Log Cabin To the Pulpit, </titlePart>
          <titlePart type="main">or, Fifteen Years in Slavery</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <docEdition>THIRD	EDITION</docEdition>
        <byline>PUBLISHED BY THE AUTHOR, </byline>
        <docAuthor>REV. W. H. ROBINSON,</docAuthor>
        <titlePart type="main">Reminiscences of my early life
while in slavery.</titlePart>
        <titlePart type="main">DEDICATED TO MY
DAUGHTER, MARGUERITE.</titlePart>
        <docImprint><publisher>JAMES H. TIFFT,</publisher>
<publisher>PUBLISHING PRINTER</publisher>
<pubPlace>EAU CLAIRE, WIS.</pubPlace> 
<date>1913. </date></docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="dedication">
        <head>OLD GLORY!</head>
        <p>The old tattered flag, that passed through the siege of the 
“Civil War” which freed the colored race from slavery and 
saved the Union from disruption. The old flag was fought 
under by the colored as well as the white boys, and was preserved 
as the Nation's emblem of freedom. “Long may it 
wave o'er the land of the free and the home of the brave.” </p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson6" n="6"/>
      <div1 type="preface">
        <div2 type="presentation">
          <head>Presentation.</head>
          <p>I present this work to the public on it's merits; 
there is no fiction about it, every incident is taken 
from reality. The author has either pasted through 
or been an eye witness to every trying ordeal and incident, 
with a very few exceptions, and he has authentic 
history to sustain him in these. Every line is dictated 
by the author, W. H Robinson, and written by 
his secretary, Miss Florence Mitchell, of Louisville, 
Kentucky.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>Endorsements.</head>
          <p>Having read the within pages I can conscientiously 
recommend the book as being of intense interest 
from first to last; full of interesting narrative, valuable 
historical information, good suggestions and wholesome 
inspiration. It is more than worth the price 
asked for it.</p>
          <closer><signed>J. M. GASS,</signed>
Editor “News,” Albia, Iowa.</closer>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <opener><dateline>April 14, 1913.</dateline>
<salute>To Whom It May Concern:</salute></opener>
          <p>It gives me pleasure to be permitted to state that 
the Rev. W. H. Robinson is personally known to me 
as a man whom God is most wonderfully using in the 
extension of His Kingdom. He is most favorably 
known in the state and enjoys the highest esteem of 
the churches. His evangelistic labors have been signally 
successful, churches being quickened, church
members reclaimed and large numbers truly converted. 
His book I consider, of great value, presenting as 
it does, a vivid and truthful story of the remarkable 
manner in which God by his grace, can use one who 
is consecrated to the service of the Master</p>
          <closer><salute>Yours very truly,</salute>
<signed>GEO. R. STAIR,</signed>
Pastor First Baptist Church, Eau Claire, Wisconsin. </closer>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson7" n="7"/>
      <div1 type="image">
        <p>
          <figure id="ill1" entity="ill1">
            <p>REV. W. H. ROBINSON, AUTHOR.</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson8" n="8"/>
      <div1 type="image">
        <p>
          <figure id="ill2" entity="ill2">
            <p>THE LATE MRS. W H. ROBINSON</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson9" n="9"/>
      <div1>
        <head>Author's Preface.</head>
        <p>My friends, it is not the purpose of the writer to 
place before the public something to bias the minds of  
the people or instill a spirit of hatred. My book reveals 
in every chapter either the pathetic moan of 
slaves in almost utter despair, yet panting, groaning, 
bitterly wailing and still hoping for freedom, or of 
slaves with their hearts, lifted to God, praying for deliverance
from the cruel bonds, the auction block, and 
years of unrequited grinding toil for those who had no 
right to their labor.</p>
        <p>Realizing, as I do, the injunction of the Lord Jesus, 
when he said, in Matthew VII, 12: “Therefore, all 
things whatsoever ye would that men should do to 
you, do ye so to them, for this is the law and the
prophets” my deliberations have been many and constant 
that God would take out of my heart all the 
spirit of retaliation or revenge. This is why my book 
has not been before the public years ago. I wanted 
to be assured of the fact that I could give to the world 
at least some thoughts that would not only be a remembrance, 
but would prove beneficial to all in whose 
hands this book may chance to fall. I would not have 
this all important fact pass from the mind and memory 
of men, that they should not give their consent, nor 
cast their ballot for the enslavement of any human being. </p>
        <p>To some of the noble men of this country, yea to 
many whose blood has stained the earth at Fairfax 
<pb id="robinson10" n="10"/>
Courthouse, Virginia, Roanoke Island, North Carolina, 
Fort Donelson, Pea Ridge Arkansas, Shiloh or Pittsburg 
Landing, Tennessee, Williamsburg, Virginia, and 
many other places too numerous to mention, it is but 
as yesterday since the noble men, who are sleeping in 
unknown graves, left their homes and loved ones to 
lay their lives on the sacrificial altar of their country, 
to perpetuate this government and help to shake the 
shackles of bondage from a race hewn from a slab of 
ebony. It is but yesterday, in our memories, since 
mothers gave their only sons, wives their husbands, 
sisters their brothers, sweethearts their intended, to 
take part in shaking the manacles from this unfortunate 
race. It is but yesterday since the sad message 
came that many of those loved ones had fallen in the 
forefront of the battle, saturated in their own blood, 
fighting for human liberty.</p>
        <p>Gratitude will not pay for the loss of those dear 
ones, nor for those who returned limbless, and with 
shattered health, but it is the greatest gift in human 
reach. May God ever bless. and he will bless, the 
Caucasian race for the Moses, in the person of an 
Abraham Lincoln, who led us across the Red Sea of 
slavery into the promised land of liberty, where today 
we can worship God under our own vine and fig tree, 
and no one dare molest us or make us afraid. </p>
        <p>Having given you this short preface I will at once 
proceed to give you a history of my life as a slave, 
and of slavery from a historical standpoint; also eleven
months of my life in England, where I received 
my first alphabetical training. </p>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <pb id="robinson11" n="11"/>
    <body>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
        <p>I was born in Wilmington, a town in North Carolina, 
March 11, 1848. Wilmington is situated near the 
mouth of the Cape Fear river, on the Atlantic coast. 
It has a good harbor on the tidal waters of Cape Fear 
river. The chief exports are cotton and tobacco from 
the uplands, and lumber, rosin and turpentine from the 
yellow pine forests of the coastal plains. The swampy 
coastal lowlands produce great quantities of rice. </p>
        <p>In reading Stanley and Livingston on Africa we notice 
that the negro race is divided into different tribes. 
Among them is the Madagascar tribe, who are noted 
for their mechanical skill. To this tribe my parents 
both belonged.</p>
        <p>My parents, Peter and Rosy, belonged to a very 
wealthy ship and slave holder, who owned two farms 
and over five hundred slaves.</p>
        <p>My father was an engineer and towed vessels in and 
out of Wilmington harbor into the Atlantic ocean. He
pursued this occupation for over fifteen years and received 
many tips by being courteous and always on the 
alert for ships heaving in sight. While the master received 
pay for the towage, my father by constant contact 
with white men, received money in many other 
ways. “As association breeds assimilation” so my 
father learned the art of making and saving money until 
he had accumulated about eleven hundred dollars. </p>
        <pb id="robinson12" n="12"/>
        <p>My mother was a cook at the great house, but hired 
her time from her mistress, for which she paid three 
dollars per month. </p>
        <p>It becomes necessary to explain how slaves would 
get money to pay for their time There were shipped 
from Wilmington a great many ground-peas or peanuts, 
as we now call them. They were brought from the 
country in bulk and so had to he sacked and sewed up. 
The slaves were hired for this work, for which they received 
one cent and a half per sack. This is one of 
the great mediums through which they made money. 
Another was, a great many hogsheads of molasses 
were brought from New Orleans and unloaded on the 
docks, and the hot sun would cause them to ferment 
and run out through the chimes. The negro women 
would catch this molasses by running their hands over 
the hogshead and wiping the molasses from their hands  
into a pail. I am often made to wonder now when I 
see people gagging at the idea of eating bread made up 
by black hands, when in those days the poor whites 
were truly glad to buy the molasses caught in the 
hands of our mothers, and like Elijah, who was fed by 
the ravens, they ate it and asked no questions. </p>
        <p>Father enjoyed the friendship of two very distinguished 
Quakers, Mr. Fuller and Mr. Elliott, who 
owned oyster sloops, and stood at the head of what is 
known in our country as the underground railroad, or 
an organization filled with love of freedom for suffering 
humanity, that had for its end the liberation of slaves 
and that only. Hundreds of men belonging to this organization 
sacrificed their lives in carrying out this noble purpose. </p>
        <pb id="robinson13" n="13"/>
        <p>Father was with Messrs Fuller and Elliott every day
towing them in and out from the oyster bay. This 
gave them an opportunity to lay and devise plans for 
getting many into Canada (the only safe refuge for the 
negro this side the Atlantic.) and my father was an 
important factor in this line.</p>
        <p>The system of deliverance by the underground railroad 
was to divide the country off into sections, and at 
every fifteen or twenty miles would be a station or 
depot. One man would haul the slaves at night to the 
end of his station and get back home before daylight, 
undiscovered, then they would be conveyed the next 
night in wagons from that station to the next, and so 
on until they reached Canada. </p>
        <p>Often the wagons had double linings, with corn or 
wheat visible, while the cavity was filled with women 
and children.</p>
        <p>Father having a foretaste of liberty to some extent, 
and growing weary of the life of a slave, with the assistance 
of his Quaker friends plans were laid for him 
to purchase his own freedom and go to Canada. Then 
his family would be sent to him by the underground 
railroad. If any one connected with the underground 
railroad was caught the penalty was a heavy fine and 
expulsion from the state.</p>
        <p>Allow me to state here that in 1875, while on the 
train going to Wilmington, North Carolina, in search 
of a sister and brother, I met a white man having the 
appearance of a lawyer. He talked very freely with 
me and I soon learned that he was from Boston, Massachusetts, 
and that he was a merchant instead of a 
<pb id="robinson14" n="14"/>
lawyer. His continued conversation with me attracted 
the attention of nearly all the passengers in the car, and 
they were not careful or considerate in their criticism, 
for they were heard to say several times, “he is a 
Northern negro lover,” or, “one of Lincoln's hirelings,”  
and such like expressions  We were truly glad 
when we reached Wilmington and could get away from 
the scrutinizing eyes and listening ears of the passengers 
in the car. He asked me if Wilmington was my 
home. I told him it was, but that I did not love a 
grain of sand of that soil. He assured me that this 
was the case with him, for said he, “my father lost his 
life here trying to help a colored man to liberty.” I 
asked him who his father was. He said, “Sam Fuller.” 
When he learned that I had known his father from my 
childhood days it seemed to draw him closer to me, 
and we were both dumbfounded for a moment when it 
was made known that his father had lost his life because 
he had tried to help my father secure his freedom. 
We both broke down and wept for a few moments, 
but I recognized the danger we were in, even in 
1875, in a southern state. So we parted with the understanding 
that we keep in touch with each other until 
we got to Indianapolis, Indiana. As there was danger 
of both being murdered we passed each other almost 
as strangers on the streets of Wilmington for over 
a week, and finally we both left on the same train. 
We spent a week together in the city of Indianapolis, 
Indiana. From the way he spent money on me it 
seemed that he thought he owed me some gratitude instead 
of my owing it to him. </p>
        <pb id="robinson15" n="15"/>
        <p>He now told me the story of the death of his father 
and how it came about. My master became suspicious, 
or mistrusted from surrounding circumstances, 
that Mr. Fuller was the deviser of father's attempt to 
buy his freedom. A few nights after father was sold 
from Wilmington a posse of men notified Mr. Fuller to 
leave the state at once, and they left a crossbone and 
skull on a stick in front of his door. He left his wife 
and four children, Samuel, Jr., the man I met on the 
train being the oldest, with the understanding that he 
would send for them in a few days. He has never 
been heard from since. The supposition is that he was 
murdered. The family remained there until the rebellion, 
when they left for Indiana, afterward going 
from there to Massachusetts. </p>
        <p>The young man's business in Wilmington was to 
look after the little homestead, which was about forty 
acres of land. I was not successful in finding my sister 
and brother, but felt amply paid by meeting an 
old friend to the negro race and one who helped my 
father in many different ways.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson16" n="16"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
        <p>The plans to free father were put into execution in 
1858  My father went to his master to ascertain what 
he would take for him. The first question master 
asked him was, what white man had put him up to 
this? His suspicion at once fell on these two Quakers. 
Father finally succeeded in convincing him that no 
white man was implicated. Then his next question 
was, “how much money have you?” Father told him 
$450, so he agreed to take $1,150 for him. This was 
an exorbitant price and he didn't think father would 
ever be able to pay it. He could have paid him the 
amount down, but in counsel the Quakers had thought 
it would not be the best thing to do for fear it would 
confuse the whole plan and jeopardize their lives.</p>
        <p>He was to pay for himself on the installment plan, 
paying $450 down, with the understanding that he 
continue six months on the tug to teach another man 
to run it, then he could work wherever he pleased. 
Every year he was to pay as much as he could, which 
he did, together with the interest.</p>
        <p>At this time the subject of slavery was being greatly 
agitated in the north, and slaves were depreciating 
in value. In 1859 my father went to California with 
a surveying company, staying one year. He returned 
during the holidays, paying $350 more on himself, 
<pb id="robinson17" n="17"/>
making a total of $800 paid on his debt. He went 
back to California after the holidays and was gone 
about three months, when the news came to us that he 
was returning in chains. We knew exactly what that 
meant; to rob him of what he had paid and sell him 
away from us, and we were not mistaken, for this was 
the exact purpose.</p>
        <p>You may wonder how we received the news, knowing 
we had no access to the telegraph or postoffice. 
Now, to explain this. To get news from one farm to 
another one slave would tell the other, and so on, until 
by this means and that of the underground railroad, 
it would reach it's destination. So father sent us the 
news in this way, clear from California to North Carolina.</p>
        <p>For two months we went every day when the boat 
came, to see if father was on it. At last the sad hour 
came when the boat arrived, bringing father bound in 
chains. We saw him pulling his whiskers (a mark of 
deep sorrow with him.) When they took him off the 
boat we found he had worn handcuffs fourteen days
and his ankles, from the manacles, were as raw as a 
piece of beef.</p>
        <p>That night they took him to the jail, or negro pen, 
and there we left them trying to unlock the handcuffs, 
for the flesh had swollen so it made it almost impossible 
to unlock them. The negro trader ordered 
mother and five of us children to go home, assuring us 
that we would see father in the morning.</p>
        <p>That night I saw mother in every attitude of prayer 
a human being could assume. Sometimes she would 
<pb id="robinson18" n="18"/>
be prostrate upon her face on the floor; sometimes on 
her knees and again in a sitting posture, imploring 
God to use his power in some way to keep father from 
being sold from us.</p>
        <p>Then about twelve o'clock that night mother said we 
would go to the great house, and so we went, notwithstanding 
the rigidness of the law; for there was a 
standing law, that any negro caught out after nine 
o'clock at night should be struck thirty-nine lashes. 
But now, as the war was dawning, they were more 
rigid than ever, and raised it to forty-nine lashes.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson19" n="19"/>
      <div1 type="image">
        <p>
          <figure id="ill3" entity="ill3">
            <p>MISS MARGUERITE ROBINSON.</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson20" n="20"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
        <p>There were four classes of men who made their living 
on the blood of the negro  The first class is the 
master proper. He feels himself too honorable to 
drive the slave from two or three o'clock in the morning 
until nine or ten at night, therefore he sees the 
necessity of the second class, so he hires a poor white 
man as overseer, to do this dirty work.</p>
        <p>The overseer had the authority, if the slave  -  man, 
woman or child  -  failed to do his task, to tie him up 
and whip him, but not to exceed one hundred and 
fifty lashes. If the crime demanded more than that 
he must get special authority from the master. The 
punishment, as will he shown further on, was very 
high for trivial offenses. </p>
        <p>Sometimes the task was too heavy for the negro 
and he could not complete it, and would rise up in his 
manhood and would not be whipped. Then his only
alternative was to run away, and this usually was the 
first thought in his mind. The third man raised 
blood hounds and trained them to hunt nothing but 
negroes. He made his living by catching runaway 
negroes, receiving the paltry sum of three dollars per 
head. The fourth man is the negro trader, who made 
a perpetual business of buying and selling negroes, as 
men do cattle in this country. He would buy up 
eight, ten or twenty, as the case might be, and locate 
<pb id="robinson21" n="21"/>
them at some central point until he had from three to 
five hundred. Then he would have a long chain and 
handcuff them on either side of the chain and march 
them to Richmond, Virginia, which was the central 
slave market of the south, owned and conducted by 
the Lees and known as Lee's negro trader's pen, and 
when there they would auction them off to the highest 
bidder. </p>
        <p>The prosperity of the poor whites, with but few 
exceptions, depended upon the amount of brutality 
that be showed towards the negro. His word was not 
valued as highly as that of the negro if it was not in 
favor with that of his employer. He lived in no better 
homes, and many of them not as good as the negro 
quarters. I need not say that they had but little or 
no aspirations, save that of raising blood hounds to 
catch the slaves with when they ran away. They 
were usually very illiterate, many of them had no 
education at all; they had no association only among 
themselves and the negroes. Their wives were glad 
to do the drudgery for that class of whites who would 
not own slaves. There were no free school systems, 
and they had not aspirations enough to pay for schooling
their children. When they went before their 
employer they put their hats under their arms, as any 
negro would do, and usually were as afraid of him as 
the negro was of the overseer. They dressed as 
hideously as they possibly could in order to strike 
terror to the hearts of the negroes; they wore broad 
brimmed slouch hats, their pants down in their boots 
and a long blacksnake whip across their shoulders; 
<pb id="robinson22" n="22"/>
they trained their voices to be as harsh as possible. 
Their very appearance would cause one to shiver. 
Their living was not as good as that of the average 
negro, for the slaves were industrious and would work 
by the light of the moon to earn a few pennies, while 
the overseer was lazy and seemed to be satisfied with 
most any kind of fare. </p>
        <p>Every week he drew a certain amount of fat meat, 
corn meal, and a little flour from his master's smoke 
houses just the same as the slaves did. He often hired 
the slaves to steal hogs or chickens for him and if 
caught the slaves would have to take it all upon themselves 
in order to keep the good will of the overseer. 
They used the same dialect as the negro in every 
respect. While the negro looked for a day of deliverance 
the overseer looked for nothing. He was at 
the height of his ambition while driving the negro.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson23" n="23"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
        <p>Let us go back to the “great house” where we left 
my mother. She awoke Master Tom and thought she 
would reach him through his religious views, so she 
said: “Master Tom, have you forgotten your 
religion? Have you the heart to sell my husband 
from me and my children after he has served you all 
these days and made you a fortune?” He said, “No, 
Rosy, I've nothing to do with that. Your husband is 
in the hands of the state of California, but I'll see that 
he is not taken out of this state.”</p>
        <p>Of course he knew that mother was ignorant as to 
the laws of the state, that he would have had to have 
been tried in the state where the offense was committed 
had there been any offense, but this was only a pretext 
he used to rob her of her husband, and her 
children of their father; the father of his money and 
liberty. </p>
        <p>Mother asked why he was brought back as a slave 
when he was buying himself and had already paid 
eight hundred dollars. He told her that father had 
become intimate with a white lady. (She could not 
have been a lady and be intimate with a negro, and 
that negro a slave.) After assuring mother that father 
would not again be taken out of the state, Master 
Tom wrote us a pass and we went back home.</p>
        <p>About three a. m. mother concluded we had better 
<pb id="robinson24" n="24"/>
go to the jail, so we went, and saw father standing at 
the window. I called him once, but he waved his 
hand to us, as if to tell us some one was down stairs, 
and motioned for us to go back home. </p>
        <p>Mother cooked a good breakfast for him, and between 
eight and nine o'clock we went back to the negro 
trader's pen, but before we got there we heard singing 
of two <sic>clases</sic>. Some religious songs, such as “God 
has delivered Daniel,” and other melodies, while 
others were singing the songs of the world, all seemingly 
rejoicing in their own way. Some were rejoicing 
because they were sold, hoping to fall into the 
hands of better masters, while others were rejoicing 
because of the hope of meeting their mother, father or 
child.</p>
        <p>We knew exactly what that meant; we knew that 
the number was complete and about to start for Richmond, 
and we were not mistaken, for there were three 
hundred men, women and children ready to start within 
thirty minutes from the time we got there. We 
hastily scanned the line over for father, but he was 
not in that gang. But there was a vehicle built 
something like our omnibuses, which convey passengers 
from the depot, only it was built of heavy oak boards, 
with staples driven in them. They would handcuff 
men that were valuable and men that would not be 
whipped. I climbed upon the wheel of this vehicle 
and saw father sitting with his face buried in his 
hands. As I spoke he came to the iron grating or 
window, and asked where mother was. I told him she 
was there, then he said to me, “William, never pull 
<pb id="robinson25" n="25"/>
off your shirt to be whipped. I want you to die in 
defense of your mother; for once I lay in the woods 
eleven months for trying to prevent your mother from 
being whipped.” He shook my hands and kissed me 
good bye through the iron bars. Then three sisters 
and two brothers climbed upon the wheel and bade 
him good bye. Now the most trying scene of all is at 
hand. Mother climbed upon the wheel and father said, 
“Rosy, I'm bound for Richmond, Virginia, and from 
there to some Southern market, I don't know where. 
We may never meet again this side of the shores of 
time, hut Rosy, keep the faith in God, and meet me in 
heaven. I want this one assurance from you before we 
part: I want to know if you believe the charge brought 
against me, for which they are robbing me of my 
liberty?” My mother assured him she did not believe 
it.</p>
        <p>The trader came up, ordered mother down from the 
wheel, and the vehicle to start. Father kissed her 
good bye, with a mutual agreement that they would 
never marry any one else, even though they never met 
again. Forty years passed into eternity from that sad 
hour until mother's death, in 1898, and father and 
mother never met again until they met on the other 
shore.</p>
        <p>This was the beginning, of sorrow in our home. It 
was not over three weeks from the time that father 
was sold away until mother and three children were 
taken to the great house, and the other children scattered 
around on the different farms. I was taken into 
the house to wait on table.</p>
        <pb id="robinson26" n="26"/>
        <p>About a month after I entered upon my new occupation 
my master told me one day, while sitting on 
the porch, to light his pipe. He smoked a pipe with a 
long reed stem and would rest the bowl of it on a 
shelf. After I lit the pipe he ordered me to bring 
him a glass of water. I went for it, but on returning 
I found he had turned a sallow complexion. I spoke 
to him but he did not answer. I called old mistress, 
(this is the way we distinguished her from the children, 
as we called all, from the least to the biggest, mistress 
and master.) She came and spoke to him, but there 
was no reply. He had died sitting there in his chair.</p>
        <p>It was the custom among the slave holders to have 
the older slaves come and view the remains of their 
masters or mistresses while they lay in state, and if 
the master was an man of any humanity, or what we 
termed a good master, they would actually shed tears 
over his body. So as usual, they called the slaves in, 
but old mistress did not know that Master Tom had 
incurred the ill-will of every slave on the place by 
selling father.</p>
        <p>Father was almost a prophet among my people, because 
he secured all the news through his Quaker 
friends, and other white men that were friendly to 
him, with whom he came in contact. Then he would 
tell it to our people. Of course the slaves held him in 
high esteem, and when Master Tom sold him they 
never again had any good feeling for him. They came 
as usual, but just outside the door they wet their fingers 
with saliva and made “crocodile tears” and passed 
on pretending to be crying, and saying, “Poor Massa 
<pb id="robinson27" n="27"/>
Tom is gone.” Of course they didn't say where he 
had gone.</p>
        <p>This may appear very deceptive, but had we not 
made some demonstration of grief our very lives 
would have been in danger. </p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson28" n="28"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
        <p>About three weeks later they began to look up the 
will, for boys then were like a good many are today, 
just waiting for the old man to die, so they could run 
through with what he had accumulated. We have 
many young men of that class today. They are not 
worthy to bear their father's name. It was found in the 
will that mother and three of the children had fallen 
to Scott Cowens  -  the meanest of all the Cowens 
family. He was a drunkard and a gambler, for he 
had taken three different women's sons, between 
the ages of twelve and fourteen years, and gambled 
them off and came back home without them, leaving 
the parents in anguish, We went to his home, 
mother as cook, the rest as servants in general. </p>
        <p>We had been there but a few months when he called 
my mother one day and asked her why she said “that 
God had sent swift judgment upon his father.” Of
course mother denied it, but in her grief she had 
 thoughtlessly said it, and somehow it had reached his
ears. He threatened mother very strongly, but didn't 
strike her. </p>
        <p>He left home one evening, telling me to be ready to 
accompany him when he returned. He did not come 
back until the next morning. I saw at once that he 
had been drinking heavily. He sat down to the 
breakfast table and ordered me to bring him a glass of 
<pb id="robinson29" n="29"/>
cool water right from the spring. I put the glass of 
water in front of him. He immediately picked it up 
and threw the water in my face, saying “I will show 
you how to bring me dirty water to drink.” </p>
        <p>One morning a few days later, he found fault with 
the biscuits and asked me what was the matter with 
them. I told him I didn't know. He then jumped 
up from the table and called mother. We, from the 
least to the largest, were taught when called by 
our mistress, or master to answer and go toward that 
voice. So mother was coming to him and he met her 
on the porch, between the kitchen and the dining room. 
He asked mother why she was crying  -  I had told her 
about his throwing the water in my face  -  and before 
she could answer him he knocked her from the porch 
to the ground. This was more than I could endure. 
An ax handle was on the opposite side from which 
mother fell. He stood over her, cursing and kicking 
her, and I knocked him down with the ax handle.</p>
        <p>I knew my only hope of escape was to run away, so  
I started at once. I had often heard ex-runaway 
slaves, men and women, tell the adventures of when 
they were in the woods and about their hiding places 
or rendezvous. I had heard it told so often at my 
father's fireside that I knew almost directly where they 
were, for I had passed close by them many times, so I 
started to look for them. I went to the three mile 
farm, arriving there about the time they were going to 
dinner. I went to an old mother  -  we were taught to 
call each old woman mother, and they called us son or 
daughter. It seemed there was a natural bond of 
<pb id="robinson30" n="30"/>
sympathy existing in the heart of every woman for 
the children of others. I told her what I had done. 
She gave me a chunk of fat meat and half of a corn 
dodger and directed me the way to a hiding place. 
Then with her hand upon my head she prayed one of 
those fervent prayers for God to hasten the day when 
the cruel chains of slavery would fall, and women's 
children would not be forced to leave home and take 
refuge among the beasts of the forest for trying to 
protect their mothers. </p>
        <p>Quite late that night I got opposite the hiding place. 
It was a low swampy place back of a thick cane brake. 
It was so dark and the cane so thick when I got to the 
place where I had been directed to turn in I was afraid 
to venture. But as I stood there I imagined I could 
hear the baying of blood hounds, and so strong was 
the imagination that it drove me in. I had several 
things to fear, for that country was infested with bears. 
More than once I had seen a bear come out of a corn 
field with his arms full of corn, go up to the fence and 
throw it over, get over, pick it up like a man, and 
walk off. Then we had reptiles, such as water moccasins 
and rattle snakes. Sometimes I could walk upright, 
sometimes I was compelled to crawl through the 
cane. About three o'clock the next morning I came 
out of the cane brake on the banks of a large pond of 
almost stagnant water. I could see the rocky mound 
or cave that I had heard so much talk of. </p>
        <p>There was no boat around and I was afraid to go 
into the water, but the same impulse that drove me 
into the cane brake caused me to go into the water. 
<pb id="robinson31" n="31"/>
With a long reed for a staff I waded into the water 
until I heard the voice of a man, in the real coarse 
negro dialect, “who is dat?” My hair was not extremely 
long, yet it seemed so to me, as I imagined I felt 
my hat going up, and I answered “dis is me.” (Of 
course he knew who “me” was.) He then began to 
question me as to my name and my parents' name. It 
was necessary for him to be very cautious whom he admitted, 
because white men often disguised themselves 
and played the role of a runaway, and in this way 
many runaways had been captured. I finally succeeded 
in convincing him that I was not a spy but an actual 
runaway. Then he allowed me to advance, and as 
I sat on the top of the rocky mound with him he 
prayed long and earnestly for the time to come when 
God would raise up a deliverer to lead us in some way 
out of bondage. And while he was thus praying I 
heard this peculiar sound, “gaw goo.” The old man 
saw I was in a terrible dilemma, and he said, “son, 
you need not be uneasy, that is only some men below 
snoring.” In a few minutes I looked across the field 
and saw two men coming with poles on their backs, 
and I got excited again, and called his attention to the 
fact. He assured me that they were men who had 
been off seeking food. They were stealing. </p>
        <p>Our people in those days were naturally good hunters, 
but never shot anything larger than a coon nor 
smaller than a chicken, always good on the wing with 
the latter. They threw their game down. It consisted 
of some fat hens and meat they had returned to 
their homes and secured.</p>
        <pb id="robinson32" n="32"/>
        <p>There was always an understanding between the 
slaves, that if one ran away they would put something 
to eat at a certain place; also a mowing scythe, with 
the crooked handle replaced with a straight stick with 
which to fight the bloodhounds.</p>
        <p>The cook came out, made a hot fire of hickory bark, 
thoroughly wet the chickens and wrapped them in 
cabbage leaves and put them in the bed of ashes; then 
he proceeded to make his bread by mixing the corn 
meal in an old wooden tray and forming it into dodgers, 
rolling them in cabbage leaves and baking in the 
ashes. These are known as ash cakes, the most 
nutritious bread ever eaten. Of course the chickens 
retained all their nutriment because the intestines had 
not been taken out of them. But now he returned to 
them and catching them by both feet he stripped the 
skin and feathers off, then took the intestines out and 
put red pepper and salt in them and then returned 
them to the oven to brown. Parched some corn meal 
for coffee. Breakfast being ready, the guests came 
from the sleeping place, fifteen in number, the two 
huntsmen made seventeen, the old man and myself 
making nineteen in all, all runaways. </p>
        <p>Among them was a man named Frank Anderson. His 
father, James Anderson, a white man of Wilmington, 
was his master. Yet he was a runaway slave, with a 
standing reward of one hundred dollars for his head.</p>
        <p>He had been a fugitive eleven months, and had 
stripes on his back like the ridges of a wash board, 
put there by his father's overseer and by the command 
of that father, simply because he had so much of his 
father's blood in him that he would not allow them to 
lacerate his back only when they overpowered him.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson33" n="33"/>
      <div1 type="image">
        <p>
          <figure id="ill4" entity="ill4">
            <p>MISS FLORENCE MITCHELL, SECRETARY,<lb/>Louisville, Ky.</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson34" n="34"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
        <p>Uncle Amos, as the watchman was called, was a 
prophet among us. He would watch every night, and 
took me as his companion, as I was the only boy. So 
I slept in the day and watched with him at night. He 
was a great astrologer, although he could not read a 
word; but strange to say, he would go out and lie flat 
on his back and watch the moon and stars, go through 
some peculiar movement with his hands, then the next 
morning he could tell almost anything you wanted to 
know. Many times it came just as he prophesied.</p>
        <p>One morning, after I had been to the hiding place 
about three weeks, the runaways inquired, as was the 
custom. “if everything was all right, or what would 
happen.” If he answered them in the affirmative, 
they were perfectly satisfied with his decision. But 
on this memorable morning he told them that we 
would have to get away at once, for if we did not we 
would be attacked within three days by negro hunters, 
for said he, “God has shown me the hounds and the 
men, and that some one will lose his life if the attack is 
made here.”</p>
        <p>So they decided to go to another rendezvous fourteen 
miles away. Uncle Amos advised each one to get 
his weapon in shape, and get provisions enough that 
night to last a few days, or until they learned something 
<pb id="robinson35" n="35"/>
about the country surrounding the other hiding 
place.</p>
        <p>When men ran away, if in the day, they returned at 
night and secured a mowing scythe and took the crooked 
handle off and put a straight handle on it. Then 
they made a scabbard of bark, and would swing their 
saber to their side. This was to fight blood hounds 
with, and if the negro hunters got too close, many 
times they were <sic>hew ndown.</sic></p>
        <p>On that night three different parties were out foraging, 
and returned with considerable provisions. But 
the next morning, while we were eating breakfast, 
negro hunters suddenly appeared with shot guns and 
drawn revolvers, and demanded every one of us to 
wade over to them. They had negro men to hold 
the hounds and cut the cane so they could pass through. 
These men had worked noiselessly all night, cutting 
the way through the cane.</p>
        <p>I told Uncle Amos several times that I thought I 
heard something, but he seemed to think it more fear 
in me than reality, and he failed to give the proper 
attention. </p>
        <p>We all jumped to our feet, with instructions from 
the old man to march over in a body, and each choose 
his man and dog to cut down when they reached the 
other shore, but the hunters were on the alert and demanded 
all to stand in a row, then march over one at 
a time. One of the hunters said to Frank Anderson, 
“if you run I'll blow your brains out.” We formed a 
line and in a moment Frank Anderson bounded off 
like a deer. We heard the crack of a gun, saw Frank 
<pb id="robinson36" n="36"/>
throw up both his hands and fall, and in a minute he 
lay cold in death. Murdered because he wouldn't consent 
to be tied up and whipped when he was late returning 
home from a Saturday night dance.</p>
        <p>One by one we all marched over and were handcuffed 
to each other and marched off to the road, and 
the colored men who were with the hunters carried 
Frank over and put him in the mule cart which they 
had with them, and he could he tracked for thirteen 
miles by the blood which dropped through the cracks 
in the cart. His father rode over the sand stained by 
the blood of his son, whom he had commanded 
to be murdered. </p>
        <p>This is but a small portion of the horrors through 
which my people passed. No tongue has ever been 
able to utter, nor has the pen been forged that can pen 
the horrors through which my people have passed. 
But they kept a constant knocking by faith at mercy's 
door, until God moved in his mighty power and 
touched the heart of Lincoln, who was a type of a 
second Moses, through whom he delivered us. They 
surrendered us to the jailor or keeper of the negro 
pen. There was no jail after all, only negro pens for 
slaves. If a poor white man transgressed the law, 
they simply took what he had and gave him time to 
get out of the country. The Lords, who were our 
masters, hoodwinked the law. If the negro transgressed, 
he paid the penalty with a lacerated back, 
from fifty to three hundred lashes. So you see there 
was no need for jails, only negro pens where slaves 
were bought and sold as goods and chattels.</p>
        <pb id="robinson37" n="37"/>
        <p>These men received for capturing us the paltry sum 
of three dollars per head as the reward for the capture 
of runaway negroes, and the additional two hundred 
offered for the head of Frank Anderson, which had 
been a standing reward from his master, as be couldn't 
be captured in the first six months after he ran away. 
This was equivalent to his father's saying that it was 
better his own son should die than have all the other 
negroes spoiled. Nearly all of us were struck thirty-nine 
lashes according to the law, then returned to our 
several masters.</p>
        <p>For some cause I was among the few exempted from 
the thirty-nine lashes. My master paid the stipulated 
amount of three dollars and ordered me home. I 
walked off in front of him under a storm of oaths and 
threats, and expecting him to kick me or knock me 
down at every step. But I was agreeably disappointed.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson38" n="38"/>
      <div1 type="image">
        <p>
          <figure id="ill5" entity="ill5">
            <p>REV W. H. ROBINSON<lb/>AND DAUGHTER, MARGUERITE.</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson39" n="39"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
        <p>When I arrived home I found that my mother, one 
brother and one sister that were with her when I left, 
had been sold to negro traders, and three brothers who 
fell to Hezekiah Cowens were also sold away, and no 
one could tell me anything about their whereabouts. 
Of course my master wouldn't tell me. This was the 
hour of great sorrow and distress with me. My master 
gave me the task of piling up stove wood, and for 
three weeks nearly every stick of wood I picked up 
was wet with tears of grief and sorrow, weeping for 
that mother who was the best friend on earth to me, 
and for my brothers and sisters, and expecting every 
day to be whipped. And this suspense was one of the 
most severe punishments or whippings I could have 
undergone.</p>
        <p>There was another old woman whom I called mother, 
doing the cooking. One day at the expiration of the 
third week, master sent me to the store to get some 
goods, and in the packages there was a cow-hide in its 
crude state, but I didn't see it wrapped up. After 
unwrapping the cow-hide my master asked me how I 
liked the looks of it. I told him that I didn't like it 
at all. We were in his bed room. He stood between 
me and the door. His wife came in with his decanter 
of whiskey, glass and water and he locked the door, 
then demanded me to pull off my shirt. I had not 
<pb id="robinson40" n="40"/>
forgotten the promise I made my father, so I fully 
made up my mind to fight him until I got a chance to 
jump out of the window. But I looked toward the 
bureau and saw an old fashioned pistol which you 
load from the muzzle and fired with a cap. My master 
was standing very close to this and the sight of it 
knocked all the manhood out of me, so I reluctantly 
pulled off my shirt with their assistance, and he tied 
my hands behind me, my feet together, and ran a 
stick between them. This left me in a doubled up 
position on the floor. He whipped and cursed me 
until he had cut my back to pieces. My mistress tried 
to take the whip from him, but he pushed her away so 
violently that once she fell on the floor. The second 
time she fell on the bed, but had secured the whip. 
He gave me a kick in my side, from which I have 
never recovered, and staggered from the room, being 
too drunk to whip me any more. His wife untied me 
and at the same time the old mother came to the door 
and said, “Master Scott, I came here to break this 
door open, for it's a shame for any woman's son 
to be cut up as you have done that child.” He knocked 
the old lady down. I went up stairs and lay down 
on my stomach with my face across my arms. The next 
morning when I awoke the blood had dried the shirt 
in the wounds on my back. The cook had to grease 
the shirt so as to get it out of the wounds. Then he 
gave her medicine to heal my back. Every day after 
this when I would go to pile up wood I had to stoop 
my whole body, for my back was so sore that  I couldn't 
bend it, and if I had not been so young (I was only 
<pb id="robinson41" n="41"/>
eleven years,) the marks would have been visible until 
now, and like many other slaves, I would have carried 
them to judgment as a testimony against him. </p>
        <p>After four or five weeks, when my back had become 
somewhat healed up, he told me one day if any one 
asked me if I had ever been whipped to tell them no. 
Is it not a wonder that negroes are not inveterate 
thieves and liars? They worked all the week for their 
masters, with only a peck of meal and three pounds of 
fat bacon, and after each day's labor they were compelled 
to go to their master's smoke house or chicken 
roost and steal enough to subsist upon the next day, to 
do that master's work, then, after this master had cut 
his back all to pieces he would compel him to tell a 
lie in order to sell him. But, thank God, we, like other 
nations, are born with the same natural instinct that 
others are, and although manhood was crushed for 
two hundred and forty odd years, yet, with the same 
surroundings and opportunities to develop them, we 
have risen above our environments.</p>
        <p>One afternoon five negro traders came; my master 
called me, met me at the door, and repeated his 
former command “if any one asked me had I been 
whipped, to tell them no.” I walked into the parlor; 
there sat five men wearing broad brimmed straw hats, 
their pants in their boots and a black snake whip 
across their shoulders. The first question they addressed 
to me was, had I ever been whipped. I suspect 
I was too slow in speaking, for the punishment 
had been too severe, and was too fresh in my memory 
for me to tell a lie on the spur of the moment. I had 
<pb id="robinson42" n="42"/>
on a long straight gown which reached to my feet. 
The trader raised that and looked at my back and 
that told the story. They offered my master a small 
price for me, he refused it, and they left. I remained 
with him about three or four weeks longer, when 
one day he wrote a note and sent me to the trader's 
pen. The keeper, Mr. Howard, read it and told me 
to take it back to James, the negro turnkey, who also 
did all the whipping in the jail. He ordered me put 
in a cell and closed the big iron door, which told me 
that I was bound for Richmond, or some other slave 
market, and I was truly glad, for I now hated the soil 
upon which I was born.</p>
        <p>I was in the trader's pen about three weeks. There 
were from one to ten slaves brought in every day. All 
of my brothers and sisters save two had been sold from 
Wilmington. Other slaveholders passing through had 
bought them, and it was said they were taken to 
Georgia. At the end of three weeks the gang of three 
hundred and fifty was made up and we were chained 
and started for Richmond, Virginia. In this gang 
was a woman named Fannie Woods. She had two 
children, the oldest about eight years, the other a 
nursing baby. She was not handcuffed as the others 
were, but tied above the elbow so she could shift the 
nursing baby in her arms. She led the older one by 
the hand. The first half of the day the little boy kept 
up pretty well; after that he became a hindrance in the 
march. The trader came back several times and ordered 
her to keep up. She told him she was doing 
the best she could. He threatened each time to whip 
<pb id="robinson43" n="43"/>
her if she did not keep up, and finally he ordered a 
negro, a strong muscular man six feet in height, who 
went along to give us water and help drive, to untie 
her, made her give the baby to another woman, then 
ordered her to take off her waist. They buckled a 
strap around each wrist and strapped her to a large 
pine tree less than ten feet from the rest of us, and 
with a blacksnake whip the colored man was made to 
hit her fifty lashes on her bare back. The blood ran 
down as water but she never uttered a sound. She 
was ordered to put on her waist. They retied her 
and told her to see if they could keep up.</p>
        <p>After going a few miles farther they sold the little 
boy she was leading to a man along the way. I heard 
the wails of the mother and the mourning of the other 
slaves on account of her sorrow, and heard the gruff 
voice of the trader as he ordered them to shut up. 
We marched until nine or ten o'clock, when we came 
to a boarding house that was kept especially for the 
accommodation of negro traders. This was a large 
log house of one room, about eighteen by twenty feet, 
with staples driven in all around the room and handcuffs 
attached to chains about four feet long. They 
would handcuff two or three slaves to each chain. In 
the summer they had nothing but the bare floor to lie 
upon; in the winter straw was put upon the floor. There was a very large fire place in this room. </p>
        <p>We stopped at this boarding house. This was our 
first night's stop after leaving Wilmington. The keeper 
of the boarding house tried to buy Fannie Wood's 
baby, but there was a disagreement regarding the 
<pb id="robinson44" n="44"/>
price. About five the next morning we started on. 
When we had gone about half a mile a colored 
boy came running down the road with a message from 
his master, and we were halted until his master came 
bringing a colored woman with him, and he bought 
the baby out of Fannie Woods' arms. As the colored 
woman was ordered to take it away I heard Fannie 
Woods cry, “Oh God, I would rather hear the clods 
fall on the coffin lid of my child than to hear its cries 
because it is taken from me.” She said, “good bye, 
child.” We were ordered to move on, and could hear 
the crying of the child in the distance as it was borne 
away by the other woman, and I could hear the deep 
sobs of a broken hearted mother. We could hear the 
groans of many as they prayed for God to have mercy 
upon us, and give us grace to endure the hard trials 
through which we must pass. </p>
        <p>We marched all that day, and the second and third 
nights we stopped in the same kind of a place as the 
first night. They were buying and selling all along 
the way, so when we reached Richmond about ten o'clock 
the fourth night, there were about four hundred and 
fifty of us, footsore, hungry and broken-hearted.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson45" n="45"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
        <p>We were taken to Lee's negro traders' auction 
pen, which was a very large brick structure with a 
high brick wall all around it. A very large hall ran 
through the center. There was no furniture in it, not 
even a chair to sit upon. In this pen the handcuffs 
were taken off for the first time since we left home. 
There were possibly three or four hundred in there 
when we arrived. Many found relatives. One woman 
found her husband who had been sold from her 
three or four years before. But I was not so fortunate 
as to find any of my people.</p>
        <p>The next morning the back door was open and we 
went down to wash. There were three or four pumps 
in the yard and long troughs near each. Some one 
would pump these troughs full of water and we would 
wash our faces and hands. There were no towels to 
wipe on, so some woman would give us her apron or 
dress skirt to dry our faces with. We then waited 
for our breakfast. The cooks handed out our tin pans 
with cabbage, or beans and corn bread, without knife, 
fork or spoon. Many having been sold before, and 
knowing how they would fare, carried such things 
with them. We sat around on the floor and ate our 
breakfast, after which we were ordered into a long 
hall, where we found wire cards, such as are used for 
wool, flax or hemp. We were ordered to comb our 
<pb id="robinson46" n="46"/>
hair with them. Of course when we started we had 
on our best clothes, which consisted of a pair of hemp 
pants and cotton shirt; most of us were barefoot. 
The women, and sometimes the men, wore red cotton 
bandanas on their heads. After our toilets were completed 
we were ordered into a little ten by twelve 
room; we went in, ten or twelve at once. There were 
five or six young ladies in the gang I went in with. 
The traders, forgetting the sacredness of their own 
mothers and sisters, paid no respect to us, but compelled 
each one of us to undress, so as to see if we 
were sound and healthy. I heard Fannie Woods as 
she pleaded to be exempt from this exposure. They 
gave her to understand that they would have her hit 
one hundred lashes if she did not get her clothes off at 
once. She still refused, and when they tried to take 
them off` by force, fought them until they finally let 
her alone. </p>
        <p>After this humiliating ordeal of examination was 
over we went into the auction room. This was a 
large room about forty by sixty feet, with benches 
around the sides, where we were permitted to sit until 
our turn came to get on the auction block. The 
auctioneering began about nine o'clock each day and 
lasted until noon, began again at one o'clock and continued 
until five p. m. This was a perpetual business 
every day in the year, and the prices were quoted on 
the bulletin and in the papers the same as our stock 
and wheat are quoted today. At these sales we could 
find the best people of the South buying and selling. </p>
        <p>I remember when I got on the block, the first bid 
<pb id="robinson47" n="47"/>
was one hundred and fifty dollars. It went up to 
seven hundred, when the bidding ceased. The negro 
trader went to the auctioneer and told him that I came 
from the Madagascar tribe and that my father was an 
engineer and a skilled mechanic. Then the bidding became 
brief. I recall that the auctioneer said, “right 
and title guaranteed,” as he slapped me on the head, 
then continued by saying “he's sound as a silver dollar.” 
I was knocked off at eleven hundred and fifty 
dollars. </p>
        <p>A poor man in East Virginia, named William Scott, 
bought me, paying four hundred and fifty dollars cash 
and giving a mortgage on his sixty acres of land, his 
stock and everything he owned, including one colored 
girl, whom he had bought four years before. The 
next morning after I was sold they brought a man to 
the traders' pen to he whipped. This man would not 
allow his overseer to whip him. He had chains on him 
that looked as though they were welded on. They 
took him upstairs in the big building where there were 
about seven or eight hundred men, women and children. 
It was about noon and they left him handcuffed 
while they went to dinner. He explained to us why 
they were about to whip him. He had gone to church 
without a pass on two occasions and refused to allow 
his master to whip him for so doing. His master declared 
he would whip him or kill him. They took the 
irons off, and ordered him to strip himself of all of 
his clothing. He promptly did so. His master said, 
“you might just as well have done this at home and 
you might have gotten off with a few hundred lashes.” 
<pb id="robinson48" n="48"/>
But to their surprise, when they told him to lie down, 
he began to knock men down right and left, with his 
feet and hands. Many went down before him. Then 
they picked out ten or twelve strong colored men, 
made them run in upon him, and though he knocked 
many of them down they were too many for him, so 
they overpowered him, and with straps fastened him 
taut upon the floor to six strong rings. These rings 
were arranged in two rows of three rings each, opposite 
each other and covering a space something over 
six feet in length. </p>
        <p>Then his master, with four or five other men, came 
up to see him whipped, one man with his tally book, 
and a negro with his black snake whip and paddle; 
they brought their demijohn of whiskey, each one taking 
a drink before they began their bloody work. 
They even gave the negro who was compelled to do 
the whipping, a drink. After they were well drunk 
the whipping began. One man would count out until 
he counted nine, then with the tenth he would cry 
tally. When the whipping first began the slave would 
not say a word, but after awhile as they cut his back 
all to pieces, he would cry out, “pray, master,” and in 
this way he pleaded for mercy until he grew so weak 
he could not utter a word. They gave him three hundred 
lashes, then washed his back with salt water and 
paddled it with a leather paddle about the size of a 
man's hand, with six holes in it. As they paddled him 
it sounded as a dead thud; you could hardly hear him 
grunt as each lick fell upon him. He was whipped 
from head to foot and the floor, where he was lying was 
<pb id="robinson49" n="49"/>
a pool of blood when the brutal work was ended. His 
master congratulated the negro whipping master for 
the way he accomplished his part of the work, gave 
him another big drink of whiskey and ordered him to 
untie the man.</p>
        <p>They all went down stairs and the other colored 
people who were in the room put the man's clothing 
on him. This was late in the afternoon. The next 
morning when I awoke I saw the men and women 
kneeling around in a circle, praying, groaning and 
crying. I walked up and looked to see what the 
trouble was, and I found the man they had whipped 
the day before cold in death. He was swollen so 
that his clothing had. bursted off. A jury of white 
men came up and held a mock inquest. I never heard 
what the verdict was. The colored men came with a 
mule cart, rolled him up in a sheet and took him to 
his last resting place. </p>
        <p>I stayed in this trader's pen three days after my new 
master bought me, and during this time I saw hundreds 
of mothers separated from their children. I 
heard the wail of many a child for its mother, and of 
the mother for her child. While one buyer had the 
mother, going in one direction, another with the child 
would be going the opposite way. I saw husband and 
wife bidding each other farewell and sisters and brothers 
being separated. There could not have been any 
darker days to them than these; it was with them as it 
was with Job, when he spake in the Third Chapter of 
Job, and said: </p>
        <p>“Let the day perish wherein I was born, and the 
<pb id="robinson50" n="50"/>
night in which it is said there is a man child conceived, 
let that day be darkness; let not God regard it from 
above, neither let the light shine upon it.”</p>
        <p>“Let darkness and the shadow of death stain it; let 
a cloud dwell upon it, let the blackness of the day 
terrify it. As for that night, let darkness seize upon 
it; let it not be joined unto the days of the year, let it 
not come into the number of the months. Lo, let that 
night be solitary, let no joyful voice come therein. 
Let them curse it that curse the day, who are ready to 
raise up their mourning. Let the stars of the twilight 
thereof be dark; let it look for light, but have 
none, neither let it see the dawning of the day; because 
it shut not up the doors of my mother's womb, 
nor hid sorrow from mine eyes.”</p>
        <p>These were the lamentations of the poor slaves, but 
still they prayed for the dawn and light of a better 
day. Like Israel, many looked long and eagerly for freedom 
but died without the sight. Thank God, over three 
million lived to see the sunlight in all its brilliancy, and 
we can now look back and say: “The Lord has done 
great things for us, whereof we are glad.”</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson51" n="51"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER IX.</head>
        <p>On the fourth morning after I was sold, I got on the 
horse behind my new master. I had a handcuff on my 
right wrist, with a chain extending down to my right 
foot and locked around my ankle. We rode until late 
in the afternoon, when we stopped at a hotel. He 
chained me to the porch and left me until after supper 
time; then gave me a piece of bread and meat, and left 
me until about ten o'clock at night, while he talked. 
Then he came after me and we went up stairs to his 
room. He chained me to his bed post, and gave me a 
quilt to lie on by the side of his bed, on the floor.</p>
        <p>The next morning we had breakfast by daylight and 
started again on our journey; to my surprise he didn't 
handcuff me this time. He talked very freely with 
me, told me he had a nice girl and if I acted all right 
we would have a good time, and he would soon buy my 
mother and father, when the poor fellow was not 
able to buy me; he had just finished paying the mortgage 
 which he gave when he bought the girl, and remortgaged 
to buy me. About nine o'clock the succeeding 
night we arrived home; when quite a distance 
from the house he called out in a loud voice for Fanny 
to open the gate. As we neared the gate, she threw 
it open. I had ridden until my limbs would not hold 
me up when I slid off the horse, so I fell prostrate 
upon the ground, but with the assistance of the girl 
and my master, I was able to get on my feet.</p>
        <pb id="robinson52" n="52"/>
        <p>His residence was a large log building of one room. 
He left me at the door and told me to stay there until 
he called me. Now, it was a custom with my people, 
when a white man went on the inside and closed the 
door and left a black man, woman or child outside, 
just so sure a black ear went to the key hole. I didn't 
want to make an exception to this rule, so when he 
went in, my ear went to the key hole. After the 
usual mode of family greeting of a man that had been 
away from home a week or ten days, he said: “The 
one who guesses what I have brought, may have it.” 
The oldest boy said, “A pair of boots, for you 
promised me a pair;” the nine-year-old girl said, “A 
large china doll,” but when the guessing came to the 
smallest one, a little girl between the age of three and 
four years, to my surprise she said, “A nigger.” 
“Correct,” said my master, “the rigger's yours; 
come in here, Bill” I went in and the formal introduction 
was made He said, beginning with the 
boy, “This is your master Charles, this is your Miss 
Mary,” but when it came to the youngest girl, he 
said, this is your Miss Alice and you belong to her. 
Now, if you are a good and obedient nigger, when she 
is grown and at her death she will set you free.” If I 
had believed this story I would have prayed to God to 
kill her then, wicked as it was. Then he gave me an 
introduction to his wife. As long as I had been with 
him he had not introduced himself until now. He 
really grew enthusiastic in introducing himself; his face 
grew red, and his voice trembled as he said: “I want 
you to understand that I'm a nigger breaker. I hear 
<pb id="robinson53" n="53"/>
you came from a family of riggers that won't be 
whipped, but I'll break you or kill you.” I knew he 
could not afford to do the latter, for I had overheard 
Robert E. Lee, from whom he had bought me, say to 
him. “I understand you have abused the girl you 
bought from me, shamefully. If you abuse this boy it 
will cost you all you are worth.” </p>
        <p>He then called the girl, who was once a pretty octoroon, 
but now her face was much disfigured where the 
mistress had stuck the hot tongs to it because she was 
so overworked she would fall asleep while she would be
carding wool at night. You could hardly see the 
traces of a once beautiful girl, now about fourteen 
years old.</p>
        <p>He said, “you two have got a good home and can 
be happy here together.” Jokingly, be said, “I'll 
have the preacher come over and marry you.” He 
thought through this union  -  he had formed in his 
mind  -  that he would raise his own slaves. </p>
        <p>After supper the mistress ordered her to bring in 
her tin pan and quart cup, at the same time wondering 
what dishes to give me to use. My master said. “Oh 
yes, I forgot to tell you I bought Bill a new pan and 
cup.” The children scampered away for the old saddle 
bags. They brought my cup and pan, and after 
using the latter for a looking glass for a time, handed 
it to me. In the tin pans she put a little gravy and a
corn dodger on each, and filled the cups with skimmed 
 milk  -  the milk had been skimmed and skimmed until 
there was not an eye of cream to be seen on it. We 
called it blue John. Fannie and I went into the kitchen 
<pb id="robinson54" n="54"/>
She said to me, “don't eat yet, we'll milk first.” 
I was very hungry, but did as she asked me. We took 
our milk buckets and went to the cow pen; there were 
two cows, so we got them close together. Fannie 
milked both, for I had never before tried to milk. We 
poured our cup of blue John into the milk pail. She 
milked both our cups full, and with our hoe cakes of 
corn bread, we ate our supper, drinking the warm, 
unstrained milk. The mistress often complained, and 
spoke of selling the cows because <sic>tbey</sic> gave such poor 
milk. We would then milk the cows into the pail 
where we had poured our skimmed milk and return 
it to our mistress. We continued this as long as I was
there, which was three or four months.</p>
        <p>My master was overseer for a man on an adjoining 
farm, named Howard, for which he was paid thirty 
dollars per month. He would leave home at three 
o'clock in the morning, giving the girl and me our task 
the night before. He would eat his dinner each day 
in the field with the slaves, and return home at about 
nine or ten o'clock at night. He hired the slaves at 
night, and sometimes in the day he would slip them 
over to work in his crop. I have known the slaves 
many times to work in his field from ten o'clock at 
night until near day-break the next morning; yet he 
never allowed the girl or me to visit the slaves on any 
other farm, or them to visit us. He was the meanest 
overseer in that section of the country, for he would 
have a whipping bee every Monday morning. </p>
        <p>He had whipping posts on the farm and the slaves 
were tied to this and whipped; you could hear the cries 
<pb id="robinson55" n="55"/>
of slaves all around from that place. I have heard 
him laugh many times and tell how the slaves would 
squirm under the lash. </p>
        <p>The farm on the other side of us belonged to a man 
named Wilkerson; he had seventy five or a hundred 
slaves, and he, also, was a cruel man. Every day, in 
going for the cows I would have to pass his farm. I 
heard him say to one of the rail splitters, “if you don't 
have your task of rails split tomorrow I will hit 
you one hundred lashes.” The man told him he was 
doing all he could do and would die before he would 
take a single lick. I made it my business the next day 
to go after the cows about the time for him to go out; 
I saw him and four or five other men; he asked the 
rail splitter if he had his task completed. The man 
answered in the negative; he then ordered him to pull 
off his shirt, which the man did, then tied his pants 
around his waist with his suspenders. The reason the 
slaves would so readily pull off their shirts was so 
they could not have anything to hold them by, their
flesh being moist they could not easily hold them. 
When his master told him to cross his hands he began 
to fight, knocking white men down as fast as they 
could come to him. Finally they made five or six 
other rail splitters, working near by, help take him. 
There were saw logs from five to six feet through, all 
round; some of the colored men caught him by the 
head and hands, while others had hold of his feet, and 
they bent him back over one of the saw-logs while he 
was fighting and cursing. His master seized the maul, 
which the man had been using to split rails with, and 
<pb id="robinson56" n="56"/>
struck him across the abdomen; bent over in the position 
he was the lick sounded like a pop-gun, and 
the man's intestines ran out, and he died across the log; 
murdered because he could not perform the task imposed
upon him. These are some of the horrible 
deeds which have stained the pages of American history, 
and which it will take centuries to mitigate. </p>
        <p>It was a common thing to hear the cries of the slaves 
all around on Monday morning. Some being whipped 
for one thing, some for another. Some were whipped 
for attending religious services on Sunday; some for 
going to frolics; sometimes a man's wife was owned by 
other masters five or six miles away; they would slip-off 
after their work was done at night to see them; 
sometimes they would be late returning, so they would 
be whipped for that. There would be a perfect pandemonium
around that community all the time.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson57" n="57"/>
      <div1 type="image">
        <p>
          <figure id="ill6" entity="ill6">
            <p>[Illustration]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson58" n="58"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER X.</head>
        <p>I would often talk to Fannie about running away; 
she would plead with me and beg me not to, because 
it would be so lonesome for her, but there was a constant 
yearning in my soul for that freedom which God 
intended for all human beings. Ultimately, after a 
careful planning of the route to be taken and a survey 
of the country, as far as I had been over, I made up 
my mind to leave. One morning my master sent me 
to the field to gather corn. I carried a basket and two 
sacks, and at noon I was to fill them and hitch up the 
mule cart and bring them home. I got the corn ready 
and sat down in the corn row. I realized then for the 
first time that there must be some efficacy in prayer. 
My mother had taught me to get on my knees and say 
my prayers, as far back as I could remember, yet I 
never knew the power there was in prayer, until on this 
memorable morning, I knelt down in a corn row and 
prayed with that fervent, childlike simplicity for God 
in some way to get me hack to my mother or into 
Canada, or else let me die and go to heaven. The 
Queen of England had said that if the slaves could 
reach the shores of Canada she would protect them, if 
it took the whole navy of England to do so. While I 
was thus in prayer it seemed that all nature was in 
sympathy with me, for not even the rustling of the 
leaves could be heard. The only thing to break the 
<pb id="robinson59" n="59"/>
monotony was the wooing of a turtle dove that sat in 
the branches of a distant tree, and seemed to he saying 
to me, “I am in deep sympathy with you.” Reasoning 
came to me as audibly as though some one was 
speaking to me, saying “you shall see your mother 
again.”</p>
        <p>I became so much elated over this message, though 
received from an unseen power, that I jumped up and 
at once fully decided what course to take. Immediately 
I proceeded to put my decision into action, so I 
emptied the corn out of the two sacks and the basket;
put the sacks in the basket on my arm and left that 
corn field with the full intention of going back to Richmond, 
Virginia.</p>
        <p>It may seem strange to the reader that I would go 
back to this place of human misery; but I had learned 
from older men and women who had been sold to some 
poor man, that if they would run away and go back to 
their former master, and tell him “that your master 
was so mean that you could not live with him, and for 
this reason you had run away and come back to him,” 
nine times out of ten he would accept this piece of deception 
practiced by the slave, and compel the poor 
man to take his money back, believing that the negro 
thought more of him than of the man he had sold him 
to, and for this reason I was going back to Richmond, 
Virginia.</p>
        <p>I went about seven or eight miles that day through 
the woods, and about dusk I came in sight of a cabin 
in the distance. I was satisfied this was the home of 
some old mother or father who had outlived the days of 
<pb id="robinson60" n="60"/>
their usefulness, and was given a peck of meal each 
week and cast off to fish or hunt for the rest of their 
living. I was not disappointed, for I found an old 
woman eighty years old; it was hard to discover until 
she spoke whether she was white or slave. The first 
words the old lady said were, “Son, you is a runaway, 
aint you? I told her that I was, and she told me “the 
overseer haven't been around yet cause dey aint done 
milking yit, but you take this path (as she pointed to a 
path) and follow it till you come to a log across de 
creek, with a fish box upon it; you sit there until you 
hear me singing this song, God has delivered Daniel, 
and why not deliver me?” She went into the house, 
while I went to the log mentioned. I sat there for 
three-quarters of an hour. I heard the milk maids 
while milking singing different melodies, then I heard 
the command of the overseer for them to take the 
cows to pasture, and in a short while I heard the feeble 
voice of the old mother as it rang out on the still, 
balmy air, singing: </p>
        <lg type="poem">
          <l>He delivered Daniel from the lion's den, </l>
          <l>Jonah from the body of the whale, </l>
          <l>The Hebrew children from the fiery furnace, </l>
          <l>And why not deliver poor me?</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Hold up your head with courage bold,</l>
          <l>And do not be afraid; </l>
          <l>For my God delivered Daniel, </l>
          <l>And He will deliver poor you.</l>
        </lg>
        <p>I started for the house and met her coming. We 
went into the cabin where she had prepared supper, 
<pb id="robinson61" n="61"/>
and I assure you I enjoyed it. The supper consisted 
of boiled fresh fish and “ash cake.” As I ate she sat 
with her hands on my head, telling me how to get 
along in the world, and pointing me to that friend that 
sticketh closer than a brother. She repeatedly said, 
“if God be for you it is more than all the world 
against you.” She made me a pallet upon the floor, 
and I slept there until about three-thirty o'clock the 
next morning, when she awoke me and gave me breakfast 
of the same diet I had had the night previous 
for supper. She also gave me four or five onions, and 
told me upon the peril of my life, not to eat a single 
one of these onions, because they would make me 
sleepy and I would be liable to be caught. But she 
said negro hunters came along there every two or three 
hours in the day; and I learned for the first time how 
to decoy the blood hounds, for she told me whenever 
I heard the baying of hounds on my trail, to rub the 
onions on the bottoms of my feet and run, and after 
running a certain distance to stop and apply the onions 
again, then when I came to a large bushy tree, to rub 
the trunk as high up as I could reach, then climb the 
tree.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson62" n="62"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER XI.</head>
        <p>About four o'clock in the morning, at the old woman's
command, I knelt by her side, she placed her 
hand upon my head and prayed fervently for my safe 
return to Richmond, and that God would touch Massa 
Lee's heart, that he might buy me back from my 
present owner. When she quit praying she told me 
that I would reach Richmond safely. She kissed me 
good bye, with tender, parting words, as a mother 
would her own son, and I left, with directions from her 
how to reach my intended destination. I had not gone 
far when an opportunity presented itself to test the 
efficacy of the onions, for about nine o'clock that day 
I heard the baying of the blood hounds in the distance 
behind me. I rubbed the onions on my feet as directed, 
and ran as fast as I could the distance of half a 
mile, when I repeated the application. I continued 
this process for about one mile and a half, going 
across the fields and through the woods, dodging the 
roads and farms where people were at work. I came 
to a thickly branched out tree in the woods. I rubbed 
onions on the trunk and climbed the tree. I could tell 
when the hounds came to the place where I first put 
the onions on my feet, because they would retrace 
their steps, until finally their voices died away, 
and I heard them no more that day. I traveled all of 
that day, and that night I slept in a low, swampy place 
<pb id="robinson63" n="63"/>
between two huge logs, on some brush, with the two 
sacks over me which I took when I left the corn field. 
By daylight the next morning I started on my journey, 
but had not gone many miles when I came in sight of 
a river. I saw that I was not far from a house, and 
went close enough to see that a ford was near the 
house where they crossed the river. The white man 
who had charge of the ford lived in the house. So I 
knew I couldn't get across the river without taking a 
boat, and that he wouldn't hire me one without word 
from my master, therefore that necessitated my waiting 
until night, so I went back in the woods to wait.</p>
        <p>I saw some colored men coming across the field and 
went to meet them, and learned through them their 
master's name and three or four slaves that he owned, 
and name of a farmer on the other side of the river. 
They told me to go to the ferryman and tell him that 
Mr. Howard, my master, had sent me to take the 
basket and two sacks to Mr. Owens, who lived on the 
other side of the river. They told me that the ferryman 
would question me very minutely, but if he asked 
how long Mr. Howard had owned me to tell him he 
bought me from negro traders two weeks before  -  for 
traders had crossed there just two weeks ago with three 
or four hundred slaves. They then left me and told 
me to wait until they returned. I did so, but under 
great suspense, because one of the men belonged to 
a tribe of negroes known as the Guineas, who would 
divulge any secret for a little whiskey or wheat bread; 
therefore I was afraid I would be betrayed. But in a 
short time they returned, relieving me of the great 
<pb id="robinson64" n="64"/>
suspense, and bringing me something to eat. They 
told me I was in an easy day's walk of Richmond after 
I crossed the river; told me what to say to Massa Lee 
when I got back, but not to go into Richmond until 
after dark. They prayed an ardent prayer for God's 
protection and guiding hand to go with me, and bade 
me good bye and God speed. I went to the ford, 
called out hello; the harsh voice of the ferryman cried 
out, “whose thar.” At the same time he was coming 
towards the river, I was fast rehearsing in my 
mind the story I was to tell him. When he got near 
me his first words were, “where in hell are you going 
this time of night?” I started to tell him that Mr. 
Howard had sent me to Mr. Owen's to take the basket 
and sacks, but before I could finish telling him, he 
ordered me to pull off my hat: that he would teach me 
some manners if I came there talking to him with my 
hat on. He then asked how long Mr. Howard had 
owned me, at the same time flashing his lantern in my 
face. But when I told him he said, “yes, I remember 
seeing you in that gang; untie the boat.” He sat 
down and lit his pipe while  I pulled the boat over. 
When we reached the other side he said “tie her up 
thar.” He looked at his watch and said “its a quarter 
up thar and a quarter back.” I'll give you fifteen 
minutes each way, if you sent back in that time I'll 
skin you alive.” If he's waiting he is having a good 
long wait. I went on my way rejoicing and saying, 
as the little colored boy said who had been accustomed 
to climbing the ladder and sleeping in one of his mistress's 
bed rooms when his master was not at home. 
<pb id="robinson65" n="65"/>
But one memorable night when he got to the bed he 
found old master was there, so he said. “may I, old 
master, may I?” Master said, “may you what, you 
black rascal, you.” Sambo as quick as lightning, said, 
“may I feed the little pigs with the big ones?” With 
an oath his master told him yes; for him to get out of 
there. Sambo was so much elated over his success 
that he said, as he started down the ladder, “wasn't 
dat well turned?” The master hearing him, inquired 
“what's that well turned?” </p>
        <p>Sambo was ready again with an answer. He said, 
“my foot slipped and I fell twice around de ladder and 
cotched myself and didn't fall yit.”</p>
        <p>After crossing the river that night I went but a 
short distance, when I made me a bed in a shock of 
fodder. The next morning before daylight as I came 
out of the shock two more runaways came out of the 
shock ahead of me. When they saw me they ran as 
fast as they could go and I after them. They did not 
wait to see whether I was white or black. They ran 
across a large field, and came to a fence. One, a very 
tall man, put his hand on the top and vaulted over. 
The other one attempted to follow but fell back. By 
that time I had caught up with him. He asked me 
why I did not tell him I was colored. I replied, “I 
couldn't cotch you.”</p>
        <p>They were men who had been sold from Richmond 
and were now running away from their masters as I 
was, and trying to get back to Lee. They had with 
them plenty to eat, so we had about as good a time 
that day as runaways could have in the woods. Long 
<pb id="robinson66" n="66"/>
before dusk we could see the statue of George Washington, 
which stood at Richmond, Virginia, with a 
negro boy chained at its base, and Washington pointing 
with his right hand, saying, “take the negro south.” 
This very great man, who, with Hancock, in 1776, 
signed the Declaration of Independence, and said the 
colonies were and ought to be free, loosed them from 
the iron hand of Great Britain; and yet that was the 
inscription written on his statue, which adorned the 
public square of the once Capitol of the Southern 
Confederacy.</p>
        <p>We hid around until dusk, when we went down to a 
spring and ate our lunch slaking our thirst from the 
clear cool water as it bubbled out from the spring, by 
lying flat down and lapping the water. I happened to 
be the first of the three to get up, and to 
my surprise there stood five negro hunters with their 
guns and revolvers pointing toward us. I said to my 
companions “here is some white men.” They said 
“whar.” Their eyes looked like great balls of cotton. 
The men commanded us to come to them. I can best 
illustrate how we appeared when we found out that we 
had been captured, by a cartoon which I once saw. 
The cartoon represented an old colored man who saw 
an opossum in a tree close to his house; he was so 
elated over the idea of possum and sweet potatoes that 
he climbed the tree. The possum jumped upon the 
limb the man was on, but it got between him and the 
trunk of the tree; the old man had his saw and began 
in earnest to saw the limb off, thinking of nothing but 
the possum; he said to his boy and dog below, “look 
<pb id="robinson67" n="67"/>
out down dar, cause sumphin gwine to drap.” And 
“something did drap,” but it was the old man himself. 
Likewise, when we three looked up into the muzzles of 
the guns and revolvers we thought something was going 
to drop, and sure enough something did, for we dropped, 
each one of us in handcuffs, and we were marched 
into Richmond. </p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson67a" n="67a"/>
      <div1 type="image">
        <p>
          <figure id="ill7" entity="ill7">
            <p>S . J. RICHARDSON,<lb/>Editor Bedford, Ind., Enterprise, who has given valuable assistance and friendship to the author.</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson68" n="68"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER XII.</head>
        <p>When we arrived at the negro trader's pen, Mr Lee 
happened to be there. He wanted to know of the 
negro hunters where they found us; they told him. 
Then he began to interrogate each of us; I told him 
that “Massa Scott was so mean to me that I could not 
live with him, so I ran off and came back to you.” 
The other two men told the same kind of story; so Mr. 
Lee ordered the negro hunters to take the handcuffs 
off, and if they wanted to make money to go and find 
negroes that were not coming back to him. They, with 
their hats in their hands, the same as the slaves, began 
to form excuses, when Lee ordered them off the premises 
without any reward. Had we not been returning 
to Mr. Lee they would have been entitled to three dollars 
per head. According to the law they were entitled 
to it at any rate, for we were runaways, but they 
were poor men with low occupations and their word 
didn't go as far as that of the slaves they were driving. 
One of the men he ordered locked up stairs, telling 
him that he had a good master, and if he behaved 
himself he would he treated all right. The man begged 
very hard not to be sent back, but his begging was all 
in vain. This man's master was wealthy, while mine 
and the other man's master were poor men, so he 
kept us and sent the other man back.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lee told me that the man who had my mother 
<pb id="robinson69" n="69"/>
had been there twice and wanted to buy me, and Scott, 
he said “was behind anyhow.” I think he meant that 
his second payment was overdue-  -  and he assured me 
that he shouldn't have me back. Mr. Lee wrote a 
note and sent me to his own house. I met an old 
colored mammy at the gate. She asked me, “where is 
you gwine?” I said, “to see Miss Lee.” She said, 
“You look like gwine to see Miss Lee. Wha dat 
you got in your han?” I said, “a letter for her.” 
She said, “gin it to me.” She took the note, telling 
me to wait. Mrs. Lee raised the window and called 
me to come up. She asked about my parents, and 
said Mr. Scott should not take me back again. She 
told the colored mammy to take me and clean me up. 
When I got in the cabin I discovered it was wash day, 
for she had a kettle of hot water on the fire place. 
She took a couple of handfuls of soft soap out of the 
gourd and stirred it in the water. When she found I 
was not undressing she looked very much surprised 
and said, “gwine out of dem rags.” She scrubbed 
my back till my flesh burned. About the time she 
was through the sixteen-year old maid came in with 
clothing for me. I tried to hide behind the old 
mother. The girl threw the clothes down and ran out. 
I put the clothes on and stayed at the trader's pen that 
evening. After that I was privileged to stay at the 
house, or pen, as I chose. I thought I was almost a free 
man, for I had on a pair of shoes, a nice suit of clothes 
and a large brass watch and chain. </p>
        <p>Master Lee told me that a man named Jake Hadley, 
who lived in Greenville, Tennessee, had my mother, 
<pb id="robinson70" n="70"/>
two brothers and a sister. He also said Mr. Hadley 
drove a big black horse so it seems that I thought 
there was only one black horse in all Virginia and that 
the Jew owned him; therefore I met with many disappointments. 
I waited and watched for more than a 
month for my new master to come, during which time 
I assisted Peter around the pen. Peter looked after 
the slaves, and did all the whipping. I cleaned the 
office and was errand boy. Most of my work was 
about the office. During the time I was there I saw 
thousands of slaves bought and sold. I saw one 
woman who had five children; she and two children, 
one a nursing baby, and a girl about eleven years old, 
were sold to negro traders, while the husband and the 
other three children were bought by a farmer who 
lived somewhere in east Virginia. The farmer went 
with the father and three children to see the mother 
and the other two children leave for Mississippi. As 
the boat pulled out from the shore and the husband 
and wife bade each other good bye, the woman, with 
one loud scream, made a sudden leap and landed in the 
deep water, with her baby clasped in her arms and the 
little girl handcuffed to her. She had preferred death 
to life separated from her husband and children. They 
were not picked up until the next day.</p>
        <p>I saw another woman whipped seventy-five lashes on 
her bare back because she wouldn't strip her clothing 
any further down than her waist, to be examined. 
They took her back the second time, but she fought 
them until they were compelled to leave her alone. 
<pb id="robinson71" n="71"/>
These last two incidents remind me of the pilgrim in 
the following song: </p>
        <lg>
          <l>“I saw a blood washed traveler in garments white <sic>assnow</sic>,</l>
          <l>While traveling up the highway, where heavenly breezes 
blow;</l>
          <l>His path was full of trials, but yet his face was bright, </l>
          <l>He shouted as he journeyed, I'm glad the burden's light.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>CHORUS. </head>
          <l>Then it's palms of victory,</l>
          <l>Crowns of glory,</l>
          <l>Palms of victory, you shall wear.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>I saw him 'mong his neighbors, they mocked his soul's alarm; </l>
          <l>The vilest wretch among them could scoff and do no harm;</l>
          <l>Forsaken by his kindred and banished from their sight,</l>
          <l>An outcast, yet he shouted, I'm glad the burden's light.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>I saw him in the conflict, where all around was strife,</l>
          <l>Where wicked men with malice, connived to take his life;</l>
          <l>I saw him cast in prison, a dungeon dark as night,</l>
          <l>And there I heard him shouting, I'm glad the burden's 
light.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>I saw him led from prison, and chained unto the stake,</l>
          <l>I heard him cry triumphant, 'tis all for Jesus sake.</l>
          <l>I saw the fires when kindled, the faggots burning bright,</l>
          <l>He said the yoke is easy, the burden is so light.”</l>
        </lg>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson72" n="72"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER XIII.</head>
        <p>This is now the year of 1860. I was twelve years 
of age and had been a runaway twice in that time. I 
had now been at Lee's trader's pen four or five weeks, 
when one day I saw a man coming with a black horse 
and buggy; something from within seemed to whisper 
to me, “this is the man who owns your mother.” My 
aspirations ran so high that I went out the back way 
and prayed that this might be he. He came into the 
office of the pen, and after a general conversation with 
Mr. Lee, he asked “if he had heard anything of that 
boy yet.” I was watching every move and listening 
to every word passed. With a wink of the eye, Mr. 
Lee said, “no.” Then he sent me to do something in 
the rear end of the building. I did it very quickly
and returned to the office again; was very busily engaged 
with my dust brush. Never since I had been 
there had I found so much to be done in the office, 
and whenever I was sent away I would do my errand 
as quickly as possible and return to the office again. </p>
        <p>Finally Mr. Hadley, for it was he, said: “boy, 
how would you like to belong to me and go 
down to Tennessee to live? While I was satisfied that 
he was the man who owned my mother, I said, “I 
wouldn't like to go with you at all, 'cause Massa Lee 
said the man that had my mother was coming after 
me.” As I spoke I couldn't keep from crying, and Mr. 
<pb id="robinson73" n="73"/>
Lee could refrain no longer, so he said “William, 
this is Mr. Hadley, the man who has your mother, and 
brothers and sisters.” And for once I saw that seemingly 
heartless man, who separated thousands of husbands 
and wives, mothers and children, sisters and 
brothers, touched to the very core, for he drew his 
handkerchief and wiped his eyes, instead of his nose, 
as he pretended to be doing. </p>
        <p>Mr. Hadley was a very kind, fatherly acting man. 
He bought me a nice suit of clothes, and gave me 
money, telling me to buy my mother, brothers and sisters 
some presents. As a general thing all Jew slave 
owners were more lenient to their slaves than any other 
nationality, perhaps because they had been in bondage 
themselves. In a few days we started for home; we 
had to stop along the way in many little towns to attend 
to business, so that we were nearly four days in 
making the trip. These were four of the longest days 
I had ever experienced in my life, for I was anxious 
to meet my mother again. I was constantly inquiring 
“how much farther is it.” On the fourth day in the 
afternoon I asked, “how long yet before we will 
reach home?” He said, “in a few days now.” The 
words had scarcely left his lips, when I saw coming 
down the road my mother and new mistress. Mother 
came upon the side of the buggy my master was on, 
and almost dragged me out of the buggy across my 
master. She was rejoicing and blessing master for his
deeds of kindness. In a few minutes my new mistress 
came up on the other side of the buggy; she pulled me 
over, and to my surprise, and for the first time in my 
<pb id="robinson74" n="74"/>
life, a white woman kissed me. This was a very new 
feature to me, and naturally embarrased me very much, 
so much so that I mentioned it many times afterwards. 
I couldn't understand how it was, I, a slave, and she 
my mistress, as others had been, and they were so 
heartless and cruel, and she so kind. But I afterwards 
learned that all the white people were not mean and 
cruel, for when I arrived home I found my mistress 
had prepared a grand dinner for us and invited in all 
the slaves. My mistress had two children, Samuel and 
Laura. I didn't call them master and mistress as I 
had heretofore called the white children, but called 
them each by their given name. I had a glorious time 
in that home and felt almost as if I were free. My 
master owned a large farm three miles from Greenville, 
where we lived. But during the month of February 
he concluded to go to the old country-  -  I think 
it was on account of the agitation of the slave question 
  -  he saw the war was coming on, so he decided to 
take us back to Wilmington and leave us there, with 
his wife and children, on his brother's farm, until he 
returned. Accordingly we all packed up and went 
back to Wilmington, N. C., my old birthplace. On 
arriving there we found another brother and sister, 
making mother and six children together again; father 
and the other six children we knew nothing of. Mr. 
Hadley went away but was gone only three weeks, 
when he returned, saying he had not gone any farther 
than Richmond, Virginia.</p>
        <p>He stayed in Wilmington a month, and when he 
was ready to go back home he asked me and my sister 
<pb id="robinson75" n="75"/>
“if we didn't want to stay with his brother awhile 
longer and come home later on.” We, not having 
the least suspicion that he had sold us, told him that 
we would. So they went home, leaving us. After a 
couple of weeks, Mr. Dave Hadley  -  that was his 
brother's name  -   told us that he had bought us, but 
we could go every two or three months to Greenville 
to see mother.</p>
        <p>It was not more than two weeks from the time I 
found that Massa Dave Hadley had bought me, when 
Joseph Cowens, the son of my original old master, 
came to Mr. Hadley's; he met me out in the yard and 
stopped me for a talk. He said, “it was a shame that 
his father had allowed my father to be sold away, that 
he was going to buy us all back and get us together 
again.”</p>
        <p>With this conversation he naturally won me, so 
when he asked me if I wouldn't like to belong to him, 
of course I said “yes.” He went into the house and 
in a short time be and Massa Dave came out together, 
and Massa Dave told me that I now belonged to 
Joseph Cowens, and that he bad bought my two brothers 
also, and in the next two months he was going to 
buy mother and the other two children. But when I 
got to his house and asked for my brothers, he said 
that he had hired them out for a year. I soon 
found out different; he had never bought my brothers, 
nor had any intention of buying them; or my 
mother, either.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson76" n="76"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER XIV.</head>
        <p>I am now back in the Cowens family, my original 
master's son, and brother to Scott Cowens  -  the man I 
knocked off the porch for hitting my mother, and who 
was afterwards drowned. I went to Joseph Cowen's 
as general servant boy in the house, and was treated as 
well as could be expected from a Cowen. I stayed 
there quite satisfied, thinking that mother and the 
other children would come in a few months, as he had 
promised they would. The last of March we moved 
out on the Summer farm, three miles from town, and 
I had to drive him to town every morning and go for 
him every evening. He was a merchant and owned 
several ships. Now I had a great deal of freedom out 
on the farm, for I did nothing but drive Massa Joseph 
back and forth, to and from town, and wait table. I 
was in the cabins and among the slaves the most of my 
time in the day, but I slept at the “great house” in 
Massa Joseph's room. I had become almost a prophet 
among my people, because I would get the news from 
the white people, and in the day would tell it to the 
slaves in the fields and cabins.</p>
        <p>He owned another farm five miles from town, and 
had a colored overseer on this farm. Uncle Tom 
was the meanest man you ever saw, in the presence of 
the white folks. He would draw back his whip as 
though he was going to knock down all around him,  
<pb id="robinson77" n="77"/>
but I never knew him to strike an old person in my 
life.</p>
        <p>The leading white men from town would come out 
two or three nights in a week and stay half of the night 
and gamble. I would take the whiskey, glasses and 
water in to them, then Massa Joe would send me off 
to bed, but I stood many an hour listening to them 
talk and discuss the question of the war, and whether 
it would be advisable to arm the negroes. They 
finally decided, as did the Egyptians, that if they did 
arm the negroes when the enemy came the slaves 
would join with the enemy and fight against them, 
so they thought it would not be expedient to do so. 
About this time, or in February, 1861, delegates from 
South Carolina, Alabama, Georgia, <sic>Louisana</sic> and 
Texas, met at Montgomery, Alabama, and formed a 
government called the Confederate States of America. 
Jefferson Davis, of Mississippi, was chosen president. 
Davis came to Wilmington and was given a great ovation, 
and in his speech he appealed very strongly to 
the ladies; he asked, “which lady there was not willing 
to give her husband, son, brother or sweetheart, to go 
upon the battle field and fight for their rights.” The 
women became frantic with their cries, “I will give 
mine,” “I wouldn't marry a man who wouldn't go,” 
etc. Then he made another appeal to the ladies, asking 
“which one of them would like to live to see the 
day when a nigger wench would be on equality with 
them?” At this point they grew raving mad,  ante 
cried, “they never wanted to see that day.” Jeff said 
he would wade in blood to his saddle skirts rather 
<pb id="robinson78" n="78"/>
than live to see that day, and yet he tried to escape in 
his wife's skirts.</p>
        <p>About this time the laws were very strict on the 
slaves, and they were not allowed a pass to go to 
a public gathering of any kind. Men who belonged 
to one man and whose wives were owned by another, and 
had been given a pass every Saturday night to go to 
see them, were now permitted to go only once a month. 
But the slaves would slip off to church and frolics and 
the patrollers were continually after them, but the 
slaves would play all kinds of tricks on them. I remember 
one time while at a prayer meeting in an old 
deserted cabin on the back part of a farm the slaves 
were singing and praying, but had several stationed all 
around the house, watching. They saw the patrollers 
coming and notified those in the house, and to my surprise 
five or six men had shovels, and each man got a 
shovel full of hot embers out of the fireplace and 
stood at the door and windows. They continued to 
sing and pray until the patrollers got to the door 
and ordered it opened. One man snatched the 
door open while the others threw the fire all over 
them; when the patrollers recovered consciousness 
the slaves were all gone. </p>
        <p>At another time I went to a dance in the woods; the 
music consisted of tambourine, banjo and bones, but 
before the dance began they tied grapevines across the 
road, just high enough to catch a man riding horse 
back across the face or neck. When they heard the 
patrollers coming they ran, and the patrollers right 
after them; many of them were crippled, but not a  
<pb id="robinson79" n="79"/> 
slave was hurt or caught, So you see, there were 
some negro as well as Yankee tricks.</p>
        <p>The slaves would have to devise many schemes in 
order to serve God. Of course they had church once 
or twice a month, but some white man would do the 
preaching, and his text would always be, “Servants 
obey your masters,” But this was not what our 
people wanted to hear, so they would congregate after 
the white people had retired, when you would see them 
with their cooking utensils, pots and kettles, go into a 
swamp and put the pots and kettles on the fence, with 
the mouths turned toward the worshipers. They would 
sing and pray, the kettles catching the sound. In this 
way they were not detected. I did not learn until 
just before the war why they carried the vessels with 
them to worship.</p>
        <p>In order to notify the slaves on other farms when 
there was going to be a meeting they would sing this 
song, and the slaves would understand what it meant. 
White people would think they were only singing for 
amusement:</p>
        <p>“Get you ready, there's a meeting here tonight.”
Matt. 7: 16.</p>
        <lg>
          <l>1	“Get you ready, there's a meeting here tonight, </l>
          <l>Come along there's a meeting here tonight, </l>
          <l>I know you by your daily walk, </l>
          <l>There's a meeting here tonight.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>2	Oh, hallelujah, to the lamb, </l>
          <l>There's a meeting here tonight, </l>
          <l>For the Lord is on the given hand, </l>
          <l>There's a meeting here tonight. </l>
        </lg>
        <pb id="robinson80" n="80"/>
        <lg>
          <l>3	If ever I reach the mountain top, </l>
          <l>I'll praise my Lord and never stop, </l>
          <l>Get you ready, there's a meeting here tonight.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>4	Go down to the river when you're dry </l>
          <l>And there you'll get your full supply, </l>
          <l>Get ready, there's a meeting here tonight.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>5	You may hinder me here,</l>
          <l>But you cannot there, </l>
          <l>God sits in heaven </l>
          <l>And he answers prayer.</l>
          <l>There's a meeting here tonight.</l>
        </lg>
        <p>They would carry with them iron lamps, with a 
greasy rag for a wick, and they would attach a sharp 
spike to the lamp so as to stick it in a tree. In this 
way they would light up the swamp, while they held 
their meeting.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson81" n="81"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER XV.</head>
        <div2>
          <head>SLAVE HOLDERS' CONSISTENT FAMILY WORSHIP</head>
          <head>THE SLAVE HOLDERS' MORNING SERVICE.</head>
          <head>SLAVEOWNERS' WORSHIP.</head>
          <lg>
            <l>Air  -  any long metre.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>“Come let us join, our God to praise, </l>
            <l>Who lengthens out our fleeting days.</l>
            <l>The shades of one more night have passed </l>
            <l>Which has to many been the last. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>And thus, Kind Providence, it seems, </l>
            <l>Has kept us through our midnight dreams.</l>
            <l>Our dogs have guarded well the door </l>
            <l>And Lord, what could we ask Thee more?</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Thy promise, Lord, has been our stay; </l>
            <l>Not e'en a slave has run away,</l>
            <l>While scores have left on every side</l>
            <l>To seek Lake Erie's doleful tide.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>O! grant us, Lord, a great display</l>
            <l>Of Thy rich mercies through this day.</l>
            <l>May we in strength our work pursue,</l>
            <l>And love Thee as slave-holders do.”</l>
          </lg>
          <p>Let us unite in prayer:</p>
          <p>“Supremely great, and worthy of all adoration art Thou, O 
Lord, our heavenly Father. The cattle upon a thousand 
hills, and the negroes in a thousand fields are Thine. We 
<pb id="robinson82" n="82"/>
thank Thee, Lord, for the manifold blessings with which Thou 
art supplying us, Thine humble and obedient servants, notwithstanding 
our merits deserve them all, for Thou hast said 
the righteous shall enjoy the good of the land. Now, Lord, 
we have not much time to pray, for Thou see'st how those 
devilish slaves are squandering away their time. Lord, revive 
Thy work in our midst. Grant us all a large increase 
of slaves for the traders this fall, that we may obtain the 
means, through Thy well directed providence, to rear Thee a 
magnificent temple in which Thou wilt love to dwell, and 
where Thou wilt love to pour out Thy spirit upon Thy Zion. 
O! Lord God, when we go into the fields among those ignorant, 
hard headed creatures, (over whom Thou hast made us 
to rule), may Thy glory so shine in our countenances that 
one of us shall subdue a thousand, and bind ten thousand 
upon the racks from the ungovernable malice of enraged 
negroes. Deliver us from the influence of a guilty conscience; 
deliver us from the abolition creeds, and from the slanderous 
tongues of enthusiastic politicians. Deliver us from insurrections 
and perplexity of minds, good Lord, deliver us. Give 
us and our dogs our daily bread, and our negroes their full 
pecks of parched corn or cotton seeds per week. Strengthen 
the horse and his rider, and make the limbs of the fugitive 
weak. Confound the cunning schemes of anti-slavery men. 
Bless the government which Thou didst redeem from the 
British yoke of oppression, and didst wash and make clean by 
the precious blood of the heroes of '76. Bless the star 
spangled banner, which floats over the land of the free and 
the home of the brave. May her stars increase in number 
and brightness, and eagle's wings be extended o'er all the 
virgin soil of our continent until his beak shall pick the fugitive 
from his lurking places in the cold regions of British 
<pb id="robinson83" n="83"/>
America, while his tail shall overshadow the slaves in Yucatan. 
And may his pinions cast their pleasant shade over all the 
free born sons of America, from Providence to Monterey, 
while he shall bear in his mighty talons, for ages to come, 
four millions of ignorant slaves with all their posterity. Hear 
us, good Lord, and according to Thy manifold mercies, bless 
and sanctify us. Give us more than we are able to ask for at 
this time, and in the end save all the white people who have 
supported Thy holy institution and performed Thy will, 
through Jesus Christ, our Redeemer, Amen.”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>SLAVE HOLDERS' CONSISTENT FAMILY WORSHIP.</head>
          <head>THE SLAVE HOLDERS' HYMN TO BE SUNG AT EVENING 
PRAYERS.  (Short Metre.)</head>
          <lg>
            <l>“A charge to keep I have,</l>
            <l>A negro to maintain.</l>
            <l>Help me, O Lord, whilst here I live,</l>
            <l>To keep him bound in chain.</l>
            <l>We thank Thee, Lord, for grace </l>
            <l>That's brought us safe this far,</l>
            <l>While many of our dying race</l>
            <l>Were summoned to Thy bar. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>No negroes have I lost  -   </l>
            <l>Not one has run away. </l>
            <l>I have been faithful to my trust </l>
            <l>Through this, another day. </l>
            <l>Lord, we cannot lie down </l>
            <l>Till we implore Thy grace, </l>
            <l>For if we do a mighty frown </l>
            <l>Will cover o'er Thy face. </l>
            <pb id="robinson84" n="84"/>
            <l>Draw nigh, just now, O Lord,</l>
            <l>And listen while we pray,</l>
            <l>And each petition  -  every word, </l>
            <l>Pray Answer and Obey.</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>SLAVE-HOLDERS' CONSISTENT SERMON.</head>
          <p>Copied from imagination's parchment roll, where this, and 
many other things, have been on perpetual record from childhood. 
Ficticious, as it is, and as ridiculous as it may appear, 
I defy any minister, white or black, who preaches to the slaves 
in the south, to preach any better doctrines and have his 
preaching harmonize with the institution of slavery. The 
whole sentiment is consistent with slavery, and the old experienced 
southerner will read many things in this discourse 
which he has heard before. This is preached more generally 
on the Sabbath, previous to the usual holidays by the 
“Rt. Rev. Bishop Policy.”</p>
          <p>“Well, darkies, I am happy to see so many shining eyes, 
and greasy faces today. It speaks two great truths; first, that 
you are all awake to your own welfare; and secondly, that 
your masters treated you well and gave you meat. You have 
come out today to hear the word of God. I hope you will 
pay strict attention to what is said, and treasure it up in good 
and honest hearts. My text is not taken directly from the 
Bible, that is, not our Bible, but yours. We all respect your 
Bible more than we do the white man's Bible, or otherwise 
the word of God, for your Bible you can obey, but ours you 
cannot. The text is recorded in the laws of Maryland, A. 
D. 1715, Chapter 44, Section 22. “All negroes and other 
<pb id="robinson85" n="85"/>
slaves already imported, or hereafter to be imported into this 
province, and all children born, or hereafter to be born of 
such negroes and slaves, shall be slaves during their natural 
lives.” In the first place, I shall show God's wisdom displayed 
in the system of slavery. Second, the master's great 
responsibility. Third and last, the consequence of disobedience. 
God's wisdom is displayed in the system of 
slavery. The text declares positively that you shall all be 
slaves during your natural lives. What a great blessing God 
has brought to you, my colored friends, through the economy 
of His divine grace. A greater blessing never was conferred 
on mortals. From the birth of Adam until the present day 
we are taught in our Bible that God wrought miracles upon 
the Egyptians  -  brought the children of Israel over the Red 
Sea  -  preserved them in the wilderness in safety. But by 
and by they entered into the land of Canaan, a land of 
freedom, and immediately they began to have trouble and 
discord. But you, my colored friends, have been prepared  
with a perpetual home through life. You are as trees planted 
by the river of waters, whose branches fail not. O that you 
might praise the Lord for his goodness and for His wonderful 
works toward you black people.</p>
          <p>Again, God's wisdom is displayed in the institution of 
slavery, in its great plan of perpetuating the negro race. 
“The white men, the masterpiece of God's creation.” when 
tracing nature through various windings, while the good Samaritans 
were seeking upon the face of God's earth for 
objects of pity and compassion, somehow, very mysteriously, 
were wafted by the kind breezes of heaven to the burning 
shores of Africa. There they found the sooty tribes of 
that hot climate very much degraded. At first they scarcely 
knew what to call them; they so much resembled the <sic>orangoutang</sic> 
<pb id="robinson86" n="86"/>
as to cause a great controversy among God's people. 
Finally they were seen to bow with reverence and adore an 
image of their own making. Again, they were seen warring, 
slaying and eating each other, and sacrificing one another by 
thousands to their <sic>deities</sic>. </p>
          <p>This disposition was so much like that of the low class of 
whites that they felt the spirit of pity and compassion move 
towards those poor God forsaken creatures, and a plan 
was immediately formed for their protection and elevation. 
They were at once taken on board ship, kindly treated, 
and safely brought to America, where they were put in the 
care of kind men who provided for them, clothed and fed 
them, and comforted them in sickness and in health. And 
here you have been until the present day. Now you can see  
what God has done for you in instituting this system of 
slavery. You were found an ignorant set, no top on your 
heads  -  and it is doubtful whether you had any soul  -  more 
than the apes that played around you. But through the 
economy of God's grace you have been transplanted upon 
American soil, and through much toil on the part of the 
white man, you are becoming quite intelligent. The white 
man, through amalgamation, has not only imparted to you 
his straight hair, high nose, blue eyes, thin lips and perfect 
form, but it is to be hoped that you have a soul much resembling 
his, which will, by his care and attention, and your 
obedience to his precepts, stand a great chance to be admitted 
upon the ground floor of God's glorious temple in 
heaven  -  this is better than a thousand lives in Africa, and 
who would despise his chains, which are but for a moment, 
and then passeth away  -  for the blessings which flow out of 
the system of slavery. The text declares that you shall be 
slaves your natural lives, which may signify that it is your 
<pb id="robinson87" n="87"/>
nature to be slaves. That is, that you are created to be servants 
of the white man, and all the children to be born of 
you are to be slaves. Yes, Susan, that little blue-eyed boy 
you are now trotting upon your knee  -  the express 
image of his young master Thomas, is to be a slave, and 
should you ever see the least disposition of his young master 
exciting his aspirations to freedom, you must crush that disposition 
immediately, and repeat to him the language of the 
text. </p>
          <p>Again God's wisdom is displayed in making you with 
strong constitutions. See what large, robust, fat, greasy 
looking fellows you all are. See what clear, white teeth you 
have. Just look at me. See what a puny, slender, delicate, 
pale looking creature I am, my teeth all decayed. I could 
not crack parched corn and cotton seeds and get fat like you 
all do. If I should take a hoe or pitchfork in my hands they 
would be soiled, and if I should work an hour they would be 
blistered so badly that I could not correct a slave again for a 
month. Just look at my hand now. The other day I took 
hold of a rough cowhide without my gloves on, and gave a 
young impudent wench, who told my wife something, forty 
lashes, and it raised this great blister you see. I was never 
made to work. Look at those great, broad-sided, good, 
healthy looking wenches sitting before me. What arms they 
have. Any of them can work from daylight until dark in 
the field, when the sun is so hot that the overseer has to ride 
under an umbrella, and your mistress would almost faint just 
walking out in the garden. Thus, you can plainly see that 
God has not made the white man to work. He is only to 
think, plead law, make laws, preach, pray, and carry the gospel 
to the heathen, and superintend God's works, while the 
blacks were made to do the hard and dirty work. For this 
<pb id="robinson88" n="88"/>
they hard constitutions peculiarly adapted. But again; God's 
wisdom is further displayed in the economy of slavery by 
creating you void of natural affections, as regards family 
sociability, and maternal and parental love for your husbands, 
wives and children. Therefore, our conscience is void of offense 
toward God or you negroes, when we separate the husbands 
from their wives and children, for it is for the purpose 
of rearing up fine temples for the glory of God and his Kingdom. </p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson89" n="89"/>
      <div1 type="image">
        <p>
          <figure id="ill8" entity="ill8">
            <p>ABRAHAM LINCOLN,<lb/>Emancipator of over four and a half million slaves; elected President November, 1860; assassinated April 12, 1865, by Wilkes Booth.</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson90" n="90"/>
      <div1 type="image">
        <p>
          <figure id="ill9" entity="ill9">
            <p>THE LINCOLN LOG CABIN.<lb/>The above engraving is from a photograph of the Lincoln cabin, taken especially for this book, Decoration day, May 30, 1907. The picture shows the cabin just as it stands today on the old Lincoln farm in Hardin Co., Ky.</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson91" n="91"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER XVI.</head>
        <lg>
          <head>THE SORROW OF PARTING CHILD.</head>
          <l>O, tell me papa, when mother dies,</l>
          <l>Will she come home again?</l>
          <l>Or will we meet above the skies,</l>
          <l>Where Christ the Savior reigns?</l>
          <l>Would you not like to die tonight,</l>
          <l>If mother, too, would die? </l>
          <l>And with sweet angels dressed in white,</l>
          <l>Meet her above the sky?</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <head>FATHER.</head>
          <l>O, yes, my child, my life is dear, </l>
          <l>And you I love full well; </l>
          <l>But I no longer can tarry here,</l>
          <l>I soon will bid this world farewell; </l>
          <l>I cannot live, my heart is broke,</l>
          <l>My grief is more than I can bear; </l>
          <l>This very strap and that great oak;</l>
          <l>Will end my life in deep despair.</l>
        </lg>
        <p>Early Friday morning, April 12, 1861, I took my 
master to Wilmington. On the way we stopped and 
took in another man. As we neared Wilmington we 
could hear the booming of cannons, for the rebels had 
fired upon Ft. Sumter, and we could hear the echo of 
the guns as it came down the Cape Fear river and was 
<pb id="robinson92" n="92"/>
borne out on the broad bosom of the Atlantic. My 
master, in great excitement, slapped his hands together, 
and with an oath, said, “its come.” Both of them 
grew deathly pale, and looked at each other as though 
they were surprised. My master hastily wrote a short 
note, sealed it and gave it to me, with directions to 
hurry home, cautioning me very particularly not to 
stop until I reached home and delivered the note to his 
wife. </p>
        <p>I saw that every white man in Wilmington was 
greatly agitated and wore a look of anxiety. In a 
moment everything that had been told me by the 
Yankee soldiers, and by the underground railroad men, 
flashed in my mind; for many of them had told me 
that I would some day be free, and we looked forward 
to that day with great expectations.</p>
        <p>I drove as fast as I could to the five mile farm, 
which was in charge of the colored overseer. Uncle 
Tom could read and write, and I wanted to know what 
was in the note. I had many times slipped him the 
newspapers from the house, and carried them back 
early the next morning before master called for them, 
and he taught me to listen carefully to every conversation 
held between the white people. I drove up to the 
fence, where fifty or sixty men and women worked in 
the field. I could hear them singing and shouting, for 
they too, had heard the booming of the cannon, and 
Uncle Tom had told them that that was a token of 
liberty. But when they saw the old “carry-all” drive 
up, each one ran to his or her work; the overseer came 
to the carriage, supposing master wanted to see him, 
<pb id="robinson93" n="93"/>
but to his surprise master was not there. He called 
the slaves around and had me explain how master acted 
at the sound of the guns, then he made a speech to 
them, telling them to pray as they had never prayed 
before. I gave him the note I had for mistress; he 
looked at the envelope, studied for a moment, 
rubbed his head, and then thoroughly wet the seal; he opened 
the letter and read it. The letter read as follows:</p>
        <p>“We have fired on Fort Sumter. I may possibly be 
called away to help whip the Yankees; may be gone 
three days, but not longer than that. You write a note 
and send William to Sawyer, [that is the overseer on 
the farm where we live] and tell him to keep a very 
close watch on the negroes, and see that there's no 
private talk among them. Have Martin, the overseer's 
son, aid you, and if Elliott or Fuller come on the 
place, give them no opportunity to talk with the 
negroes. </p>
        <p>Your husband, JOE COWENS.”</p>
        <p>(This Fuller referred to in the note is the son of the 
Fuller mentioned in a previous chapter, and who was 
murdered because he was suspected of being connected 
with the underground railroad, and also of aiding my 
father, who had already partially paid for his freedom, 
trying to get away.)</p>
        <p>After reading the note Uncle Tom told me to drive 
back and go around by the Salisbury road. This took 
me nearly two miles out of the way, but in the middle 
of this road was a large mud puddle. He told me to 
<pb id="robinson94" n="94"/>
drive in there, very fast, then get out and wade in the 
water, and get the envelope wet and muddy. He 
showed me how to smear It over with my hands so 
mistress would not detect that it had been opened. He 
also showed me how to make saliva or crocodile tears. 
He said mistress would be on the porch watching for 
me, and that I should pretend to cry, at the same time 
get the envelope from my pocket, handing it to her 
with the left hand. She would take it with her right 
hand, tear it open and drop the envelope on the 
ground. As soon as she was gone I was to pick it up 
and destroy it. Mr. Fuller was in the house, having 
come to see master on business, so when mistress heard 
the carriage coming she came to the big gate to meet 
it, thinking master was returning, and left Mr. Fuller 
in the house. When I saw her coming I made some 
crocodile tears by wetting my fingers with saliva. 
As soon as she saw that master was not with me, she 
came rushing to the buggy and found me shedding 
tears as fast as I could. In a very tender tone, with 
her hand upon my head, she asked me what was the 
matter. At this I broke down completely and cried 
aloud, at the same time feeling in my pocket for the 
envelope, and telling my sad story, between sobs, of 
how I had dropped it in the mud hole. She eagerly 
grasped it and tore it open, not noticing that it had 
ever been opened before, and patting me on the head, 
she said, “hush, mistress can read it.” That instantly 
healed my pretended broken heart and dried up my 
manufactured tears.</p>
        <p>She started for the house, forgetting she had not 
<pb id="robinson95" n="95"/>
cautioned me, so she came back and told me “that Mr. 
Fuller was in the house, and for me not to mention 
anything to him or any one on the place, concerning 
the cannon firing.” She then wrote a note and gave it 
to me to take to Mr. Sawyer. She had dropped the envelope 
and I was glad when she was out of sight. 
Picking up the envelope I put it in my mouth, chewed 
it up, removed a harness peg, put the pulp in the hole, 
and replaced the peg. If the old barn is still standing
the envelope is there yet. I took the note to Mr. 
Sawyer and in a short time he was at the house in close 
consultation with her. Then he went after his son 
Martin, and they both went over to five mile farm, 
where Uncle Tom was overseer. She wrote another 
note to Mr. Bailey, a poor white man living about a 
mile away, and he came at once and took charge of our 
farm. He was once overseer on our place , but was so 
cruel that massa discharged him. So now he served 
as an extra two or three days at a time for the different 
overseers in the community, for which he received 
seventy-five cents per day, and what he could get the 
slaves to steal for him, for notwithstanding their inhumanity 
to the slaves, they kept up a constant trade 
with them. They stole their master's corn, wheat, 
chickens, hogs, etc., and carried them to the overseer,
for which he would give them a little flour, and occasionally 
a dime or two, and very often when he was 
about to whip them he would let them off by their 
promising to bring him some meat or chickens. 
Master came home that night, and after supper five or 
six of the leading men from Wilmington came. After 
<pb id="robinson96" n="96"/>
I brought in the demijohn, glasses and water, master 
told me that I could go to bed, because he would want 
me to go away with him early the next day. But 
instead of going to bed I pulled off my shoes, tip-toed 
down stairs and peeped through the keyhole, and not 
making an exception to the rule, my ear did its share 
of listening. They got into a hot discussion, and I 
heard one of them say, “if the Yankees whipped, 
every negro would be free.” I became satisfied that 
the negro was the bone of contention, and that the 
light of liberty was probably about to dawn, so I went 
to bed. </p>
        <p>On the morning of April 15th, 1861, I left home 
with my master to go to the war and whip the Yankees 
in three days; I carried a club for the first three days 
to knock off Yankees' horns with, for my master told 
me that they had horns. We were gone more than 
three months; we didn't whip them, but were gaining 
a victory in every battle that was fought, and this was 
encouraging to the rebels. You could hear the southern 
ladies singing “Old Lincoln and his hireling 
troops would never whip the South.” We came home 
on a week's furlough, then returned to be gone six 
months, but before the expiration of the six months, 
my master was killed by a shell bursting at Greenville, 
Tennessee, near the place where John Morgan was 
killed. </p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson97" n="97"/>
      <div1 type="image">
        <p>
          <figure id="ill10" entity="ill10">
            <p>W. H. ROBINSON, a captured colored servant, taking the oath of allegiance, dressed in a Rebel General's uniform, before General Thomas. This was but one of the Union soldiers' jokes played on us.</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson98" n="98"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER XVII.</head>
        <p>At first the northern people were chagrined and disheartened. 
Then came a renewed determination. 
They saw the real character of the war, and no longer 
dreamed that the south could be subdued by a mere 
display of military force. They were to fight a brave 
people  -  Americans  -  who were to be conquered only 
by a desperate struggle. During the first year of the 
war the Confederates had captured the large arsenals 
at Harper's Ferry, near Norfolk. They had been 
successful in the two great battles of the year  -  Bull 
Run and Wilson's Creek; also in the minor engagements 
at Big Bethel, Carthage, Lexington, Belmont, 
and Ball's Bluff. The Federals had saved Fort Pickens 
and Fort Monroe, and captured the forts at Hatteras 
Inlet and Port Royal. They had gained the victories 
of Phillippi, Rich Mountain, Boonville, Carricks' 
Ford, Cheat Mountain, Carnifex Ferry and Danville. 
They had saved for the union, Missouri, Maryland, 
and West Virginia. Principally, however, they 
had thrown the whole south into a state of siege  -  the 
armies on the north and the west by land, and the 
navy in the east by sea, maintaining a vigilant blockade.</p>
        <p>After the death of my master I remained as cook 
for the company until November, 1863, when at Blue 
Springs, Tennessee, Generals Thomas and Burnside 
<pb id="robinson99" n="99"/>
routed Hood and Forrest, after a short contest; and in 
the retreat, I, with many others, was captured. I was 
with the cooks' brigade. There were about fifty of us, 
and each one was riding one of those long eared fellows, 
that lean against the fence and say, “I have no 
one to love me.” </p>
        <p>In the retreat we had quite a deep ditch, or gully, to 
cross. My animal was heavily loaded with camp kettles, 
tin pans and kitchen utensils in general. When 
the cavalry got to this ditch they commanded their 
horses to mount, and the horses leaped over, but I 
suspect in the excitement I forgot to give the necessary 
commands, for my long eared friend's fore feet reached 
the other shore safely, but his hind feet fell short 
of the mark, and down in the ditch we went; such a 
scramble you never saw. But I found that there were 
many rebel soldiers in there, who were tired of the 
Yankee lead and wanted to be captured. I was 
scrambling to get out, but they told me to lie still, and 
in a few moments Yankee soldiers  -  both cavalry and 
infantry, seemed to have popped up out of the earth; 
while some pursued the fleeing rebels, others took us 
to the general's headquarters. The rebels were sent 
to the northern prisons, and the cooks and colored servants 
that had been captured, were next brought before 
General Thomas and disposed of. I was the last 
man in the line, and when I came before the general, 
his first words to me were, “you're a fine looking fellow. 
Here we are fighting to free you and you are 
here dressed up in a suit of rebel uniform.” He then 
called his cook  -  a quaint looking, cross-eyed old man, 
<pb id="robinson100" n="100"/>
who like myself, was “hewn out of a slab of ebony.” 
He said, “Nathan, what shall we do with this boy?” 
“Hang him to the highest tree we can find,” said 
Nathan. “Well, bring me the best rope you can find.” 
Nathan obeyed. He came with a rope as large around 
as his wrist, and about twenty feet long. The general 
asked him if he thought that would hold me; he 
answered in the affirmative, and General Thomas told 
him to throw it over the limb of a tall oak which stood 
near by. But an officer by the name of Lane rode up 
and said: “General, maybe this boy will take the 
oath of allegiance.” I would have taken most anything 
about this time. Then the general inquired of 
me if I would take the oath. I told him I would. By 
this time some one said, “hold up your right hand.” 
Another said, “hold up your left hand,” 
another said, “your right foot,” and another said, “your left 
foot.” I obeyed orders as fast as they were given 
until it came to the left foot. I had up all I could 
possibly get up. After having all the fun the, wanted 
with me, the general told Nathan to take me back 
and wash and clean me up. Uncle Nathan took me to 
his tent, where he had a kettle of boiling water. It 
looked as if he were going to scald a hog; then began 
the washing process. After the old man had rubbed 
and washed me until my flesh burned, and I had put 
on a castaway suit of General Thomas', I went to 
headquarters. After standing before the large mirror 
in the general's tent. I thought I was the richest, 
freest man in America. They had carried the joke to 
such an extent  -  for I really thought they were going 
<pb id="robinson101" n="101"/>
to hang me  -  that I was sick. They administered 
some medicine to me and I lay down across the general's 
bed, General Thomas himself having told me to. 
When I awoke about 3 p. m. I was between the two 
generals, Burnside and Thomas. When I moved towards 
one he would crowd against me, and if I moved 
towards the other he would crowd in, until I was 
squeezed as tightly as possible between the two. They 
were both awake, and I could feel their sides heaving 
until they could not restrain their laughter any longer, 
then General Thomas said, “lie still boy, this white 
won't rub off.” This was my first day of freedom. </p>
        <p>General Thomas questioned me concerning my parents, 
and on learning that my mother was in Greenville, 
<sic>Tennesse</sic>, he said; “you will see her within three 
days if the rebels don't whip us.” Accordingly we 
left Blue Springs that day enroute to Madison Court 
House, Virginia. which brought us through Greenville 
where mother was. It was hard to prevent me 
from being the advance guard. For two days they 
were trying to hold me back, until we finally reached 
Greenville, and I saw the house in which mother lived. 
Seeing that no rebels were near, the officers allowed 
me to advance. Before I reached the house I saw 
mother and my Jewish mistress, Mrs. Hadley, standing 
on the porch. Everybody seemed very much excited, 
and the rebel army was retreating. </p>
        <p>Having changed my uniform from the rebel gray to 
the Yankee blue, my mother did not recognize me 
until I was at the gate; then she came running and 
shouting “this is William.” I was saying in one 
<pb id="robinson102" n="102"/> 
breath  -  not waiting for one question to be answered 
before I asked another, “how are you?” I am free, 
are you? Get ready to go to the Yankees; has master 
the same black horse and buggy?” She told me he 
had. I told her to go pack up while I hitched the 
horse to the buggy. When I returned to the house 
the soldiers had surrounded it and asked me where my 
mother was. I ran up stairs. tried to open mother's 
door, when she informed me that Massa  Jake had 
locked her in. The soldiers were hurrying me to get 
my mother and come on  I told them Massa had 
locked her in, and one of them gave me an ax and 
told me to break the door open. I told mother to 
stand back from the door. At the same time Massa  
Jake came in with a shot gun in his hand, but before 
he could raise it dozens of muskets were aimed at him. 
By this time I had the door open, and there stood 
mother with a rope around the bureau, and every loose 
article she could get hold of was wrapped in her straw 
tick, all tied up ready for moving. She was expecting 
to move the whole cargo in a buggy.</p>
        <p>I had her unpack as quickly as possible and gather 
up her clothes and little keepsakes, so we could be 
out of the yard as soon as possible. I shall never forget 
the courtesy shown mother by two or three soldiers, 
in helping her in the buggy. Being all ready, 
and our buggy placed in line with the other contrabands  -   
for there were between one hundred anti fifty 
and two hundred wagons, mule carts, pack horses, 
mules and even <sic>milch</sic> cows, we started on our journey.</p>
        <p>Most of the southern men had gone to war, and  
<pb id="robinson103" n="103"/> 
those who were too old to go had taken the women and 
gone to the cities, leaving the farms and country homes 
virtually in charge of the colored people. I had an 
uncle who was left in charge of a farm three miles 
from town. We passed by his place on our way to 
Virginia, and when we came in sight of the farm we 
could see colored people by the hundreds, who had 
gathered from other farms. The news spread like 
wild fire all over the country that the Yankees had 
come. </p>
        <p>The “great house” was kept furnished the year 
round and left in the colored overseer's charge, because 
the family would come back and forth, sometimes 
staying weeks at a time. The veranda was filled 
with men, women and children, singing, shouting and 
praising God in the highest. I hastened into the yard 
and was soon the center of attraction. Uncle Isaac 
was soon by my side, picking me up and carrying me 
around, shouting at the top of his voice, while I was 
struggling to get down, and trying to drown his voice 
so I could tell him that he was free, and to pack up at 
once and go with us. </p>
        <p>I was inviting him to liberty, yet I had not a shelter 
in all the world to put my head save the canopy of 
Heaven. But I had heard of a country where all men 
were free, and like Bunyan's Pilgrim I had started to 
make it my home.</p>
        <p>I finally succeeded in loosing myself from his strong 
embrace, and then I made a short speech to all, telling 
them to hitch their ox and mule carts, and load up 
their things and go to the Yankees. There was considerable 
<pb id="robinson104" n="104"/>
fear about their doing as I said, until 
some of the soldiers appeared, and helped to dispel this 
fear by confirming what I had said. It was not long 
until the yard was fairly lined with wagons, carts and 
every conceivable beast of burden. They began to 
tear down their old bedsteads, built against the walls 
of their cabins, and gather up their rude furniture, 
when the Yankees asked what was in the “great house.” 
On learning that it was furnished they demanded that 
it be opened, and that the people take everything 
they wanted and load their wagons. My uncle had 
the key but refused to open the door, saying “that 
belongs to old Master.” Fifteen or twenty soldiers 
then seized a huge log of wood and broke the door 
down. </p>
        <p>'Twas but a few minutes until the great place was 
gutted. The piano was the only piece of furniture 
remaining, and some women wanted to take that for 
their girls when they became educated. Now the wagons 
were loaded to their utmost capacity. I can't afford 
to spoil a good joke because of race, color or 
nationality. Then the children were put on, and it 
seems to me now that the mothers must have taken 
some kind of paste and put on the backs of the children, 
so as to stick them up against the furniture. They 
were so thick around the wagons it seemed there was 
not a spot left where there was not a baby. They 
were of all sizes and colors; they were black, dark 
brown, pumpkin colored, yellow and half white. And 
they were all crying with a different voice, giving different 
tunes to the song they were singing. It was 
<pb id="robinson105" n="105"/>
certainly a menagerie when the procession left the 
farm. Some of the babies were crying alto, some 
soprano, some bass, but most of them baritone  -  because 
it was bare of all music.</p>
        <p>Of course all of our masters were honorable, and 
these children were all called by their master's name  -   
but they didn't call them papa all the time. Many of 
their mothers were as honorable as a woman could be 
under the circumstances, but many times in order to 
save their backs from being lacerated they obeyed the 
command of their master, and their commands were 
not always honorable. </p>
        <p>The soldiers now moved forward toward Knoxville, 
Tennessee. We had four or five hundred men, women 
and children in this great march from a land of servitude 
to a land of liberty. Sometimes like Pharaoh of 
old, the old masters would pursue their slaves, and 
even come into the camp but the slaves' fears would 
soon be dispelled by the stern command of some Yankee 
soldier or officer, who would order the <sic>rebs</sic> to 
leave the camp. Many times they subjected them to 
some humiliating treatment  -  such as riding the rail 
horse, or carrying a barrel up the hill and rolling it 
down again, and they would continue this process for 
hours. After skirmishing for a week or ten days we 
arrived at Knoxville, Tennessee, where we sold the 
horses, mules, oxen, buggies and wagons to General 
Thomas. I bought an old log cabin on the old battle 
field for my mother. I was to give seventeen dollars 
for this property. I could count from one to fifty, 
but I could not tell the denominations; I didn't know a 
<pb id="robinson106" n="106"/>
ten dollar bill from a one; so I counted out seventeen 
bills and paid for the place. Later I learned that I 
had paid some forty or fifty dollars for it. </p>
        <p>About this time, in 1863, Frederick Douglas went 
to Washington to see President Lincoln, telling him 
“that our people were digging breast works, exposed 
to the shot and shell, and why not give them guns and 
let them have a hand in freeing themselves and saving 
the union.” Lincoln's reply was that the feeling at 
the north was running so high he didn't know what 
the result would be, for no measure of the war was 
more bitterly opposed than the project of arming 
slaves. It was denounced at the north, and the confederate 
congress passed a law which threatened with 
death any white officer captured while in command of 
negro troops, leaving the men to be dealt with according 
to the laws of the state in which they were taken. 
Douglas said he returned home, but slept little that 
night, for he continually called on God to in some way 
bring peace out of the confusion, and open the way 
for colored men to get on the field of battle as enlisted 
soldiers. The next morning by nine o'clock Douglas 
said he was at the capitol and closeted with the president. 
To his surprise Lincoln told him that Grant 
had sent for a division of colored soldiers. Lincoln 
commissioned Douglas as recruiting officer, and sent 
him to Boston Massachusetts, where he mustered in 
the 54th and 55th colored regiments. These were the 
first colored regiments organized in the free states.</p>
        <p>Col. Shaw led the 54th regiment in its first battle at 
Fort Wagner. After keeping us in reserve for three 
<pb id="robinson107" n="107"/>
hours while the union soldiers were falling like Wheat 
before the sharpened sickle, Col. Shaw asked to lead 
the black phalanx into the battle, notwithstanding he 
knew it meant certain death to him if he was captured, 
the confederates having said they would not take any 
union soldier prisoner who was in command of colored 
troops, for they did not recognize the colored men as 
citizens or soldiers, therefore would not consider them 
or their leaders as prisoners of war. Col. Shaw sent 
his orderly back to the wagon train. He returned in 
a few moments and handed the Colonel a bundle, which 
contained a regimental silk flag with the inscription, 
“To the 54th Colored Regiment, Robert G. Shaw, 
Colonel. Presented by the White Ladies of Boston, 
Massachusetts.” Our regiment went wild at the sight 
of the flag. They carried Col. Shaw up and down the 
line on their shoulders, cheering like mad. As he 
handed the flag to Carney, the flag bearer, the Colonel 
said, “Carney, will you return this flag to us in honor?” 
His answer was, “Colonel, I will do so or report to 
God the reason I do not.” The roll was called and 
twelve hundred men and officers answered to their 
names. The battle was on. Our gallant Colonel's side 
was torn by a shell a few moments after. His dying words 
were, “boys, don't let the flag go down.” His body 
never touched the ground, being borne to the rear by 
his colored troops, one of whom was instantly killed. 
His place was immediately filled by another. Carney's 
right arm was shot off during the battle. As he fell, 
holding the flag with his left hand and in his teeth, he 
shouted, “boys, don't let the flag go down.” 
<pb id="robinson108" n="108"/> 
When the roll was called after the battle seventy-seven 
had answered to their last roll call, having fallen defending 
the flag and fighting for their liberty. Colonel 
Shaw was buried with his many black soldiers who lost 
their lives in this fierce battle. </p>
        <p>At one time, in order to be in season for an assault, 
these regiments marched two days through heavy 
sands and drenching storms. After only five minutes 
rest, we took our place at the front of the attacking 
column. The men fought with unflinching gallantry, 
and planted their flags. So willing were the negroes 
to enlist, and so faithful did they prove themselves in 
service, that in December, 1863, over fifty thousand 
had been enrolled, and before the close of the war that 
number was quadrupled.</p>
        <p>I recognized then that I was to take part in one of 
the greatest wars of modern times. The war of the 
rebellion was now on, when the numbers engaged in it, 
and the extent of territory affected are considered. It 
was primarily a war based on sentiment. The long, 
but peaceful and prayerful contest of the abolitionist 
against the slave power, and the earnest and faithful 
prayer of the slave himself, all crowded the throne of 
a just God, and had aroused the whole country, so 
that everywhere, in every state in the union, there was 
a sharp division of opinion among the people. It is 
true always, however, that God makes the wrath of 
man to serve him, and out of the wear of the rebellion 
the slave fought his way to freedom. What a glorious 
record the Afro-American made in that war! It is one 
of the brightest pages in all history. In the early  
<pb id="robinson109" n="109"/>
stages of the war he was not even allowed to drive the 
teams, to dig trenches or to throw up breastworks for 
the union army. Tile soldiers of the north declared 
that this was a white man's war, and that sentiment 
had made it very difficult for the government at Washington 
to call for colored troops, but before the close 
of the war he was a regularly enlisted soldier in all the 
departments, to the number of 200,000, and had fought 
with such valor, such heroism, from Fort Wagner to 
Fort Fisher, from New Market Heights to Petersburg, 
that when the victorious union army at last marched 
into Richmond, the fallen and deserted capitol of the 
lost cause, he was accorded the first place of honor at 
the head of the column! Thirty six years afterwards 
Colonel Theodore Roosevelt, of the rough riders, commented 
on the bravery of the black soldiers after the 
brilliant charge of a successful capture of San Juan 
Hill. Thirty six years after Colonel Robert Gould 
Shaw was buried with his negroes, in the sands of 
Morris Island, the world has looked with enthusiasm 
upon the heroic deeds and gallantry of the negro soldier, 
and today he is filling his station from West Point,
the military center of the world, to the navy that plows 
the distant seas and watches the gate way to this nation. 
This fact is demonstrated when you recall to memory 
the 25th of January, 1898, when the battleship Maine 
steamed into the harbor of Havana. She went there 
on an errand of peace, the representative of a friendly 
power. On the 15th of February the Maine was 
blown to atoms by a floating mine, together with 
two hundred sixty-six American sailors, of whom more 
than thirty were negroes.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson110" n="110"/>
      <div1 type="image">
        <p>
          <figure id="ill11" entity="ill11">
            <p>THE HEROES</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <lg type="verse">
          <head>THE HEROES</head>
          <byline>By Stuart Maclean</byline>
          <l>Bring laurel and myrtle, oak and bay,</l>
          <l>And wreaths of roses, white and gold,</l>
          <l>And drape their graves on this holy day</l>
          <l>With the flag they loved in the days of old;</l>
          <l>For the red is the red of the blood they gave,</l>
          <l>The white is the smoke of the belching gun,</l>
          <l>And the blue is the blue of the sky they clave</l>
          <l>To gain the stars in the crowns they won.</l>
        </lg>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson111" n="111"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER XVIII.</head>
        <p>In 1864, near Blue Springs, Tennessee, three union 
soldiers became separated from their army, and when 
passing through a small oak grove one of them got 
into the quicksand. The others, supposing their companion 
was closely following them, pursued their 
course. </p>
        <p>This poor hero was left behind, struggling for his 
life in the quicksand, for three days and nights, buoying 
himself up from sinking, with the aid of such sticks 
and brush as he could reach. This location was but a 
short distance from a large southern mansion. The 
men had all gone to war and there were left but a few 
old colored mothers to protect the old mistress.</p>
        <p>Aunt Nancy Jordan dreamed one night, or saw a 
vision, as she termed it, that she saw a man in trouble 
near the springs, and that she heard a voice saying: 
“Nancy, go to the east spring.” She claimed to have 
heard that call three different times that night in her 
dreams, and early the next morning she took her pail 
and went to the spring. When near the place, she 
heard a human voice pleading for help. She then 
realized her dream or presentiment, and on looking saw 
union soldier buried to his armpits in the quicksand. 
She knew just what it meant, and started toward 
him. He murmured for her not to come too 
close. Her reply was “God bless you chile, I knows 
<pb id="robinson112" n="112"/>
all about dis place.” She felt her way as close to him 
as possible, or until she felt the quicksand giving way 
under her, then she gathered brush and bridged her way 
over to him, or near enough to reach him with a 
long handled gourd. She then went to the spring, 
which was not over twenty feet away, and secured 
water for him, as his tongue was so badly swollen that 
he could scarcely speak. She held the gourd to his 
lips, slaked his thirst, and then began the work of 
rescue, piling brush around him. She then got hold 
of his arms and assisted him out so that he could sit 
upon the brush. </p>
        <p>That spring was never used by the people from the 
mansion on account of the quicksand, and alkali in the 
water. Nancy returned to the house with her pail of 
water, then hurried back with food in the pail upon 
her head. In this way she fed him for three weeks, 
at the end of which time one morning she heard the 
tramp, tramp of a mighty army. Bands were playing 
and bugles sounding.  Then she saw old Missie 
 scampering for the cellar, for, said she: “Nancy, 
they are Lincoln's hirelings, for they are all dressed 
in blue.” Aunt Nancy hurried to the spring and told 
the soldier that the Yankees were coming. He at once 
came from his hiding place. When he reached the 
yard of that mansion he found it swarming with union 
soldiers. He said to Aunt Nancy, “I can't leave you 
here, for you must go with us.” She replied: “I 
promised old master not to leave old missie till he 
comes back from de wah.” But he assured her that it 
meant her freedom, and asked if she had not prayed to 
<pb id="robinson113" n="113"/>
be free? She replied: “Yas sah,” and that if it 
meant her freedom she would bid old missie good bye.</p>
        <p>There was a pathetic scene at this parting. Old 
mistress ventured to the porch and took her last long 
look at her old ex-slave, as the Yankee soldier was 
helping her into the wagon.</p>
        <p>Aunt Nancy became cook in the camp for the officers,  
and this soldier, whom she had rescued, looked after 
her as though she were his mother. He was an 
Englishman, and had come to this country about the 
time of the beginning of the war. He naturalized and 
enlisted. When he was discharged he took Aunt 
Nancy to England with him and presented her to his 
mother as the preserver of his life. She had been in 
London two years or more when I arrived there, and 
was among the most honored women of the city.</p>
        <p>She came back to America on the same steamer that 
I came on. She was certainly looked upon as a sanctified
christian woman. </p>
        <p>The soldier who took her over was bringing her back. 
He would have her dress in the same costume she wore 
when she rescued him from the quicksands, and thus 
gave an exhibition every few days. She was not 
now the same illiterate Aunt Nancy that she was three 
years ago for contact with educated and refined 
people had polished her up wonderfully. </p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson114" n="114"/>
      <div1 type="image">
        <p>
          <figure id="ill12" entity="ill12">
            <p>MARTYRED PRESIDENT MCKINLEY.</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson115" n="115"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER XIX.</head>
        <head>THE NEGRO IN IT.</head>
        <lg>
          <l>1	In the last civil war,</l>
          <l>The white folks they began it. </l>
          <l>But before it could close,</l>
          <l>The negro had to be in it.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>2	At the battle of San Juan hill,</l>
          <l>The rough riders they began it;</l>
          <l>But before victory could be won</l>
          <l>The negro had to be in it.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>3 	The negro shot the Spaniard from the trees,</l>
          <l>And never did regret it, </l>
          <l>The rouge riders would have been dead today,</l>
          <l>Had the negro not been in it.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>4	To Buffalo McKinley went,</l>
          <l>To welcome people in it,</l>
          <l>The prayer was played, the speeches made, </l>
          <l>The negro he was in it.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>5	September sixth, in Music Hall, </l>
          <l>With thousands, thousands in it,</l>
          <l>McKinley fell from the assassin's hand  -   </l>
          <l>And the negro, he got in it.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>6 	He knocked the murderer to the floor,</l>
          <l>He struck his nose, the blood did flow;</l>
          <l>He held him fast, all near by saw it,</l>
          <l>When for the right the negro is in it. </l>
        </lg>
        <pb id="robinson116" n="116"/>
        <lg>
          <l>7	J. R. Parke is his name, </l>
          <l>He from the state of Georgia came;</l>
          <l>He worked in Buffalo for his bread, </l>
          <l>And there he saw McKinley dead.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>8 	They bought his clothes for souvenirs,</l>
          <l>And may they ever tell it  -  </l>
          <l>That when the president was shot,</l>
          <l>A brave negro was in it.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>9 	McKinley now in heaven rests;</l>
          <l>Where he will ne'er regret it;</l>
          <l>And well he knows, that in all his joys,</l>
          <l>There was a negro in it.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>10	White man, stop lynching and burning </l>
          <l>This black race, trying to thin it  -   </l>
          <l>For if you go to heaven or hell,</l>
          <l>You will find some negro in it.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>11	You may try to shut the negro out </l>
          <l>The courts, they began it,</l>
          <l>But when we meet at the judgment bar</l>
          <l>God will tell you the negro is in it.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>12	Pay them to swear a lie in court,</l>
          <l>Both whites and blacks will do it;</l>
          <l>Truth will shine, to the end of time,</l>
          <l>And you will find a negro in it.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>13	If there's a position to be filled,</l>
          <l>In congress or in senate, </l>
          <l>We people of this nation pray</l>
          <l>This negro may get in it.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>MRS. LENA MASON.</l>
        </lg>
        <pb id="robinson117" n="117"/>
        <p>I enlisted in the 54th Massachusetts, where I remained 
nine months; was transferred to the 28th 
Indiana, on account of having an uncle in that regiment. 
I remained in the army from July, 1863, until 
December, 1865. Was in the following regular battles: 
Battle of the Wilderness, Kenesaw Mountain, 
Chancellorsville, Virginia, Culpepper, Virginia, 
Antietam, Maryland, Blue Springs, Missionary Ridge, 
Nashville, and Greenville, Tennessee and many other 
 skirmishes. </p>
        <p>I was mustered out on December 29, 1865, with no 
home to go to, no starting point or object in life. The 
rebels had raided Knoxville Tennessee, and mother, 
with all the colored people, had left there, and I could 
gain no knowledge concerning her whereabouts. I saw 
my mother in 1863, when I left her in the little log 
cabin in Knoxville, and I never saw her again for 
fifteen years. The medium then used in finding any 
of our people was the church. Any one looking for a 
lost relative would send letters of inquiry to all the 
different churches in the United States and Canada, 
describing the person, and giving names of masters  
they had belonged to, so far as they knew. So I tried 
to find my mother, and at the expiration of a few years 
I heard of a woman in Huntsville, Alabama, answering 
the description. There was great difficulty in finding 
our people because they were sold so often, and had to 
take the name of each master. Knowing that my 
mother was a christian woman, and would be identified 
with some church I wrote to all the churches in Huntsville, 
and finally received an answer, stating that a 
<pb id="robinson118" n="118"/>
woman answering that description had lived there, but 
not of that name  -  for I inquired for Rosy Hadley, the 
name of her last master. </p>
        <p>I then went to Huntsville, and after spending a 
month of constant research and inquiry I had to give it 
up as futile. I returned to Nashville, but did not give 
up the search through the medium of letters. Finally
I received a letter from Chattanooga. I went there 
and spent more than two months, but to no avail. 
After this I heard nothing from her, or concerning 
her, for over six years. During this time I learned 
that I had a brother in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. 
After the exchange of a few letters we were satisfied 
that we were brothers, and he came to see me. It 
proved to be my oldest brother, James, who had run 
away from Wilmington in 1860. He went to an 
underground railroad station twelve miles from Wilmington. 
Here he was put in a box, this box was 
enclosed in another box, and the second box in a third 
box, and sent by express to New York, where he was 
released from his somewhat cramped quarters in Rev. 
Henry Ward Beecher's parlor. To give him air, holes 
were bored in each box, care being taken that they 
were not opposite each other. From New York he 
went to Toronto, Canada, was educated by the Presbyterian 
church, serving many years as a pastor. He 
died in 1890. About three hours before his death he 
sat propped up in bed, and preached a sermon, using 
as his text “Blessed is the man who dyeth in the Lord. 
He shall rest from his labors and his works do follow  
<pb id="robinson119" n="119"/>
		
him.” After his remarkable escape he always went by 
the name of “Box Brown.” </p>
        <p>Through him I found another brother, who was a 
locomotive engineer over the Grand Rapids and Indiana 
railroad. We three were soon together and again began 
a zealous search for mother, ultimately locating 
her in Lebanon, Tennessee. It was not long until we 
found her, though not in Lebanon, for when we reached 
there we learned that she had been gone from that 
place nearly a year. She had gone back to Knoxville, 
in which city I found her, and when she saw me, 
she exclaimed, like  Simeon of old on seeing Jesus, “now 
Lord let me die in peace, for mine eyes have seen my 
son William” </p>
        <p>That memorable morning, as I left the city of Nashville,
with my fireman's uniform on, and two hundred 
dollars in my pockets, my heart was buoyant with 
expectation, for it was no more hope, but a grand 
reality, that I would see the faces of the dearest earthly 
friends I had  -   a mother and two sisters. The arrangements 
for the meeting had been made unbeknown 
to mother. At train time my sisters were on the alert 
for me, and as I neared the house they called mother's 
attention to some one coming. Mother came to the 
door, walking with a cane; she said, “that walks something 
like my William.” But the sight of mother so 
elated me that I bent my steps quick and fast toward 
the house. When I was close enough for her to recognize 
my face, she uttered the words before stated. </p>
        <p>I am lost for language to describe the scene which 
followed. The only thing which cast a shadow over  
<pb id="robinson120" n="120"/>
the pleasure of our meeting was when mother asked, 
“if we had heard anything from father?” The house 
of joy was turned into lamentation, but after a while 
quiet was restored. We never saw or heard from 
father after he was sold. We learned that another 
brother, named Andrew, was about eight miles from 
Knoxville. In a few days he joined us and we spent a
glorious time together. There were now mother and 
six children together  -  two sisters and four brothers.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson121" n="121"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER XX.</head>
        <p>I returned to Nashville  -  which I considered home  -   
after several weeks' visit with mother. I re-entered 
on my duties as fireman  -  for I was a member of the 
City Fire Department, and had been engaged as <sic>hosecart</sic> 
driver for eight months. Shortly after my return 
we were called out to a large fire. While fighting 
the fire the captain called to “Jim Howard.”
After calling several times and no one seemingly hearing 
him, he called “Jim Cowens,” and that attracted 
my attention. I looked to see who would answer, and 
seeing a man on top of the house answering, I immediately 
climbed on the building.</p>
        <p>I inquired of Jim “where he came from,” and many 
similar questions, and it was but a few minutes until 
we recognized each other as brothers. Now you can 
better imagine what followed than I can express it. It 
came to the ears of the City Council of the City of 
Nashville, “that two brothers who had served eight 
months in No. 2 Hose Company, had just recognized 
each other as brothers  -  having been separated for sixteen 
years.” In honor of our meeting they gave us a 
public reception. </p>
        <p>One extreme always follows another, for in three 
weeks from the time of our recognition, my brother 
was thrown seventy-two feet from the hook and ladder 
<pb id="robinson122" n="122"/> 
against the stone custom house, and every bone in his 
body was broken; he died instantly. </p>
        <p>I served seventeen months in the fire department, 
and resigned to accept a situation as singer and banjo 
player in a troupe gotten up by S. C. Wallace. The 
troupe was known as the “Tennessee Singers” (not the 
original Tennessee Jubilee Singers, yet we attracted 
the attention of the public at large to the extent that 
we were constantly in demand. ) We made a tour from 
Nashville, Tennessee, to Indianapolis, Indiana, thence to 
Terre Haute, Indiana, from there to Chicago, Springfield. 
Bloomington, Illinois, LaPorte, Indiana, Detroit, 
Michigan, and Windsor, Canada. On our return trip 
we sang in the following cities in Michigan: Grand 
Rapids, Battle Creek, Kalamazoo and Niles, then back 
through Indiana and Kentucky to Nashville, Tennessee. 
We sang nothing but the southern melodies  -  songs 
composed by our fathers and mothers in the days of 
slavery. We disbanded in November, 1868.</p>
        <p>In January, 1869, I hired to what was known as the 
Hanlon's Wizard Oil Company, with seven others, at 
twelve dollars per month and board. The contract 
was for one year. If there was any one thing I was 
accomplished in it was picking the banjo and singing; 
and I soon became the center of attraction along these 
lines. We gave street concerts for advertising the oil. 
We made a tour of the leading cities of Indiana, Illinois 
and Michigan, thence to New York City, where we 
took passage, May 21, 1869, on the steamer “City of 
New York,” for London, England.</p>
        <p>Everyone treated me so different than I was used to 
<pb id="robinson123" n="123"/>
during the time of slavery, that I forgot, to some extent, 
the hardships through which I had passed, and 
more than once stopped and inquired of myself “is this 
heaven, and am I in it?”</p>
        <p>The passage over was a very pleasant one, and we 
arrived in London the 27th day of June, 1869. We 
neared London  -  the metropolis of the world. I saw 
hundreds of vessels, the white winged messengers of 
commerce , coming from all directions, loaded for London 
harbor. </p>
        <p>The news had been cabled before us that we would  
arrive June 27th and hundreds of the populace were 
at the harbor. Their curiosity had been aroused to 
the highest tension. We repaired to Hotel de France,
where we were the center of attraction; hundreds 
followed the carriages in which we rode to the hotel, 
and ran over each other in order to get a look at the 
ladies and gentlemen from America. After supper we 
went to St. Paul's Cathedral  -  which had a seating capacity 
of over two thousand. Here we gave our first 
concert. The people were wild with enthusiasm, and 
fairly rained shillings, three cent pieces and bouquets 
to us on the stage. </p>
        <p>At the close of this first concert, a gentleman by the 
name of William S. Beckenworth, known as Lord 
Beckenworth, with one son and two daughters, made 
their way to the stage. After introducing themselves 
they requested me to go home with them that night, 
which I could not do without the consent of the manager, 
Mr. Howard. They at once went to him, and 
he promised them that I could go the next night, 
<pb id="robinson124" n="124"/>
After the sale of medicine the next night I was escorted 
to the cab by this family, and carried to their 
home as a guest; and in one single bound I leaped from 
“Bill Cowens to Lord Cowens, or the Gentleman from 
America.” </p>
        <p>Now the great panorama of my life, as a free man, 
began. My associations were entirely different to 
those I had been used to  -  even in my master's home. 
As I recall that night it becomes a night of wonder to 
me. As I entered that palace, on St. Mark's avenue, 
as a guest, they seated me in the center of their spacious 
parlor, and served me with refreshments. One of 
the daughters placed a napkin across my chest and 
gave me a server, upon which were several varieties 
of very fine fruit. Eighteen or twenty of their friends 
were present, and all except myself seemed to enjoy 
the luxuries to the highest extent. This being my first 
time to be served on social equality with white people, 
of course I was very much embarrased. I put some of 
the most delicate fruit in my mouth, but it seemed 
almost impossible for me to masticate it, for the 
longer I chewed it the larger it seemed to grow, until 
I could not swallow. Of course I told them that I 
was not hungry and did not care for the refreshments, 
but way down in my heart I was wishing that I had 
the server, with the refreshments upon it, behind the 
house  -  in a few minutes they would have known that 
I had been there. After a time, pitying my <sic>embarrasment</sic>, 
the tray was removed, and I was asked to tell 
them something of myself and family. </p>
        <p>I entertained them for an hour and a half or two  
<pb id="robinson125" n="125"/>
hours, and the party retired for the night: but before 
leaving each one gave me a shilling, and left with the 
understanding that I was to tell them more about my 
people the next night. After the father had family 
prayer they showed me the room I was to occupy and 
bade me good-night. </p>
        <p>After locking the door, and carefully examining the 
windows with a scrutinizing eye, I searched every 
crack and crevice in the room, Then I got under the 
bed and felt the springs. I had heard my master, 
years before, tell about trap doors under the beds in 
New Orleans, and that people would get into bed 
only to find themselves in some dark alley. They had 
passed through a trap floor and down a  slide. Of 
course, in these cases, the motive was robbery. I 
don't know why I was fearful, since I had no money 
save what the people had given me. But the great, 
unsolvable mystery surrounding me was, why I, an 
ex-slave, should be paid such high respect among 
strangers.</p>
        <p>There was a night shirt for me to sleep in, also a 
breakfast gown of heavy velvet. I examined both 
these articles of comfort laid them back where I
found them, took both the sheets off the bed and 
folded them up, laid them on a chair and climbed in 
bed. I began to sink so fast in the middle of the big 
feather bed  -  had anyone been on the outside they 
could have heard me gasping and catching my breath 
  -  for with all my careful searching for the trap door I 
thought I was gone, but I finally landed on my pillow 
of repose. </p>
        <pb id="robinson126" n="126"/>
        <p>The second night was almost a repetition of the first. 
I was like the country lad who went to the city to visit 
a lady friend. He used a little of the weed. Not 
being accustomed to use a cuspidor he spat over in a 
corner. The lady noticing it, pushed the cuspidor to 
one side of him. He shoved it away. She tried putting 
it in front of him. Finally, in desperation, he 
blurted out, “if you don't take that gol darned thing 
away I'll spit in it.” I looked at the night shirt and 
said to myself, “if that is here another night, I will 
put it on,” also the breakfast robe, I thought the same 
thing concerning it. So the third night, finding the 
night shirt still there, I put it on; the next morning 
on going down to breakfast I put on the breakfast robe. 
I saw the girls cast glances at each other and wink, as 
 much as to say “he's learning.”</p>
        <p>I was in England eleven months and a half, and during 
that time I slept only three nights out of Lord 
Beckenworth's house. We went to the different hamlets, 
as far as forty miles from London, but always 
returned there at night. The roads in London were so 
carefully kept that you could drive forty miles there
while driving half that distance in America. But the 
first five months of our time were spent principally in 
the different cathedrals and opera houses in London. 
During the first three or four weeks of that time there 
were from twenty to twenty-five guests at Lord Beckenworth's 
house every night to hear me talk about my 
slave life. But after that his two daughters conceived, 
and put into execution, the grandest thought that 
could have entered their minds. That was, to try to 
<pb id="robinson127" n="127"/>
instill in me the idea of education. They bought books 
and started on their laborious work, excusing the visitors 
that came each night, and inviting them to come 
only on Friday nights, and this they did in large numbers.  
At first the two sisters were both teachers, one 
sitting in class with me while the other taught, and 
vice versa. Many nights we sat up from 10 to 12 
o'clock  -  for I was very anxious to learn. After getting 
rudiments in my mind I learned with surprising 
quickness, and knew my letters as if by magic. 
I could have worn out both of these girls physically, 
so they decided to take turn about, one each night. 
And for ten consecutive months I attended school in 
this home, these two angels of mercy being my teachers. 
They were faithful, tireless and unfeigned in 
their efforts to give me some educational light. When 
I got so I could spell words of two syllables I was like 
the old fellow when he had learned his alphabet. 
He said “he had too much edification to stay here or any 
whar else.”</p>
        <p>Once a week the visitors would attend in large numbers 
to see how much I had advanced, and I delighted 
very much in reciting before them. They were very 
much amused when I came to spell certain words, 
especially “baker.” I spelled it in that dialectical way, 
pronouncing each syllable in such a way that it would 
cause a burst of laughter each time. As I have said 
before, I learned very rapidly, had an uncommon verbal 
memory, and in eight months' time was able to read 
plain reading and could write fairly well. I recall the 
first letter I wrote. It was to Ulysses S. Grant, at 
<pb id="robinson128" n="128"/> 
that time president of the United States. I wanted to 
write to the greatest man in the world, and I thought 
after Lincoln Grant was next. I reminded him of an 
incident that occurred during the battle of Kenesaw 
Mountain, in 1864. He and his staff rode up, a tree 
limb knocked his hat off, and I thoughtlessly stepped 
out of my ranks, picked up the hat and handed it 
to the general. I received a very severe reprimand 
from my captain, but General Grant called him and in 
a few words, unheard by me, he satisfied the captain. 
Then he said to me, “boy, if we both live to get out 
of the war, let me know where you are and I'll remember 
you for this favor.”</p>
        <p>So I wrote to President Grant, informing him that I 
was alive, and had risen from the ranks of a private 
soldier in the union army to a Lord, (in title but not 
in wealth) in England. Miss Emeline  -  the older daughter 
of Lord Beckenworth, wrote also, as I dictated and 
wrote  -  for I spoke audibly every word I wrote. Of 
course, when I had finished my letter it looked as if 
blueing had been poured into a plate and a chicken had 
walked into it, then over the paper. All the lawyers 
in the United States could not have read it. But Miss 
Emeline's letter was enclosed with mine. This was 
the first letter I ever wrote in my life, and a day or 
two after I mailed it I began to trouble the postmaster. 
I went twice a day, expecting an answer from 
my letter, not considering it had to cross the sea. I 
was like two negro men, one a runaway from the 
south, who had crossed the line and gotten safely into 
the north; the other was a barrister in the north. The 
<pb id="robinson129" n="129"/>
runaway negro inquired of the lawyer the way into 
Canada. The latter scratched his cranium for a 
moment, cleared his throat, pulled off his gloves,
looked over his spectacles and said, “well, sa-ar, if 
you go by de steamboat and it blowed down whar is 
you? If you go on the steam kears and dey blowed up, 
dar you is; but if you go on the junegraph (meaning 
telegraph) you are dar now.”</p>
        <p>I wrote my letter to America and thought by the 
day it was “dar now.” But in about thirty days 
the post master was made glad, and I made to rejoice. 
It certainly must have been a source of joy to him to 
be honored with the privilege of handing me the first 
letter I ever received for myself in my life; but he 
must have been gladdened to be relieved of a troublesome 
customer. The president paid me a very high 
compliment for the exalted station I had reached in so 
short a time, and invited me to visit the White House 
on my return to America. He advised me to remain 
in England until I was thoroughly polished at the 
hands of this noble family, so that I might return a 
useful man to my race and the nation. He wrote Miss 
Emeline a fine letter, commending me as a soldier, 
and thanking her for the interest she and her sister 
had taken in the new citizen of America, hewn out of a 
slab of ebony.</p>
        <p>Eleven months spent almost entirely away from my 
people, save a few hours at night, and constant association 
with the Caucasian race, wrought quite a wonderful 
change in myself and habits. As association 
breeds assimilation, I had gotten almost entirely rid of 
<pb id="robinson130" n="130"/>
that southern dialect. My aspirations began to mount 
above my environments and from that time I began to 
seek higher things in life. The spirit of manhood 
which lay slumbering in my breast began to awaken. </p>
        <p>This ambition to make something of myself was 
further strengthened by an incident which <sic>occured</sic> at 
this time. Frederick Douglas, marshall of the District 
of Columbia, was paying London a visit. Queen 
Victoria, in order to give the people an opportunity of 
seeing this great man, took him in the royal carriage 
through the principal streets of the city. The carriage 
was drawn by twelve horses, and each horse was 
led by a man in uniform. All London turned out to 
do honor to America's famous colored orator. The 
sight of Mr. Douglas as he stood up in the carriage, 
hat in hand, his silvery hair falling to his shoulders, 
bowing right and left to the crowds of people who 
were shouting themselves hoarse in their enthusiasm, 
fired me with the desire to become a public speaker. </p>
        <p>Soon I began to get ready to embark for America 
again. I had made many friends during my stay in 
England, who proved to be friends indeed, for the 
night before my departure they gave me a grand reception, 
two hundred and twenty dollars and enough 
clothing to last me a year. This was to enable me to 
attend school, and every year for four years, they 
sent me fifty dollars. It was as sad to me parting from 
these English friends as it ever was to part with my 
brothers and sisters. When I got in the carriage the 
next day dozens of friends stood around bidding me 
adieu, and God's blessings. But thank God, I am not  
<pb id="robinson131" n="131"/>
returning the same “William Cowens,” in appearance 
or knowledge, as when I left; for new thoughts and 
new ideas, that had lain slumbering under the iron 
heel of oppression for twenty-one years, groaning for 
light and liberty, are now awakened, and thank God, 
the light of a new day is dawning upon me.</p>
        <p>On board the vessel, instead of entertaining the 
guests with banjo picking and southern songs, I could 
talk of things of a higher life, and the passengers soon 
became interested in me. So much so that for thirty 
nine days a gentleman, by the name of Joseph P. Ray, 
and his wife, became my tutors; taking up my lessons 
where I had left off in England, hearing my last lesson 
the day we landed in New York. </p>
        <p>I wandered around this large city for two months 
trying to find a permanent location, but everything 
seemed either to high or too fast for me, so I decided 
to go back to Nashville, Tennessee. I soon put my 
decision into execution and arrived in Nashville in 
June. The Methodist Episcopal established a school 
known as the Freedman's Bureau, from which 
sprang the great Central Tennessee College. At this 
time it was only an obscure log hut; today, it is the 
Atheneum of Education. I entered school here, and 
continued three years, until my money was exhausted. 
I then went to work half the day and attended school 
the other half, and continued in school in this manner 
for one term. Many times I had nothing in my dinner 
pail but corn bread and stewed apples. Often I was 
ashamed for others to see how I was faring, and went 
off by myself to eat my lunch. My teacher, noticing 
<pb id="robinson132" n="132"/>
that I had about the same thing each day, asked me if 
I never ate anything else but corn bread and dried 
apples. I felt very much humiliated to tell her that 
that was all I was able to have. She encouraged me 
very much by telling me of others that had become 
great men in this country, who had had even less opportunities 
than I, yet they pushed their way to the 
topmost round of the ladder of fame. She also told 
me that a path of great success was before me, if I 
only continued as I had started. After that day she 
never failed to divide her dinner with me. I learned 
very fast under her, but finally had to quit school 
entirely and go to work. I worked one year  -  taking 
care of three different persons' horses, and making 
fires in the winter. I saved my money, and when 
school opened the next year I started again. After 
that term I went to night school.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson133" n="133"/>
      <div1 type="image">
        <p>
          <figure id="ill13" entity="ill13">
            <p>STEPHEN D. LEE.<lb/>Commander-in-Chief Confederate Veterans.</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson134" n="134"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER XXI.</head>
        <p>In 1874 I entered the freshman class in college: I 
met with another <sic>embarrasment</sic> here, for every one in 
the class was ahead of me. As I did not complete the 
high school course it made it more difficult for me in 
college. But I had that spirit of determination, and 
studied with a will, and by the close of the term I had 
caught up with all the class but three; had made many 
friends, and was considered by all far from being the 
dullest boy in the class.</p>
        <p>About this time I became very much interested in 
politics, and the issue of the day was so common that 
it did not require a man of great ability to become 
a stump speaker. All I had to do was to remind my 
people of the fact that the Yankees freed them, and 
that these Yankees were the present republican party; 
frequent mentioning of the name of Abraham Lincoln 
would stir all the patriotism there was in them. I soon 
became very popular among my race, so much so that 
I was consulted on every point of the least importance. 
I was an ardent lover of books, and read quite extensively. 
I would read many nights all night, and my 
memory served me well. It was the height of my 
ambition to be a political orator, for I had in me that 
retaliating spirit, and thought there was no better way 
to give vent to my feelings towards the southern people 
than to tongue-lash them in politics. But after consulting 
<pb id="robinson135" n="135"/>
a few men I saw that I had the wrong spirit, 
and that if I accomplished anything it must be through 
the spirit of love and not of vengeance. If I wanted to 
be a useful man to my people and country, I would 
have to learn “that vengeance belongeth to the Lord.”</p>
        <p>Later I was hired at Lebanon, Tennessee, as teacher. 
I had a class of forty. The majority of them was old 
people forty-five and fifty years old. I taught them 
two terms  -  each term being only four months. The 
other four months in the year I worked at most anything 
I could catch. I became impatient with that 
slow way of making money, so I resigned my school 
and went back to Nashville. Through a friend I was 
given a situation as porter for the Woodruff Sleeping 
Car Company, which was afterwards bought out by 
the Pullman Company. I continued in the employment 
of George L. Pullman for six consecutive years, 
during which time I was on every road of any importance 
in the United States and old and New Mexico. </p>
        <p>While running from Mackinaw City, Michigan, to 
Cincinnati, I came near being killed. At Ft. Wayne, 
Indiana, I stepped off my car while in motion, and was 
dragged seventy-two feet on my back, all the while 
hanging to the boxing of the car, the wheels running 
between my legs. The people turned their backs to 
keep from seeing me cut to pieces. As the car stopped 
I relaxed my hold, and they picked me up unconscious, 
and for some time they thought that life was 
extinct. They telegraphed my wife that I was dead, 
but finally I regained consciousness and was returned  
<pb id="robinson136" n="136"/>
home that night on the same train. This laid me up 
for three months.</p>
        <p>After I was restored to my natural strength I accepted 
a position on board a steamboat on Lake Michigan, 
as steward or cook, for the Graham Passenger Steamboat 
Company, plying between St. Joseph and Benton 
Harbor, Michigan, and Chicago, Illinois. During this 
time I saw some very stormy seasons. I especially 
recall one of them  -  the night the Alpena went down 
with her human cargo of seventy souls. I was on the 
steamer Traitor, enroute for Chicago from Green Bay; 
it was one of the most ferocious seas  -  so said some of 
the old captains who had sailed the sea for many years, 
that they had ever seen. We answered the signals for 
help sent out by the ill-fated Alpena. Our captain 
called a council to decide whether we would attempt 
to go to her aid in the midst of the terrific storm then 
raging. It was unanimously agreed to take our 
chances, and the ship was turned about, several times 
nearly capsizing. Before we succeeded in reaching her 
the signals ceased and we knew that our efforts had 
been in vain, for the beautiful steamer Alpena, with 
every soul on board, had gone down to a watery grave. 
We finally weathered the storm and landed safely in 
Chicago harbor. On the return trip I fell over board 
and had a very narrow escape from death, but the captain 
soon hauled his vessel to, and picked me up after 
I had gone down and come up the second time. </p>
        <p>In 1877, while cooking at the New England hotel, 
in Clark street, Chicago, I was one night in the third 
story of a gambling den, owned and run by two brothers  -   
<pb id="robinson137" n="137"/>
Dan and Jim Scott, two very wealthy colored 
men. They kept hotel, roomers, and ran a gambling 
den, all in one building. I had drifted away during 
my railroad and sailing careers into a class of company 
that led me to this miserable life. It seemed for 
a time that all the good that had been accomplished 
through my many friends, and self denial and perseverance, 
were all overshadowed with darkness, in 
immorality and sin. But thank God, on New Year's 
night, 1877, while standing at the gambling table, I 
heard my mother's voice, as I thought, as audibly as I 
ever heard it in my life. She said, “my son,” in that 
tender, motherly way in which none save a mother can 
speak, “is this what you promised me when you were 
wearing the shackles of bondage?”</p>
        <p>I at once recalled the day when mother left me in 
Wilmington to go back to Greenville, Tennessee, when 
she said, “son, I have nothing in this world to give 
you, but remember that manners and good behavior 
will carry you through the world; get the religion of 
Jesus in your heart, and if we never meet again on 
earth meet me in heaven.” I resolved on that night 
that I would not stop until I was converted. All the 
entreaties and prayers of my mother came rushing 
upon my mind, and I decided at once that they should 
not be in vain. My mind fully made up, I left the 
gambling den that night, never to enter it again.</p>
        <p>The next day I accepted a situation as head cook in 
Evanston, Illinois, eighteen miles from Chicago. I 
was deeply convicted and began to reason of righteousness, 
temperance and the judgment to come. The 
<pb id="robinson138" n="138"/>
more I reasoned, the deeper was my conviction, until 
it seemed that the clock on the wall as it ticked said 
“repent.” I became so interested concerning my 
soul's welfare, that I could not keep my mind on my 
business, so I began to seek the Lord in prayer. In 
June of the same year I walked out of the hotel about 
eleven o'clock, didn't stop to draw my money; the train 
was due for Chicago and was at the depot when I arrived 
there. I was so completely absorbed in thought, 
and stirred about the salvation of my soul that I walked 
by the train, up the track towards Chicago. It 
seemed as though a voice was constantly saying to me, 
“repent.” I had not walked very far when a voice 
said, “you had better pray.” Of course it was the 
reasoning of the spirit within. I walked down the embankment 
and for the first time since I was ten years 
old, I called on God for redemption through the blood 
of Jesus. I became so intensely earnest that I did not 
notice the section hands working near by. I arrived 
in Chicago about dusk, went to a saloon and called for 
a drink  -  a very unusual thing for me, because I never 
went into a saloon before alone. I had often taken a 
drink through the influence of company. But now, 
Satan, finding that I was trying to extricate myself 
from sin, and from the wrath of a sin avenging God, 
made his greatest struggle to impede my progress. 
He knew that the wine cup was a sure remedy to 
carry out his wishes. I never was a lover of strong 
drink, but now I walked up to the bar and called for 
gin, as one of the regular hard drinkers would do. </p>
        <p>This was one of the remedies that the devil furnished  
<pb id="robinson139" n="139"/>
me to drive away trouble, but it failed in this case; 
for I took two drinks and it took no effect whatever 
upon me, for my soul was crying for deliverance. I 
left the bar room, went to the Union depot and bought 
a ticket for La Porte, Indiana, but I got off at a little 
station before I got to La Porte, as I thought of a 
Baptist preacher I knew about three miles from there.
It was midnight, and very dark when I got off the 
train. I inquired of the depot agent the way to this 
preacher's home. The road lay through a dense, 
thick woods, and after wandering until about two 
o'clock in the morning I found the place.</p>
        <p>I remained at his home about three weeks, and 
would go each day to the woods with him and help 
him pile up brush, trim trees, etc. I imagined all 
the while that a tree was going to fall upon me and 
kill me. The very axe the preacher was chopping 
with seemed to be crying “repent,” and I became so 
troubled that all hunger and thirst seemed to have 
left me. There was but one thought uppermost in my 
mind and that was, “that I might find peace with 
God.”</p>
        <p>One day the preacher persuaded me to stay at the 
house, saying I was too weak to go with him to the 
woods. He knew what was ailing me, I could tell 
that in his morning and evening devotion, as he would 
offer me to the throne of grace with so much fervor. 
After he was gone I took the shot gun, saying to his 
wife that I would go hunting. I had gone but a short 
distance when something seemed to say to me, “you 
might as well take that gun and blow your brains out.”  
<pb id="robinson140" n="140"/>
Of course this was the reasoning of the devil, making 
his last great effort to decoy me and destroy my soul. 
But God has promised in His word that He will be 
a help in every time of need, and this great truth demonstrated 
itself to me in this hour of peril, for when 
my foot had almost slipped, and my soul was almost 
into eternity  -  where hope is a stranger, and mercy 
could never reach my undone condition, the great 
spirit of God whispered in my soul, “woe be unto 
your damnation.”</p>
        <p>I hid the gun beneath a brush pile, and started to a 
man's house about two miles away. As soon as I went 
into the house he told his wife to hurry dinner and 
clean up the dinner dishes, and that they would have a 
word of prayer. I knelt down behind a big drum 
stove in that log cabin, with my mind fully made up 
to stay there until God converted me; and in less time 
than it will take me to tell it I was happily converted 
to Christ. </p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson141" n="141"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER XXII.</head>
        <p>It seemed as though I had been wearing a heavy 
logging chain about my body, and in a moment it fell 
from me. It looked as if the entire end of the house 
had given way, and I could see with that eye of faith 
into the very kingdom of God. I expect one day 
to behold Christ in His glory, yet I am satisfied that I
shall never see Him any plainer, and He will never 
look any more natural than He did that day in my 
vision. While beholding this great panorama, Christ 
handed me a little testament, and pointed towards a 
large body of woods, saying, “preach my word to 
these people.” In a moment every tree was transformed 
into a vast multitude of people, and I stepped 
upon a stump, and began to preach from Romans, 
First Chapter and sixteenth verse   -   “Now I'm not 
ashamed of the gospel of Christ; for it is the power of 
God unto salvation to every one that believeth; to the 
Jews first, and also to the Greek.” </p>
        <p>I need not say to any soul that has been awakened 
by the light of the gospel that we bad a wonderful 
downpouring of the spirit that day, and of all the 
places on earth, that is the dearest to me. </p>
        <p>I had worn the shackles of a literal bondage for fifteen 
years, but in due season God emancipated me 
from being the goods and chattels of other men, so I 
could think and act for myself as a man; but thank 
<pb id="robinson142" n="142"/>
God, in 1877, he liberated my soul from a greater 
bondage, for human bondage enslaves only the body, 
while sin enslaves both soul and body. But I can now 
praise God in the highest and sing this song, composed 
and sung by my people of the southland. It was a 
song of notification, and alluded to the underground 
railroad and their preparation for escape into Canada. </p>
        <lg>
          <l>“Free at last, free at last, </l>
          <l>Thank God Almighty, I'm free at last.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>1 	When I was a sinner just like you,</l>
          <l>Thank God Almighty, I'm free at last,</l>
          <l>I prayed and mourned till I came through,</l>
          <l>Thank God Almighty, I'm free at last.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>2	I never shall forget that day,</l>
          <l>Thank God Almighty, I'm free at last;</l>
          <l>When Jesus washed my sins away,</l>
          <l>Thank God Almighty, I'm free at last.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>3	The very time I thought I was lost,</l>
          <l>Thank God Almighty, I'm free at last;</l>
          <l>My dungeon shook and my chains fell off.</l>
          <l>Thank God I'm free at last.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>4	This is religion, I do know,</l>
          <l>Thank God Almighty, I'm free at last;</l>
          <l>For I never felt such a love before,</l>
          <l>Thank God Almighty, I'm free at last.”</l>
        </lg>
        <p>The first night after I was converted, I lay down 
before the fire place  -  for it was a log house, with a 
large, old fashioned fire place. The preacher and his 
family were eating supper in the same room. He  
<pb id="robinson143" n="143"/>
said he had not stopped talking to me over five minutes 
when he noticed me clapping my hands and praising 
God. But in that few minutes I had found myself 
in a dense wilderness; I could hear the howling and 
roaring of some kind of a hideous beast that would 
strike terror to any living soul, and all was gloom 
and darkness around me. By faith I looked towards 
the hill of Zion, and, like Peter of old, I cried out, 
“Lord, save me or I perish.” In a moment the darkness 
dispersed, and the light, in all its splendor and 
beauty, shone around me. The same man who handed 
me a testament in the first vision, gave me the same 
kind of a book, pointed to the trees and said, 
“preach My word to these people.” In a moment 
every tree and hush was transformed into a multitude 
of people. I stepped upon the stump and preached 
from the same text as before. This was Saturday 
night and I was sixteen miles from La Porte, Indiana. </p>
        <p>Sunday morning the preacher, Rev. Bailey, and 
myself started for La Porte. There were no trains on 
Sunday morning, so we rode half the distance on a 
hand-car with the section men, and walked the remainder 
of the way. We sat on a fence to rest, facing 
a beech woods, and I rested my head in my hands 
and closed my eyes. I had a repetition of the same 
vision, this being the third time that I saw the same 
thing. I did not tell this part of my conversion for 
two years afterwards, for I was satisfied that it was a 
Divine call to the ministry of the Lord Jesus. Ultimately, 
an old minister, by the name of Andy Ferguson, 
a member of the A. M. E. church, who was  
<pb id="robinson144" n="144"/>
traveling the La Porte circuit,  -  after hearing me talk 
in class meeting several times, asked me to tell him 
exactly how I was converted. After two years I told
him the whole story of my conversion, and he said, 
“son, I knew God had called you to the ministry.” I 
was wonderfully moved to preach the gospel but felt 
that I could not afford to give up my occupation of 
cooking, at which I was making from seventy-five to a 
hundred dollars per month. for an uncertainty. I 
knew how hard it was to raise money for the ministers, 
and like Jonah, I went for nearly five years before I 
entered the field of labor which God would have me do. </p>
        <p>I made several vows and broke them. Finally I 
vowed if I could accumulate a certain amount of money 
I would take up the cross and bear it the best I could. 
I made and saved the amount so quickly that I hardly 
knew how it came, and avenues were opened to my 
advantage on every side.</p>
        <p>I joined the Missionary Baptist church, though I 
was of Methodist belief; hut I was cooking where 
there was no other church save the Baptist. I joined 
them and gave them fifty dollars toward the building 
of a new church, with the understanding that if ever a 
Methodist church was organized there they were to 
give me a letter of recommendation, and refund twenty-five 
dollars to the Methodist church. I was soon made 
a member of the Chain Lake Association of Michigan. </p>
        <p>In 1884 a Methodist church was organized 
and although I was not there, the Baptists refunded 
the twenty-five dollars. I remained in the Baptist 
church until 1891, when I joined Simpson's Chapel 
<pb id="robinson145" n="145"/>
M. E. church, Indianapolis, Indiana. I was admitted 
that same year as a member of the Indiana District 
conference. In March,  92, at Shelbyville, Kentucky, 
Bishop Foster took up my credentials as elder in the 
Baptist church, and gave me a sheep skin or credentials, 
as elder in the Methodist Episcopal church.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson146" n="146"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER XXIII.</head>
        <p>In 1877 I married Miss Alice Goins, of Riverside, 
Michigan, who held up my arms in the ministry for 
sixteen years while I tried to preach Christ. There 
were born to us three children, Dora, Marguerite and 
William. William died in his infancy. The grim 
monster, consumption, seized upon my companion, and 
for five years she bore up like a heroine, many times 
almost compelling me to go to church and preach, 
when I was fearful that she would die before I returned. 
But she would say, “my dear, I'm all right, you may 
save one soul tonight.” She would also quote that 
passage of scripture: Luke 15th Chapter and 10th 
verse, which reads, “Likewise I say unto you, there is 
joy in the presence of the angels of God over one sinner 
that repenteth.”  </p>
        <p>On the morning of April 14, 1892, she sat in the 
door of our home in Grape Creek, Indiana, looking so 
constantly and distant that it attracted my attention. I 
asked her what she was looking at so steadily, and her 
answer was like a thunder bolt to my heart. She 
said, “I am looking at the beautiful carpet this day 
for the last time on earth, for I shall eat my supper in 
heaven tonight.” She had me call our daughters. 
When they came she said, “girls, I am going to leave 
you and papa. I want you to hold up your papa's 
arms as I have done for the last sixteen years. I want 
<pb id="robinson147" n="147"/>
you to stay with him until he marries again.” She 
then said to me, “William, I want you to marry as 
soon as you can find some settled woman. I know you 
could easily marry some young girl, for you don't 
look very old, but I want you to marry a settled woman.” 
She continued by saying, “William, you know how I 
used to set the light in the window for you, and watch 
for you to come home when I was not able to go with 
you to your preaching place.” I said, “yes, Alice.” 
“Well,” said she, “I will set the lamp in the window 
of heaven, and will wait and watch for you until you 
come.” “Dora, I don't want you to do anything that 
will hinder your father in the ministry, and pray for 
him daily that God may sustain him in his labor; be a 
good girl and meet mamma in heaven.”</p>
        <p>I called in my family physician; he was so wonderfully 
touched with the spiritual force and power with 
which she talked that he could scarcely contain himself. 
He wrote upon the back of a book, saying: 
“Reverend, your wife can live but a very short time,” 
and bade me good bye. </p>
        <p>The incident relative to the lamp occurred in Lexington, 
Kentucky, while I was holding a series of revival 
meetings. She was so low that we did not like to 
leave her alone while we were at church, but she insisted 
on the lamp being placed on a table near the 
bed, so she could read, and said that just at 9:30 she 
would put it in the window. We could see the light 
when we reached the top of a hill, and she said, “if 
you do not see the light in the window when you get to 
the top of the hill you will know that I have passed  
<pb id="robinson148" n="148"/> 
over the river.” I recall different times when I 
thought I had reached the spot where I should see it, 
and not seeing it fell in despair, thinking she had gone, 
but others ran ahead and told me that the light was in 
the window. </p>
        <p>None but they who have passed through the trying 
ordeal of the loss of a wife or husband can sympathize 
with one in this dark and trying hour. </p>
        <p>At half past eight that night members and friends 
filled my home; at eight forty-five she began to sing a 
song which she used to sing while in health, “I know 
my name is written in the Lamb's book of life, I know 
my name is written in heaven.” A few minutes before 
nine she took my hand and said, “husband, have I 
been a good wife?” With the very fountains of my 
heart running over with grief I could say nothing else 
but “yes, a thousand times, yes.” </p>
        <p>Though it was my daily study to make her happy 
yet I could never be able to pay the debt of gratitude 
I owe her. I feel that all that I am I owe to her for her 
patience and kindness towards me; for when I would 
despair, and the gloom of disappointment would gather 
around me, she would put her arms around my neck, 
kiss me, and say, “papa, let's pray,” and in that 
plaintive, simple way she would take me and my 
troubles to God. It was her constant study to see and 
know that I was happy. </p>
        <p>Five minutes past nine the chariot swung low, and a 
loving wife and mother was gone, as we thought. I 
was on my knees by the bed, with her head resting on 
my arm; in my excitement I raised her up, and she 
<pb id="robinson149" n="149"/> 
opened her eyes, sang another verse of the same song, 
asked the church to take care of her husband and 
daughters, bade us all good bye, and in a moment her 
spirit had moved out of the old tenement house of clay, 
and she</p>
        <lg>
          <l>“Is now drinking at the fountain,</l>
          <l>Where she always will abide; </l>
          <l>For she has tasted life's pure water </l>
          <l>And her soul is satisfied.”</l>
        </lg>
        <p>I can never describe that night of sorrow, but thank 
God the consolation which she left in her dying testimony, 
and her life for sixteen years, sustained me 
through every conflict, and has been a great source of 
joy since her departure. Often since that night, when 
the clouds would hang low and heavy over me, in my 
imagination I could hear her say, “be of good cheer.”</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson150" n="150"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER XXIV.</head>
        <p>After the funeral services of my wife I returned to 
my lonely home and tried to make some plans for the 
future. Left with two girls one a small child, I was 
forced to take almost a new start in life. Keeping the 
younger girl, Marguerite, in school, my daughter 
Dora and I went out to battle with life and for the 
Kingdom of God. Many trying incidents and perplexities 
came to me but the tender, loving voice that 
had encouraged me in days gone by was hushed in 
death, and I must needs meet them almost alone. </p>
        <p>Finally my plans were laid for five years of Evangelistic 
service. We began our work in Michigan, and 
the result of our first year's labor was over eighteen 
hundred souls brought to Christ. The next year I 
purchased a tabernacle, with a seating capacity of over 
fifteen hundred. I hired four good singers, and that 
was indeed a wonderful year. My record showed over 
two thousand saved. We then went to Indiana, and 
for three consecutive years continued in this line of 
work, after which I accepted the pastorate of a circuit at 
Greenfield and Martinsville Indiana. We built a splendid 
church at Martinsville. From here we went to 
Laurenceville, Illinois where our success was wonderful.</p>
        <p>In this town a saloon keeper was happily converted 
one night. He invited the congregation and myself 
to his saloon at nine o'clock the next morning for 
a feast. Curiosity brought a large crowd at the appointed 
hour. When we had gathered, the saloon keeper, 
with two other men, rolled out three barrels 
<pb id="robinson151" n="151"/>
of whiskey, several kegs and cases of beer and other 
intoxicants, and broke them open. Whiskey and beer 
ran like water in the streets, and the town was intoxicated 
with the fumes. We praised the Lord for this 
external instead of internal application. </p>
        <p>After two years in this town I returned to Evangelistic 
work, and have continued in it until the present 
time. Great meetings have been held in Ohio, Illinois 
and Wisconsin. The greatest meeting in Illinois was 
about three years ago. In eight weeks we saw nine 
hundred people converted and added to the different 
churches. In Waymond Chapel, Chicago, we held an 
all night meeting, at which there were seventy conversions. 
The church quickened and spiritualized, for 
which I give God the glory.</p>
        <p>My daughter Dora helped me in my work until 1897, 
when she married and went to live in San Francisco, 
California. Three years later she was taken suddenly 
ill. After a partial recovery her husband was bringing 
her to Louisville, Kentucky, to spend the summer 
with us. Upon reaching Chicago she was taken worse 
and was hurried to a hospital. I received a letter one 
morning, asking me to meet her in Chicago. The 
same afternoon a telegram came from her husband, 
telling me to come at once if I would see her alive. I 
started on the first train. I shall never forget that 
race with death. I reached Chicago the next morning, 
but too late; her spirit had taken its flight. Her dying 
words were, that she had gone to join mother, and for 
me to meet her in glory. With God's help I expect 
to do so.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson152" n="152"/>
      <div1>
        <head>
          <sic>CHAPTER XVIII.</sic>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>THE CHILD'S INQUIRY.</head>
          <p>As much as unfeeling men talk and preach about 
“Negro insensibility,” and as much as slavery dotes 
upon her mysterious power of blotting out and annihilating 
the principles of humanity, yet it is plainly 
seen that God has planted in the bosom of the black 
man a quality of His own nature, that the ruthless 
hand of time and the strong arm of oppression has not 
extinguished. </p>
          <p>To make my point clearer I will explain the 
usual form of marriage between house slaves. When 
a couple wished to marry, if the marriage was agreeable 
to the owners, a wedding feast was spread by 
them, the colored people furnishing coon, possum and 
sweet potatoes. When everything was ready the old 
negro preacher, (who by the way could not read a 
word) went through a certain form prescribed by the 
master. If the couple marrying was young, the young 
mistresses held a broom stick knee high. If the bride 
and groom were more advanced in years, older ladies 
held it. At the end of the ceremony the colored 
preacher said to the bride and groom, “now, when 
you jump the broom stick I announce you man and 
wife.” This is how the expression you are all so 
familiar with originated. </p>
          <pb id="robinson153" n="153"/>
          <p>I will relate an incident which came under my observation, 
which will better illustrate this marriage 
farce. A loving couple, united in the usual way, had 
lived in harmony for five years and eight months, during 
which time not a cloud of discord had come between 
them; nothing had marred their peace but the 
thought that they must spend their lives in the midst 
of groaning and cracking of whips, of which they 
themselves must share a common fate. To make the 
nuptial ties stronger they had been blessed, as they 
thought, with a little girl, whose dark eyes and waving 
hair satisfied Henry that the child was his. One 
pleasant evening a South Carolinian was seen talking 
with the master of that happy pair, and coming before 
the door they both came to a full halt, while the 
stranger gazed full in the faces of the three, and after 
a few moments, passed in profound silence, he said to 
the master: “I'll give it.” As they turned away 
from the door, the silence was broken by a low whisper 
from the lips of little Mary, saying, “one of us is 
sold, papa.” Like the disciples, they each asked, “is it  I?” Morning found them undisturbed, and Mary hurried 
the work over, and as usual, left the cabin for the 
cotton field, repeating in her mind, “is it I?” So 
excited was her mind that she spent another sleepless 
night, and so conscious was she that she was the victim 
[from reading in the eye of the Carolinian his predominating 
passions], that when she left the house she kissed 
her child and pressed it against her bosom as though 
she would crush it to death. Reluctantly she closed 
the door and departed, to return no more forever. The 
<pb id="robinson154" n="154"/>
husband's ears were made sad at noon, when a slave 
boy said to him, as he called him to the gate, “your 
wife is sold to South Carolina! I saw her chained in 
the gang and the last words I heard her say, were, “0! 
that I had never seen a husband! O! that I had hugged 
my child to death this morning.” But the child's 
inquiry and the father's answer will show whether humanity 
was extinct in them:</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="robinson155" n="155"/>
        <div2>
          <head>THE INFANT'S DREAM.</head>
          <lg>
            <head>CHILD.</head>
            <l>“O, where has mother gone, papa?</l>
            <l>What makes you look so sad?</l>
            <l>Why sit you here alone, papa?</l>
            <l>Has anyone made you mad?</l>
            <l>O, tell me, dear papa.</l>
            <l>Has master punished you again?</l>
            <l>Shall I go bring the salt, papa,</l>
            <l>To rub your back and cure the pain?</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <head>FATHER.</head>
            <l>Go away my child, you are too bad;</l>
            <l>You notice things too soon;</l>
            <l>Did you not see that I was sad, </l>
            <l>When I came home at noon? </l>
            <l>Go to the gate and call mamma,</l>
            <l>And see if she's in sight.</l>
            <l>The hour is late, I fear your ma </l>
            <l>Will not be home tonight.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <head>CHILD.</head>
            <l>O no, papa, I am afraid </l>
            <l>To go to the gate alone;</l>
            <l>I fear there's men in the high grass laid, </l>
            <l>To catch little Mary Jones.</l>
            <pb id="robinson156" n="156"/>
            <l>But what makes mother stay so long?</l>
            <l>'Tis getting very late.</l>
            <l>Papa, go bring my mother home,</l>
            <l>And I'll stay at the gate.</l>
            <l>When mother left me early this morn,</l>
            <l>She kissed me and she wept; </l>
            <l>I saw the tears come trickling down</l>
            <l>Upon the pillow where I slept.</l>
            <l>She pressed me to her bosom, hard,</l>
            <l>As though it was the last embrace.</l>
            <l>She sobbed, but did not say a word,</l>
            <l>Nor would she let me see her face. </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <head>FATHER. </head>
            <l>Pull off your shoes, my dearest child, </l>
            <l>And say your evening prayer; </l>
            <l>And go to bed and after a while,</l>
            <l>Perhaps your mother will be there.</l>
            <l>Go hush those little eyes to sleep,</l>
            <l>And dream some pretty dream tonight,</l>
            <l>Perhaps in the morning when you wake</l>
            <l>You'll find all things all right.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <head>CHILD.</head>
            <l>O' tell me, papa, don't drive me away, </l>
            <l>'Tis dark, the stars are thick and bright. </l>
            <l>Is mother sold. O, tell me, I pray, </l>
            <l>I fear she'll not be home tonight; </l>
            <l>O come papa, come go with me,</l>
            <l>Perhaps we'll meet her in the lane;</l>
            <l>And then she'll sing a song to me,</l>
            <l>And take me in her arms again.</l>
          </lg>
          <pb id="robinson157" n="157"/>
          <lg>
            <head>FATHER.</head>
            <l>Come here my daughter, come to me,</l>
            <l>I find that I must tell you true, </l>
            <l>Come now, and sit upon my knee  -   </l>
            <l>The dismal tale I'll tell to you.</l>
            <l>Your mother's sold; she's sold, my dear, </l>
            <l>Her face you'll see no more.</l>
            <l>Her cheering voice no more you'll hear </l>
            <l>On this side of Canaan's peaceful shore.”</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson158" n="158"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER XXV.</head>
        <p>I have gone by the name of “Cowens” in this history, 
and the reader may be curious to know how I 
came by the name of “Robinson” as I have not mentioned 
any of my masters by that name. </p>
        <p>Two of my masters were named Cowens, one was 
Robert E. Lee commander-in-chief of the confederate 
army, another was Scott, and the fifth was Hadley. </p>
        <p>I have told you that my father was prince of a 
tribe in South Africa known as the Madagascar tribe. 
They heard the <sic>ficticious</sic> story of Robinson Cruso. In 
the African dialect the definition was “Rob-o-bus-sho,” 
meaning Robinson Cruso. </p>
        <p>An aunt, who spent sixteen years in South Africa as 
a missionary, found some of father's relatives, and one 
of his brothers, supposed to be over ninety years old, 
gave her a great deal of information concerning our 
family history. </p>
        <p>After a diligent search of over fourteen years for 
the different members of our family, nine children 
met with mother and held what today would be known 
as a family reunion, but then we called it a three days' 
feast in the wilderness. Each of us had a different 
name. Our missionary aunt was with us, and after 
her explanation to us of how father was brought away 
in slavery we decided to establish a family name and 
record. After carefully talking it over, a unanimous 
<pb id="robinson159" n="159"/> 
vote was taken to discard all other names and hereafter 
answer to our father's name, which meant Robinson. 
I am prouder of my father's heathen name than 
of all the professed christian names that I was compelled 
to acknowledge while a slave. I pray God that 
none of us who bear the name of our father will ever 
bring dishonor to it, and may God help my daughter 
and me to carry the gospel to his native land. </p>
        <p>Will you help us by purchasing our book? </p>
        <closer><salute>Yours for Christ and Africa.</salute>
<signed>W. H. ROBINSON.</signed></closer>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson160" n="160"/>
      <div1>
        <head>A RETROSPECTION.</head>
        <p>It is now 48 years since the greatest of all the wars has closed. Today the muskets 
of the soldiers  -  North and South  -  are stacked, and we entwine our wreath of flowers 
about them, and look upon them with much reverence  -  truly relics of other days  -  days 
that must live in our memory only, for this is another age. But as we look on them 
we are reminded that this great country could never have attained its present status 
without this great conflict. So we have a wreath placed on these old guns and tender 
memories for the boys both North and South who carried them. Our country needed 
the sacrifice  -  you gave your lives and we are sure that the “God of Battles” will give 
you the reward.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson161" n="161"/>
      <div1 type="image">
        <p>
          <figure id="ill14" entity="ill14">
            <p>THE OLD ORGAN USED IN THE SONG SERVICE OF REV. ROBINSOBN'S MEETINGS.</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson162" n="162"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER XXVI.</head>
        <div2>
          <head>KEEPING THE CHARGE OF THE LORD.</head>
          <lg>
            <l>A charge to keep I have, </l>
            <l>A God to glorify; </l>
            <l>A never crying soul to save, </l>
            <l>And fit it for the sky; </l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>To serve the present age,</l>
            <l>My calling to fulfill;</l>
            <l>O may it all my powers engage,</l>
            <l>To do my Master's will!</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Arm me with jealous care,</l>
            <l>As in Thy sight to live;</l>
            <l>And O, Thy servant, Lord, prepare, </l>
            <l>A strict account to give!</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Help me to watch and pray,</l>
            <l>And on Thyself rely, </l>
            <l>Assur'd if I my trust betray,</l>
            <l>I shall for ever die. </l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <pb id="robinson163" n="163"/>
        <div2>
          <head>SERMON ON “THE EXALTATION OF CHRIST.”</head>
          <p>Text. <sic>Philippians</sic>, 2nd, 9, 10, 11.</p>
          <p>“Wherefore God also hath highly exalted Him, and given 
Him a name which is above every name, that at the name of 
Jesus every knee should bow, of things in heaven and things 
in earth, and things under the earth and that every tongue 
should confess that Jesus Christ is Lord to the Glory 
of God the Father.”</p>
          <p>The text represents Christ as the most exalted Being in 
existence. The cause which moved the pen of inspiration to 
this divine utterance grew out of a consideration of the degraded 
and relapsed condition of the church at Philippi, a 
famous city of the province of Macedonia, situated on the 
great highway between Thrace and Anapolis.</p>
          <p>It was founded possibly by the descendants of Jashet, 
through the line of Gomer. Philip, the king of the province, 
remodeled it and gave it its present name, after which it became 
the metropolis of Western Asia. It was also noted for 
the products of gold, silver, etc., in whose mines men were 
engaged in great numbers, thousands of feet beneath the surface. 
This lucrative traffic brought to Philippi strangers from 
every nation, hence the city became the central point of 
scholastic lore and the strong hold of Grecian mythology. 
Paul had visited this empire of Paganism, A. D. 52, 
organized the church, and preached Christ unto them, etc.</p>
          <p>Date and occasion of the Epistle to the <sic>Philippians</sic>, A. D., 
62. Paul found himself a prisoner at Rome, where he had 
been sent from Caesasea for trial in the Roman court. The 
<pb id="robinson164" n="164"/>
church at Philippi on learning of his imprisonment raised a 
collection for him and sent it by Epaphroditus, their minister, 
who on his arrival at Rome called at the jail, where he found 
the object of his mission with a chain around his waist and 
ankle, and hard at work on a tent, for he was a tent maker by 
trade. The preacher from Philippi informed Paul of the relapsed 
and degenerated condition of his church in the polluted 
city of <sic>Philippians</sic>. Object of the epistle was, first to encourage 
and confirm the faith of the church in Christ Jesus. 
Second, to caution it against idolatry and heathen mythology. 
Third, he warns them to shun Judaizing teachers, and fourth, 
he sets forth the Divinity of Christ and the exalted position 
of His dual nature, the last of which is the theme of our discourse, 
“The Exaltation of the Humanity of Christ.”</p>
          <p>May we not pause a moment, and with unshod feet approach 
the holy ground of this sacred mystery, and inquire 
into this sublime and peerless act of exaltation of humanity? 
On the last day of creation man was left at the foot of 
the ladder of the intelligent being, just a little lower 
than the angels, but the language of the text through 
the <sic>hyposative</sic> union clothes him with divinity, lifts him far 
above all creatures, and makes him a life member of the 
<sic>triune</sic> God Head, hence the union of the divine, and human 
nature stands without a parallel in the annals of events. For 
this mysterious act the invisible curtains of divinity were 
drawn back, and the human soul thrown upon the dissecting 
table of infinite wisdom. The infinity of days steps behind 
the screen of his incomprehensibleness, stoops and absolves 
himself into the spiritual and carnal elements of the finite, 
passes under the fierce rod of chastisement, enters 
Joseph's tomb, binds the king of terrors to his 
chariot wheel and leads to captivity the captive, and gives  
<pb id="robinson165" n="165"/> 
gifts unto men by removing Eden to Paradise, and the renewal 
of the moral image of God in the soul by the <sic>indwelling</sic> 
of the Holy Spirit.</p>
          <lg>
            <l>Hosanna to our conquering King.</l>
            <l>All hail Incarnate Love,</l>
            <l>Ten thousand songs and glories wait </l>
            <l>To crown Thy head above.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Thy victories and thy deathless flame </l>
            <l>Through all the world shall run, </l>
            <l>And everlasting ages sing </l>
            <l>The triumphs Thou hast won.</l>
          </lg>
          <p>For through the incarnation man and God are brought face 
to face; by the death and resurrection they are made friends, 
and man is placed in a position where he can leap from the 
eventful stage of immortality to the drama of the immortal, 
where he can stand in the blazing light of the throne and see 
Jesus, the second Adam, clothed in divine majesty and ruling 
the world. Wherefore God also hath highly exalted him, 
and given him a name which is above every name, that at the 
name of Jesus every knee should bow, of things in heaven, 
and things in earth and things under the earth, and that every 
tongue should confess that Jesus Christ is Lord to the glory 
of God the Father. Things in heaven. Where is heaven, 
and what are the things referred to in the text? The poet 
answers the first in the following lines:</p>
          <lg>
            <l>“There is a land far away amid the stars</l>
            <l>Where they know not the sorrow of time,</l>
            <l>Where the pure waters wander through valleys of 
gold, </l>
            <l>And life is a treasure sublime. </l>
          </lg>
          <pb id="robinson166" n="166"/>
          <lg>
            <l>Our gaze cannot soar to that beautiful land</l>
            <l>But our visions have told of its bliss,</l>
            <l>And our souls by the gates of its garden are 
fanned,</l>
            <l>When we faint in the desert of this.” </l>
          </lg>
          <p>The didactive import of the above delineation directs the 
eyes of the soul at once to the center of the universe, the 
sensorium of the Godhead, the home of the angels; a city 
with blazing walls, and towering spires, shining domes and 
pearly gates, and whose streets are paved with gold, upon 
which the feet of the redeemed walk, and where cherubic 
legions dance upon a sea of glass all mingled with fire, and 
phalanx of seraphim bask in the golden sunlight of the city 
of God. These are the things which are in heaven, and they 
have been described and classified by Dr. Bright, as follows: 
First, the seraphim, whose duty it is to give glory to God as 
creator of all things, acknowledging his triune character by 
crying, Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God of hosts, the whole 
earth is full of Thy glory. Second, the cherubim. They form 
the highest order of intelligent creatures, stand in an especial 
nearness to God, and are engaged in the loftiest adoration 
and are associated with the mercy seat. Third: This is a 
superior order of angels, who, under the command of Gabriel, 
stand as connecting links between God, as creator, and Jesus 
Christ as mediator, between God and man. Fourth: The 
fourth is under Michael, the angel liaison of heavens. Warriors 
who fought the dragon and threw him over the battlement 
of heaven, down nine times the space that measures 
day and night to mortal men. The fifth order is under the 
supervision of Uriel. They compose the fire department, 
and execute vengeance upon the earth by hurling forth sheeted 
<pb id="robinson167" n="167"/>
flames of red tongued lightning and hot thunder bolts, and 
belching out liquid and sulphurious flames from burning 
craters. The sixth order is commanded by the angel 
Raphael. They are the health officers of the world. The 
seventh and last is composed of the glorified saints of all 
ages. The general assembly and church of the first born, 
which are written in heaven, and the spirits of just men made 
perfect. All the above are the things which are in heaven, 
and they are the ones who are commanded in the text 
to bow at the name of Jesus, for we read in the gospel of 
peace, that when the incarnate feet of the immaculate touched 
the Bethlehemic manger chanting legates from glory 
came to proclaim the Savior's name, the sound was heard 
upon the plane that God and man were reconciled 
again. [Things in earth.] “In surveying the great system 
of nature with a christian and philosophic eye, it may be considered 
from a different point of view,” says the learned Dr. 
Dick. Hence, in explaining this part of the text, we shall 
start from a scientific point by noticing, first, the surface of 
the earth, second, the atmosphere. The student of science is 
confronted upon the threshold of his observation with countless 
phenomena, all dissimilar one from another, yet controlled 
by law of the survival of the fittest. The surface of the 
earth contains a multiplicity of objects all <sic>dissimlar</sic> in shape, 
size, color, motion and substance; craggy cliffs and towering 
mountains, verdant hills arrayed with clumps of trees and beds 
of flowers, broad and spacious plains, dotted with cities, 
towns and hamlets, waving fields of grain, blooming vineyard,
meandering rivulets, flowing streams, roaring cataracts and 
belching volcanoes, bubbling springs, stagnated ponds, spacious 
lakes and rolling rivers. But let me lengthen the horoscope 
of imagination a little. Go see the outlines of a picture 
<pb id="robinson168" n="168"/>
whose phenomenal background is far more sublime than 
the one whose negative lingers in the mental camera of the 
vision. See the erect form of him who is made in the image  
of his creator, and around him are gathered the rational and 
intelligent children of his flesh and blood, beneath whose 
shadow fifty thousand animal species are leaping and dancing. 
They are all sizes, from the mite to the elephant, from 
the creatures of which, if ten thousand of them were united 
they would not form an object one half the size of a grain of 
sand; yet all of these animals have organs, joints, limbs, feet, 
claws, hoofs, wings, fins; some flying, some crawling, some 
rolling, some walking on two feet, some on four, some on 
eight and some on eight thousand. Some with two eyes, 
some with ten thousand. These are some of the things in 
the earth. Now the chief. Hence, after he fell the whole 
creation groaned and <sic>travailed</sic> in pain together, until Calvary's 
bleeding conqueror burst the seals of Joseph's new 
tomb and sent up a shout of victory from the church militant 
to the church triumphant.</p>
          <lg>
            <l>“Look, ye saints, the sight is glorious, </l>
            <l>See the man of sorrow now,</l>
            <l>From the fight returns victorious,</l>
            <l>Every knee to Him shall bow.</l>
            <l>Hark! those loud triumphant chords!</l>
            <l>Jesus takes the highest station,</l>
            <l>O what joy the sight affords.”</l>
          </lg>
          <p>The atmosphere is teeming with rational spirits, sent from 
God to look after the souls of men. The air we breathe 
swarms with legions of invisible insects, every drop of water 
abounds with millions of living beings. The blood is a living 
<pb id="robinson169" n="169"/> 
stream of insects, crawling and flowing through the trunk of 
the animal kingdom, and for aught we know these insects are 
the underlying principles of our intelligence, for they work 
on and on from birth until death, as though they were conscious 
of what they were doing. Hence, these and the 
spirits in the air, are called upon to bow at the name of Jesus. </p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson170" n="170"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER XXVII.</head>
        <head>SUBJECT, PRAYER  -  LUKE 18:  -  1.</head>
        <p>Sermon delivered in Allen Chapel, Kansas City, Missouri, 
July 15th, 1906, by Rev. W. H. Robinson.</p>
        <p>“And he spake a parable unto them to this end, that men 
ought always to pray, and not to faint. Who can pray so 
that God will hear?” First Ps., 66:  -  18. “If I regard iniquity 
in my heart the Lord will not hear me.” It means to look 
at “with favor,” to “respect,” “approve,” “regard.” God will 
not hear the man who in his heart looks upon sin with any 
favor or allowance. God looks at sin with <sic>abhorence</sic>. He 
is of purer eyes than to behold evil, and cannot look on 
iniquity, etc. We must have the same attitude toward sin 
that He has to be heard of Him. If we regard sin He will 
not regard us when we pray. Herein lies the very simple 
explanation why many of us pray and are not heard. Second 
Prov. 28-29. “He that turneth away his ear from hearing 
the law, even his prayer shall be abomination.” He cannot 
pray so that God will hear. If we turn our ears away 
from what God says to us in His law, He will turn His ears 
away from what we say to Him in our prayers. We have an 
illustration of this in Zach. 7-11-13. “But they refused to 
hearken and pulled away the shoulder, and stopped their 
ears that they should not hear. Yea, they made their hearts as 
an adamant stone lest they should hear the law and the words 
which the Lord of Hosts hath sent.” </p>
        <pb id="robinson171" n="171"/>
        <p>In His spirit by the former prophets, therefore came a great 
wrath from the Lord of Hosts. Then it came to pass as He 
cried and they would not hear, so they cried and I would not 
hear, saith the Lord of Hosts. Many are saying: “The 
promises of God are not true, God does not hear my prayer.” 
Has God ever promised to hear your prayer? God plainly 
described the class whose prayers He hears. Do you belong 
to that class? Are you listening to His words? If not He 
has distinctly said He will not listen to your prayers. And 
in not listening to you He is simply keeping His word. Let 
us notice (Prov. 1: 24-25-28, R. V.) “Because I have called 
and you have refused! I have stretched out my hand and 
no man regarded. But ye have set at naught all my counsel 
and would none of my reproof Then shall they call upon 
me, but I will not answer; they shall seek me diligently but 
they shall not find me.” Third, Prov. 21-13. “Whoso stoppeth 
his ears at the cry of the poor, he also shall cry but 
shall not be heard.” Third proposition: “Whosoever stoppeth 
his ears at the cry of the poor cannot pray so God will 
hear. If we will not listen to the poor when they cry unto us 
in their need, the Lord will not hearken unto us. The 
world's maxim is, “the Lord helps those who help themselves.” 
Luke 18-9-10-11-12. And he spake this parable unto certain 
ones which trusted in themselves that they were righteous 
and despised others. Two men went up into the temple to 
pray; the one a Pharisee. and the other a Publican. The 
Pharisee stood and prayed thus with himself; “God I thank 
thee that I am not as other men are; extortioners, unjust, 
adulterers, or even as this Publican. I fast twice in the 
week, I give of all that I possess.”</p>
        <p>The truth is, the Lord helps those who help others. 
Fourth, Luke 18-13-14. “And the Publican standing afar off 
<pb id="robinson172" n="172"/> 
would not lift up so much as his eyes unto heaven, but smote 
upon his breast, saying,  God be merciful to me a sinner.” I 
tell you this man went down to his house justified rather 
than the other, for “every one that exalteth himself shall be 
abased, and he that humbleth himself shall be exalted.” 
This prayer itself is the first act of faith. The first and most 
natural and most proper thing for one who honestly wishes to 
turn from sin and believe on Christ and to be saved, is to 
pray. The Lord Jesus looked on with delight when he could 
say to Ananias of the stubborn rebel, Saul of Tarsus, “behold 
he prayeth.” Acts 9-11. “And the Lord said unto him, 
arise and go into the street which is called Straight, and inquire 
in the house of Judas for one called Saul of Tarsus, for 
behold he prayeth.”</p>
        <p>We should be sure, however, that the sinner really is sorry 
for sin, and really wishes to forsake it before we tell him to 
pray for pardon. You can get him on his knees even before 
this, and so get him to realize that he is in God's presence, so 
that his rebellious heart may be humbled, but do not have 
him pray until he really does wish to turn from sin. </p>
        <p>Fourth Proposition. The great sinner who is sorry for and 
humbled by his sin, and who desires pardon, can pray so that 
God will hear. The question is often asked, “shall we get 
unconverted people.” If a man is sorry for his sin and wishes 
to forsake it and find mercy, and is willing to humble himself 
before God and ask for pardon, he is taking the very steps by 
which a man turns around, or is converted. To tell a man 
he must not pray under such circumstances, is to tell him that 
he must not be converted until he is converted, that he must 
not turn until he is turned round. To get him to pray is just 
the thing to do, “for whosoever shall call upon the name of 
the Lord shall be saved. (Rom. 10-3). But how, some one 
<pb id="robinson173" n="173"/>
may ask, can he pray until he has faith? The answer is very 
simple, hence the necessity of prayer. The text says, men 
ought always to pray and not to faint. You see when the 
Lord commanded Ananias to go to the house of Judas, how 
he shook and trembled and even reminded the Lord of the 
fact that Saul had come there on a mission of persecution, 
and at that very moment he had letters of authority from the 
High Priest to bring back to Jerusalem all that he found calling 
on the name of Jesus, but when he was informed by the 
great High Priest and captain of our salvation, that “behold 
he prayeth,” it destroyed every vestige of fear, and he went 
rejoicing on his mission and greeted him as brother Saul, and 
Saul laid his desire before Him at once, and that was that 
His eyes might be opened. It was a prayer from an humble 
and contrite heart. Hence it was answered. He told him 
how he was struck blind on the way from Jerusalem to 
Damascus. He told of the blazing magnetic sun light that 
shone in his pathway. He told of the voice that spake unto 
him, (Acts 9-4.) He told of his answer (Acts 5.) It was 
Saul's first real prayer, though it took the heavy rod of <sic>chastisment</sic> 
to bring him to it. God heard and answered his 
prayer, and will hear yours, sinner, if you will humble yourself 
before Him. As soon as Paul received strength he began 
to preach redemption through the blood of Christ. 
(notice Rom. 1-16). For I am not ashamed of the gospel of 
Christ; for it is the power of God unto salvation to every 
one that believeth; to the Jew first and also to the Gentile. 
Hence, men ought always to pray and not to faint. Prayer 
is the key that unlocks heaven's door, and gives man a foreglimpse 
of that house not made with hands, and brings him 
back into full unity with his Father who art in heaven. It 
takes him back through the moulds of God's eternal power, 
<pb id="robinson174" n="174"/>
and restores the image that was defaced by sin into the likeness 
of his creator. “For, as in Adam, all die; even so in 
Christ shall all be made alive.” (1st Cor. 15-22).</p>
        <p>In the year of 1871, when the gold fever was at its height 
in Cheyenne, Wyoming, two young men, inspired by the 
thought of wealth, sacrificed everything, left home and friends 
for the wilds of that unsettled territory, seeking their fortune. 
They were quite fortunate and obtained considerable gold, 
but their anxiety is greater now than it was when they were 
going, for they were not afraid of losing their lives when they 
had no gold, but now they are in constant fear. Therefore 
they had to be on the alert day and night for fear of the band 
of robbers who would murder them for their gold. Hence 
one would walk his beat with gun in hand, with a vigilant 
eye, while the other slept, and vice versa, and they continued 
this for twenty-eight days until they finally reached the border 
states. One night the picket discovered a dim light in the 
distance, quietly awoke his partner and prepared to defend 
themselves from their supposed enemies. Upon reconnoitering 
they soon discovered they had reached the border 
of civilization, and that the dim light discovered was the 
home of an old christian man and his wife, who were only 
too glad to give them shelter, and food such as they had. 
After supper they went up in the loft to go to bed, but not 
being fully satisfied of their safety, neither undressed. One 
slept with rifle in hand, while the other sat at the head of the 
stairs as a sentinel until a late hour in the night, when the 
angelic voice of the old mother was heard singing one of Zion's 
praises. The sentinel sprang to his feet, with joy in 
his soul, as she continued to sing: </p>
        <pb id="robinson175" n="175"/>
        <lg>
          <l>“I'm a poor wayfaring stranger,</l>
          <l>While journeying through this world of woe,</l>
          <l>Yet there's no sickness, toil nor danger,</l>
          <l>In that bright world to which I go.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>I'm going there to see my father, </l>
          <l>I'm going there no more to roam.</l>
          <l>I'm just a going over Jordan</l>
          <l>I'm just a going over home.”</l>
        </lg>
        <p>He rushed to the bed, shook his partner, saying: “John, 
come here quick.” His partner seized his gun and started, 
but he said, “John, lay down your gun and listen.” The old 
folks continued to sing:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>“I know dark clouds will gather round me.</l>
          <l>I know my way is rough and steep.</l>
          <l>Yet brighter fields lie just before me, </l>
          <l>Where God's redeemed their vigil keep.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>I'm going there to see my mother,</l>
          <l>She said she'd meet me when I come.</l>
          <l>I'm just a going over Jordan, </l>
          <l>I'm just a going over home.” </l>
        </lg>
        <p>In a moment they stood in silence in each other's arms, 
with their hearts overflowing with joy. When the silence was 
broken one said to the other, “John, that sounds like our 
mothers in old Indiana.” About this time the old mother 
sang the last verse.</p>
        <pb id="robinson176" n="176"/>
        <lg>
          <l>“I'll soon be free from every trial,</l>
          <l>My body will sleep in the old church yard.</l>
          <l>I'll drop the cross of self denial,</l>
          <l>And enter on my great reward.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>I'm going there to see my Savior,</l>
          <l>To sing His praise in heaven's dome;</l>
          <l>I'm just a going over Jordan</l>
          <l>I'm just a going over home.”</l>
        </lg>
        <p>After this the old mother prayed one of those earnest, 
fervent prayers, asking God to watch over and protect the 
strangers in their home. John said to his partner, “let's undress 
and go to bed for we're all right; we are in a praying 
home.”</p>
        <p>Men ought always to pray and not to faint. Paul, the 
great Gentile preacher, with Silas, his brother, was cast into 
the Philippian jail for preaching Christ as the only hope of 
salvation. They were thrust into prison with their feet in 
the stocks. (Acts 16-22-28th verse). Paul might have asked 
this question of his companion; “why do we stay in this 
dungeon, with our feet in the stocks and our backs bleeding? 
Where is the Christ that met me on the highway to Damascus? 
Where is the God of our fathers, Abraham, Isaac and Jacob, 
who trusted in God and conquered every foe? He has 
promised not to leave nor forsake us.” Let us sing one of the 
songs of Zion, after which they prayed until the heavens 
vibrated and reverberated with the prayers of these saints, 
and God sent down some of heaven's <sic>embassadors</sic>, some of 
the swift winged messengers, and as they hovered above that 
prison the prison was shaken from center to circumference, 
and the bolts and bars were loosened, and God unlocked the 
<pb id="robinson177" n="177"/> 
shackles and manacles that held them in the stocks, and they 
walked out into the corridor of the jail praising God in the 
highest. The jailer felt the shaking of the prison as a mighty 
earthquake. He rushed into the prison and seeing the doors 
all opened, and seeing no man he drew his sword and would 
have taken his own life, for it was certain death for a Roman 
soldier to allow a prisoner to escape. But Paul cried with a 
loud voice, saying; “Do thyself no harm, for we are all here.” 
Then he called for a light, and sprang in and came trembling 
and fell down before Paul and Silas and brought them out, 
and said, “Sirs, what must I do to be saved?” And they 
said, “believe on the Lord Jesus Christ and thou shalt be 
saved, and thy house,” and that night the Philippian jailer and 
his house were converted and baptized unto God, the result of 
prayer.</p>
        <p>Men ought always to pray and not to faint.</p>
        <lg>
          <l>“Prayer is the soul's sincere desire, </l>
          <l>Unuttered or expressed, </l>
          <l>The motion of a hidden fire</l>
          <l>That trembles in the breast  -   </l>
          <l>Prayer is the simplest form of speech </l>
          <l>That infant lips can try; </l>
          <l>It lifts us from the mire and clay </l>
          <l>And plants our feet on high.</l>
          <l>Oh, Thou, by whom to God, we come, </l>
          <l>The truth, the life, the way,</l>
          <l>The path of prayer Thyself hath trod,</l>
          <l>Lord, teach us how to pray.”</l>
        </lg>
      </div1>
      <pb id="robinson178" n="178"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER XXVIII.</head>
        <div2>
          <head>SUBJECT, STANDARD.</head>
          <p>Sermon delivered by Rev. W. H. Robinson, Albia, 
Iowa, A. M. E. Church,  March 28th, 1907.</p>
          <p>“Go through, go through the gates, prepare ye the 
way of the people, cast up, cast up the highway, 
gather out the stones, lift up a standard for the 
people.” This is the prophet's fervent zeal for God's 
promises to his church. Ministers are incited to like 
importunity. Isaiah, the son of Amos, prophesied 
B. C. 760 years, or about that time. God has had a 
man for every time, emergency and purpose. When 
He would raise up a people to Himself, he called 
Abraham, a Chaldean. When He would preserve 
that people's life He prepared a Joseph. When He 
would lead those people to a land of promise he 
called a Moses, a fugitive from Egypt. When He 
heard the cries from the Babylonian captives, who 
cried by reason of their sore affliction, he had a Nehemiah. 
When he heard the cries of the slaves in the 
southland He called in Abraham Lincoln, from the 
Log Cabin in Kentucky, to be the chief magistrate of 
this great nation. Although the nation was baptized 
in human blood, and Lincoln died the death of a martyr, 
he became the great standard of liberty in 
<pb id="robinson179" n="179"/>
America. When the voices of the Cubans and the 
<sic>Philipinoes</sic> reached the throne of our God He gave to 
us a William McKinley, who dared to do and to die 
because he was inspired by the Holy Ghost, all of 
whom became great standards for God and suffering 
humanity.</p>
          <p>Isaiah declared for Zion's sake he would not hold 
peace, and for Jerusalem's sake I will not rest until 
the righteousness thereof go forth as brightness, and 
the salvation thereof as a lamp that burneth and the 
Gentiles shall see their righteousness and all Kings thy 
Glory, and thou shalt be called by a new name which 
the mouth of the Lord shall name. Thou shalt also be 
a crown of glory in the hands of the Lord and a royal 
diadem in the hand of thy God. This subject has a 
two-fold meaning; a spiritual and literal. The spiritual 
and literal. The spiritual, Isaiah points the people 
to the coming King, and said to his kingdom there 
should he no end. [See Isaiah 9-6.] For unto us a 
child is horn, unto us a son is given, and the government 
shall he upon His shoulders, and His name shall 
be called wonderful counselor, the almighty God, the 
everlasting father, the Prince of Peace. (Isaiah 9-7: 
Of the increase of His government and peace there 
shall be no end. Upon the throne of David and upon 
his kingdom, to order it anti to establish it with judgment 
and with justice from henceforth, even forever. 
(See Isaiah 63; 1st to 6th verses). Who is this that 
cometh from Edom with dyed garments from Bozrah? 
This that is glorious in his apparel, traveling in the 
greatness of his strength? I that speak in righteousness 
<pb id="robinson180" n="180"/> 
mighty to save. Wherefore art thou red in 
thine apparel, and thy garments like him that treadeth 
in the wine fat? I have trodden the wine-press alone 
and of the people. </p>
          <p>There was none with me, for I will tread them in 
my fury, and their blood shall be sprinkled upon my 
garments, and I will stain all my raiments, for the day 
of vengeance is in my heart, and the year of my redeemed 
is come. And I looked and there was none to 
help, and I wondered that there was none to uphold; 
therefore mine own arms brought salvation unto me, 
and my fury it upheld me, and this is the great standard 
that was to be a light to the feet of the Gentiles, 
and a lamp to the pathway that was to shine away the 
darkness of the valley of the shadow of death. (Text) 
“Go through, go through the gates, prepare ye the 
way of the people. Cast up, cast up the highway, 
gather out the stones, lift up a standard for the people.” 
The four gates to the garden of Eden were closed by 
the fall of Adam. The four gates of the city of New 
Jerusalem were opened by the birth, suffering death, 
resurrection, and ascension of the Lord Jesus Christ. 
For death reigned from Adam to Christ, but life shall 
reign from time to eternity, for Jesus said (St. John 
11:25). “I am the resurrection and the life, he that 
believeth in me, though he were dead, yet shall he 
live (26th) and whosoever liveth and believeth in me 
shall never die.” (See Matthew 3: 1st to 4th verses.) 
“In those days came John the Baptist preaching in the 
wilderness of Judea, and saying, repent ye, for the 
kingdom of Heaven is at hand. For this is he that  
<pb id="robinson181" n="181"/> 
was spoken of by the prophet Isaiah, saying, the voice 
of one crying in the wilderness, prepare ye the way of 
the Lord. Make His path straight.” John was the 
great standard of righteousness in the wilderness. 
Then cometh Jesus from Gallilee to Jordan unto John 
to be baptized of him. But John forbade Him, saying, 
“I have need to be <sic>baptizied</sic> of thee; and cometh Thou 
to me?” And Jesus answering said unto him: “Suffer 
it to be so now, for thus it becometh us to fulfill all 
righteousness.” Then He suffered Him, and Jesus, 
when he was baptized, went up straightway out of the 
water, and lo the heavens were opened unto Him, and 
He saw the spirit of God ascending and descending  like 
a dove and lighting upon Him, and lo, a voice from 
heaven saying, this is thy beloved Son, in whom I am 
well pleased. </p>
          <p>And this is the standard that Isaiah saw through the 
spirit more than 760 years before he came, and prophesied 
concerning Him. Priests and prophets prayed to 
see the light of the coming king, who was to redeem 
Israel from the curse of a broken law, for the sentence 
of death was passed upon all men. Therefore (Job 14- 
14) ask this question: “If a man die shall he live 
again?” And Jesus, the standard of salvation, answered 
and said, “because I live ye shall live also.” (John 
14-19.) And he said unto Mary and Martha, the two 
orphan girls who had lain their only brother in the 
silent city of the dead and were now kneeling at the 
feet of Jesus and bewailing their loss, when Martha 
said unto Him, “if thou hadst been here my brother 
had not died, but I know that even now whatsoever  
<pb id="robinson182" n="182"/>
thou ask of God, God will give it thee,” Jesus said 
unto her, “thy brother shall rise again.” “Martha 
said unto Him, “I know that he will rise again in the 
resurrection at the last day.” Jesus said unto her, “I 
am the resurrection and the life, he that believeth in 
me, though he were dead yet shall he live:” (John 11
-21 and 25th verses). So the world need not worry or 
have any fear concerning eternal life, for God has so 
declared that before one jot or tittle of His word shall 
fail, heaven and earth shall pass away. (Rev. 21:1-3). 
And John declared “he saw a new heaven and a new 
earth, for the first heaven and the first earth were 
passed away, and there was no more sea, and I, John, 
saw the holy city, New Jerusalem, coming down from 
God out of heaven, prepared as a bride adorned for 
her husband.” And we know that it must have been 
a beautiful sight that dazzled the eyes of the most expectant. 
“And I heard A great voice out of heaven 
saying, behold, the tabernacle of God is with men, and 
He will dwell with them and they shall be His people, 
and God himself shall be with them and be their God.” 
This is a glorious promise. This destroys the very 
fear of death from the minds of God's true pilgrims, so 
that they wade out into the turbulent waters of the 
valley and shadow of death, and, like David the shepherd 
king, defy the presence of death. And as he 
sees the approaching of the grim monster, he buckles 
on <sic>armour</sic>, his <sic>habiliment</sic>, girds up his loins  -  with a 
girdle of God's eternal truth, tries his shield that bears 
the marks of many spears shot at him by the enemy, 
<pb id="robinson183" n="183"/>
unsheathes his sword and marches out to meet the last 
enemy to be conquered, which is death. </p>
          <p>Hush! I hear the din of the battle. It is fierce, 
long and loud. The combatants on one side are fighting 
for truth and righteousness; the other side for 
death and destruction. The captain on one side is 
Apolian, the prince of the powers of the air. The 
other one is the Alpha and Omega. the beginning and 
the end, the first and the last, who conquered the 
powers of death and hell, robbed the grave of her 
victory and death of its sting, mounted the clouds of 
the morning with a convoy of angels as his escort, 
soared back to his father's house with a promise of 
another comforter to the world, and sitteth at the 
right hand of God the Father Almighty, where he 
maketh intercession for the Saints.</p>
          <p>The great standard of righteousness, the literal side 
of the prophet's definition, points to the Babylonian 
captivity. Looking down through the telescope of 
time, he sees the Israelites, the chosen people of God, 
the Abrahamic seed, 767 years before the event really 
takes place, led away from Jerusalem, and their native 
land, by Nebuchadnezzar, king of Babylon, captives. 
Isaiah heard the echo of their wails, and the deep 
groaning of their souls as they are marching from their 
native land destined to a life of servitude which must 
last for 70 years. They yet bear the scars and sore 
feet of weary years of an Egyptian bondage, where 
they toiled 450 years under Pharaoh, the King of 
Egypt. Led out by Moses, God's standard bearer, 
they could hear the hoof and steel of Pharaoh's horses 
<pb id="robinson184" n="184"/>
and chariots. They could hear the stern command of 
that mighty king, urging his army on to overtake 
them. I can hear their wails to Moses, their leader 
and standard bearer. I can see Moses, God's standard 
bearer, as he goes to headquarters for orders, as he 
listens to the tramp of his enemies, and the rumbling 
of their chariot wheels. He makes this inquiry; “Lord, 
what shall I do?” God said to him; “tell the people 
to stand still and see the salvation of God, for the 
enemy you see today you shall soon see them no more 
forever.” He commanded Moses to take the staff that 
he had in his hand, and pass it three times over the 
waters of the Red Sea, and the water became frightened 
at itself, for God sent down a trade wind that night 
and divided the water from the water. Having thus 
pontooned the Red Sea, dry land appeared, and the 
people marched over dry shod. God put a pillar of 
cloud by day and a pillar of fire by night, so it was 
darkness to the Egyptians by day and by night, but 
light to the Israelites. When Israel had crossed the 
Red Sea and the Egyptians attempted to do the same, 
God spoke to the waters, and the Egyptians were destroyed. 
Israel looked back, and sang this triumphant
song:</p>
          <lg>
            <l>“Isaac, a ransom while he lay</l>
            <l>Upon the altar bound;</l>
            <l>Moses, an infant cast away,</l>
            <l>By Pharaoh's daughter found. </l>
          </lg>
          <pb id="robinson185" n="185"/>
          <lg>
            <l>Didn't old Pharaoh get lost,</l>
            <l>Get lost: get lost?</l>
            <l>Oh, didn't old Pharaoh get lost, </l>
            <l>All in the Red Sea?”</l>
          </lg>
          <p>Said they, the horseman and his rider are over-thrown, 
and God has delivered his people from the 
hand of Pharaoh?”</p>
          <p>[Text] Lift up a standard for the people. They 
wandered forty years in the wilderness. They were unfaithful 
and unthankful. They murmured and complained 
all the time. When they were hungry, God 
fed them bread made up by the spoken word of His 
Power and fed it to them fresh and flakey every morning. 
And Jesus says I am the bread of life. Jesus is 
to the soul what the manna was to the body of the 
Israelites. For forty years they wandered in the wilderness, 
because of their disobedience, and today the 
church of God is wandering because of retrogration 
from the true standard of God. We are taking on too 
much of the world, and too little of God. Israel's 
sins led them into many pitfalls. Finally they were 
bitten by the fiery serpents, and died by the thousands. 
God commanded Moses, the standard bearer, to mould 
a serpent of brass and lift it up in the wilderness and 
to tell the people to look upon it and they should be 
healed. But thousands died because they would not 
look. Jesus said, “as Moses lifted up the serpent in 
the wilderness, even so must the son of man be lifted 
up.” As the great standard of the human family, the 
Lord help us to look and live. Sinners, which will 
<pb id="robinson186" n="186"/>
you do? Look and live, or close your eyes and die? 
(Text) Lift up a standard for the people. (See illustration). 
In 1869 your humble servant made a trip 
to London, England. While there I met a German 
whose sympathy was very strong for me and my people 
in this country, and we were together nearly every 
day while there. He had been a sailor for forty years, 
and I being a natural born mariner it blended us very 
close together. We would stand upon the pier of that 
great harbor, where we could see the white winged 
doves of commerce coming from every civilized quarter 
of the earth, and as I saw the different flags at the 
mastheads I would say to my friend. “where does that 
ship come from?” Without waiting to read the inscription 
on the ensign he would say, “from Italy”. 
“And this one?” “from France.” “And this?” from 
Germany.” “And this?” from Russia.” “And this” 
“from Spain etc.” But when I saw the old star 
spangled banner I did not have to ask any questions. 
I knew it was the standard that was unfurled over me at 
Blue Springs, Tennessee. In November, 1863, just 
after being captured from the confederate army, General 
Thomas had me stand in the door of his tent, and 
ordered the national flag unfurled. It was very calm, 
not a breath of air stirring, but just as General Thomas 
stepped to my side it seemed as if God sent a providential 
breeze along, and it wrapped the old flag all 
around us. General Thomas, who controlled the union 
army of the Tennessee said, “today this flea makes you 
a free man.” I wept for joy, standing under the 
great standard of liberty, for I could now sing the 
<pb id="robinson187" n="187"/>
national air, the land of the free and the home of the 
brave. In the true sense of patriotism I had worn the 
shackles of literal bondage for years, but in due season 
God emancipated me from being the goods and chattels 
of other men, so I could think and act for myself as a 
man. But thanks be to God, in 1877, he emancipated 
my soul from the bondage of sin. </p>
          <p>When I saw the standard of America I asked no 
questions. So it ought to he with every true child of 
God, who has been freed from the bondage of sin, and 
made heirs and joint heirs of the Lord Jesus Christ and 
become such lofty standards that we would be living 
epistles, read and known of all men as the standards of 
Jesus. (Text). Lift up a standard for the people. 
There are so many ways we can be standards. First, 
by faithfulness to the cause we represent. Second, by 
our Christian fidelity, truth and righteousness. Love 
God supremely. Be at peace with all men. In order 
to do this we must keep aloft the standard of prayer, 
which is a weapon sharper than any two edged sword. 
It is a standard of power that even the heathen in the 
jungles of Africa recognize and reverence, though their 
deity is nothing but a dumb idol. They bow down to 
it and utter some form of prayer. Hence we can see 
the necessity of the standard of prayer. (See illustration). 
In 1871 this country sent a representative to 
Madrid, Spain. In the Spanish courts they 
found some technicality in the official acts of Mr. 
Woods. They gave him a trial and sentenced him to 
death, and within three days of the time of execution 
the law said, a man sentenced to death must be executed 
<pb id="robinson188" n="188"/> 
the very day and minute specified in his sentence. 
If not, it gave him sufficient grounds for a new trial. 
The honorable James G. Blaine was at that time secretary 
of war, and saw the necessity of prolonging the 
time, so that Mr. Woods could have a fair and impartial 
trial, that he might vindicate himself. He 
asked Queen Victoria, of England, to order her representatives, 
with the flag of her country, to be on the 
spot of execution. He also made the same request to 
the czar of Russia. He ordered an American representative, 
with the stars and stripes, with the other 
nations, and a few minutes before the time of execution 
they wrapped Mr. Woods up in these three flags. 
Twenty four men, with loaded guns, are waiting for 
orders to send the leaden messenger of death into the 
body of Mr. Woods. The time is up. Attention is 
called But there is no command to fire. The question 
is asked, “why don't you give the command to 
shoot? The time is up.” The answer is, “how can 
we shoot a man through the flags of three great nations?” 
The time of execution is past. Mr. Woods was taken 
back to prison, had a fair and impartial trial, and was 
set at liberty. Now, if the standards of three nations 
can save a man from a literal death, what must the 
standard of Calvary do? Every strand of thread in 
that flag is stained in the blood of Calvary's lamb. And 
Jesus said unto the dying thief, “today shalt thou be 
with me in paradise.” (Text): Lift up the standard 
for the people. He was crucified, dead and buried. 
The third day he arose from the dead, and said, “I am 
he that liveth, and was dead, and behold I am alive 
forevermore, and have the keys of death and hell. 
Amen.”</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="robinson189" n="189"/>
        <div2>
          <head>MY THANKS BE UNTO YOU.</head>
          <p>The following are a few voluntarily contributed testimonials 
by friends who have read my life's history 
work entitled, “From Log Cabin to the Pulpit,” all 
of which I most heartily appreciate and extend my sincere 
and earnest thanks to those who have thus taken 
such warm interest in both myself and daughter, and 
in the work we are endeavoring to accomplish for humanity 
through the aid of and in the name of the Lord 
Jesus Christ, our Savior, and the Savior of all mankind 
who wish his help and are willing to follow him 
and his teachings. God extends his help to all. </p>
          <closer>
            <signed>
              <name>W. H. ROBINSON. </name>
            </signed>
          </closer>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <opener><dateline>EAU CLAIRE, WIS.,  JULY 8, 1913.  </dateline>
<salute>TO WHOM IT MAY CONCERN: </salute></opener>
          <p>I have been personally acquainted with Rev. W. H. 
Robinson, of this city, for several years. I have 
read his book, “From Log Cabin to the Pulpit,” 
which contains his life's history and reminiscences of 
the Civil war, which gave him his freedom from slavery, 
and I cannot recommend either him or his publication 
too highly, and hope all my friends will read 
this history of his life.</p>
          <closer><salute>Respectfully Yours, </salute>
<signed><name>G. E. CLARK, D. D. S.</name></signed></closer>
        </div2>
        <pb id="robinson190" n="190"/>
        <div2>
          <opener>
            <dateline>EAU CLAIRE, WIS., JUNE 14, 1913.</dateline>
          </opener>
          <p>I believe that the story of the life of W. H. Robinson, 
as told by himself, is one of those interesting bits 
of personal history, reaching back into the slavery days 
of our nation. I also believe that the purpose of the 
man himself is high and earnest. He is trying to 
make his life count for the best things.</p>
          <closer><salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>A<name>. E. LEONARD, </name>
First Congregational Church, </signed></closer>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <opener>
            <dateline>EAU CLAIRE, WIS., JUNE 27, 1913. </dateline>
          </opener>
          <p>I have known W. H. Robinson for some time, and 
am glad to give personal testimony to my belief in him 
as an earnest, honest, consecrated christian gentleman. 
I have not read his autobiography, but having heard 
him in the lecture on his life, am sure that the book 
will be found intensely interesting, and profitable reading. </p>
          <closer>
            <signed><name>L. E. OSGOOD,</name>
Pastor Second Congregational Church. </signed>
          </closer>
        </div2>
        <pb id="robinson191" n="191"/>
        <div2>
          <opener>
            <dateline>EAU CLAIRE, WIS., JUNE 2, 1913.</dateline>
          </opener>
          <p>I have read the book entitled “From Log Cabin to 
the Pulpit,” by the Rev. W. H. Robinson, and find 
many interesting narrations of striking events. The 
book is well worthy the attention of all interested in 
the history of our country. </p>
          <closer>
            <signed><name>M. BENSON,</name>
Minister in Methodist Episcopal Church. </signed>
          </closer>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <opener><dateline>CHICAGO, ILL., JUNE 27, 1910. </dateline>
<salute>TO WHOM IT MAY CONCERN:</salute></opener>
          <p>This is to certify that I am personally acquainted 
with Evangelist Wm. H. Robinson, who has been in 
this city for the past few months doing excellent service. 
His work in the churches of this city has been 
great. I therefore recommend him to the ministers of 
the A. M. E. Zion church or in any other field. He 
will render you valiant service. I am sure that whatever 
you may do for him will he appreciated.</p>
          <p>His daughter is one of the sweetest singers in Israel, 
and a faithful christian worker. I am,</p>
          <closer><salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed><name>J. B. COLBERT,  </name>
Pastor of Walter's A.M.E. Zion Church</signed><signed><name>B. G. SHAW,</name>Presiding Elder, Chicago District, of the Michigan Conference. </signed></closer>
        </div2>
        <pb id="robinson192" n="192"/>
        <div2>
          <opener><dateline>EAU CLAIRE DISTRICT                   WEST WISCONSIN CONFERENCE.
LAKE STREET METHODIST EPISCOPAL CHURCH</dateline>
<dateline>FRANK LEE ROBERTS, PASTOR,
Residence 329 Lake Street,</dateline>
<dateline>EAU CLAIRE, WISCONSIN.</dateline>
<salute>TO WHOM IT MAY CONCERN:</salute></opener>
          <p>This is to certify that the Rev. Wm. H. Robinson is 
personally known to me as a devout, consecrated 
christian. and a man of considerable ability. His time 
is devoted to the building of God's Kingdom on earth, 
and his labors have been abundantly blessed. Many, 
because of his ministry, can testify to the saving power 
of Jesus Christ. I have read his book entitled, “From 
Log Cabin to the Pulpit” and am of the opinion that it 
merits a wide reading. To whomsoever this book is 
allowed to present its message, I predict a wider vision 
of true usefulness and a firmer desire to live a holy 
life. Such is the testimony herein that one must needs 
marvel at the wonderful way in which God leads the 
way upward for a human soul. </p>
          <closer><salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed><name>FRANK LEE ROBERTS,</name>
Pastor Lake Street Methodist Episcopal Church. </signed></closer>
        </div2>
        <pb id="robinson193" n="193"/>
        <div2>
          <opener><dateline>METHODIST EPISCOPAL CHURCH, 
WEST WISCONSIN CONFERENCE 
(EAU CLAIRE DISTRICT)</dateline> 
REV. S. A. BENDER, SUPERINTENDENT. 
<dateline>EAU CLAIRE, WIS., JUNE 6, 1913. </dateline></opener>
          <p>It is a genuine pleasure to write a word of appreciation 
of “From Log Cabin to the Pulpit.” It is a 
pleasure because of the intrinsic worth of the book, 
and the writer's appreciation of the personal character 
of the author.</p>
          <p>No one of a religious spirit can read this book without 
having his faith in the fact of God's providential 
care in the behalf of the humblest of His children 
greatly strengthened. The book is of worth also as a 
contribution to the history of the institution of slavery, 
and of the epoch of emancipation. This autobiography 
makes for optimism, and inspires the reader to a more 
manful fight to attain spiritual freedom. He who 
reads this book will be a better man for spending a 
time with our author in the recital of this own God 
guided life from slavery to freedom. </p>
          <p>We wish for this book a large circulation, and bid 
it God speed on its mission.</p>
          <closer>
            <signed>
              <name>S. A. BENDER. </name>
            </signed>
          </closer>
        </div2>
        <pb id="robinson194" n="194"/>
        <div2>
          <head>A LETTER TO THE PEOPLE OF EAU CLAIRE,
WISCONSIN. </head>
          <p>In 1910 we became residents of Eau Claire. I want 
to say that I have traveled quite extensively, at home, 
and abroad, but I have never met such a body of warm 
hearted ministers as in Eau Claire; men who at once 
became interested in my daughter and self, and seemed 
to have no thought of the “black rubbing off.” They 
belong to that class of men who look beyond the color 
of the skin or the texture of the hair, and they immediately 
extended a brotherly hand. “As the priest, 
so the people.” Like a strong cable they have held 
me up. With one hand in God's, and the other in the 
hands of the good people in Eau Claire I could not fall.</p>
          <p>My first service here was in the Lake Street Methodist 
Episcopal Church, by invitation of Rev. Guy W. 
Campbell and his good people. I preached four nights 
and gave a lecture entitled, “From Log Cabin to the 
Pulpit.” God raised up in a very short time many, 
many warm hearted friends in that church. See letter 
of recommendation written. to Rev. C. H. Harris, 
pastor of the Holcombe Methodist Episcopal Church, 
Holcombe, Wisconsin. </p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="robinson195" n="195"/>
        <div2>
          <opener><dateline>LAKE STREET METHODIST EPISCOPAL CHURCH, 
WEST WISCONSIN CONFERENCE,
EAU CLAIRE DISTRICT,</dateline>
GUY W. CAMPBELL, PASTOR. 
<dateline>EAU CLAIRE, WIS., OCT. 18, 1910. </dateline>
<salute><name>REV. C. H. HARRIS, </name>
Holcombe, Wis. </salute></opener>
          <p>Dear Brother:  -  I tried to get you by phone Sunday 
evening but could not. Now  I will try you by letter.</p>
          <p>I have recently had a negro and his daughter hold a 
few nights' services in my church. He is an ex-slave 
and a very good speaker. He spoke three nights in 
succession in my church and then gave a lecture on 
the subject, “From Log Cabin to the Pulpit”  His 
sermons and lecture were good.</p>
          <p>Now he wants to put in a few weeks around here 
before he goes to Texas to take up Evangelistic work 
there. I could get him for you for the first of next 
week, beginning the 24th if you desire him. He will 
come on this arrangement. Your church will provide 
entertainment, he will preach three nights and then 
give the lecture for 25 and 10 cents a ticket, the proceeds 
of which he takes as his compensation. </p>
          <p>He was at the Salvation Army Barracks here last 
week, and they were so pleased with his work that they 
insisted on his staying this week also.</p>
          <p>I spoke to Brother Straw last week about getting 
this man a few nights' appointments about here, and 
he immediately suggested Holcombe. He has heard 
<pb id="robinson196" n="196"/> 
him preach and give his lecture, and desired me to convey 
his unqualified recommendation to you. </p>
          <p>We will not have many opportunities from now on 
to secure such men. Their ranks are being thinned 
about as fast as those of the old soldiers. This will 
give your young people an opportunity to hear and 
see a real ex-slave. </p>
          <p>Now if you want this man write me as soon as possible. 
His name is W. H. Robinson. He and his 
daughter are fairly good singers also.</p>
          <closer><salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed><name>GUY W. CAMPBELL.</name></signed></closer>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <p>We spent two weeks in Holcombe with the result 
that twenty-five were happily converted and united 
with the church. From there we went to other points 
in Wisconsin. In Eau Claire and vicinity, to date, we 
have seen over eight hundred people born into the 
Kingdom of God, for which we give Him the glory, 
for God forbid that I glory in anything save the cross 
of Christ. May God bless the people of Eau Claire 
for their kindness to us.</p>
          <p>I want to thank my landlord, Mr. Stephen D. 
Hoover, and Mr. A. V. Mayhew, who made it possible 
for me to finance this edition of my history. I appreciate 
their true friendship. May they live long to do 
much good for the Master's Kingdom; also Mr. B. R. 
Barland, real estate man, for his untiring interest in 
us.</p>
          <pb id="robinson197" n="197"/>
          <p>Believing that the large and fruitful work extending 
over a series of years by the Rev. W. H. Robinson, as 
an Evangelist, and his daughter assisting him as a 
singer, is worthy of recognition, and to the end that 
loyal effort, in the cause of truth and righteousness 
may not go unrewarded. </p>
          <p>I believe the good people of Eau Claire will join with 
me in the sentiment and aid which have enabled the 
worthy Evangelist to publish in book form a narrative 
of his very interesting life; a life beginning as a slave, 
with its atrocious incidents; his experiences as a union 
soldier; the acquiring of an education, and the consecrated 
use of that education for the uplifting of humanity; 
the object of such publication being the very 
commendable desire to carry the gospel to his people 
in Africa, his father's native land.</p>
          <p>If we as citizens, and friends of humanity, will each 
purchase a copy, we will certainly get value received 
from the contents of this valuable book, and at the 
same time help him to answer the call of His Master,
“Go ye into all the world and preach the gospel to 
every creature. </p>
          <closer>
            <signed>
              <name>B. R. BARLAND. </name>
            </signed>
          </closer>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <p>I wish also to thank the publisher and his helpers 
for the interest taken in me, and for the good work 
they have done in getting out a more presentable 
book than the former ones were. Their suggestions 
and help in various ways have enabled me to re-edit 
my book, and to bring this edition up to a higher 
standard. </p>
          <p>I send this little book on its mission of love to all. </p>
          <closer><salute>Yours for Christ, </salute>
<signed><name>W. H. ROBINSON. </name></signed></closer>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
    <back>
      <pb id="robinson198" n="198"/>
      <div1>
        <head>INDEX.</head>
        <list type="simple">
          <item>Presentation  -  Endorsements . . . .  <ref target="robinson6" targOrder="U">6</ref></item>
          <item>Author's preface . . . . <ref target="robinson9" targOrder="U">9</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER I  -  My family history, etc.  -  The Underground Ry. . . . . <ref target="robinson11" targOrder="U">11-15</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER II  -  Plan for father's freedom  -  Our Quaker friends 
  -  Father buys his freedom  -   The trip to California  -  The betrayal  -  
His return in chains . . . . <ref target="robinson16" targOrder="U">16-18</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER III  -  The overseer and taskmaster  -  The slave 
hunter  -  Lee's negro traders' pen at Richmond, Virginia . . . . <ref target="robinson20" targOrder="U">20-22</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER IV  -  The false charge against father  -  Returned to 
slavery again  -  Pathetic parting  -  Our family scattered . . . . <ref target="robinson23" targOrder="U">23-27</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER V  -  Mother and three children willed to Scott Cowens 
  -  Cowens strikes mother and I strike him  -  I run away . . . . <ref target="robinson28" targOrder="U">28-32</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER VI  -  Uncle Amos, the prophet  -  Murder of Frank 
Anderson  -  Lincoln, our second Moses  -  Three dollars paid 
for return of runaway negroes . . . . <ref target="robinson34" targOrder="U">34-37</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER VII  -  Separated from my mother  -  Terrible whipping 
from my master  -  In the traders' pen at Richmond  -  Heinous
treatment of Fannie Woods and her babies . . . . <ref target="robinson39" targOrder="U">39-44</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER VIII  -  Humiliating treatment of the ladies  -  I was 
sold on the block for $1,150  -  A slave whipped to death  -   
Mothers separated from their children . . . . <ref target="robinson45" targOrder="U">45-50</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER IX  -  Another new master  -  My first supper and the 
clever ruse of the milk-maid  -  Horrible murder of a slave
whose task was too heavy . . . . <ref target="robinson51" targOrder="U">51-56</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER X  -  My second runaway  -  The old colored mother 
who befriended me  -  The efficacy of onions . . . . <ref target="robinson58" targOrder="U">58-61</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER XI  -  The hounds after me and the use of onions 
  -  My ruse to cross the ferry  -  Quick witted Sambo  -  Captured 
again . . . . <ref target="robinson62" targOrder="U">62-67</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER XII  -  Back to Lee's traders' pen again  -  A mother 
drowns herself and child  -  I learn of my mother . . . . <ref target="robinson68" targOrder="U">68-71</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER XIII  -  Bought by Mr. Hadley and see mother again
  -  I am kissed by a white woman  -  My happiness with 
mother soon ended . . . . <ref target="robinson72" targOrder="U">72-75</ref></item>
          <pb id="robinson199" n="199"/>
          <item>CHAPTER XIV  -  Back to Cowens family again  -  Uncle Tom, 
the overseer  -  The war approaching  -  The Southern Confederacy 
first meets at Montgomery, Alabama  -  Jefferson 
Davis elected president His speech at Wilmington  -  How
the slaves held church  -  Negro tricks . . . . <ref target="robinson76" targOrder="U">76-80</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER XV  -  Slave holders' consistent family worship and 
sermon . . . . <ref target="robinson81" targOrder="U">81-88</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER XVI  -  Ft. Sumpter fired upon  -  The war begun in 
earnest  -  Joy of Uncle Tom and the slaves  -  How I delivered 
a note to my mistress  -  I go to the war with my master
to “whip the Yankees in three days” . . . . <ref target="robinson91" targOrder="U">91-96</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER XVII  -  The first battles of the war  -  Death of my 
master and my capture by the Yankees  -  The incident before 
“Pap” Thomas  -  Am now a soldier for the union  -   
Meet my mother at Greenville  -  Taking a load of contrabands 
with us on the march  -  How I paid for a cabin  -  The
first colored troops from the free states . . . . <ref target="robinson98" targOrder="U">98-109</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER XVIII  -  Rescue of union soldier by Aunt Nancy 
Jordan . . . . <ref target="robinson111" targOrder="U">111-113</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER XIX  -  The negro in it  -  My enlistment  -  Regular 
battles I was in  -  Search for mother  -  My brother's escape 
from slavery  -  Mother found  -  Re-union of mother and six
of the children . . . . <ref target="robinson115" targOrder="U">115-120</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER XX  -   My work in the Nashville fire department  -   
Finding of another brother  -  Reception given us  -  Brother's 
terrible death  -  Tour with Tennessee Singers  -  Engagement 
with Hanlon's Wizard Oil Company  -  Trip to London, 
England  -  Education begins  -  Letter to President Grant  -  
Return to America . . . . <ref target="robinson121" targOrder="U">121-132</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER XXI  -  Entrance into college and politics  -  I teach 
school  -  Enter employment of car company  -  Narrow escape 
from death  -  My great conviction Happily converted . . . . <ref target="robinson134" targOrder="U">134-140</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER XXII  -  My visions  -  I join Baptist church  -  Afterward 
join M. E. church and become member of Indiana District 
conference  -  Credentials given me by Bishop Foster . . . . <ref target="robinson141" targOrder="U">141-145</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER XXIII  -  My marriage  -  Children  -  Death of wife . . . . <ref target="robinson146" targOrder="U">146-149</ref></item>
          <pb id="robinson200" n="200"/>
          <item>CHAPTER XXIV  -  Taking up Evangelistic work  -  My daughter 
Dora's death . . . . <ref target="robinson150" targOrder="U">150-151</ref></item>
          <item>The child's inquiry . . . . <ref target="robinson152" targOrder="U">152-157</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER XXV  -  Origin of my family name . . . . <ref target="robinson158" targOrder="U">158-159</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER XXVI  -  Keeping the charge of the Lord  -  Sermon, 
“The Exaltation of Christ” . . . . <ref target="robinson162" targOrder="U">162-169</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER XXVIII  -  Sermon. “Prayer” . . . . <ref target="robinson170" targOrder="U">170-177</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER XXVIII- -Sermon, “Standards” . . . . <ref target="robinson178" targOrder="U">178-188</ref></item>
          <item>Testimonials . . . . <ref target="robinson189" targOrder="U">189-193</ref> </item>
          <item>Author's letter of thanks . . . . <ref target="robinson194" targOrder="U">194-197</ref> </item>
        </list>
      </div1>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI.2>