<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % external-entities SYSTEM "./extEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY % internal-entities SYSTEM "./intEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY levtp SYSTEM "levtp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY levvs SYSTEM "levvs.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY levcv SYSTEM "levcv.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>Memoirs of Margaret Jane Blake of Baltimore, Md.,  
and Selections in Prose and Verse:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Sarah R. Levering</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Chris Hill</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by</resp>
          <name>Chris Hill</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns"> Sarah Reuning and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1999</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca.  100  K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1999.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, 
teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability 
is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note anchored="yes">Call number  E 444 .B63       
(Langsdale Library, University of Baltimore)</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>MEMOIRS OF MARGARET JANE BLAKE OF BALTIMORE, MD.,
 AND SELECTIONS IN PROSE AND VERSE</title>
<author>Sarah R. Levering</author><imprint><pubPlace>200 South 10th Street, Philadelphia</pubPlace><publisher>Press of Innes &amp; Son</publisher><date>1897</date></imprint></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>This electronic edition has been transcribed from the original provided by 
Langsdale Library, University of Baltimore.</p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ 
respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been 
preserved.</p>
        <p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor 
(SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
<edition>21st edition, 1998</edition></bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Blake, Margaret Jane, 1811-1880.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Maryland -- Baltimore -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Freedmen -- Maryland -- Baltimore -- Biography.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2000-02-16, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-08-31, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-08-19, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Sarah Reuning</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-07-29, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Chris Hill</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="cover image">
        <p>
          <figure id="cover" entity="levcv">
            <p>[Cover Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="title page image">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="levtp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="title page verso image">
        <p>
          <figure id="verso" entity="levvs">
            <p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main"><hi rend="bold">Memoirs</hi><lb/>
OF<lb/>
<hi rend="bold">Margaret Jane Blake</hi><lb/>
OF<lb/>
<hi rend="bold">Baltimore, Md.,</hi></titlePart>
          <titlePart type="main">AND<lb/>
<hi rend="bold">Selections in Prose and Verse</hi></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <lb/>
        <byline>BY
</byline>
        <docAuthor>
          <hi rend="bold">Sarah R. Levering.</hi>
        </docAuthor>
        <pb id="levverso" n="verso"/>
        <docImprint>
          <docDate>COPYRIGHT, 1897<lb/>
BY SARAH R. LEVERING.</docDate>
          <publisher>PRESS OF INNES&amp; SON<lb/>
200 SOUTH 10TH STREET, PHILADELPHIA</publisher>
        </docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <div1>
        <pb id="leviii" n="iii"/>
        <p>To my Mother<lb/>
of blessed memory<lb/>
is this little volume inscribed.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1>
        <pb id="levv" n="v"/>
        <head>PREFACE</head>
        <p>THE negro enslaved of yore is now a free man, and as a
citizen of an enlightened nation is fully entitled to an
education to enable him to enjoy the blessings of
freedom.</p>
        <p>The Presbytery of Baltimore hold in possession the deed
for a pretty little farm located in Harford county, Maryland,
on the Little Gunpowder River. It is hilly ground, far above
the river, the foot of the hills only washed by the stream. It
is impossible for the water to rise high enough to damage
crops or buildings on the land. The land is good, with
abundant sweet, cold spring water to be had in all seasons;
the spring has never been known to fail. One farmer
occupied the premises twelve years and had a large family of
children who were the healthiest of the healthy in all the
region around. The proceeds from the sale of this booklet
will be appropriated to the improvement of “Dingley Dell,”
the farm upon which the Presbytery of Baltimore proposes
to establish a manual labor school for the benefit of the
<pb id="levvi" n="vi"/>
Afro-American citizens, as they prefer being called. Said
school is to be established as soon as there are funds
enough to erect suitable buildings. A large sum of money
will be required to establish this enterprise, and the sooner
the money is collected the sooner it will be an accomplished
fact. Now, if every Afro-American will pay the price of this
little book a good sum will be realized, and perhaps some
other friend or friends of education may be moved to write
another book for the same cause and help along the much-desired 
object. The Presbytery will be encouraged to move
forward, to the joy of all who feel any interest in this matter.</p>
        <p>Some may wish to know why the selection of pieces was
added to the memoir of Margaret Jane Blake. All of them
were written by persons with whom she was acquainted and
some were composed on persons in whom she felt great
interest. The “Unwelcome Guest” is a partial description of a
beautiful house in which she served as a housemaid. A
careful examination of the lines called “The Bride” will show
the maiden name of the lady in whose service she died.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed>THE AUTHORESS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1>
        <pb id="lev7" n="7"/>
        <head>MARGARET JANE BLAKE.<lb/>
A MEMOIR.</head>
        <docAuthor>BY SARAH R. LEVERING.</docAuthor>
        <epigraph>
          <p>“A good name is rather to be chosen than great riches.” <bibl>— <hi rend="italics">Proverbs</hi>.</bibl></p>
        </epigraph>
        <p>THE subject of this memoir, though born a slave, was of
illustrious parentage, inasmuch as her father and mother
were virtuous and patriotic, this combination having always
been esteemed the foundation of noble character. Her father,
Perry Blake, was a marine in the United States navy, and
Commodore Porter himself informed my father that Perry
Blake fought bravely under his command. He was a
powerfully built man, and no doubt he rendered willing and
efficient service to his country in the War of 1812-15 against
Great Britain. Perry Blake was married to Charlotte, a slave
belonging to my father. Charlotte was as patriotic as her free
husband, and took long walks to bear provisions to the
young men of her master's household who were under arms
during the attack of the British on the city of Baltimore. Her
unremitting and cheerful service during this anxious
<pb id="lev8" n="8"/>
time in comforting the soldiers with home news and
dainties won the gratitude of her master, Mr. Jesse Levering,
and he manumitted Charlotte, thus making her equal to her
husband. But it was strange that she looked back to her old
home with infinite longing and desired to return to her
bonds. This could not be granted her, and, failing in that
petition, she begged that none of her children should be set
free. That was agreed upon, and during my parents' lifetime
the children of these free parents remained slaves. Perry and
Charlotte Blake had several children. Margaret Jane was
born in 1811, in my father's house on Lombard street, in the
city of Baltimore, Maryland, and throve with the children of
the family until the measles broke out among the young
folks, and several of them were left in a weak condition after
the scourge had passed through the household. Margaret
was one of the weaklings, and was indulged over-much,
perhaps, and became somewhat self-willed, but only to an
amusing degree. One day she was seated on the front steps,
getting the fresh air, when a woman belonging to the
neighborhood addressed her with numerous questions
about the family and as to the treatment she received from
her mistress. I
<pb id="lev9" n="9"/>
presume the strange voice among the childish group drew
my mother to the window over their heads in time to witness
the interview. Margy listened patiently and politely to all the
lady had to say, then lifting one hand to an ear she replied:
“Woman, all you have said goes in at this ear, and goes out at
the other one.” After such a rebuke the gossiper did not
waste further time at that portal. Many a hearty laugh has
been enjoyed at the child's answer to her mischievous
interrogator. Time passed on. Margaret grew to be a large
girl, and I was born in 1825, and when the baby was big
enough it fell largely to Margaret's charge. Well do I
remember one delightful race I enjoyed in Margy's arms,
though only four years old at the time. It was in 1828, on the
4th of July. The corner-stone of the Baltimore and Ohio
Railroad was to be laid—the pioneer railroad of the country!
Being a great enterprise, it was duly celebrated with
distinguished guests to participate in the ceremonies. The
venerable Charles Carroll, of Carrollton, aged ninety-one
years, was to lay the cornerstone with a silver trowel. A
grand procession, with flags flying and floats displaying
various trades, all richly adorned, and the whole animated by
martial
<pb id="lev10" n="10"/>
music, went up Baltimore street. The servant girls from our
neighborhood went with the host of sightseers, taking along
with them the children under their care, I among them. When
our vantage ground was gained, corner of Eutaw street,
Margy lifted me up in her arms to behold what has never
faded from my memory—the magnificent civic demonstration
in honor of the first railroad that was built on the Western
Continent. The printing-press float pleased me best of all,
with its attendant imps dressed as mercuries, who scattered
sheets that were being printed as the procession moved
along. The last division passed, the blare of the trumpets
grew faint from a distance. Then the girls turned down Eutaw
street, full of fun, and singing a popular song of the day,
“The Blue Bonnets are over the Border,” “Hurrah for the
Bonnets of Blue,” raced to the top of their speed back home.
It was a ride full of peril as well as fun, but Margy was
sure-footed and she landed me on terra firma unharmed. She loved
children, and all children that ever were placed under her care
loved her. Our family grew larger and we moved into a larger
house, Margy going along with us. Charlotte was off with
her husband, and Margy was installed as housemaid.
<pb id="lev11" n="11"/>
One day she was occupied near the front door in some sort
of cleaning, when a little boy drew her attention. He was
trying to reach the bell-knob, but, failing in his efforts,
Margy hastened to his assistance. Alas! for her kind heart
caused her to move too quickly from her elevated position.
She fell and was badly injured. The injury sustained by her
on this occasion caused an internal tumor from which she
suffered great pain at intervals during the rest of her life.</p>
        <p>Another servant had been added to the household by
purchase. My father attended a sale of household goods
and chattels; a sickly-looking girl, emaciated to a painful
degree to sensitive perceptions, moved his compassion, and
Ann Dutton was sent home to my mother's fostering care.</p>
        <p>Ann's first act on reaching her new home was to attack
the <hi id="italics">slop barrel</hi>, from which she extracted food to comfort her
famished system.</p>
        <p>Margy and Ann never became very warm friends,
although associated in the same family for so many years.
According to the rules of the peculiar institution, the
bought slave was always looked down upon by those “to
the manner born.” And Margy was a dark woman, Ann of
mixed blood; the mixture
<pb id="lev12" n="12"/>
she claimed to have was Indian; the unmixed nature held
herself purer than the mongrel. Ann was a woman of
fashion, as far as she possibly could go; Margy was plain in
her tastes and always clean and neat in her attire. Thus
there were three good and sufficient reasons, according to
them, for their frequent disagreements.</p>
        <p>Both were good servants, well-mannered, industrious,
truthful, faithful in the discharge of every duty in their
sphere. Neither pampered the whims of the children within
the range of their influence, but were quick to reprove
whatever fault they deemed it proper to correct, and the
children knew it was right for them to yield respectful
attention without giving back any impertinence when
reproved. My mother of blessed memory taught her children
to request service of her slaves, never to command or exact
service from them. “If they are slaves,” she would say,
“they are God's creatures, and you must treat them politely.”</p>
        <p>Ann took the name of Duncan, in honor of the Rev. John
M. Duncan, a popular minister of Baltimore in the days of
which I write, and it being allowable for slaves to assume
any name they preferred she was known from thence always
by that name while
<pb id="lev13" n="13"/>
she lived with us. Both of these young women had offers of
marriage, but neither of them chose to marry, because their
children would be held in bondage, and they were unwilling
to breed slaves for any master. If all the bondwomen had
been of the same mind, how soon the institution would have
vanished from the earth, and all the misery belonging to it
been lifted from the hearts of the holders and the slaves!
Glorious in the estimation of all true patriots is the memory of
Abraham Lincoln for having signed the Emancipation Act.
Our country was forced, while colonies of Great Britain, to
take the slaves brought to our shores in Dutch ships by the
mother country. I have yet to learn that any of the unhappy
creatures were landed on British soil proper. Very many of
them tilled the soil and picked the cotton and gathered the
coffee berries on the West India islands under British rule,
and terribly they suffered on the island of Jamaica, notably
not many years ago by a general massacre, reminding the
reader of history of the massacre of the Helots in Greece
while Greece was still a heathen country. But Great Britain
had the grace to investigate and condemn the massacre in
Jamaica, while no voice ever was raised in censure of the
flow
<pb id="lev14" n="14"/>
of blood that stained the soil of classic Greece that I ever
read of. There the master had the life and death of his slave
under absolute control. Slavery, as we knew it here, was a
mitigated evil, really more harmful to the masters and their
families than to the slaves, and now that it is banished from
our soil, even the heaviest owners are prepared to say it is a
good riddance.</p>
        <p>After a few years, death and reverse of fortune caused
changes in our family which were displeasing to Margaret,
and she was allowed to choose a home for herself, and the
wages paid for her services went to pay for her clothes and
her physician's bills. She had much suffering from the tumor
and often was obliged to return to her old home for rest and
to be nursed back to ordinary health. The first place where
she hired was in the family of Mr. J. B., and her record there
was one of obedience and faithfulness. She claimed some
indulgence and it was granted her, for they knew she had
been allowed many privileges. The second place where she
hired was in the family of Mr. H. G. Here, too, she claimed
her privileges, and they were granted her, for she was liked
and the family desired to retain her. During this time with
<pb id="lev15" n="15"/>
Mrs. G., Blake was much annoyed by the abolitionists. She
complained very much of them. They tormented her. She
would say: “I want my freedom, but I do not want to <hi rend="italics">steal</hi>
it.” Mrs. G. went one summer to the North to visit her
husband's relatives and gained the consent of Margaret and
her mistress that she could attend her as lady's maid. Mother
consented to the trip being taken, hoping the change of
scene and climate might benefit Margaret's health, knowing
that the moment she set foot on that soil she was free, and if
she pleased to do so she might stay there. But Margaret was
of a different mind. Upon the arrival of the party in the city of
New York lodgings were taken in a hotel, and the Irish
waiters belonging to the establishment immediately bothered
the lady's maid with attentions, inviting her to walk out with
them to view the city. Icily she repelled them. “No,” she
replied, “I will not walk out with you in the streets of New
York. I shall not do in New York what I would be ashamed to
do in Baltimore. Colored women are disgraced in Baltimore if
they are seen in the company of white men on the streets.”
“Are you free?” asked the waiters. “I am as free as you
are,” she rejoined; “I come
<pb id="lev16" n="16"/>
and go as I please.” Thus the free slave rebuffed her white
suitors. She was afraid of them.</p>
        <p>When night came on she begged Mrs. G. to have a bed
laid on her bedroom floor, that she might be safe from the
impudent Irish waiters. She was afraid they might steal her
off and sell her to Georgia. That arrangement was made to
Blake's satisfaction. She was safe from the much-dreaded
Irish waiters. The party she was traveling with proceeded on
their way and soon reached one of the New England States
to spend the summer among relatives who were permanent
residents there.</p>
        <p>The pleasant visit ended, and Mrs. G. prepared to turn
Southward. And Margaret? How was it with her? She, too,
was ready to return to Baltimore. The free slave? Yes; the
free slave returned to face her mistress and her young
ladies, not ashamed to show her face to her people!</p>
        <p>Ann Dutton, or Duncan, as she preferred to be called,
was of a different mind. One day she informed her mistress
that she was desirous of attending a funeral to take place
that afternoon. Permission was given her to attend the
funeral, and she was much helped in her work that she might
be there in proper
<pb id="lev17" n="17"/>
time. When she was ready to leave the house it was noticed
that she wore a wadded merino cloak, a long cloak with a
large cape to it. Her mistress said to her: “Ann, why do you
wear that heavy cloak this warm afternoon ?” “Oh!” she
replied, “the evenings are cool, and I shall need it before I get
back.”</p>
        <p>So she departed. Night fell, and Ann still out! The family
became anxious about her and feared she might be ill-treated
by rough crowds on the streets. It was the night of the day
of General William H. Harrison's election to the Presidency,
and much excitement prevailed. Wait! wait! and no Ann
Duncan in sight yet! At last it occurred to one of the family,
in consideration of the strange freak of the donning of her
heavy cloak, to go to her room and examine her bureau. Her
room was looked over and not a garment was to be seen that
belonged to her. All gone! We never saw her more. It was a
cleverly-managed escape.</p>
        <p>The election day was chosen by a large party of fugitives
to make for Canada.</p>
        <p>Margaret often told us of Ann's movements. She married
up there, and, after many years, desired to return to her
former owners, but we were not willing
<pb id="lev18" n="18"/>
to receive her. She had to abide by her choice. To Ann's
credit it must be said she took nothing away with her but
what belonged to her. She had a good supply of clothes for
the approaching winter, and a sheet from her bed (one was
missed) must have been used to tie her garments in and then
dropped from her window to the yard below to be carried off
for her to the place of departure.</p>
        <p>Not long after this occurrence we left Baltimore and went
to Ellicotts Mills, ten miles from the city. Blake did not wish
to leave Baltimore and was allowed to remain there. From
that time she went and came as suited her, and never was
with us but as an invalid to be nursed or as a visitor to be
entertained. It was concluded after we moved to Harford
county, Md., to allow Blake to buy herself. The family with
whom she hired named the price, and she was granted her
wages to pay for herself. The price agreed upon was not
large, and before Blake was old she had her free papers. It
was a happy day for me when I accompanied my dear nurse
to Bel-air to obtain her free papers. Three of us went with
her, and a joyous party it was—glad in her happiness.</p>
        <p>After the slaveholders' rebellion she showed me
<pb id="lev19" n="19"/>
her free papers; she was spending the summer with us in
Harford county, Md., while her employers were in Europe,
and had brought her papers with her.</p>
        <p>“Oh!” she said, “there was not a drop of blood shed for
my freedom.” It gave her the utmost satisfaction to consider
that she was free before that war. She inquired if it was
necessary for her to keep the free papers. I told her it was
not necessary, but she had better keep them; it might be
pleasant to look at her papers.</p>
        <p>The last change Blake made in service was to enter the
family of Mr. Walter B. B. She remained in that family many
years, helping Mrs. B. to rear her children from their infancy.
Among them she was called Mammy Blake, and is never
spoken of except as <hi rend="italics">Mammy</hi> Blake.</p>
        <p>Baby Eleanor grew to womanhood, was wooed and won
to wifehood, and, loving old Mammy Blake, and devotedly
loved by her in return, she attended her young lady up to
the pulpit railing where the gallant groom waited for his
promised bride, in Brown Memorial Church. To see the gayly
turbaned negress bearing the wraps of the dainty bride was
a rare sight as she entered the church, dispensing odors
from the
<pb id="lev20" n="20"/>
orange blossoms that adorned her spotless bridal robes, as
leaning on her father's arm he led her up the aisle to bestow
her upon Mr. McC., of Chicago, Mammy Blake bringing up
the rear of the bridal procession. It was the crowning
indulgence of the life of the affectionate servant.</p>
        <p>After Mrs. McC. was established in Chicago Mammy
Blake was taken out there to help her to raise the infants her
home was blessed with.</p>
        <p>While Blake was still living with Mrs. Walter B. B., her
little son Walter was present when a little girl from the North
was visiting them, and was kissed by Mammy Blake. The
little girl was terrified, and immediately wiped off the kiss,
saying she did not want to be made black, like her. The little
Walter resented the indignity done to his dear old mammy,
and threw his arms around her neck, kissing her fondly,
exclaiming: “My old mammy will never make anybody
black.”</p>
        <p>In the winter of 1879 Mrs. McC. came on from Chicago to
Baltimore with her infant daughter, Mary G. McC., and her
nurse, Mammy Blake, to spend the Christmas holidays with
her mother's family.</p>
        <p>In a letter to me Mrs. McC. says: “I brought her
<pb id="lev21" n="21"/>
from Chicago for the Christmas holidays, and she took cold
soon after we reached Baltimore, which developed into
erysipelas, and I was obliged to return to Chicago without
her, with the understanding that she would follow as soon
as she was well enough. She grew worse, and because
mother was very ill at the time and worried very much over
her, father and the doctor thought it best for her to go to the
hospital (Baltimore Infirmary), where she died March 10
1880. She was buried in Laurel Cemetery, and I have just
now ordered a stone with her name on it and the date of her
birth, if you know it. Mother wants on it, ‘Faithful unto
Death.’ ”</p>
        <p>No word more fitting to be placed on her tombstone.
Fidelity was the keynote of her life. She served her earthly
masters well, and when her heart was turned by the grace of
God to the Lord Jesus Christ she held her faith to the end, in
childlike simplicity, growing more and more like her Divine
Master until the close of her life, and to all who were
acquainted with her there is an assurance given that she has
realized the promise of, “Be thou faithful unto death, and I
will give thee a crown of life.”</p>
        <closer>
          <signed>S. R. L.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div1>
      <div1>
        <pb id="lev22" n="22"/>
        <head>MORNING PRAYER.</head>
        <argument>
          <p>[Designed for young children, as a companion to the evening prayer<lb/>
of “Now I Lay Me Down to Sleep.”]</p>
        </argument>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>Now I wake to see the light,</l>
          <l>I pray the Lord who gives me sight</l>
          <l>To keep me through the live-long day,</l>
          <l>And help me put all sin away.</l>
        </lg>
        <closer>
          <signed>
            <name>S. R. L.</name>
          </signed>
        </closer>
      </div1>
      <div1>
        <pb id="lev23" n="23"/>
        <head>HAPPINESS.</head>
        <docAuthor>S. R. L. </docAuthor>
        <epigraph>
          <p>“Where grows? where grows it not? if vain our toil<lb/>
We ought to blame the culture, not the soil;<lb/>
Fixed to no spot is happiness sincere;<lb/>
'Tis nowhere to be found, or everywhere.”</p>
        </epigraph>
        <p>THE universal desire for happiness is a proof that all were
created to be happy; but few with sincerity can declare
themselves as happy people, and if the acknowledgment is
made it is accompanied with a sigh for some unattained
good. When Adam, our great federal head, made in the
image of his Creator, was placed in Eden, he was perfectly
happy, but with his innocence his happiness fled, and we
his children inherit misery from our great progenitor, and
miserable we remain until restored to purity by the second
Adam. None need hope for other than a fitful, fleeting joy
before he yields his heart to heavenly influences; not until
then can he expect to have a solid, lasting joy, a continued
happiness that will flow on like a mighty river, deepening as
it flows to the end
<pb id="lev24" n="24"/>
of life. Sin is the great cause of misery; but many fail of
finding happiness, even after the oppressive burden of sin is
removed, because they are not content to find it in small
things, but are continually looking for great occasions that
never come. To the great majority of the human race it is a
negative rather than a positive state, and so some are happy
but do not know it. Each individual may increase his stock of
happiness by cultivating the soil of the heart a little deeper—in
forgetting self and remembering his companions on the road
of life a little more than is usually the case. By a pleasant
word to the depressed, a kindly act to the necessitous,
giving sympathy to the afflicted, and smiles to the
prosperous, our interest is made known to our fellow-
voyagers and we are ultimately gainers by a reflex happiness
in witnessing the pleasure we give to others by our
ministrations. Education is the most fruitful source of
happiness, considered apart from religion; it subdues what is
gross in our nature, elevates our tastes and prepares us for a
full enjoyment of the beauties of nature, which are so
lavishly spread over the broad earth for the joy of all. The
poor as well as the rich man, the invalid and those who are in
robust health, can alike study the
<pb id="lev25" n="25"/>
varying landscape, the cloud-capped mountain with its
leaping cascades, and the magnificent arch of heaven with
its midnight stars, or gorgeous canopy of clouds at sunset.
Every child should have its attention directed to objects of
beauty in nature at an early period, especially to flowers,
trees and insects, which are so abundant everywhere. The
habit of noticing small things will grow as years increase and
will be a life-long benefit, giving a love for Nature and
yielding a pleasure that calls for no repentance and that
necessarily leads the mind from Nature up to Nature's
God.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="lev26" n="26"/>
      <div1>
        <head>AURORA BOREALIS OF APRIL 15, 1869.</head>
        <byline>SEEN BY </byline>
        <docAuthor>S. R. L.</docAuthor>
        <p>THIS latitude (Harford county, Maryland) was
favored with an Aurora of unusual magnificence.
It brought vividly to mind the Esquimaux
name for this celestial phenomenon, “The
dance of the Spirits.” I shall endeavor to depict
in words a scene which I hope to retain in
“memory's halls” to the latest day of my life,
as it will be to me “a joy forever.” The light
was noticed at sunset, and as the shades of evening
fell it took the distinct form of the Aurora Borealis.
A lovely arch of silvery rays formed close on
the line of the horizon. From this sprung other rays
higher up toward the zenith. About nine o'clock I
saw from the coruscations that something more brilliant
yet might be expected and determined to watch
for it. At this time, detached from the double arch
and higher up, was a peculiar figure in shape like an
immense boomerang. In a few minutes it had flashed
away, to reappear in other forms. After ten o'clock,
<pb id="lev27" n="27"/>
upon taking another observation, I found that the arch had
moved higher. It was now about forty-five degrees from the
horizon. At the east was a large space of steady silver light,
tinged with crimson. On a line with this at the west was a
similar field of steady glowing silver light. From the edges of
these two fountains of light brilliant coruscations emanated,
and the whole northern heavens were gorgeously
illuminated. All the coruscations were advancing by long
and rapid waves to the zenith, where were already to be seen
a great number of forms like angels' wings. Gradually these
flashed around and settled in clouds as the center of a dark,
vivid, immense crimson star, from which extended in every
direction long, brilliant, silvery-white rays. Awe-struck, I
stood gazing up into the heavens, my heart being filled to its
utmost capacity with adoring love to the great Creator of
such ineffable beauty and gave utterance to a fervid “Glory
to God! ” If an angel had darted down to earth from the
center of that resplendent star it would have been just what I
hoped for. But no angel <sic corr="descended">desceeded</sic>. It flashed away in long
waves of silver, to dance about in other shapes. At one
period of greatest activity I fancied a sound was produced
from the
<pb id="lev28" n="28"/>
aurora of a slight crackling, scarcely discernible in the still
night air. After eleven o'clock, being fully satisfied, I
re-entered the house in profound meditation as to what must be
the glories of our heavenly home, as the earth is so full of
such perfect beauty. I turned to the Holy Book and read:
“And I saw no temple therein, for the Lord God Almighty
and the Lamb are the temple of it. And the city had no need
of the sun, neither of the moon to shine in it: for the Glory of
God did lighten it, and the Lamb is the light thereof.”</p>
      </div1>
      <div1>
        <pb id="lev29" n="29"/>
        <head>“THIS DO YE AS OFT AS YE DRINK IT IN<lb/>
REMEMBRANCE OF ME.”</head>
        <lg>
          <l>Not 'mid pleasure's thoughtless throng,</l>
          <l>Not in halls of festive mirth,</l>
          <l>Where witty jest and mellow song</l>
          <l>Ring through the air, may I drink wine.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Not around the social board,</l>
          <l>Where friend meets friend in happy mood,</l>
          <l>And health to health is freely poured,</l>
          <l>And laughter sounds, may I drink wine.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>In the house of God, where waiting,</l>
          <l>With the favored ones of Heaven</l>
          <l>For the coming of the blessing</l>
          <l>Of His sacred presence dear.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>When a sense of sin oppresses,</l>
          <l>And my heart with grief is bowed</l>
          <l>For the cruel gibes and lashes</l>
          <l>Which my Saviour meekly bore.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>When I recollect the death-pang</l>
          <l>Of the blessed Son of God,</l>
          <l>Who on the cruel cross did hang,</l>
          <l>Only then must I drink wine.</l>
        </lg>
        <closer>
          <signed>S.  R.  L.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div1>
      <div1>
        <pb id="lev30" n="30"/>
        <head>A HAPPY LIFE.</head>
        <head>[Inscribed to Mrs. W. B. B.]</head>
        <lg>
          <l>Gracefully thy girlhood glided</l>
          <l>'Mid a most delightful home,</l>
          <l>Where, by loving parents guided,</l>
          <l>Thou and sisters fair didst roam.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>When thy wedded troth was plighted</l>
          <l>To a husband noble, fond,</l>
          <l>All thy happy life was lighted</l>
          <l>By the rosy nuptial bond.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Then were added sons and daughters,</l>
          <l>And thy cup of bliss was full,</l>
          <l>And thy loving heart ne'er falters</l>
          <l>Till to God thou bringst them all.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>In the mother's heart God wakened</l>
          <l>Hopes for an eternal joy,</l>
          <l>For the band of children wakened</l>
          <l>All thy love without alloy.</l>
        </lg>
        <pb id="lev31" n="31"/>
        <lg>
          <l>Now thou standest by confession</l>
          <l>With the saints of God arrayed,</l>
          <l>In the garments of Salvation,</l>
          <l>Washed in Jesus' precious blood.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>May God's Holy Spirit guide thee</l>
          <l>Into scenes divinely fair,</l>
          <l>Where thy raptured soul may see</l>
          <l>joys that need not fear despair.</l>
        </lg>
        <closer>
          <signed>S. R. L.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div1>
      <div1>
        <pb id="lev32" n="32"/>
        <head>THE UNWELCOME GUEST.</head>
        <p>THERE is a feeling, an earnest desire, in every
human breast, to know more than is allowed
us weak mortals to know of the Mysteries
of the Spirit Land. To me there is an
inexpressible charm in any story that savors of the
supernatural, and next to hearing about spiritual
manifestations to others has been a fervent wish to
be myself favored with the sight of a ghost. But
when mortals are favored by a visit from an
inhabitant of the Spirit Land terror is so immediately
the result as to prevent our growing any wiser than
we already are through the Scripture revelation
pertaining to eternity. After waiting long years to see
a ghost my unholy curiosity was gratified, and, like
others on similar occasions, I also was too glad to see
the phantom depart to question him on the important
subjects of eternity, concerning eternal life, and
misery. Not very many years ago my circle of friends
in a not distant city lost by death, after a lingering
illness, one of its most valued members, a man of
<pb id="lev33" n="33"/>
great talents and kindly home virtues; a lover of his fireside,
and perfectly devoted to those who shared it with him.
Feeling deeply the loss his family had sustained, in the
earnestness of my sympathy I made them a visit of
condolence, and, as was to be expected, found the once-
happy home shrouded in gloom. Their place of residence
was a chateau-like building, being several stories in height,
each story containing suites of apartments opening into
each other and connected by immense halls and dim
corridors. Upon the day of my arrival (the season was early
spring, the air being still keen with frost) we assembled at
four o'clock, the usual hour for dinner, in the large dining-room,
which was the last apartment in the suite containing
the elegant drawing-room and the well-filled library.
Opposite a door opening into the library was one which led
out into a corridor communicating with the kitchen, and
through which the servants were passing back and forth in
arranging the dinner upon the table. Two great windows
lighted this room on the east, and opposite them was a third
door which opened upon one of the grand lofty halls. As we
seated ourselves at table an unwonted silence fell upon us.
Wondering at this, and not caring to
<pb id="lev34" n="34"/>
break the stillness, which continued after we were seated, I
ate the delicacies provided and glanced around at the familiar
adornments of the place. Each article occupied the same
position as upon the occasion of my last visit under happier
auspices. There stood the massive mahogany sideboard with
its wealth of rich china and sparkling glass. The lovely marble
vases I had so often admired, as usual, graced the
mantelpiece, but upon a picture familiar enough in other days
my gaze dwelt the longest. It was a picture illustrating that
passage of Scripture history which describes David as a
minstrel youth excelling upon the harp and called into the
presence of the lordly King Saul to charm away by his
soothing strains the evil spirit which tormented the king. The
figures in it were nearly of life size, and as the silence around
the table continued unbroken I enjoyed my dinner, and as I
did so still studied the picture. There was the minstrel, clad in
his simple garments, with exquisite grace grasping the
instrument from which so much was expected. Michal, in all
the redundancy and fresh charm of early womanhood, is
endeavoring with all the solicitude of a daughter depicted in
her face to attract the attention of her father
<pb id="lev35" n="35"/>
to his favorite harp; but the stern old king, half crouching in
 his royal robes upon his throne, has not yet yielded to its
sweet influence—the demon still lashes his soul into frenzy,
and was looking through his lurid eyes directly into mine.
Half frightened already by the Satanic look out of Saul's
eyes, hearing the corridor door open, I gladly turned my
attention to it, fully expecting to see a friendly, beaming sable
face, but, instead, beheld advancing directly toward the
table the whilom master of the house. His formerly stately
figure was now enlarged until it very nearly reached the
ceiling, which was sixteen or eighteen feet high, and was clad
in the moldy habiliments of the grave. His cold, piercing eyes
were fixed on mine, as in almost breathless amazement and
terror I watched his slow progress across the room. Hastily,
fearfully, I peered at each face around the board. Every head
was bent close over his or her plate; not a creature lifted a
hand toward the once-loved father and friend as he paced by
each of us. One daughter, trembling by my side, in a hoarse
whisper informed me it was always so: he made his
appearance in these horrid garments regularly every day at
that hour. Thus was the fearful silence accounted
<pb id="lev36" n="36"/>
for. The dread of the specter sealed their lips, and
hoping that I, not being a member of the family, might not
see the fearful vision, they did not inform me of the
unwelcome visitor; but to see it was also granted to me, and
truly it <sic>may said</sic> one ghost is enough to see in a lifetime.
When the awful object reached the hall-door he held it, half
closed, in his hand, the husband of one of his daughters
inquired in an exceedingly timid tone of voice: “Are you
coming back again?” “No! ” shouted the ghost in a voice of
thunder, at the same time opening the door wide and closing
it after him with great violence, admitting a furious blast of
icy cold wind which blew over me with full force and startled
me out of a deep and awful dream. Oh! the joy of waking to
find myself in my own snug chamber, in a retired farmhouse,
in dear old Harford county, and not a visitor in a magnificent
chateau frequented by shadows from the spirit land, and
entirely satisfied to remain unenlightened as to the
mysteries of the future state beyond the veil of Death.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1>
        <pb id="lev37" n="37"/>
        <head>IMPROMPTU.</head>
        <head>[Naming a little <sic corr="cousin">couisin</sic> in Ohio.]</head>
        <lg>
          <l>Eugenia Howard I select</l>
          <l>Out of my teeming brain</l>
          <l>By which to call our little pet</l>
          <l>From mischief, harm or rain.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>When childhood's years have flown apace,</l>
          <l>A merry maiden she,</l>
          <l>Eugenia still will have a grace</l>
          <l>With lover, maid and me.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>My task is done; I can no more</l>
          <l>Than wish the child may seem</l>
          <l>To father's pride and mother's love</l>
          <l>A pearl of rarest gleam.</l>
        </lg>
        <closer>
          <signed>S. R. L.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div1>
      <div1>
        <pb id="lev38" n="38"/>
        <head>THE BRIDE</head>
        <head>[Blake waited on in Brown Memorial Church]</head>
        <lg>
          <l>Ne'er saw I a blither maiden,</l>
          <l>Ever smiling, ever gay,</l>
          <l>Living thus with pleasure laden,</l>
          <l>Living on from day to day,</l>
          <l>In a whirl of sportive measure</l>
          <l>Ever casting joy around,</l>
          <l>Binding all our hearts at leisure,</l>
          <l>Rifling us of senses sound.</l>
          <l>On thy life may ne'er a shadow</l>
          <l>Of affliction's presence drear</l>
          <l>Kill thy liveliest hopes below.</l>
          <l>Step thou on from sorrow clear.</l>
        </lg>
        <closer>
          <signed>S. R. L.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div1>
      <div1>
        <pb id="lev39" n="39"/>
        <head>SONG.</head>
        <docAuthor>By  R. E. H. LEVERING, Lancaster, Ohio</docAuthor>
        <lg>
          <l>Gaze, dearest one, at evening time,</l>
          <l>On brightest star above,</l>
          <l>And know that in the female train</l>
          <l>Thus shines the one I love!</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Cull from the garden, love, its pride,</l>
          <l>With perfum'd beauty rife,</l>
          <l>And know that, like its charms, thou art</l>
          <l>The sweetest flower of life!</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Oh, take the gem from coronet,</l>
          <l>More precious than the rest,</l>
          <l>A type to be of virtue, thine,</l>
          <l>Most pure in woman's breast!</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>Then take the glories of this world</l>
          <l>And weigh thy charms with them;</l>
          <l>For thee I'd spurn them all away,</l>
          <l>My flower, my star, my gem!</l>
        </lg>
        <pb id="lev40" n="40"/>
        <lg>
          <l>Then to thy bosom bind with care</l>
          <l>The fadeless evergreen,</l>
          <l>To note that like thy spotless love</l>
          <l>Unchangeable is mine!</l>
        </lg>
      </div1>
      <div1>
        <pb id="lev41" n="41"/>
        <head>ACROSTIC.</head>
        <docAuthor>BY ORIGINALIAD.</docAuthor>
        <head>[Exhibiting the name of a little girl twelve years old.]</head>
        <lg>
          <l>Should I extol thy wit refined,</l>
          <l>A tribute pay to thy young mind,</l>
          <l>Rob'd in the charms of native sense,</l>
          <l>A promise of much excellence?</l>
          <l>Has not thy soul a brighter worth?</l>
          <l>Read in the book of God its birth!</l>
          <l>E'en from His hand who framed the sky,</l>
          <l>Brought forth the glorious orbs on high,</l>
          <l>Enrich'd the earth with every good,</l>
          <l>Crown'd all with Jesus' precious blood—</l>
          <l>Consider from His hand it came,</l>
          <l>A God forevermore the same!</l>
          <l>Love, then, thy Father—be his child—</l>
          <l>Enjoy His government so mild.</l>
          <l>Vain is the wish elsewhere to find</l>
          <l>Enlight'ning pleasure for the mind.</l>
          <l>Rich is the joy he can bestow;</l>
          <l>In life, the antidote of woe!</l>
          <l>No bliss does He refuse to give!</l>
          <l>Go to thy God, and ever live!</l>
        </lg>
      </div1>
      <div1>
        <pb id="lev42" n="42"/>
        <head>LINES ON MISS C., OF BALTIMORE.</head>
        <docAuthor>By R. E. H. LEVERING, Lancaster, Ohio.</docAuthor>
        <lg>
          <l>Moved by some heathen God of ancient time,</l>
          <l>Italia's sons performed their deeds sublime;</l>
          <l>Struck sweet their harp in praise of beauty rare,</l>
          <l>Shrined in their hearts as loveliest of the fair!</l>
          <l>Roused by an inspiration still more sweet,</l>
          <l>A holier love a kindred love to meet,</l>
          <l>Come forth the first affections of my heart,</l>
          <l>Held in soft bonds by Love's superior art!</l>
          <l>Each charm more lasting than mere Beauty's ray,</l>
          <l>Loud speak her merit and extend her sway—</l>
          <l>Golconda's gold in Hymen's path unsought,</l>
          <l>Cold, calculating artifice is not</l>
          <l>On her bright fame a warning and a blot!</l>
          <l>Long may enduring charms like Rachel's prove</l>
          <l>Examples high to foster holiest love!</l>
        </lg>
      </div1>
      <div1>
        <pb id="lev43" n="43"/>
        <head>THE BUTTERFLY.</head>
        <lg>
          <l>The lovely Sarah thought, quite sly,</l>
          <l>To catch, one day, a butterfly;</l>
          <l>She threw her apron to enclose</l>
          <l>The longed-for prize, as in a noose;</l>
          <l>The beauteous insect, watchful still,</l>
          <l>The snare avoided with much skill,</l>
          <l>And fled, a most rejoicing one,</l>
          <l>With added wisdom snares to shun,</l>
          <l>A lesson leaving for the maid</l>
          <l>In noble practice just displayed,</l>
          <l>To wit: that loveliest females are,</l>
          <l>Like butterflies, exposed to snare,</l>
          <l>And should combine, in things of love,</l>
          <l>The wily serpent with the dove,</l>
          <l>And, always watching, never find</l>
          <l>In confidence misplaced or blind,</l>
          <l>A loss which time cannot repair—</l>
          <l>The loss of virtue in a snare!</l>
        </lg>
        <closer>OLD HONESTY, Lancaster, Ohio.</closer>
      </div1>
      <div1>
        <pb id="lev44" n="44"/>
        <head>“LITTLE CHILDREN, LOVE ONE ANOTHER.”</head>
        <p>A FEW words for the children who may read this
booklet, and my full intention will be carried out.</p>
        <p>For ten years my life was among children as a teacher
in the public school near my home in Harford county. I
loved the children. My Master loved little children and
blessed them. As His disciple, it was my duty to bring the
children to Him that He might bless them. I encouraged them
to read and study the Scriptures of truth that testified of His
birth, His life and His death. The result of this teaching will
only be known when the books recording the deeds done in
the body shall be opened and the dead, both small and
great, be judged. Now, all children who read the Scriptures
of truth know that there are two places mentioned for the
souls of human beings to live in—Heaven for the obedient
children of God, and Hell for the disobedient children of God—
and they know the way to Heaven is Christ. Whoever
accepts Him as a personal Saviour is sure of reaching the
abode of the
<pb id="lev45" n="45"/>
saints of the Lord, the Heaven of which we read in the Holy
Bible. There God dwells in light and love and joy abounds;
happiness pure and unalloyed is found. No fancy can
imagine the joys of Heaven. It is vain to try; we cannot do it.
The disobedient children of God, who love sin too well to
reject it, and who will not accept salvation as the gift of God
through the blood of Christ, will surely be cast into Hell, to
live forever and ever in the blackness of darkness and where
the devil and his evil angels are never to be released from
torment.</p>
        <p>It is growing more and more the custom to draw the
attention of sinners away from dread of everlasting woe and
fix their minds on the blessed abode of the righteous; but
they must be told of the choice they are called upon to make—
to enter the service of the God of love and light, or to serve
the Prince of Darkness; to live for God and Heaven, or to
continue in sin and go to Hell. Some say God is too merciful
to punish his erring children. Rewards and punishments
regulate domestic life, the schools, commonwealths, the
whole world, all creation that we have any knowledge of.
You children know full well when you break your mother's
rules and do as you please
<pb id="lev46" n="46"/>
you have a dread of that slipper or that rod, or the short
rations of good things in her cupboard, or the dark closet,
where in extreme cases you may be shut up until repentance
and promises of good behavior cause her to release you.
Your mothers love you, but if you do naughty deeds the
mothers, because of their love for you, must punish you to
secure good behavior. The earthly parent punishes only for
a short time. The Heavenly Father punishes evil-doers with
everlasting woe.</p>
        <p>If you will turn to your Bibles and read the first chapter of
Proverbs you will find in the seventh verse these words:
“The fear of the Lord is the beginning of knowledge: but
<hi rend="italics">fools despise wisdom and instruction</hi>.” Now turn the leaves
of the written Word of God and find the fourteenth Psalm,
and you will read in the first verse : “The fool hath said in his
heart, There is no God.”</p>
        <p>Now, children, I beg of you to fear the Lord. Do not rank
yourselves among the fools who say in their hearts, “There
is no God,” or if they give any credence of His existence
they will say we do not know Him, we cannot understand
Him. If He does exist, He is too full of love to punish His
poor, weak creatures
<pb id="lev47" n="47"/>
with everlasting destruction in Hell, if they do not obey
the Holy Scriptures and follow after the blessed Lord Jesus
who came to earth from Heaven to seek and to save such
poor weak sinners as we are. The serpent who tempted Eve
to disobey God while she was innocent in the Garden of
Eden and had no fear of death except as she was warned not
to eat of the tree that was in the midst of the garden, “Lest
ye die,” told her, “Ye shall not surely die.” So he continues
to contradict all the teaching of our Heavenly Father. In
various ways he continues to lure us into all sorts of evil
doings, which will surely end in the loss of the precious soul
unless we repent and believe in the Lord Jesus Christ. Avoid
all places where you will be sure to meet the enemy of souls.
The saloons, the gaming places (and they are many), the
theaters, so attractive from their music and dancing and
falseness in general, especially the false view they give of
amusement. The poison cup, the dagger of the assassin, the
death agonies of the victims of both these fearful agents
should never be shown to the public as a fund of
amusement; rather of horror, to be kept away from all human
beings. Such teachings can only end in producing such
fearful fruit as Wilkes
<pb id="lev48" n="48"/>
Booth bore when he ended the life of our venerated
President Abraham Lincoln. Many very good people regard
the theater as a place of innocent amusement. But behind all
the glare of the pretty lights and bright scenes depicted on
the stage, it is well known much misery exists among the
actors and actresses, many sad histories of private life
hidden behind the mimic life portrayed upon the stage,
painful mysteries and secrets which can never be penetrated
by mortal man, and will only be revealed at the last day
when the three books will be opened on the throne of
judgment—the Lamb's Book of Life and the two books, one
of evil deeds and the other of good deeds, out of which all of
us are to be rewarded for good or evil, as we have acted on
this earth.</p>
      </div1>
      <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>