<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % external-entities SYSTEM "./extEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY % internal-entities SYSTEM "./intEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY mallor24 SYSTEM "mallor24.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY mallor30 SYSTEM "mallor30.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY mallor38 SYSTEM "mallor38.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY mallortp SYSTEM "mallortp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>Old Plantation Days:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Col. W. Mallory  </author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Fiona Mills</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by </resp>
          <name>Fiona Mills</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text 
encoded by</resp>
          <name id="ns"> Susan Huffman and Natalia 
Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1999</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca.   150  K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1999.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, 
teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability
 is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note anchored="yes">Call number    E444 .M23     
(Rare Book Collection, UNC-CH)</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>Old Plantation Days</title>
          <author>Mallory, Col.
W.</author>
          <imprint>
            <pubPlace>[Hamilton, Ontario]: </pubPlace>
            <publisher>S. n.</publisher>
            <date>[1902?]</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Pages 41-48 are missing from the original copy.</p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ 
and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation 
in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text 
using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Mallory, William, b. 1826.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Southern States -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Blacks -- Canada -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Southern States -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Southern States -- Social conditions -- 19th
century.</item>
            <item>Fugitive slaves -- Southern States -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- Poetry.</item>
            <item>African American missionaries -- Africa.</item>
            <item>United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 --
Afro-Americans.</item>
            <item>United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Participation,
Afro-Americans.</item>
            <item>Zulu (African people) -- South Africa -- History -- 19th
century.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>1999-06-21, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Steve Kelley </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-05-03, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and 
final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-02-19, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Susan Huffman </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML 
encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-01-29, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Fiona Mills </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="title page image">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="mallortp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">OLD PLANTATION DAYS</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <docEdition>THIRD EDITION</docEdition>
        <docAuthor>COL. W. MALLORY<lb/>
EX-SLAVE</docAuthor>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="introduction">
        <pb id="mallory1" n="1"/>
        <head>INTRODUCTORY.</head>
        <p>In presenting this small book to the public, I am only
endeavoring to place before my readers a portrayal of the daily
happenings in the life of a slave.</p>
        <p>The events here described are true in every particular, and
will all bear the search-light of truth. Many people are to-day
living who can vouch for the authenticity of every event of
importance mentioned within the covers of this book.</p>
        <p>I also desire in this way to express my thanks to the
Canadian public, and Hamiltonians in particular, for the many
proud positions to which they have elevated me, and for the
consideration and kindness with which I have invariably been
treated by Canadians as a people.</p>
        <p>Trusting that my efforts to lay bare the treatment of the
colored man during his period of bondage may be met with the
encouragement and reward commensurate with the sufferings the
negro, as a race, endured, I have the honor to subscribe myself,</p>
        <closer>
          <signed>COL. WM. MALLORY <hi rend="italics">(ex-slave)</hi>
<lb/>
AUTHOR.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="verse">
        <pb id="mallory2" n="2"/>
        <lg type="poem">
          <head>THE PERSECUTED NEGRO.</head>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>In the dark dens of the dismal swamp</l>
            <l>The hunted negro lay;</l>
            <l>He saw the fire of the midnight camp,</l>
            <l>And heard at times the horses' tramp</l>
            <l>And a bloodhound's distant bay.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Where Will-o'-the-Wisps and glow-worms shine</l>
            <l>In bulrush and in brake,</l>
            <l>Where waving mosses shroud the pine,</l>
            <l>And the cedar grows, and the poisonous vine</l>
            <l>Is spotted like the snake.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Where hardly a human foot could pass,</l>
            <l>Or a human heart would dare;</l>
            <l>On the quaking turf of the green morass</l>
            <l>He crouched in the rank and tangled grass</l>
            <l>Like a wild beast in his lair.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>A poor old slave, infirm and lame;</l>
            <l>Great scars deformed his face;</l>
            <l>On his forehead he bore the brand of shame,</l>
            <l>And the rags that hid his beaten frame</l>
            <l>Were a picture of disgrace.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l><sic corr="All">Oll</sic> things above were bright and fair—</l>
            <l>All things were glad and free—</l>
            <l>Little squirrels darted here and there,</l>
            <l>And wild birds filled the echoing air</l>
            <l>With songs of liberty.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>On him alone was the doom of pain</l>
            <l>From the morning of his birth;</l>
            <l>On him alone the curse of Cain</l>
            <l>Fell, like the hail on the garnered grain,</l>
            <l>And struck him to the earth.</l>
          </lg>
        </lg>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="text">
        <pb id="mallory3" n="3"/>
        <head>Col. Wm. Mallory's Escape<lb/>
From Slavery.</head>
        <p>In the year 1826, on a plantation in North Carolina, I, ex-slave
Col. William Mallory, first saw the light of day. For seven years I
was allowed to remain with my parents, brothers and sisters, and
was then sold to a Frenchman from Virginia by the name of
LeBlanc. He was a half-brother to Simon Legree, whose character
has been so well portrayed by Mrs. Harriet Beecher-Stowe in her
story of “Uncle Tom's Cabin.” From the day I was sold to LeBlanc
up to the present—a lapse of sixty-two years—I have neither seen
nor heard of any of my relatives, and there are many more men and
women now under the protection of the British flag who have been
forced to undergo the same cruel separation from parents and
relatives through the same accursed cause—slavery.</p>
        <p>My first knowledge of slavery came to me when I was a little
toddler. A white man was brought to me by my parents, and I was
told by them that he was my master. As time passed on I thought it
was strange that I should have to call him master, and I thought it
stranger still that he should be allowed to whip the negroes till the
blood flowed.</p>
        <p>I remained with Mr. LeBlanc until the marriage of his daughter, on
which occasion I changed owners and became the property of the
son-in-law, Mr. Susten Allen, a member of the White House at
Washington. For fourteen years I remained with them, being assigned
to the position of body-servant to my master, who, like many others
at that time, was too lazy and indolent to wait upon himself. During
my stay with Mr. <sic corr="Allen">Allan</sic> I attended every session held at the White
House, and in my capacity as body-servant was admitted to the
House on all occasions. It was there I first heard of Canada as
a land where slavery was unknown, and where the negro could
live free and untrammeled.</p>
        <pb id="mallory4" n="4"/>
        <p>I had no education, and no opportunity was given me of
procuring any. All that could be learned by the average slave was
that which could be gathered from listening to and treasuring up
the scraps of conversation we could overhear when our owners
were talking together. Having heard so much of this grand
country which lay to the north, I became imbued with the
resolution to improve the first opportunity and try to find my way
to it and freedom.</p>
        <p>Many acts of brutality on the part of my master and his
overseers occurred during the fourteen years I stayed with Mr.
Allen, and one in particular impressed itself on my mind and
showed to me the vital necessity of escaping to freedom if I ever
wished to call my life my own. On one broiling hot day in
midsummer my master called a poor slave out of the cane-field,
and for no appreciable cause had an overseer shave his head and
afterwards flog him with his blacksnake whip. After the flogging a
tight-fitting cap, lined with tar and pitch, was placed on the poor
fellow's head, and he was compelled to stand in the hot, torturing
sun until he fell to the ground. A few strokes of the lash not
serving to revive him, an examination was made, when it was
found that the poor slave was dead. His lifeless body was coolly
kicked into a corner of the fence and left there until sundown,
when some of his fellows were sent to give him a hurried and
unblest burial.</p>
        <p>Another poor slave was whipped until he couldn't stand
because my master caught him in the act of prayer; and a white
man, caught teaching the slaves to read and pray, was shot down
like a dog.</p>
        <p><sic corr="A">O</sic>policeman, a “guardian of the peace,” was what may be
called the public whipper. He received a fee of fifty cents per head
for every man, woman, boy or girl he flogged. This fee was in
addition to his regular salary as a constable, and he found
constant employment.</p>
        <p>I have seen children taken from their parents with as little
compunction as one would exhibit in taking the calf from the
cow. I have seen the young woman sold to the
<pb id="mallory5" n="5"/>
buyer, and he in turn would traffic in her charms; the young man
taken from his wife and sold to a buyer from a distant part of the
States; and one old woman's son was taken from her, tied by a
rope around his neck to the pommel of his new owner's saddle,
and compelled to leave his poor old mother, probably never more
to see her alive.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of acts of equally brutal a nature could be told had
I the inclination to indulge in a recital of all the horrible events I
saw during the days of my captivity, but my book is not intended
to deal with the lives of slaves at large, but purely a personal
narrative.</p>
        <p>Late in the fall of the year 1860 the opportunity of escaping—
so long watched and patiently waited for—offered itself, and in
company with three other slaves I started upon my perilous
journey. Necessity compelled that our road should be far removed
from the highways, as large handbills, offering rewards for our
capture, were freely distributed, and to be seen meant to be taken
and returned to our former homes and punished terribly as an
example to the other hands on the plantation and as a warning of
the fate that awaited any who desired to take their liberty out of
the hands of their oppressors.</p>
        <p>We three travelled continually onward towards Canada and
freedom, sometimes being hounded from swamp to swamp and
bush to bush, and frequently being compelled to ford and swim
streams in our efforts to throw the dogs off our tracks. On one
occasion, about three months after having started on the hunt for
that God-given gift—Liberty, we were nearly overtaken by a pack of
hounds, and were compelled to strike out across country and
each man shift for himself. Having been in my youth a remarkably
rapid runner, I soon left my companions far behind, and I cannot
say whether they escaped, were captured, or died from starvation
and exposure.</p>
        <p>I was now forced to continue my way alone, and under those
circumstances was it to be marvelled at that the country through
which I passed should appear, to my eyes, to be
<pb id="mallory6" n="6"/>
the most dismal on the face of the earth? To add to my sufferings
and discomfort I had to encounter the rigors of winter weather.
The ice, sleet and snow were unknown quantities to the slave,
who had never before ventured so far north from the place of his
birth, and the experience was by no means a pleasant one,
unprovided as I was with clothing suitable for cold weather. My
means of subsistence consisted of everything that I could in any
way obtain, and many a meal have I had from men of my own
nationality who endangered their own safety in order to appease
the pangs of hunger which assailed me.</p>
        <p>One night, after having journeyed all day long, I saw a house
standing by itself in a small clearing, and after having taken a
close survey of the surroundings and having seen nothing of an
alarming nature, I made bold to go to the door and ask for
something to eat. A white man answered my summons at the door,
and on making known my wants he invited me to enter his house
and rest myself while he procured me something to eat, at the
same time telling me he was an Abolitionist and a friend to
all colored men. The only other occupant of the place at
that time was the little child of the man, a girl about three
years of age. The man busied himself preparing my
meal, and my attention being taken up by the antics of the child,
my entertainer managed, unknown to me, to send word to a couple
of slave hunters who were in his neighborhood, that there was an
escaping slave at his house. Imagine my surprise, when, after
having watched the child at play for some time, I accidentally
raised my eyes towards the front door, to see the doorway filled
by the forms of the two slave-hunters with rifles levelled at my
breast, and at the same time hear a stern command to remain where
I was on peril of my life.</p>
        <p>Quicker than thought was my action. Not waiting to
reply to them, I suddenly reached forward and raised the
little child from the floor, and holding her between my body
and the rifles of my pursuers, I backed to the rear door of
the house, darted into the yard, dropped the child to the
<pb id="mallory7" n="7"/>
ground, and ran for the woods at top speed, but, unfortunately,
I did not escape unhurt, one of the marksmen being kind
enough to leave his card in the shape of a wound along the tips
of my fingers, where his rifle bullet hit me.</p>
        <p>After dodging and doubling about the bush for a long time
they gave up the search for me, and I was enabled to procure
some rest in a clump of bushes, which afforded me a safe
hiding-place. Soon after entering my retreat I heard a
sound somewhat resembling a cough, and, peering out from the
bushes, I saw a colored woman who appeared to be trying to find
something or somebody. After having watched her actions for
some time, I determined to make my presence known to her, with
the result that I found I was the one she was searching for.
Her name was Taylor, and she was the wife of
the man who owned her. Their place of residence was near
enough to where I had been betrayed <sic corr="and so">an dso</sic> nearly captured to
allow of them hearing the rifle shots, and surmising that some
poor slave may be running away, she set out from home to
endeavor to be of some assistance.</p>
        <p>I was afraid of another trap, but became assured after a
time that I had nothing to fear from Mrs. Taylor. She and her
daughter, a fine, grown young woman, took me to the house,
bound up my wounds, hid me in an out-of-the-way
place, fed, clothed and cared for me till I was in fit condition to
take the road again and shift for myself.</p>
        <p>Previous to starting out from the plantation of Mr. Allen I
had secured a revolver which at times stood me in good stead,
and to which I was fortunate enough to cling through
all my vicissitudes, and which trusty weapon I still possess.</p>
        <p>After leaving the hospitable roof of the Taylor family my way led
along the banks of a small river, and as I was fortunate
enough to secure a boat which some one had left moored to a
tree, I was able to proceed much more comfortably upon my
journey. For some nights I followed the river course, being
compelled to secrete my boat in the daytime and betake
myself to the bush or some hole in the rocks until night made
it safe for me to stir abroad again. One day
<pb id="mallory8" n="8"/>
soon after leaving Taylor's house, I was terrified to see a small
boat, containing three men, coming down stream and heading
directly for the spot in which my best friend at that time—my
boat—was hidden. In a few minutes they again appeared to view
with my boat in tow, and I was again reduced to the necessity of walking.
On the following Saturday night I resumed my tramp as soon as
darkness settled down. I followed the river bank, keeping a sharp
lookout for means of conveyance by water, as it left no trail, and I
was soon favored by fortune in the shape of another boat which I
unhesitatingly confiscated to my own use.</p>
        <p>In the morning (Sunday) I left my boat and struck off through
the country on foot. I was now in the State of Pennsylvania. I
walked on all day, and at night I was near the borders of <sic corr="Pittsburgh">Pittsburg.</sic>On going to a farmhouse I found some kind friends in the persons
of the farmer and his family. Their name was Butler, and as Mr. B.
was fond of music he asked me could I play an instrument.
Fortunately I could play a little on the violin, and as there
happened to be one in the house I was enabled, in a small
measure, to repay him for his kindness to me. He insisted on my
remaining all night, and after a sleep in a comfortable bed, he gave
me a hearty breakfast and I again resumed my tramp much
refreshed. I travelled all day Monday, meeting with no hindrances,
and at night I again found shelter.</p>
        <p>On the Tuesday morning I passed through a small village
and chanced to meet two men on horseback. They stopped me
and wanted to know who I was and where I was going. I gave a
fictitious name and stated that I was going on an errand. My
questioner wasn't disposed to credit my story, and charged me
with being a runaway slave. I denied the soft impeachment and
offered to go back with them to the village to prove the truth of
my story. My little scheme to deceive them wouldn't work, and
one of the men dismounted in order to secure me, but the sight of
a dirk in the hands of a powerful young colored man induced him
to remount his horse and gallop off towards the village. I was
<pb id="mallory9" n="9"/>
now in rather a hazardous position, for my late interlocutor would
certainly rouse the villagers and a chase would be the result. I
made use of my abilities as a runner, and soon found shelter in a
nearby swamp. As it was the springtime of the year, and I was
well towards the north, the waters of the swamp were none too
warm, and a cold drizzling rain did not add any to my comfort. For
the greater portion of the day I was compelled to wade waist deep
in muck, water and ice, and my sufferings were excruciating in the
extreme. I had no food, and at night I left the swamp and found my
way to a farmhouse, where I procured something to eat.</p>
        <p>By this time I thought it passably safe to travel by day and
rest at night, and I took advantage of any shelter that offered
itself. Before I got far from the village previously mentioned, I one
night took refuge in a barn and made myself a bed in the hay-loft.
Soon after composing myself to rest, a man entered the barn with
his team, fixed the horses for the night and ascended the steps of
the loft in order to throw down some hay for the animals. In
groping around in the dark for the fodder he accidentally grasped
me by the leg. I thought it was all up with me, but luckily I
managed to escape from the barn and again entered the swamp.
The farmer soon aroused the neighborhood, and as soon as the
dogs could be loosed they were set upon my trail. By this time I
had secured a good headway in the swamp, and could hear the
noise of my pursuers and the baying of the hounds behind me.
They followed me across the morass, for I couldn't throw the dogs
off my scent. Seeing a barn in a clearing I made for it, and decided
to leave my fate to Providence.</p>
        <p>My pursuers soon arrived at the building and were going
farther into the swamp when one of the men suggested that the
barn be searched. Accordingly, one of the dogs was sent in, and
after sniffing about for a while he went out without discovering
me. They were about to go on again when another man suggested
that “Bull” be sent in, and if any one was in the building he
would rout him out. “Bull” entered,
<pb id="mallory10" n="10"/>
stayed sniffing about for a time and then retired. My pursuers
were then satisfied that no one was in the building, and they
departed to continue the search elsewhere.</p>
        <p>I continued to hide in barns and outhouses for some weeks
longer, and many hazardous ventures and hairbreadth escapes—
which I hope to relate fully in a future work I am contemplating—
fell to my lot before I at last got into the hands of the
Abolitionists, who conducted me, by means of the “Underground
Railway” to Canada, where I could freely and gladly sing:</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>I've<hi rend="italics">won</hi> my way to Canada,</l>
          <l>That free and happy land;</l>
          <l>No more in cruel slavery</l>
          <l>Need William Mallory stand.</l>
          <l>Fare-the-well, old master,</l>
          <l>That's enough for me!</l>
          <l>I'm <hi rend="italics">here</hi>, in dear old Canada,</l>
          <l>Where colored men are free.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="hymn">
          <l>I will not have the driver's lash</l>
          <l>Raised high above my head;</l>
          <l>I will not have a peck of corn</l>
          <l>Dealt out to me for bread;</l>
          <l>For God, in His great goodness,</l>
          <l>Came down to Calvary</l>
          <l>And bore the burdens of the Cross</l>
          <l>To set His people free.</l>
          <l>Fare-the-well, old master,</l>
          <l>That's enough for me!</l>
          <l>I'm <hi rend="italics">here</hi> in dear old Canada,</l>
          <l>Where colored men are free.</l>
        </lg>
        <p>Soon after crossing the line into Canada I found employment
on different farms and gardens, and eventually arrived at
Hamilton, in which city I decided to remain. About this time Mr.
Abraham Lincoln was nominated and elected to the Presidency of
the United States. Hardly had the
<pb id="mallory11" n="11"/>
election been ratified when the fire of sedition, which had been for
years smouldering and quietly spreading over the Southern
States, burst out in all its fury.</p>
        <p>Victory for the North in the Presidential campaign had been
agreed upon by the Southerners as the signal for immediate
action, and the result was that this great nation became embroiled
in a disastrous conflict. <sic corr="As">Os</sic> discussion grew warmer and warmer,
President Lincoln saw that slavery—which was the root of the
trouble—would have to be abolished in order to bring the matter to a focus.
Accordingly, he caused to be released from bondage some three
thousand of slaves in the District of Columbia, and, in addition,
offered freedom to all colored men who would join and serve in
the Northern Army. He, by this means, instituted the measure of
Emancipation, which brought the dispute to its real issue—a fight
for or against slavery.</p>
        <p>The proclamation offering freedom to the negroes was issued
in 1863, and the result was that fourteen millions of slaves in the
Northern States were set at liberty. Many of them immediately
entered the army and contributed not a little to the ability of the
North to carry on the war.</p>
        <p>On the day he signed the proclamation, President Lincoln,
after hours of hand-shaking with visitors to the White House,
remarked: “My signature looks a little tremulous, but my
resolution is firm. I told the Southerners that if they did not return
to their allegiance and cease murdering our soldiers I would strike
at the pillar of their strength. The promise shall be kept, and not
one word will I ever recall.”</p>
        <p>On the surrender of Richmond the President visited that city,
and it was then that his tender heart was gladdened, for he saw
some of the first signs of the benefits of his proclamation
regarding emancipation. Hardly had his presence in the city
become known before hordes of freed negroes thronged about
him with wild eyes of delight, endeavoring to express in their
simple way their thanks to the deliverer. In 1864 the colored men
of Baltimore presented him with a beautifully bound copy of the
Bible. The book
<pb id="mallory12" n="12"/>
was edged with a band of pure gold, and a massive plate of the
same precious metal adorned each cover. On the front plate was
engraved the figure of Lincoln in the act of removing the shackles
from the limbs of a slave, and at his feet was a scroll with the word
“Emancipation” engraved thereon. On the back plate was
inscribed the following:</p>
        <p>“Presented to Abraham Lincoln, President of the United
States, the friend of universal freedom, from the loyal colored
people of Baltimore, as a token of respect and gratitude.”</p>
        <p>But a terrible calamity was impending. While all the North
was rejoicing over the return of peace, and celebrating the
anniversary of the fall of Sumter, the assassination of Lincoln was
consummated. John Wilkes Booth was the unhappy assassin, and
he chose this occasion as the most fitting opportunity of carrying
out his fell purpose. The President was at Ford's theater, attending
the performance, in company with his family and some friends,
when this fiendish assassin, by a scheme, secured admission to
the President's box, placed a <sic corr="pistol">uistol </sic>to the back of Lincoln's head
and pulled the trigger. Soon the dread news was made public, but
of all the grief-stricken people none were more cast down than the
<sic corr="negroes">egroes</sic>—for whom it might truthfully be said Abraham Lincoln
died. That night thousands of freed slaves walked the streets,
wringing their hands and expressing their despair by loud cries of
distress.</p>
        <p>It was desired by many that Lincoln be laid to rest in
Washington, but other opinion prevailed, and he was interred in
Illinois. In that State, in one of the cemeteries of Springfield—the
town in which many of his most happy days were spent—the body
of the good President lies.</p>
        <p>On the next page will be found a poem to the memory of
Abraham Lincoln. It has been composed by me, and I take this
opportunity of presenting it to the public, at the same time placing
on record my small tribute to the memory of the man whose
glorious career was so fearfully ended by the hand of the grim
monster—Death.</p>
        <pb id="mallory13" n="13"/>
        <lg type="verse">
          <head>IN MEMORIAM.</head>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Celestial Choir, enthroned in realms of light;</l>
            <l>Columbia's scenes of glorious toils I'll write.</l>
            <l>While Freedom's cause her anxious breast alarms</l>
            <l>She flashes dreadful in refulgent arms.</l>
            <l>See mother Earth her offspring bemoan,</l>
            <l>And nation gaze at scenes before unknown.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Famed by thy valor, for thy virtues more,</l>
            <l>Hear every tongue thy guardian aid implore!</l>
            <l>Proceed, great chief, with Virtue on thy side;</l>
            <l>Thy every action let the goddess guide.</l>
            <l>A crown, a mansion, and a throne that shine</l>
            <l>With gold unfading, Lincoln, be thine!</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>From this low vale of sorrow and of strife,</l>
            <l>With honors laden, and in full of time,</l>
            <l>To realms of joy and heights of bliss sublime</l>
            <l>Great Lincoln has winged his raptur'd way</l>
            <l>And walks with Angels in the blaze of day.</l>
          </lg>
        </lg>
        <pb id="mallory14" n="14"/>
        <p>When the American war of the Rebellion broke out I
returned to the States and took up arms on behalf of my poor,
downtrodden race, and against the slave owners and men of the
South. The first battle in which I was engaged was the famous
battle of Bull's Run, where I took my place in the ranks as a private
and bore my share of the brunt of battle. There had been a great
deal of opposition to the use of colored men as troops, and it was
not until July, 1862, that that objection was removed. It was then
that Congress authorized the employment of colored men as
soldiers, and from that time until the close of the war Victory
seemed to follow the colored troops.</p>
        <p>The History of the American War mentions time and again
the gallant conduct and undaunted <sic corr="mien">mein</sic> maintained by the
colored regiments during this terrible period of strife, when the
hand of brother was lifted against brother, and when father and
son opposed each other on the bloody field of battle. At the close
of the year 1862 the number of colored troops in the field was one
hundred and fifty thousand.</p>
        <p>At this time I secured my promotion to the rank of Colonel,
and had an opportunity of showing my ability at the battle of
Vicksburg. After the battle we pressed on towards New Orleans,
which city was captured, thus opening up the Mississippi River
district. At New Orleans we were hemmed in on all sides for a long
time, but after a series of sharp skirmishes with the enemy we were
relieved from our unpleasant predicament. On leaving the vicinity
of New Orleans we were engaged in a number of minor battles
with the Confederate troops. No fighting of any importance fell to
my lot after that until the great battle of Gettysburg took place.</p>
        <p>In that great affair one hundred thousand men bore arms for
the North, and the Confederate army was represented by a force
of ninety-seven thousand men, two hundred and eighty cannons
and a large contingent of cavalry. It was at this fight that I had the
honor of assisting in the capture of two thousand five hundred
Confederate troops and
<pb id="mallory15" n="15"/>
twelve stands of colors. The loss to both sides was great—two
thousand eight hundred and thirty-four men on the side of
Freedom giving up their lives that day, thirteen thousand seven
hundred and thirty-three men were wounded, and six thousand
two hundred and forty-three were reported missing—in all, making
a grand total of twenty-three thousand two hundred and ten men
who shed their blood that the flag of Freedom should float
proudly over the nation. The Confederate loss was estimated at
twenty-eight thousand men, five thousand of whom were killed,
and the remaining twenty-three thousand wounded and missing.</p>
        <p>This great and decisive battle practically ended the war. Such
sights as I saw on that memorable day will never be effaced from
my memory, and I lay claim to the great honor of being the only
Black Colonel who assisted to gain the great victory won on the
field of America's Waterloo—Gettysburg.</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>Hail! bright auspicious day;</l>
          <l>Long shall America</l>
          <l>Thy praise resound.</l>
          <l>Joy to our native land—</l>
          <l>Let every heart expand—</l>
          <l>For Lincoln is at hand</l>
          <l>With glory crowned!</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>Hushed by the din of arms!</l>
          <l>Henceforth the olive's charms</l>
          <l>Shall war preclude.</l>
          <l>These shores a head shall own—</l>
          <l>Unsullied by a throne—</l>
          <l>Our much lov'd Lincoln,</l>
          <l>The great, the good.</l>
        </lg>
        <p>The last struggle in connection with the war occurred in the
month of May following the Battle of Gettysburg. The fight was
short, sharp and decisive, and took place on the Rio Grande near
Santiago. Soon afterward we received our honorable discharge
from further military duty. We had
<pb id="mallory16" n="16"/>
taken part in an honorable struggle for supremacy, honorably had
we conducted ourselves, and honorably were we rewarded with
the consciousness that we had assisted in liberating millions of
our brethren from bondage and had freed them forever from the
hand of the oppressor and the whiplash of slavery. It is no
wonder that Victory perched upon our standards and that
white-winged Peace could at last fold her wings and rest over the whole
nation.</p>
        <lg type="verse">
          <head>POEM BY EX-SLAVE WM. MALLORY.</head>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>On Canada's happy shore I stand</l>
            <l>And cast a wistful eye</l>
            <l>On Britain's fair and happy land,</l>
            <l>Where my possessions lie.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Sweet fields this side the American States</l>
            <l>Lay stretched in living green;</l>
            <l>Behind the slaves the devil stood,</l>
            <l>While Niagara rolled between.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>But tremulous negroes start and shrink</l>
            <l>To get on Canada's shore;</l>
            <l>They knew the Queen was on their side—</l>
            <l>And that for ever more.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>She reigns over the black—the white,</l>
            <l>She helped to set them free,</l>
            <l>And now they're at their liberty,</l>
            <l>They cry—“God Bless the Queen!”</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Millions of slaves in the cane and cotton fields</l>
            <l>Sent up their prayers to God,</l>
            <l>That He might free them from their chains</l>
            <l>And the overseers' cruel rod.</l>
          </lg>
        </lg>
        <p>At the close of the war I returned to Canada and resumed my
residence in Hamilton. Bringing back with me some hard-earned
money, I invested in a piece of property
<pb id="mallory17" n="17"/>
on John street south, where for a number of years I carried on a
business in hay, straw and wood. I became interested in the
welfare of the colored race as a nation, and wished to forward their
spiritual as much as their physical welfare. I have always held a
prominent position in the Church, and about twenty years ago I
was appointed by Bishop Nazareh as a missionary. I have served
in that capacity under the three succeeding bishops—Disney,
Hawkins, and our present Bishop C.O. Washington.</p>
        <p>Some years ago a number of colored missionaries organized
an expedition to Africa, and I was honored by receiving an
appointment as a member of the mission band. On our way to
Africa the vessel stopped for a time at the Grand Canary Islands,
and I, with a companion, had the extreme pleasure of seeing the
splendors contained within the of the world-famous Roman
Catholic Cathedral there situate. Our guide was one of the priests
connected with the Cathedral, and he very kindly spent
considerable time showing us everything of importance in and
about the sacred edifice.</p>
        <p>Our mission to Africa is being prosecuted with great vigor,
and the natives of that benighted country are rapidly becoming
Christianized through the efforts of missionaries of our own color.</p>
        <p>The success of our work in Africa caused me on my return
home to endeavor to enlist the sympathies of my brethren in this
great work of evangelization, and with that end in view I issued
the following
<q type="manifesto" direct="unspecified"><text><body><div1 type="manifesto"><head>MANIFESTO.</head><opener><salute>“<hi rend="italics">To the Colored People of Canada:</hi>—</salute></opener><p>“The time has come when we should put our shoulders to<lb/>
“the wheel and go forward and assist in Christianizing<lb/>
“and evangelizing the colored people of dark Africa. If<lb/>
“Africa is to be civilized, it must be done by our own race.<lb/>
“Now this can be done by educating our race so they will go<lb/>
“forward as if to the cry of battle; when we will take our
<pb id="mallory18" n="18"/>
“Bibles in our hands, as we did in the days gone by of<lb/>
“slavery, when we shouldered our muskets and fought for<lb/>
“freedom. We have lawyers, doctors and ministers in our<lb/>
“ranks. Then, why not assist the white people in doing<lb/>
“this great and noble work? I propose raising money for<lb/>
“the purpose of sending some of our own race to that<lb/>
“country, and I ask for your co-operation, as well as your liberal<lb/>
“and hearty support.”</p></div1></body></text></q></p>
        <p>Previous to my trip to Africa the Northwest <sic corr="Rebellion">Rebellian</sic> broke
out and I immediately placed myself in communication with the
Minister of Militia, Sir Adolph Caron, whose letter to me relative
to the matter I still have in my possession.</p>
        <p>Quite recently I evolved a missionary scheme for the
elevation of my race, and in connection with that scheme I was
presented to Sir Oliver Mowat, while the Legislature
was in session at Toronto. Hon. J.M. Gibson, member for
Hamilton, was the gentleman who kindly presented me to
Ontario's Premier, who heartily endorsed my missionary
scheme and assisted it in a pecuniary way.</p>
        <p>Soon afterwards I went to Ottawa, and through the
medium of Mr. Alex. McKay and Mr. Ryckman—members
for Hamilton—I was presented to the late Sir John Thompson,
Premier of Canada. He also took a favorable view of my scheme,
and assisted financially and otherwise. Before leaving Ottawa I
was invited to address the House, and was fortunate enough to
be able to hold the attention of my audience from the
commencement to the close of my speech.</p>
        <p>On the death of Sir John Thompson I lost a friend of
inestimable value. He, in conversation with me, expressed great
interest in my welfare, and told me that on his return from England
he wished me to call on him, as he had never before had an
opportunity of conversing with a man who actually had gone
through the trials and tribulations incidental to the life of a slave.</p>
        <p>The photo-engraving on the front of the cover of this book
is a correct representation of myself when presented to
<pb id="mallory19" n="19"/>
the honorable gentlemen mentioned above, and also as when I
<sic corr="addressed">addresses</sic> the House on that occasion.</p>
        <p>Among other pleasant memories in the time when Sir John A.
Macdonald was returned to power. I was appointed on a
deputation to confer with Sir John, at the Royal Hotel, on the <sic corr="ways">wals</sic>
and means to secure his re-election, which end was gained, and he
remained in power from that time till he passed way from earth.</p>
        <p>When the Prince of Wales came to Canada and visited
Hamilton I was appointed Marshal for the day, in company with
four white citizens; and when Princess Louise came to Hamilton I
was again distinguished by being appointed a Marshal, and later
in the day I was again highly honored by being presented to Her
Royal <sic corr="highness">Highnes</sic> by the late Judge Sinclair and John Calder, Esq. Her
Highness graciously extended her hand to me and conversed with
me relative to my race and its well-being. I told her I had been a
slave, but had escaped, and had won freedom under the British
flag. She congratulated me on my escape, and expressed deep
regret that a race, represented by such an intelligent man as I,
should ever have been enslaved.</p>
        <p><sic corr="All">Oll</sic> of this only goes to show that the colored man, by
honesty, industry and sobriety, combined with self-respect, may
hold up his head and move on terms of equality with the white
people in this fair country of Canada.</p>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head>NOTES AND INCIDENTS.</head>
          <p>During my period of servitude with Mr. Allen my abilities as
a runner were often called into requisition in order to assist my
master in levying <sic corr="tribute">tributte</sic> on the pockets of other
planters. Many a time have I been called to get out on the road
and run a couple of hundred yards against a champion from some
other plantation, and never—up to the time of my escape
<sic corr="from bondage">fro mbondage</sic>—was I headed by an opponent. My record
as a pedestrian was added to on the occasion of the
Battle of Bull's Run, when it was reported that <hi rend="italics">I actually
outrun the bullets!</hi></p>
          <pb id="mallory20" n="20"/>
          <p>The name of the famous battle should be changed from “Bull's Run”
to “Everybody's Run,” for on that day Northerners and Southerners run
and didn't know what they were running for or where they were running
to.</p>
          <p>I once heard a gentleman say that he had been told by a colored man
that he would rather be enslaved than free. I say there's a large mansion
on Hamilton Mountain already fitted up for the reception of him, or any
other colored man, who would wish to again bear the burdens and suffer
from the brutality of slavery and slave-owners. I would rather exist on
one meal a day, as a free man, than live in luxury in bondage.</p>
          <p>I have heard it remarked by white men that a colored man couldn't
go into business the same as his white brethren. Look in the States! The
black man is to be found in Congress (a representative from both races),
in drug stores, wood and lumber dealers, judges, lawyers, doctors,
professors in colleges and universities, ministers of the gospel, and many
negroes—in both Canada and the United States—have been the
recipients of high distinctions at the hands of the white man.</p>
          <p>The best organ ever made in Canada was built in Kingston, Ont.,
and the maker was a negro.</p>
          <p>Amongst the sad pictures of slave life that may be presented to my
readers, the saddest was that of slave women pleading with their masters
(and erstwhile husbands) not to sell their children. Some of the children
<sic corr="sold">cold</sic> by their combined owner and father could hardly be distinguished
from the white people. All pleadings were in vain. Either the father had
no regard for his offspring, or he had a heart of adamantine properties.
No man with one grain of soul could
<pb id="mallory21" n="21"/>
sell his own flesh and blood! Was it not the acme of cruelty to rob a
female of that priceless jewel—virtue—and then tear from her already
bleeding heart that which would serve, in a measure, to sear over the
wounds inflicted on her by her ruthless owner? Can such dastardly acts
go unpunished? I tell you these men will all be rewarded for their deeds
and misdeeds, and full measure for measure will be extracted from each
and every one of these miscreants on the last great day when the trumpet
shall sound and the grave give up its dead.</p>
          <p>During the war the regiment with which I was connected was
ordered to Georgia. While <hi rend="iyalics">en route</hi> I was appointed as scout to the
expedition, and on one of my excursions for signs of the enemy I fell in
with my former owner, Mr. Allen. He was hiding from his pursuers,
and taking compassion on him, I assisted him to escape. Since the
close of the war I have seen him once, when he assured me that if slavery
days were ever again to return to the States, and he should ever again
become an owner, the slaves on his plantation should be ruled with
the rod of mercy, and that harshness and cruelty would be unknown
quantities within his domain.</p>
          <p>Some people treat my race with respect, while others have the old
feeling that was rampant in the South, but every honest colored man and
woman deserves the respect and proper consideration due any gentleman
or lady.</p>
          <p>The course of procedure followed out in making a good negro-hunter
out of a dog in the South was about as follows: They would take
a hound pup of any breed—the larger the <sic corr="breed">bread </sic>the better for
the purpose—shut him up closely and not let him see a negro
until he was old enough to be “sicked on” to any desired object. Then he
was made to chase the slaves “in fun,” and if he caught his man he was
rewarded with pieces of raw meat. The slave used in the training
<pb id="mallory22" n="22"/>
process would be compelled by the dog's trainer to resort to all
the artifices that an escaping slave could use to throw a dog off
the scent, such as climbing trees, walking in water, doubling on
his own track, etc., in order that the dog might become thoroughly
proficient in his business. The dog's reward was always a liberal
supply of raw meat, while the poor slave's reward was invariably
an application of rawhide for not running more swiftly.</p>
          <p>The Stars and Stripes is the emblem of America. The stars are
all right, but the stripes have been most infernally excruciating to
millions of my brethren.</p>
          <p>John Brown died endeavoring to liberate the slaves. His work
did not stop the work of liberation, for God raised up thousands
who only waited for the opportunity of doing something in that
cause.</p>
          <p>I could name several Presidents with whom I was personally
acquainted, but I merely make mention of the name of Lincoln, as
he was the one who liberated four millions of slaves—my
brethren—when the Constitution of the United States declared that
we were a free and independent race.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head>WAR AVERTED.</head>
          <head>Colonel Mallory Makes a New York Railway Official Take
Back Water.</head>
          <p>Col. Mallory is back in Hamilton again. After lecturing in St.
Catharines he paid a visit to Washington in company with a
colored friend to see about a pension. On returning to New York,
it is said, Col. Mallory thought it would be a good idea to have a
ride on the elevated railway,
<pb id="mallory23" n="23"/>
and with that end in view presented himself at the ticket office and
procured the necessary pasteboards without the agent seeing his
hands or face. Col. Mallory and his friend took seats.</p>
          <p>Shortly afterwards the conductor put in an appearance.</p>
          <p>“You can't travel in this car,” said he.</p>
          <p>“Why not?” asked Mallory.</p>
          <p>“Because colored people are not permitted to ride.”</p>
          <p>“I bought my ticket, and I intend to stay where I am,”
replied the Colonel.</p>
          <p>“You'll have to get out!”</p>
          <p>“I am not going to get out.”</p>
          <p>“I will put you off!”</p>
          <p>“I dare you to anything of the kind.”</p>
          <p>“I could throw off half a dozen like you!”</p>
          <p>“You'd better pause before you act. If you throw me from
this car my fall will shake the British Empire and involve two great
nations in war. I am a subject of Queen Victoria, so you had better
beware!”</p>
          <p>The superintendent of the line happened to be on board, and
hearing the rumpus he stepped into the car.</p>
          <p>Mallory explained the position to him, and that official
“called down” the conductor and gave Mallory and his friend
passes over the whole system.</p>
          <p>It is a dangerous thing to fool with Mallory when lie is on
his diplomatic travels.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head>COLONEL MALLORY GETS A WATCH.</head>
          <p>At the regular meeting of Mount Albion Lodge of
Freemasons the brethren presented to Col. Wm. Mallory a
handsome gold watch as a mark of recognition for the gallant
stand which the Colonel has always taken in the interests of the
African race, both here and in foreign lands, wherever their rights
are assailed. The Colonel was much affected by the presentation,
and hopes somehow, sometimes and somewhere to prove his
gratitude by acts as well as words.</p>
          <pb id="mallory24" n="24"/>
          <p>
            <figure id="ill1" entity="mallor24">
              <p>Colonel Mallory Making His Escape From Slavery.</p>
            </figure>
          </p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <pb id="mallory25" n="25"/>
          <head>How Col. Mallory's Father
Fought Boers.</head>
          <head>Thrilling Story of a Battle Between The Zulus and Boers
Many Years Ago.</head>
          <p>Yesterday Col. Mallory was in a reminiscent mood, and he
gave a few friends a short account of his father and the manner in
which he came to America. The Colonel's statement, in substance,
was as follows:</p>
          <p>Some of my friends were pleased to be amused because I
offered my services to the government to fight the Boers in South
Africa. Well, I have nothing to be ashamed of, and nothing to
<sic rend="apologize">apologise</sic> for on that account. Any man may rightly offer his
services to the government which protects him; and, even if I am
getting old, I am not sure but there is a little fight left in the old
man yet.</p>
          <p>But I had another reason for offering to go to <sic corr="Africa">Ofrica</sic>, the
land of my fathers, to fight against those who robbed my people
of their land, destroyed them as a tribe, and made me a slave. The
story is a long one; but I can give the main points of it in a few
words. In the early years of the last century my father was the
chief of a small band belonging to the great Zulu nation, which
controlled early all the territory from the Zambesi to the Orange
River, and from the Indian ocean to the great Kalahari desert. The
Zulus were not civilized, as white men understand the word. They
were hunters and warriors. They lived according to the light they
had; they observed the traditions and customs of their fathers;
and they asked only that the white man should
<pb id="mallory26" n="26"/>
leave them alone in the condition in which it had pleased the Great
Father of the white man and the black man to place them. But the
Dutch settlers in the Cape Colony were not willing to leave them
alone. Those settlers had more land of their own than they could
use for their crops and their cattle; but still they were not satisfied.
They looked away to the north and they coveted the fertile plains
of the Zulu nation. With them to desire a thing was to acquire a
right to it. In their eyes the Zulus, who had lived in that country
from immemorial times, had no right which a white man was bound
to respect; and so they gathered their young men and started
northward to kill and rob the Zulus, who had never done them any
wrong.</p>
          <p>But just at that time it was not prudent for them to provoke a
conflict. The great Tshaka had made of the Zulus one nation and
had an army able to sweep the Boers into the sea. He desired,
however, to be at peace with the whites and he sent the chief
(Sotobi) and <sic corr="my">wy</sic> father to Cape Town to treat with the governor
and have it arranged that the Boers should not invade his
territories. The British authorities were, however, not prepared to
treat with Tshaka. They had not long been in possession of Cape
Colony; there was no English population there; they did not fully
understand the strength of Tshaka nor appreciate his designs;
and they made it impossible for the envoys to reach Cape Town.
And so the two chiefs turned back. Sotobi went directly to
Tshaka's capital to report the failure of his mission, while my
father turned westward to join his band on the bank of a river near
the northern boundary of what was lately the Transvaal Republic,
and is now a British Colony. This was not the settled home of the
band, but a temporary hunting camp. According to custom a light
wall of thorny shrubs had been built around the kraal as a <sic corr="defense">defence</sic>
against beasts and bands of marauders.</p>
          <p>As my father, accompanied only by one faithful friend,
reached a hill overlooking this valley, he was astonished to see
that white men were firing with muskets and hunting
<pb id="mallory27" n="27"/>
rifles at the kraal. The Zulus made no reply, because the Young
men of the party were absent on a hunt, and because they had no
firearms. They were armed only with the primitive weapons of the
South African warriors and hunters.</p>
          <p>For a few minutes my father was unable to decide what he
ought to do. His first impulse was to dash upon the assailants. But
this, <sic corr="as">is</sic> was evident, would accomplish nothing but his own death.
Then he saw the party of Zulu hunters returning from the chase.
He, therefore, made a wide detour to avoid the Boers, and
succeeded in joining this party. Quickly throwing aside their game
the hunters prepared for a counter attack upon the Boers. As they
reached the summit of the hill they perceived that the white men
had crawled up to the barrier of the kraal, and had set the thorns
on fire. Under cover of the smoke my father and his companions
descended the hill and made a determined rush upon the
besiegers. They were brave men; but the men they met were brave
also. Besides, the Boers had a decided advantage in numbers, and
carried firearms. The battle did not last long. One by one the Zulus
fell until not one was left. By this time the frail fortification of the
camp was consumed, and the Boers, rushing in, destroyed all who
could offer any resistance. Those who were too old to be valuable
or so young as to need care were killed; the rest were carried
away into slavery. Before departing the Boers examined the fallen,
and among these were two or three who were only stunned or not
badly wounded, and these they took with them. Among these was
my father. When he was in part recovered from his wounds they
set him to work; but he was a most intractable servant. Neither
blows nor chains could tame. Several times he tried to escape; and
more than once he fought with his captors. At length he was
taken, with a number of others, to the coast in Portuguese territory
and sold to a captain of a Spanish slaver. This man landed his
cargo at Charleston, South Carolina, and my father was sold to a
man named Hezekiah Spruel, who lived near Raleigh, North
Carolina. He was
<pb id="mallory28" n="28"/>
thousands of miles from his home; his wife and children were
dead; his band was destroyed; hope died within him, and he
accepted his fate. He married again, and I was the third of his
children, born about the year 1825.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>COL. MALLORY'S HERO BROTHER.</head>
          <p>Before the Civil War in the United States there was a great
fire in Charleston, South Carolina. A great part of the city was
destroyed, and the whole of it was in danger. The flames from the
burning buildings were swept by <sic corr="the">e</sic> wind toward other buildings,
and blazing boards were carried long distances, in many cases
setting fire to houses far from the actual conflagration. One of
these brands was carried to the spire of St. Michael's Cathedral,
which is about 400 feet high, the highest in America, and it
appeared as if the noble edifice was doomed to destruction. But at
the critical moment a man was seen to emerge from the spire a
short distance above the roof of the church and to climb up and
up until he reached the spot, threw down the burning board, and
with his hands extinguished the blaze which had been started.
Thus the sacred structure was saved from destruction. On his
return to the earth this man was found to be a slave, and in
gratitude to him for his great service he was set free, and he
remained a respected and useful citizen of Charleston for many
years. <sic corr="A">O</sic> beautiful poem was written to commemorate the event.</p>
          <p>The late Rev. Father Hinchey met with this poem in the
course of his reading, and making inquiry into the matter
<pb id="mallory29" n="29"/>
learned that the name of the colored hero was Mallory. He
thereupon called upon Col. Wm. Mallory, of this city, and asked
him if he had any knowledge of the Mallory of Charleston. The
Colonel told him that many years ago he and an elder brother were
slaves in Louisiana, and from that State they started toward
Canada in the hope of gaining their freedom. After many
adventures and great suffering William succeeded in crossing the
<sic corr="Detroit">Ietroit</sic> river at Malden, and he has been a citizen of Hamilton
during the greater part of the time that has since passed. But the
elder brother was captured and taken back, and the Colonel has
received no certain information of him since. But he has reason to
think that the man who <sic corr="saved">seved</sic> St. Michael's Cathedral was his
long-lost brother; and, though the latter is now dead, the Colonel is
writing to Charleston to get further information on the subject. He
was advised by Father Hinchey to do so some time before the
reverend gentleman's death. It would be strange if he should learn
that, of the two men who set out on the search for freedom from
the swamps of Louisiana, the one should find success in Canada
and the other by heroically saving a church from destruction.</p>
          <pb id="mallory30" n="30"/>
          <p>
            <figure id="ill2" entity="mallor30">
              <p>Col. Mallory's Brother Saving St. Michael's.</p>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <div3 type="letter">
            <pb id="mallory31" n="31"/>
            <opener><dateline>Hamilton, Ont., September 3rd, 1902.</dateline>
<salute>My Dear Colonel Mallory:</salute></opener>
            <p>I have caused <sic corr="inquiries">enquiries</sic> to be made as to the name of the
“Slave” who was known as “The Hero of St. Michael's
Cathedral, Charleston, South Carolina,” and I find that he was well
known around Charleston, that he was celebrated for many feats
of strength and agility, not the least of which was the saving of
that Catholic Cathedral in Charleston. That his name was Mallory,
and I have not the least doubt but that he was a brother of your
own, as he was said to hail from the same place where you told me
you were born. He would probably be an elder brother of yours.</p>
            <closer><salute>Yours very truly,</salute>
<signed>M. MALONE.</signed></closer>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>HOW HE SAVED ST. MICHAEL'S.</head>
            <p>The following poem about St. Michael's Church, Charleston,
South Carolina, will be familiar to many, as it has often been
recited by readers. The “Slave” therein referred to has been for
many years a resident of this city, and is seen daily on our streets.</p>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Do you beg for a story, my darling, my brown eyed Leopold; </l>
              <l>And you Alice with a face like morning and curling locks of gold;</l>
              <l>Then come if you will, and listen, stand close beside my knee,</l>
              <l>To a tale of a Southern city, proud Charleston on the sea.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb id="mallory32" n="32"/>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>It was long ago, my children, ere ever the signal gun</l>
              <l>That blazed about Fort Sumpter had waked the North as one;</l>
              <l>Long ere the wondrous pillar of battle, cloud and fire,</l>
              <l>Had marked where the unchained millions marched on to their
hearts desire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>On the roofs and glittering turrets, that night, as the sun went
down,</l>
              <l>The mellow glow of the twilight shone like a jewelled crown;</l>
              <l>And, bathed in the living glory, as the people lifted their eyes,</l>
              <l>They saw the pride of the city, the spire of St. Michael's rise.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>High over the lesser steeples, tipped with the golden ball,</l>
              <l>That hung like a radiant planet caught in its earthward fall,</l>
              <l>First glimpse of hope to the sailor who made the harbor round,</l>
              <l>And last slow-fading Vision dear to the outward bound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>The gently gathering shadows shut out the waning light;</l>
              <l>The children prayed at their bedsides as you will pray tonight;</l>
              <l>The noise of the Buyer and Seller from the busy mart had gone,</l>
              <l>And in dreams of a peaceful morrow, the city slumbered on.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>But another light than sunrise aroused the sleeping street,</l>
              <l>For a cry was heard at midnight, and the rush of tramping feet,</l>
              <l>Men stared in each other's faces through mingled fire and smoke,</l>
              <l>While the frantic bells went clashing, clamorous stroke on stroke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>By the glare on her blazing tree the houseless mother fled,</l>
              <l>With the babe she pressed to her bosom shrieking in nameless
dread,</l>
              <l>While the fire-king's battalions scale wall and capstone high,</l>
              <l>And planted their flaming banners against an inky sky.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb id="mallory33" n="33"/>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>From the death that raged behind them, and the crash of ruin
loud,</l>
              <l>To the great square of the city, were driven the surging crowd,</l>
              <l>Where firm in all the tumult unscathed by the fiery flood,</l>
              <l>With its heavenward pointed finger the church of St. Michael
stood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>But even as they gaze upon it, there arose a sudden wail,</l>
              <l>A cry of horror, blended with the roaring of the gale,</l>
              <l>On whose scorching wings, up driven, a single flaming brand</l>
              <l>Aloft on the touring steeple clung like a bloody hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>“Will it fade?” The whisper trembled from a thousand whitening
lips;</l>
              <l>Far out on the lurid harbor they watched it on the ships,</l>
              <l>A baneful gleam that brighter and ever brighter shone,</l>
              <l>Like a flickering, trembling Will-o'-wisp to the steady beacon
grown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Uncounted gold shall be given to the man whose brave right
hand</l>
              <l>For the love of the perilled city plucks down yon burning brand;”</l>
              <l>So cried the Mayor of Charleston, that the people heard;</l>
              <l>But they looked, each one at his fellow, and no man spoke a word.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Who is it that leans from the belfry with face <sic corr="upturned">uptprned</sic> to the sky,</l>
              <l>Clings to a column and measures the dizzy spire with his eye;</l>
              <l>Will he dare it, the hero undaunted, that terrible sickening height,</l>
              <l>Or will the hot blood of his courage freeze in his veins at the sight?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>But see! He has stepped on the railing; he clings with his feet and
hands;</l>
              <pb id="mallory34" n="34"/>
              <l>And firm on the narrow projection, with the belfry beneath him, he
stands,</l>
              <l>Now once, and once only they cheer him, a single tempestuous
breath,</l>
              <l>And there falls on the multitude gazing a hush like the stillness of
death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Slow-steadily mounting, nuheading aught save the goal of
the fire,</l>
              <l>Still higher and higher, an atom, he moves on the face of the spire,</l>
              <l>He stops! Will he fail? Lo! for answer, a gleam like a meteor's
track,</l>
              <l><sic corr="And">Ond</sic> hurled on the stones of the pavement, the red brand lies
shattered and black.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Once more the shouts of the people have rent the quivering air;</l>
              <l>And at the church door the mayor and council wait, their feet on
the stair;</l>
              <l>And the eager throng behind them press for a touch of his hand,</l>
              <l>The unknown saviour, whose daring could compass a deed so
grand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>But why does a sudden tremor seize on them while they gaze?</l>
              <l>And what meaneth that stifled murmur of wonder and amaze?</l>
              <l>He stood at the gate of the temple he had perilled his life to
save;</l>
              <l>And the face of the hero, my children, was the sable face of a
slave.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>With folded arms he was speaking, in tones that were not loud,</l>
              <l>And his eyes, a blaze in their sockets, burnt into the eyes of the
crowd;</l>
              <l>“You may keep your gold; I scorn it; but answer me, ye who can,</l>
              <pb id="mallory35" n="35"/>
              <l>If the deed that I have done before you was not the deed of a
man?”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>He stepped but a short space backwards; and from all the women
and men</l>
              <l>There were only sobs for answer; and the mayor called for
a pen,</l>
              <l>And the great seal of the city, that he might read who ran,</l>
              <l>And the slave who saved St. Michael's went out of its door a
Man.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>P. S.—St. Michael's Church, Charleston, spire is nearly 400
feet high and is the highest steeple in <sic corr="America">Amreica.</sic></p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>COLONEL MALLORY.</head>
          <p>As Col. William Mallory is about to issue a new and <sic corr="enlarged">enlarger</sic>
edition of his autobiography, it may not be amiss to glance at the
life and adventures of a man who has been a citizen of Hamilton
for more than forty years.</p>
          <p>Born near Raleigh, North Carolina, William was, at the age of
seven, sold to a Louisiana planter, and taken to the estate of his
purchaser, below Baton Rouge. Here he remained until the year
1859, when he resolved to try to gain his freedom, and in this
venture he was fortunate enough to succeed, with some
assistance from the “under-ground railroad.” He crossed the
<sic corr="Detroit">detroit</sic> river at Malden, and soon afterward came to Hamilton,
where with short periods of absence he has since resided.
</p>
          <pb id="mallory36" n="36"/>
          <p>He has always been active in politics. His first political work
was done in the days when Sir Allen Macnab sought the
suffrages of the people; and he was afterwards a supporter of the
Hon. Isaac Buchanan. When Sir John Macdonald announced
the National Policy as that which he desired for Canada, the
colonel took the stump, and, both on the platform and in other
ways, he rendered good service to the cause. Since that time he
has been an active worker in the political field.</p>
          <p>He has always been looked upon as a representative of his
race. When the Prince of Wales (now King Edward the Seventh)
visited Hamilton in 1861, Col. Mallory was one of the marshals;
and he was a member of the committee which welcomed the
Princess Louise to this city. The Princess kindly conversed with
the colonel for a considerable time, and expressed her
astonishment that so intelligent a man could ever have been held
in slavery. Again, when the Duke of York came to Hamilton the
colonel was selected to represent the colored citizens on the
reception committee.</p>
          <p>He has sent copies of his former pamphlet to Sir John
Macdonald, to Sir Wilfrid Laurier, to Sir Oliver Mowat, to the
present King, to Queen Victoria and to His Holiness the Pope.
From <sic corr="many">may</sic> of these he has flattering letters of thanks.</p>
          <p>The colonel has always been held in high esteem in Hamilton
for his integrity and for the missionary work he has done for his
race; and he has received many marks of esteem and recognition,
among them a valuable watch from the Masonic body, of which
he was the Master.</p>
          <p>A large number of the best-citizens of Hamilton have
subscribed for the new edition of his autobiography, which is
now in the printer's hands, and will shortly be issued.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <pb id="mallory37" n="37"/>
          <head>THE TWO MALLORYS.</head>
          <p>A few days ago the Spectator called attention to the daring
feat of a colored man named Mallory, who gained his freedom by
saving from destruction the Cathedral of St. Michael, in
Charleston, South Carolina; and it was then explained that the
matter was called to the attention of Col. William Mallory, of this
city, by the late Father Hinchey. It is rather singular that Father
Hinchey read, almost at the same time, the <sic corr="poem describing">poe mdescribing</sic> the
Charleston incident, and a local paragraph telling how Col. Mallory
had saved the life of a child in this city. This affair happened on
the 12th of August, last year. A team of frightened horses was
plunging down the market square, and a little girl, the daughter of
John White, was in their course, when the colonel, at great
personal risk, ran to her rescue, and carried her safely to the store
of C. H. Peebles. That gentleman says to the colonel: “I can say
that Col. Mallory snatched a child from in front of a team of horses
that were running away in front of our store; and, I believe, saved
her life.”</p>
          <p>Col. Mallory has secured a copy of the poem describing the
saving of St. Michael's Cathedral, and will shortly have it
published.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <pb id="mallory38" n="38"/>
          <p>
            <figure id="ill3" entity="mallor38">
              <p>Colonel Mallory Rescuing the Daughter of Mr. and Mrs. John White.</p>
            </figure>
          </p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <pb id="mallory39" n="39"/>
          <head>COL. MALLORY, LIFE SAVER.</head>
          <opener><dateline>Hamilton, September 12th.</dateline>
<salute>Col. William Mallory, Hamilton:</salute></opener>
          <p>Dear Sir,—I desire to express my gratitude to you for saving
my child on August 13th. The little girl was in danger of being
crushed by a runaway team, when you, at the imminent hazard of
your own life, rushed in, seized the horses, and dragged the child
from almost under their feet. For this heroic act I trust that you
will receive your reward. I have offered you a sum of money for
your good deed; but this you have refused. I can now only tender
you my heartfelt thanks, ask for you the approval of your fellow-citizens
and pray that the blessing of heaven shall rest upon you.</p>
          <closer>
            <signed>MR. and MRS. JOHN WHITE.</signed>
          </closer>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <p>On the occasion of the visit of the Duke of Cornwall and
York to Hamilton, Col. Mallory presented to His Royal Highness a
copy of his book entitled “The Key to Slavery.” The Colonel has
received the following gracious reply:
</p>
          <p>“The private secretary to the Duke of Cornwall and York is
desired to thank Col. W. Mallory for the copy of his pamphlet,
‘The Key to Slavery,’ which he has been good enough to offer for
His Royal Highness' acceptance.”
<date>October 12th, 1901.</date></p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <pb id="mallory40" n="40"/>
          <head>COLONEL MALLORY TO THE FRONT.</head>
          <p>EDITOR HERALD,—The plan as proposed by the temperance
people to do away with the liquor traffic I consider entirely wrong. I
have always thought so, and now I am prepared to prove it. I admit it is
an unnecessary evil but we have the remedy in our own hands if we
would only take it. We have asked the two Governments if they would
give us Prohibition, and now they turn around and ask us if we want it. I
am prepared to take the platform any day and prove my statements.</p>
          <closer>
            <salute>COL. WM. MALLORY.</salute>
          </closer>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>TO EVANGELIZE GEORGIA.</head>
          <head>Col. Mallory Thinks That Country Most Needs the Missionary.</head>
          <p>Col. Mallory is in town again. He has been in the land of the free,
from the slavery of which he escaped many years ago. For a long time
the evangelization of darkest Africa has been the Colonel's pet scheme,
but recent developments in the land where he spent his slavery days, in
Georgia, have convinced him that there is no place in the world where the
missionary is as badly needed as in Georgia. Hanging, without trial, he
thinks, would not be tolerated even in Africa, so he purposes devoting
the rest of his life to the evangelization of Georgia—and is out with a
request for the needful.—<hi rend="italics">Hamilton Times.</hi></p>
          <lg>
            <l>I had a banjo made of gold,</l>
            <l>And all the strings was twine,</l>
            <l>And all the tune that I could play</l>
            <l>Was “I wish that girl was mine.”</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <pb id="mallory49" n="49"/>
          <lg type="hymn">
            <head>10. Heavenly Land Up Yonder.</head>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>There's a heavenly land up yonder,</l>
              <l>There's a heavenly land up yonder,</l>
              <l>There's a heavenly land up yonder,</l>
              <l>O when shall I get there.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Led Him away to Pilate's bar,</l>
              <l>When shall I get there.</l>
              <l>They could not condemn Him thar,</l>
              <l>When shall I get there.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>There's a heavenly land up yonder, etc.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Pilate says wash my hands,</l>
              <l>When shall I get there.</l>
              <l>I find no fault in this just man,</l>
              <l>When shall I get there.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>There's a heavenly land up yonder, etc.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Jews and the Romans in one band,</l>
              <l>When shall I get there.</l>
              <l>Crucified the Son of Man,</l>
              <l>When shall I get there.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>There's a heavenly land up yonder, etc.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Crucified the Son of Man,</l>
              <l>When shall I get there.</l>
              <l>He rose and went to heaven again,</l>
              <l>When shall I get there.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>There's a heavenly land up yonder, etc.</l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <pb id="mallory50" n="50"/>
          <lg type="hymn">
            <head>17. De Massa ob de Sheepfol'.</head>
            <lg type="STANZA">
              <l>De massa ob de sheepfol'</l>
              <l>Dat guards de sheepfol' bin,</l>
              <l>Looks out in the gloomerin' meadow</l>
              <l>Where the long night rain begins,</l>
              <l>“So he calls to the hirelin shepherd:</l>
              <l>Is my sheep is dey all come in.”—<hi rend="italics">Repeat.</hi></l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—Oh de massa guards de sheepfol' bin,</l>
              <l>And he wants to know is my sheep come in,</l>
              <l>And he calling, calling, calling softly, softly,</l>
              <l>calling for dem all to come agadderin' in.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Oh den says de hirelin shepherd,</l>
              <l>Der's some dey's black and thin,</l>
              <l>And some dey is poor old wedders</l>
              <l>Dat can't come home again.</l>
              <l>“Dey is lost and good fa nuffin,</l>
              <l>And the rest dey is all brung in.”  - <hi rend="italics"> Repeat.</hi></l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Den de massa ob de sheepfol'</l>
              <l>Dat guards de sheepfol' bin,</l>
              <l>Goes down in the gloomerin' meadow</l>
              <l>Where the long night rain begins,</l>
              <l>So he lets down the bars of the sheepfol'</l>
              <l>Calling softly come in, come in.”—<hi rend="italics">Repeat.</hi></l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Then up thro' the gloomerin' meadow</l>
              <l>Thro' the cold night rain and wind,</l>
              <l>Then up thro the gloomerin' rain path</l>
              <l>Where the sleet falls piercing thin,</l>
              <l>The poor lost sheep of the sheepfol'</l>
              <l>Dey all comes agaddering in.—<hi rend="italics">Repeat.</hi></l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <pb id="mallory51" n="51"/>
          <lg type="hymn">
            <head>28. RUN, MARY, RUN!</head>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—Run, Mary, run, run Mary run, 0 run Mary
run,</l>
              <l>I know the other world is not like this.—<hi rend="italics">Repeat.</hi></l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Fire in the east and fire in the west,</l>
              <l>I know the other world is not like this.</l>
              <l>Bound to burn the wilderness,</l>
              <l>I know the other world is not like this.
<hi rend="italics">Repeat.</hi></l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—Run, Mary, run, etc.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Swing, low, chariot in the east,</l>
              <l>I know the other world is not like this.</l>
              <l>Let God's children have some peace,</l>
              <l>I know the other world is not like this.</l>
              <l>Swing, low, chariot in the west,</l>
              <l>I know the other world is not like this.</l>
              <l>Let God's children have some rest,</l>
              <l>I know the other world is not like this.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—Run, Mary, run, etc.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Swing, low, chariot in the north,</l>
              <l>I know the other world is not like this.</l>
              <l>Give me the gold without the dross,</l>
              <l>I know the other world is not like this.</l>
              <l>Swing, low, chariot in the south,</l>
              <l>I know the other world is not like this.</l>
              <l>Let God's children sing and shout,</l>
              <l>I know the other world is not like this</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—Run, Mary, run, etc.</l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <pb id="mallory52" n="52"/>
          <lg type="hymn">
            <head>29. My Lord Delivered Daniel.</head>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—My Lord delivered Daniel, my Lord delivered
Daniel,</l>
              <l>My Lord delivered Daniel, why can't He
deliver me.—<hi rend="italics">Repeat.</hi></l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Some say that John the Baptist</l>
              <l>Was nothing but a Jew,</l>
              <l>But the Bible doth inform us</l>
              <l>That he was a preacher too.</l>
              <l>Yes, he was!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—My Lord delivered Daniel, etc.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Oh, Daniel cast in the lions' den</l>
              <l>He prayed both night and day,</l>
              <l>The angel came from Galilee</l>
              <l>And locked the lion's jaws.</l>
              <l>That's so!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—My Lord delivered Daniel, etc.</l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <lg type="hymn">
            <head>30. Steal Away to Jesus !</head>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—Steal away, steal away, steal away to Jesus,</l>
              <l>Steal away, steal away home I ain't got long to
stay here.—<hi rend="italics">Repeat.</hi></l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>My Lord calls me, He calls me by the thunder,</l>
              <l>The trumpet sounds within my soul</l>
              <l>I hain't got long to stay here.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—Steal away, steal away, etc,</l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <pb id="mallory53" n="53"/>
          <lg type="hymn">
            <head>32.  Sinner You'd Better Get Ready!</head>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—Oh! sinner you'd better get ready, ready, my
Lord, ready.</l>
              <l>Oh! sinner you'd better get ready, for the time
is a coming when a sinner must die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Oh! sinner man you'd better pray,</l>
              <l>Time is a coming when a sinner must die.</l>
              <l>For it looks like judgment every day,</l>
              <l>Time is a coming when a sinner must die.</l>
              <l>I heard a lumbering in the sky,</l>
              <l>Time is a coming when a sinner must die.</l>
              <l>It made me think my time was nigh,</l>
              <l>Time is a coming when a sinner must die</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—Oh! sinner you'd better, etc.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Heard of my Jesus, many one said,</l>
              <l>To move poor sinners' sins away.</l>
              <l>I'd rather pray myself away</l>
              <l>Than to lie in hell and burn one day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—Oh! sinner you'd better, etc.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>I think I heard my mother say</l>
              <l>'Twas a pretty thing to serve the Lord,</l>
              <l>But when I get to heaven I'll be able for to tell,</l>
              <l>Oh! how I shunn'd that dismal hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—Oh! sinner you'd better. etc.</l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <pb id="mallory54" n="54"/>
          <lg type="hymn">
            <head>48.  My Lord is Writing All the Time.</head>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Come down, come down, my Lord come down,</l>
              <l>My Lord's writing all the time.</l>
              <l>And take me up to wear the crown,</l>
              <l>My Lord's writing all the time.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—Oh, He sees all I do, He hears all I say,</l>
              <l>My Lord's writing all the time.  - <hi rend="italics"> Repeat.</hi></l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>When I was down in Egypt's land</l>
              <l>I heard some talk of promised land.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—Oh, He sees all I do, etc</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>O Christians you had better pray,</l>
              <l>For Satan's round you every day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—Oh, He sees all I do, etc.</l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <lg type="hymn">
            <head>44.  He's the Lily of the Valley.</head>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—He's the lily of the valley, O my Lord,</l>
              <l>He's the lily of the valley, O my Lord.  - <hi rend="italics"> Repeat</hi></l>
              <l>King Jesus in His chariot, O my Lord,</l>
              <l>With four white horses side by side, O my Lord.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>What kind of shoes are those you wear? O my Lord,</l>
              <l>That you can ride upon the air, O my Lord.</l>
              <l>These shoes I wear are Gospel shoes, O my Lord,</l>
              <l>And you can wear them if you choose, O my Lord.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—He's the lily of the valley, etc.</l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <pb id="mallory55" n="55"/>
          <lg type="hymn">
            <head>45.  Bright Sparkles in the Churchyard.</head>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>May the Lord, He will be glad of me,</l>
              <l>May the Lord, He will be glad of me,</l>
              <l>May the Lord, He will be glad of me,</l>
              <l>In the heaven He'll rejoice.</l>
              <l>In the heaven once, in the heaven twice, in the
heaven He'll rejoice.  - <hi rend="italics">Repeat.</hi></l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Bright sparkles in the churchyard</l>
              <l>Give light unto the tomb,</l>
              <l>Bright summer, spring's over,</l>
              <l>Sweet flowers in their bloom.—<hi rend="italics">Repeat.</hi></l>
              <l>My mother once, my mother twice, my mother she'll
rejoice.</l>
              <l>In the heaven once, in the heaven twice, in the heaven
she'll rejoice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Mother rock me in the cradle all the day,</l>
              <l>Mother rock me in the cradle all the day,</l>
              <l>Mother rock me in the cradle all the day,</l>
              <l>All the day. all the day, O rock me in the cradle all
the day.—<hi rend="italics">Repeat.</hi></l>
              <l>Oh, mother don't you love your darling child?</l>
              <l>Oh, rock me in the cradle all the day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Mother rock me in the cradle,</l>
              <l>Mother rock me in the cradle,</l>
              <l>Mother rock me in the cradle all the day.  - <hi> Repeat.</hi></l>
              <l>All the day, all the day, oh, rock me in the cradle all
the day.</l>
              <l>You may lay me down to sleep my mother dear,</l>
              <l>Oh, rock me in the cradle all the day.—<hi>Repeat.</hi></l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <pb id="mallory56" n="56"/>
          <lg type="hymn">
            <head>54.  Way Ober Yonder on the Hilltop!</head>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>There's gwine to be a glorious time by-and-by,</l>
              <l>Way ober yonder on the hilltop!</l>
              <l>Where the moon shines bright in the cloudless sky,</l>
              <l>Way ober yonder on the hilltop!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>At that great camp meeting we'll work no more, we'll</l>
              <l>play a little tune upon the old banjo, and de bells</l>
              <l>keep a ringing on the golden shore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—Way ober yonder where de children am a
singing,</l>
              <l>And de bells dey keep ringing,</l>
              <l>Way ober yonder on the hilltop.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Take de narrow little railroad smooth and straight,</l>
              <l>Way ober yonder on the hilltop!</l>
              <l>If you trabble by the broad gauge you'll sure to be late,</l>
              <l>Way ober yonder on the hilltop!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>You fashionable people with your pomp and pride, all</l>
              <l>painted up and powdered and your hair all dyed like</l>
              <l>the label on the bottle, you'll be left outside.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—Way ober yonder, etc.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>When Gabriel blows his silver horn,</l>
              <l>Way ober yonder on the hilltop!</l>
              <l>Get you ready for to trabble in the early morn,</l>
              <l>Way ober yonder on the hilltop!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>But you needn't come along if you don't look neat,</l>
              <l>you must throw dem worldly shoes from off your feet,</l>
              <l>or dey'll never let you walk up in the golden streets.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>CHO.—Way ober yonder, etc.</l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>