<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % external-entities SYSTEM "./extEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY % internal-entities SYSTEM "./intEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY richvs SYSTEM "richvs.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY richsp SYSTEM "richsp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY richtp SYSTEM "richtp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>The Negro Servant :</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Richmond, Legh, 1772-1827</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Tom Horan</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by</resp>
          <name>Tom Horan</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Chris Hill and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1999</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca. 90K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1999.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal 
use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="text"> The Negro Servant</title>
            <title type="title page"> Annals of the Poor, Containing the Dairyman's Daughter, 
(with considerable additions) The Negro Servant, and The Young Cottager.</title>
            <title type="spine"> Annals of the Poor.</title>
            <author>Legh Richmond, A. M.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent> 51 p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>New Haven</pubPlace>
            <publisher>Whiting and Tiffany</publisher>
            <date>1815</date>
            <authority/>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="yes">Call number  C-8 R532A   (Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library,
 Duke University Libraries)</note>
            <note anchored="yes">The electronic edition has been transcribed from pages 137-187 of “Annals of the Poor.
 Containing The Dairyman's Daughter, (with considerable additions) The Negro Servant, and 
The young Cottager.” </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>All footnotes are inserted at the point of reference.</p>
        <p>The electronic edition has been transcribed from pages 137-187 of “Annals of the Poor. 
Containing The Dairyman's Daughter, (with considerable additions) The Negro Servant, 
and The young Cottager.” </p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and 
Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Christian life.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Religion.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Religious life.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2000-06-26, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-12-17, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-12-16, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Chris Hill</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-12-10, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Tom Horan</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="spine">
        <p>
          <figure id="spine" entity="richsp">
            <p>[Spine Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="title page">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="richtp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="title page verso">
        <p>
          <figure id="verso" entity="richvs">
            <p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">Annals of the Poor. </titlePart>
          <titlePart type="main">Containing <lb/>The Dairyman's Daughter, <lb/>(with considerable additions) 
<lb/>The Negro Servant, 
<lb/>and 
<lb/>The young Cottager.</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <docAuthor>By the Reverend 
<lb/>
Legh Richmond, A.M.
<lb/>
Rector of Turvey, Bedforshire; and Chaplain of His Royal Highness
<lb/>
the Duke of Kent and Strathern</docAuthor>
        <epigraph>
          <p><hi rend="italics">Thou, O God, hast prepared of thy goodness for the poor 
...</hi>Psl. 68, v.10</p>
        </epigraph>
        <docImprint><pubPlace>New-Haven</pubPlace>
<publisher>Published by Whiting and Tiffany
<lb/>
Sign of Frankiln's Head,
<lb/>
Corner of College Green.</publisher>
<date>1815.</date></docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="opening">
        <pb id="rich138" n="138"/>
        <p><hi rend="italics">“The day spring from on high hath visited us, to give light to them
that sit in darkness and in the shadow of death, to guide our feet into
the way of peace.”</hi>—Luke, i. 78, 79. </p>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="main text">
        <pb id="rich139" n="139"/>
        <head>THE<lb/>
NEGRO SERVANT.</head>
        <div2 type="part">
          <head>PART I.</head>
          <p>If a map of the world, instead of being coloured,
as is usual, with many gay and brilliant tints
in order to distinguish its various continents,
kingdoms, and islands, from each other, were to be
painted with darker or brighter hues, corresponding
with the spiritual character of the inhabitants,
what a gloomy aspect would be presented to the
eye of the <hi rend="italics">Christian</hi> geographer by the greater
portion of the habitable glove!—How dark would
be the shade thus cast over the larger districts of
the vast continents of Asia and America! and
what a mass of gloom would characterize the
African quarter of the world!</p>
          <p>Here and there a bright spot would mark the
residence of a few missionary labourers devoting
themselves to God, and scattering the rays of
Christian light among the surrounding heathen;
but over the greater part “the blackest of darkness”
would emblematically describe the iron
<pb id="rich140" n="140"/>
reign of Mahometan superstition and Pagan idolatry.</p>
          <p>The Christian prays that God would “have respect
unto the covenant; for the dark places of
the earth are full of the habitations of cruelty.”
He hopes to see the nations “open their eyes,
and turn from darkness to light, and from the
power of Satan unto God, that they may receive
forgiveness of sins, and inheritance among them
which are sanctified by faith.”</p>
          <p>The curse originally pronounced on the descendents
of Ham, has, in a variety of respects,
both temporal and spiritual, been awfully fulfilled:
“A servant of servants shall he be.” Slavery, as
well of mind as body, has been continued amongst
the Africans through their generations, in a manner
which at once proves the truth of the divine prediction,
and yet calls aloud for the ardent
prayers and active exertions of Christians in their behalf.
The time will come when the heathen
shall be proved to have been given to Christ
“for an inheritance, and the uttermost part of the earth
for his possessions.” The degraded Hottentot and
the poor benighted Negro will look down from the
ends of the earth unto Jesus and be saved. “Money
shall go to and fro, and knowledge shall thereby
<pb id="jwl141" n="141"/>
be increased.” The Redeemer “shall see of
the travail of his soul, and be satisfied,” in
beholding the gathering together, not only of the
outcasts of Israel, that are ready to perish; but of
churches and people from all the tongues, and kindreds,
and nations of the earth. In the day of
his appearing, the sons of Africa will vie with
their brethren of the North, and the West, and the
East, in resounding the praises of God their Saviour,
from one end of the earth to the other.</p>
          <p>In the meantime, we rejoice in every occasional
instance of the love and power of God in effecting
the conversation of some, who appear as the
first fruits of that harvest which shall hereafter so
fruitfully grow up, to the honour of Christ and the
blessedness of his redeemed people.</p>
          <p>The following narrative of real facts may, perhaps,
illustrate the importance of the foregoing remarks.</p>
          <p>During a residence of some years continuance,
in the neighbourhood of the sea, an Officer in the
navy called upon me, and stated, that he had just
taken a lodging in the parish for his wife and
children; and had a Negro, who had been three years
in his service. “The lad is a deserving fellow,”
said the Officer, “and he has a great desire
<pb id="rich142" n="142"/>
to be baptized; I have promised him to ask you
to do it if you have not any objections.”</p>
          <p>“Does he know any thing,” I replied, “of the
principles of the Christian religion?”</p>
          <p>“O yes, I am sure he does,” answered the
Captain; “for he talks a deal about it in the kitchen,
and often gets laughed at for his pains; but
he takes it all very patiently.”</p>
          <p>“Does he behave well as your servant?”</p>
          <p>“Yes, that he does: he is as honest and civil a
fellow as ever came aboard a ship, or lived in a
house.”</p>
          <p>“Was he always so well behaved?”</p>
          <p>“No,” said the Officer; “when I first had him,
he was often very unruly and deceitful; but for
the last two years he has been quite like another
creature.”</p>
          <p>“Well, sir, I shall be very glad to see him, and
think it probable I shall wish to go through a
course of instruction and examination; during
which I shall be able to form a judgment how far
it will be right to admit him to the sacrament of
baptism. Can he read?”</p>
          <p>“Yes,” replied his master; “he has been taking
great pains to learn to read for some time
<pb id="rich143" n="143"/>
speaks English better than many of his countrymen,
but you will find it a little broken. When
will it be convenient that I should send him over
to you?”</p>
          <p>“To-morrow afternoon, Sir, if you please.”</p>
          <p>“He shall come to you about four o'clock, and
you shall see what you can make of him.”</p>
          <p>With this promise he took his leave. I felt
glad of an opportunity of instructing a native of
that land whose wrongs and injuries had often
caused me to sigh and mourn: the more so, when
I reflected <hi rend="italics">who</hi> had been the aggressors.</p>
          <p>At the appointed hour, my negro disciple arrived.
He was a very young looking man, with a
sensible, lively, and pleasing countenance.</p>
          <p>I desired him to sit down, and said, “your
master informs me that you wish to have some
conversation with me respecting Christian baptism.”</p>
          <p>“Yes, Sir, me very much wish to be a Christian,” said he.</p>
          <p>“Why do you wish so?”</p>
          <p>“Because me know that Christian go to heaven
when he die.”</p>
          <p>“How long have you had that wish?” I said.</p>
          <p>“Ever since me hear one goot minister preach</p>
          <pb id="rich144" n="144"/>
          <p>“Where were you born?”</p>
          <p>“In Africa. Me was very little boy when me
was made slave by de white men.”</p>
          <p>“How was that?”</p>
          <p>“Me left father and mother one day at home to
go get shells by de sea-shore, and as I was stooping
down to gather dem up, some white sailors
came out of a boat and took me away. Me
never see father nor mother again.”</p>
          <p>“And what became of you then?”</p>
          <p>“Me was put into ship, and brought to Jamaica,
and sold to a master, who kept me in his house
to serve him some years; when, about three
years ago, Captain——, my master dat spoke to
you, brought me to be his servant on board his
ship. And he be goot master; he gave me my
liberty, and made me free, and me live with him
ever since.”</p>
          <p>“And what thoughts had you about your soul
all that time before you went to America?” I
asked him.</p>
          <p>“Me no care for my soul at all before den. No
man teach me one word about my soul.”</p>
          <p>“Well, now tell me farther about what
happened to you in America. How came you there?”</p>
          <p>“My master take me dere in his ship, and he
<pb id="rich145" n="145"/>
stop dere one month, and den me hear de goot
minister.”</p>
          <p>“And what did that minister say?”</p>
          <p>“He said, me was great sinner.”</p>
          <p>“What, did he speak to you in particular?”</p>
          <p>“Yes, me tink so; for dere was great many to
hear him, but he tell dem all about me.”</p>
          <p>“What did he say?”</p>
          <p>“He say about all de tings dat were in my
heart.”</p>
          <p>“What things?”</p>
          <p>“My sin, my ignorance, my know noting, my believe
noting. De goot minister made me see dat
me <hi rend="italics">tink</hi> noting goot, nor <hi rend="italics">do</hi> noting goot.”</p>
          <p>“And what else did he tell you?”</p>
          <p>“He sometimes look me in de face and say,
dat Jesus Christ came to die for sinners, poor
black sinners, as well as white sinners. Me tought
dis was very goot, very goot indeed, to do so for
wicked sinner.”</p>
          <p>“And what made you think this was all spoken
to you in particular?”</p>
          <p>“Because me sure no such wicked sinner as me
in all de place. De goot minister must know me
was dere.”</p>
          <pb id="rich146" n="146"/>
          <p>“And what did you think of yourself while he
preached about Jesus Christ?”</p>
          <p>“Sir, me was very much afraid, when he said
de wicked must be turned into hell-fire, For me
felt dat me was very wicked sinner, and dat make
me cry. And he talk much about de love of Christ
to sinners, and dat make me cry more. And me
tought me must love Jesus Christ: but me not
know how, and dat make me cry again.”</p>
          <p>“Did you hear more sermons than one during
that month?”</p>
          <p>“Yes, Sir; massa gave me leave to go free
times, and all de times me wanted to love Jesus
more, and do what Jesus said; but my heart seem
sometime hard, like a stone.”</p>
          <p>“Have you ever heard any preaching since that
time?”</p>
          <p>“Never, till me hear sermon at dis church last
Sunday, and den me long to be baptized in Jesus'
name; for me had no Christian friends to baptize
me when little child.”</p>
          <p>“And what have been your thoughts all the
time since you first heard these sermons in America?
did you tell anybody then what you felt?”</p>
          <p>“No, me speak to nobody but to God den. De
goot minister say, dat God hear de cry of de poor;
so me cry to God, and he hear me. And me often
<pb id="rich147" n="147"/>
tink about Jesus Christ, and wish to be like him.”</p>
          <p>“Can you read?”</p>
          <p>“A little.”</p>
          <p>“Who taught you to read?”</p>
          <p>“God teach me to read.”</p>
          <p>“What do you mean by saying so?”</p>
          <p>“God give me desire to read, and dat make
reading easy. Massa give me Bible, and one
sailor show me de letters; and so me learned to read
by myself, with God's goot help.”</p>
          <p>“And what do you read in the Bible?”</p>
          <p>“O! me read all about Jesus Christ, and how
he loved sinners; and wicked men killed him, and
he died, and came again from the grave, and all
dis for negro. And it sometime make me
cry, to tink dat Christ love so poor negro.”</p>
          <p>“And what do the people say about your reading
and praying, and attention to the things of God?”</p>
          <p>“Some wicked people dat do not love Jesus
Christ, call me great fool, and negro dog, and
black hypocrite. And dat make me sometime
feel angry: but den me remember Christian
must not be angry for dat. Jesus Christ was called
ugly black names, and he was quiet as a lamb;
and den me remember Jesus Christ, and me
say noting again to dem.”</p>
          <pb id="jwl148" n="148"/>
          <p>I was much delighted with the simplicity and
apparent sincerity of this poor Negro; and wished
to ascertain what measure of light and feeling he
possessed on a few leading points. St. Paul's summary
of religion
<ref targOrder="U" id="ref1" n="1" rend="sc" target="note1">*</ref><note id="note1" n="1" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref1"><p>* 
Now abideth faith, hope, charity; these three: but
the greatest of these is charity. (I Cor. xiii. 13.)</p></note> occurring to me, I said, “Tell
me what is faith? what is your own faith? what do
you believe about Jesus Christ, and your own
soul?”</p>
          <p>“Me believe,” said he, “dat Jesus Christ came
into de world to save sinners; and dough me be
chief of sinners, yet Jesus will save me, dough me
be only poor black Negro.”</p>
          <p>“What is your hope? What do you hope for,
both as to his life and that which is to come?”</p>
          <p>“Me hope Christ Jesus will take goot care of
me, and keep me from sin and harm, while me
live here; and me hope, when me come to die, to
go and live with him always, and never die again.”</p>
          <p>“What are your thoughts about Christian love
or charity? I mean, whom and what do you most
love?”</p>
          <p>“Me love God de Fader, because he was so
goot to send his Son. Me love Jesus Christ, because
he love me. Me love all men, black men
<pb id="rich149" n="149"/>
and white men too; for God made dem all. Me
love goot Christian people, because Jesus love
dem, and dey love Jesus.”</p>
          <p>Such was my first conversation with this young
disciple; I rejoiced in the prospect of receiving
him into the church, agreeably to his desire. I
wished, however, to converse somewhat father,
and inquire more minutely into his conduct; and
promised to ride over, and see him in a few days
at his master's lodgings.</p>
          <p>When he was gone, I thought within myself,
“God hath indeed redeemed souls by the blood
of his Son, out of <hi rend="italics">every</hi> kindred and tongue, and
people and nation.” If many of them for a season
are devoted to earthly slavery,<ref targOrder="U" id="ref2" n="2" rend="sc" target="note2">*</ref>
<note id="note2" n="2" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref2">* 
This circumstance took place before the abolition
of the British slave-trade.</note> through the
cruel advice of man; yet, blessed be God, some
amongst them are, through divine grace, called to
the glorious liberty of the children of God; and
so are redeemed from the slavery of him who takes
so many captive at his will.</p>
          <p>It is happy thought, that “Ethiopia shall soon
stretch forth her hands unto God. Sing unto God,
ye kingdoms of the earth, O sing praises unto the
Lord.”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="part">
          <pb id="rich150" n="150"/>
          <head>PART II.</head>
          <p>WHEN we endeavor to estimate the worth of
an immortal soul, we are utterly lost in the
attempt. The act of spiritual computation is not
governed by the same principles and rules which
guide our speculations concerning earthly objects.
The value of gold, silver, merchandise, food, raiment,
lands, and houses, is easily regulated by
custom, convenience, or necessity. Even the
more capricious and imaginary worth of a picture,
medal, or statue, may be reduced to something
of systematic rule. Crowns and sceptres have had
their adjudged valuation, and kingdoms have been
bought and sold for sums of money. But who can
affix the adequate price to a human soul? “What
shall it profit a man, if he shall gain the whole
world, and lose his own soul? or what shall a man
give in exchange for his soul?”</p>
          <p>The principles of ordinary arithmetic all fail
here; and we are constrained to say, that He
alone who paid the ransom for sinners, and made
the souls of men his “purchased possessions,” can
comprehend and solve the arduous question. They
are indeed “bought with a price:” but are “not
<pb id="rich151" n="151"/>
redeemed with corruptible things, as silver and
gold; but with the precious blood of Christ, as of
a lamb without blemish and without spot.” We
shall only ascertain the value of a soul, when we
shall be fully able to estimate the worth of a
Saviour.</p>
          <p>Too often have we been obliged to hear what is
the price which sordid unfeeling avarice has affixed
to the <hi rend="italics">body</hi> of a poor negro slave; let us now
attempt, while we pursue the foregoing narrative,
to mediate on the value which infinite Mercy has
attached to his <hi rend="italics">soul.</hi></p>
          <p>Not many days after the first interview with my
negro disciple, I went from home with the design
of visiting and conversing with him again at his
master's house, which was situated in a part of the
parish near four miles distant from my own. The
ride which I took lay over a lofty down, which
commands a prospect of scenery seldom exceeded
in beauty and magnificence. It gave birth to silent
but instinctive contemplation.</p>
          <p>In rising upwards by the road which winds
round from the foot of the hill to its summit, I was
struck with the gradual unfolding or prospect,
which meets the eye at different stages of the ascent.
At every step of the traveller's progress, a
<pb id="rich152" n="152"/>
new and expanding range of lovely objects claims
his attention. The effect which on this delightful
eminence is singularly produced by the successive
development of near and distant beauty, is at
length crowned by the perfect circle of fine landscape
and sea-view which the high ground at the
top of the hill exhibits.</p>
          <p>The down itself was covered with sheep, grazing
on its wholesome and plentiful pasture. Here
and there a shepherd's boy kept his appointed station,
and watched over the flock committed to his
care. I viewed it as an emblem of my own situation
and employment. Adjoining the hill lay an
extensive parish, wherein many souls were given
me to watch over, and render an account of, at the
day of the great Shepherd's appearing. The pastoral
scene before me seemed to be a living parable,
illustrative of my own spiritual charge. I felt
a prayerful wish, that the good Shepherd who
gave his life for the sheep, might enable me to be
faithful to my trust.</p>
          <p>It occurred to me, about the same time, that my
young African friend was a sheep of another more
distant fold, which Christ will yet bring to hear
his voice. For there shall be one fold and one
Shepherd, and all nations shall be brought to
<pb id="rich153" n="153"/>
knowledge that he alone “restoreth our souls, and
leadeth us into the paths of righteousness for his
name's sake.”</p>
          <p>On the left hand of the hill, as I advanced eastward,
and immediately under its declivity, extended
a beautiful tract of land intersected by a large
arm of the sea, which (as the tide was fast flowing
in) formed a broad lake or haven of three miles in
length. Woods, villages, cottages, and churches,
surrounded it in most pleasing variety of prospect.
Beyond this lay a large fleet of ships of war, and
not far from it another of merchantmen, both safe
at anchor, and covering a tract of the sea of several
miles in extent. Beyond this again, I saw the
fortifications, dock-yards, and extensive public
edifices of a large seaport town. The sun shone
upon the windows of the buildings, and the flags of
the ships, with great brightness, and added much
to the splendour of the view.</p>
          <p>I thought of the concerns of empires, the plans
of statesmen, the fate of nations, and the horrors
of war. Happy will be that day, when He shall
make wars to cease unto the end of the earth, and
peace to be established on its borders!</p>
          <p>In the mean time, thankfulness is due for those
vessels and instruments of defence, which, under
<pb id="rich154" n="154"/>
the guidance of God, preserve our country from
the hand of the enemy and the fury of the destroyer.
What, thought I, do we not owe to the exertions
of the numerous crews on board those
ships, who leave their homes to fight their country's
battles, and maintain its cause, while we sit
every man under his vine and fig tree, tasting the
sweets of a tranquillity unknown to most other nations
in these days of conflict and bloodshed!</p>
          <p>On my right hand, to the south and south-east,
the unbounded ocean displayed its mighty waves.
It was covered with vessels of every size, sailing in
all directions: some outward bound to the most
distant parts of the world; others, after a long
voyage, returning home, laden with the produce
of remote climes: some going forth in search of
the enemy; others sailing back to port after the
hard-fought engagement, and bearing the trophies
of victory in the prizes which accompanied them
home.</p>
          <p>At the south-west of the spot on which I was
riding, extended a beautiful semicircular bay, of
about nine or ten miles in circumference, limited
by high cliffs of white, red, and brown coloured
earths. Beyond this lay a range of hills, whose
tops are often buried in cloudy mists, but which
<pb id="rich155" n="155"/>
then appeared clear and distinct. This chain of
hills, meeting with another from the north, bounds
a large fruitful vale, whose fields, now ripe for
harvest, proclaimed the goodness of God in the
rich provision which he makes for the sons of men.
It is he who “prepares the corn; he crowns the
year with his goodness, and his paths drop fatness.
They drop upon the pastures of the wilderness,
and the little hills rejoice on every side. The
pastures are clothed with flocks; the valleys also
are covered over with corn: they shout for joy,
they also sing.”</p>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>——“The roving sight</l>
            <l>Pursues its pleasing course o'er neighbouring hills,</l>
            <l>Of many a different form and different hue;</l>
            <l>Bright with the rip'ning corn, or green with grass,</l>
            <l>Or dark with clover's purple bloom.”</l>
          </lg>
          <p>As I looked upon the numerous ships moving
before me, I remembered the woods of the Psalmist:
“They that go down to the sea in ships, that
do business in great waters: these see the works
of the Lord, and his wonders in the deep. For
he commandeth and raiseth the stormy wind
which lifteth up the waves thereof. They mount
up to the heaven, they go down again to the
<pb id="rich156" n="156"/>
depths; their soul is melted because of the trouble.
They reel to and fro, and stagger like a drunken
man, and are at their wits end. Then they cry
unto the Lord in their trouble, and he bringeth
them out of their distresses. He maketh the storm
a calm, so that the waves thereof are still. Then
are they glad, because they be quiet: so he bringeth
them unto their desired haven. O! that men
would praise the Lord for his goodness, and for
his wonderful works to the children of men.”
(Ps. cvii.)</p>
          <p>The Negro Servant then occurred to my mind.
Perhaps, thought I, some of these ships are bound
to Africa, in quest of that most infamous object of
merchandise, a cargo of black slaves. Inhuman
traffic for a nation that bears the name of Christian!
Perhaps these very waves, which are now
dashing on the rocks at the foot of this hill, have,
on the shores of Africa, borne witness to the horrors
of forced separation between wives and husbands,
parents and children, torn asunder by merciless
men, whose heart have been hardened
against the common feeling of humanity by long
custom in this cruel trade. “Blessed are the merciful,
for they shall obtain mercy.” When shall
the endeavours of <hi rend="italics">that</hi> truly Christian <hi rend="italics">friend</hi> of the
<pb id="rich157" n="157"/>
oppressed negro be crowned with success, in the
abolition of this wicked and disgraceful traffic?<ref targOrder="U" id="ref3" n="3" rend="sc" target="note3">*</ref></p>
          <note id="note3" n="3" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref3">
            <p>* 
The day has arrived, when the persevering efforts
of Mr. Wilberforce, to accomplish this happy purpose,
have been fully answered. The slave trade is abolished.
The church of God rejoices at this triumph of the
cause of Christ over the powers of darkness.</p>
          </note>
          <p>As I pursued the meditations which this magnificent
and varied scenery excited in my mind, I
approached the edge of a tremendous perpendicular
cliff, with which the down terminates; I dismounted
from my house, and tied it to a bush.
The breaking of the waves against the foot of the
cliff at so great a distance beneath me, produced
an incessant and pleasing murmur. The sea-gulls
were flying between the top of the cliff where I
stood, and the rocks below, attending upon their
nests, built in the holes of the cliff. The whole
scene, in every direction, was grand and impressive:
it was suitable to devotion. The Creator
appeared in the works of his creation, and called
upon the creature to honour and adore.</p>
          <p>To the believer, this exercise is doubly delightful.
He possesses a right to the enjoyment of
nature and Providence, as well as to the privileges
of grace. His title-deed runs thus: “All things
<pb id="rich158" n="158"/>
are yours; whether Paul, or Apollos, or Cephas,
or the world, or life, or death, or things present, or
things to come; all are yours; and ye are Christ's,
and Christ is God's.”</p>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>“He looks abroad into the varied field</l>
            <l>Of nature, and though poor perhaps, compar'd</l>
            <l>With those whose mansions glitter in his sight,</l>
            <l>Calls the delightful scenery all his own.</l>
            <l>His are the mountains, and the valleys his,</l>
            <l>And the resplendent waters: his t'enjoy</l>
            <l>With a propriety that none can feel,</l>
            <l>But who, with filial confidence inspir'd,</l>
            <l>Can lift to heaven an unpresumptuous eye,</l>
            <l>And smiling say—‘My Father made them all.’</l>
            <l>Are they not his by a peculiar right,</l>
            <l>And by an emphasis of int'rest his,</l>
            <l>Whose eye they fill with tears of holy joy,</l>
            <l>Whose heart with praises, and whose exalted mind</l>
            <l>With worthy thoughts of that unwearied love</l>
            <l>That plann'd, and built, and still upholds a world</l>
            <l>So cloth'd with beauty for rebellious man?”</l>
          </lg>
          <p>I cast my eye downwards a little to the left towards
a small cove, the shore of which consists of
fine hard sand. It is surrounded by fragments of
rock, chalk-cliffs, and steep banks of broken earth.
Shut out from human intercourse and dwellings,
<pb id="rich159" n="159"/>
it seems formed for retirement and contemplation.
On one of these rocks I unexpectedly observed a
man sitting with a book, which he was reading.
The place was near three hundred feet perpendicularly
below me; but I soon discovered by his
dress, and by the black colour of his features, contrasted
with the white rocks beside him, that it
was no other than my negro disciple; with, as I
doubted not, a Bible in his hand. I rejoice at
this unlooked-for opportunity of meeting him in
so solitary and interesting a situation. I descended
a steep bank, winding by a kind of rude staircase,
formed by fishermen and shepherds' boys in
the side of the cliff, down to the shore.</p>
          <p>He was intent on his book, and did not perceive
me till I approached very near to him.</p>
          <p>“William, is that you?”</p>
          <p>“Ah! Massa, me very glad to see you. How
come Massa into dis place? Me tought nobody
here, but only God and me.”</p>
          <p>“I was coming to your master's house to see
you, and rode round by this way for the sake of
the prospect. I often come here in fine weather,
to look at the sea and the shipping. Is that your
Bible?”</p>
          <pb id="rich160" n="160"/>
          <p>“Yes, Sir;<ref targOrder="U" id="ref4" n="4" rend="sc" target="note4">*</ref>
<note id="note4" n="4" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref4"><p>* 
In the course of conversation, he sometimes addressed
me with the word “Massa,” for “Master,” according
to the well-known habit of the negro slaves in the
West-Indies; and sometimes, “Sir,” as he was taught
since his arrival in England; but the former word seemed
to be most familiar to him.</p></note> dis my dear goot Bible.”</p>
          <p>“I am glad,” said I, “to see you so well employed.
It is a good sign, William.”</p>
          <p>“Yes, Massa, a sign dat Good is goot to me; but
me never goot to God.”</p>
          <p>“How so?”</p>
          <p>“Me never tank him enough: me never pray
to him enough: me never remember enough, who
give me all dese goot tings. Massa, me afraid my
heart is very bat. Me wish me was like you.”</p>
          <p>“Like me, William? Why, you are like me, a
poor helpless sinner, that must, as well as yourself,
perish in his sins, unless God, of his infinite
mercy and grace, pluck him as a brand from the
burning, and make him an instance of distinguishing
love and favour. There is no difference; we
have both come short of the glory of God: all have
sinned.”</p>
          <p>“No, me not like you, Massa: me tink nobody
like me, nobody feel such a heart as me.”</p>
          <pb id="rich161" n="161"/>
          <p>“Yes, William, your feelings, I am persuaded,
are like those of every truly convinced soul, who
sees the exceeding sinfulness of sin, and the greatness
of the price which Christ Jesus paid for the
sinner's ransom. You can say in the words of the
hymn,
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg><l>‘I the chief of sinners am,</l><l>‘But Jesus died for me’.”</l></lg></q></p>
          <p>“O yes, Sir, me believe that Jesus die for poor
negro. What would become of poor wicked negro,
if Christ no die for him? But he die for de
chief of sinners, and dat make my heart sometime
quite glad.”</p>
          <p>“What part of the Bible were you reading,
William?”</p>
          <p>“Me read how de man upon de cross spoke to
Christ, and Christ spoke to him. Now dat man's
prayer just do for me: ‘Lord, remember me.’
Lord, remember poor negro sinner: dis is my
prayer every morning, and sometime at nigh
too; when we cannot tink of many words, den
me say de same again, Lord, remember poor
negro sinner.”</p>
          <p>“And be assured, William, the Lord hears that
<pb id="rich162" n="162"/>
prayer. He pardoned and accepted the thief upon
the cross, and he will not reject you; he will in no
wise cast out any that come to him.”</p>
          <p>“No, Sir, I believe it; but dere is so much sin
in my heart, it makes me afraid and sorry. Massa,
do you see dese limpets,<ref targOrder="U" id="ref5" n="5" rend="sc" target="note5">*</ref>
<note id="note5" n="5" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref5"><p>* A kind of shell-fish, which abound in the place
where we were, and which stick to the rocks with
exceedingly great force.</p></note> how fast dey stick to de
rocks here? Just so, sin stick fast to my heart.”</p>
          <p>“It may be so, William: but take another comparison:
do you cleave to Jesus Christ by faith in
his death and righteousness, as those limpets cleave
to the rock, and neither seas nor storms shall separate
you from his love.”</p>
          <p>“Dat is just what me want.”</p>
          <p>“Tell me, William, is not that very sin which
you speak of, a burden to you? You do not love
it; you would be glad to obtain strength against it,
and to be freed from it; would you not?”</p>
          <p>“O yes; me give all dis world, if me had it, to
be without sin.”</p>
          <p>“Come then, and welcome, to Jesus Christ,
my brother; his blood cleanseth from all sin. He
gave himself as a ransom for sinners. ‘He hath
<pb id="rich163" n="163"/>
borne our griefs and carried our sorrows. He
was wounded for our transgressions; he was
bruised for our iniquities; the chastisement of
our peace was upon him, and with his stripes we
are healed. The Lord hath laid on him the iniquity
of us all.’ ‘Come, freely come to Jesus,
the Saviour of sinners.”</p>
          <p>“Yes, Massa,” said the poor fellow, weeping,
“me will come: but me come very slow; very
slow, Massa: me want to run, me want to fly. Jesus
is very goot to poor Negro, to send you to tell
him all dis.”</p>
          <p>“But this is not the first time you have heard
these truths?”</p>
          <p>“No, Sir, dey have been comfort to my soul
many times since me hear goot minister preach
in America, as me tell you last week at your
house.”</p>
          <p>“Well, now I hope, William, that since God
has been so graciously pleased to open your eyes,
and affect your mind with such a great sense of
his goodness, in giving his Son to die for your
sake; I hope that you do your endeavour to keep
his commandments; I hope you strive to behave
well to your master and mistress, and fellow-servants.
He that is a Christian inwardly, will be a
<pb id="rich164" n="164"/>
Christian outwardly; he that truly and savingly
believes in Christ, will show his faith by his works,
as the apostle says. Is it not so, William?”</p>
          <p>“Yes, Sir, me want to do so. Me want to be
faithful. Me sorry to tink how bat servant me
was before de goot tings of Jesus Christ come to
my heart. Me wish to do well to my Massa, when
he see me and when he not see me; for me know
God always see me. Me know, dat if me sin
against mine own Massa, me sin against God, and
God be very angry with me. Beside, how can
me love Christ, if me do not what Christ tell me?
Me love my fellow-servants, dough, as I tell you
before, dey do not much love me, and I pray God
to bless dem. And when dey say bat tings, and
try to make me angry, den me tink, if Jesus
Christ were in poor Negro's place, he would not
revile and answer again with bat words and temper,
but he say little, and pray much. And so
den me say noting at all, but pray God to forgive
dem.”</p>
          <p>The more I conversed with this African convert,
the more satisfactory were the evidences of his mind
being spiritually enlightened, and his
heart effectually wrought upon by the grace of God.</p>
          <pb id="rich165" n="165"/>
          <p>The circumstances of the place in which we met
together, contributed much to the interesting
effect which the conversation produced on my
mind. The little cove or bay was beautiful in the
extreme. The air was calm and serene. The
sun shone, but we were sheltered from its rays by
the cliffs. One of these was stupendously lofty
and large. It was white as snow: its summit hung
directly over our heads. The sea-fowl were flying
around it. Its whiteness was occasionally
chequered with dark green masses of samphire,
which grew there. On the other side, and behind
us, was a more gradual declivity of many-coloured
earths, interspersed with green patches of
grass and bushes, and little streams of water trickling
down the bank, and mingling with the sea at
the bottom. At our feet the waves were advancing
over shelves of rocks covered with a great variety
of sea-weeds, which swam in little fragments
and displayed much beauty and elegance of form
as they were successively thrown upon the sand.</p>
          <p>Ships of war and commerce were seen at different
distances. Fisherman were plying their
trade in boats nearer to the shore. The noise of
the flowing tide, combined with the voices of the
sea-gulls over our heads, and now and then a distant
<pb id="rich166" n="166"/>
guns fired from the ships as they passed along,
added much to the peculiar sensations to which
the scene gave birth. Occasionally the striking of
oars upon the waves, accompanied by the boatman's
song, met the ear. The sheep aloft upon the
down sometimes mingled their bleatings with the
other sounds. Thus all nature seemed to unite
in impressing an attentive observer's heart with
affecting thoughts.</p>
          <p>I remained for a considerable time in conversation
with the Negro, finding that his master was
gone from home for the day, and had given him
liberty for some hours. I spoke to him on the
nature, duty, and privilege of Christian baptism;
pointed out to him, from a prayer-book which I
had with me, the clear and scriptural principles
of our own church upon that head, and found that
he was very desirous of conforming to them. He
appeared to me to be well qualified for receiving
that sacramental pledge of his Redeemer's love;
and I rejoiced in the prospect of beholding him
no longer a “stranger and foreigner, but a
fellow-citizen with the saints, and of the household of
God.”</p>
          <p>“God,” said I to him, “has promised ‘to sprinkle
many nations,’ not only with the waters of baptism,
<pb id="rich167" n="167"/>
but also with the dews of his heavenly grace.
He says, he will not only ‘pour water on him
that is thirsty,’ but ‘I will pour my spirit upon
thy seed, and my blessings upon thine offspring.’”</p>
          <p>“Yes, Massa,” said he, “he can make me to
be clean in heart, and of a right spirit; he can
purge me with hyssop, and I shall be clean: he
can wash me, and I shall be whiter dan snow.”</p>
          <p>“May God give you these blessings, and confirm
you in every good gift!”</p>
          <p>I was much pleased with the affectionate manner
in which he spoke of his parents, from whom
he had been stolen in his childhood; and his
wishes that God might direct them by some means
to the knowledge of a Saviour.</p>
          <p>“Who knows,” I said, “but some of these ships
may be carrying a missionary to the country
where they live, to declare the good news of salvation
to your countrymen, and to your own dear
parents in particular, if they are yet alive?”</p>
          <p>“O! my dear fader and moder: my dear gracious
Saviour,” exclaimed he, leaping from the
ground as he spoke, “if dou wilt but save deir
souls, and tell dem what dou hast done for
sinners—but—”</p>
          <p>He stopped, and seemed much affected, “My
<pb id="rich168" n="168"/>
friend,” said I, “I will now pray with you for
your own soul, and for those of your parents
also.”</p>
          <p>“Do, Massa, dat is very goot and kind; do pray
for poor negro souls here and every where.”</p>
          <p>This was a new and solemn “house of prayer.”
The sea-sand was our floor, the heavens were our
roof: the cliffs, the rocks, the hills, and the waves,
formed the walls of our chamber. It was not indeed
a “place where prayer was wont to be made;”
but for this once it became a hallowed spot; it
will, by me, ever be remembered as such. The
presence of God was there.—I prayed.—The Negro
wept.—His heart was full. I felt with him,
and could not but weep likewise.</p>
          <p>The last day will show whether our tears were
not the tears of sincerity and Christian love.</p>
          <p>It was time for my return; I leaned upon his
arm as we ascended the step cliff in my way
back to my house, which I had left at the top of
the hill. Humility and thankfulness were marked
in his countenance. I leaned upon his arm
with the feelings of a <hi rend="italics">brother</hi>. It was a relationship
I was happy to own.—I took him by the hand
at parting, appointed one more interview previous
<pb id="rich169" n="169"/>
to the day of baptizing him, and bid him farewell
for the present.</p>
          <p>“God bless you, my dear massa.”</p>
          <p>“And you, my fellow Christian, for ever and
ever.”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="part">
          <pb id="rich170" n="170"/>
          <head>PART III.</head>
          <p>The interesting and affecting conversation
which I had with the Negro servant, produced a
sensation not easy to be expressed. As I returned
home, I was led into meditation on the singular
clearness and beauty of those evidence of
faith and conversion of heart to God, which I had
just seen and heard. How plainly, I thought, it
appears, that salvation is “freely by grace through
faith; and that not of ourselves; it is the gift of
God; not of works, lest any man should boast.”
What but the Holy Spirit, who is the author and
giver of the life of grace, could have wrought such
a change from the once dark, perverse, and ignorant
heathen, to this now convinced, enlightened,
humble, and believing Christian? How manifestly
is the uncontrolled sovereignty of the divine will
exercised in the calling and translating of sinners
from darkness to light! what a lesson may the nominal
Christian of a civilized country sometimes
learn from the simple, sincere religion of a converted
heathen!</p>
          <p>I afterwards made particular inquiry into this
<pb id="rich171" n="171"/>
young man's domestic and general deportment.
Every thing I heard was satisfactory; nor could I
entertain a doubt respecting the consistency of his
conduct and character. I had some further conversations
with him, in the course of which I pursued
such a plan of scriptural instruction and examination,
as I conceived to be the most suitable
to this progressive state of mind. He improved
much in reading, carried his Bible constantly with
him, and took every opportunity, which his duty
to his master's service would allow, for perusing it.
I have frequently had occasion to observe, that
amongst the truly religious poor, who have not
had the advantage of being taught to read in early
youth, a concern about the soul, and a desire to
know the word of God, have proved effectual motives
for their learning to read with great ease and
advantage to themselves and others. It was
strikingly so in the present case.</p>
          <p>I had, for a considerable time, been accustomed
to meet some well-disposed persons once a week,
in a cottage at no great distance from the house
where he lived, for the purpose of religious conversation
and ministerial instruction. Having found
these occasions remarkably useful and interesting,
I thought it would be very desirable to take
<pb id="rich172" n="172"/>
the Negro there, in order that they might all become
witnesses to the simplicity and sincerity of
real Christianity, as exhibited in the character of
this promising young convert. I hoped it might
prove an eminent mean of grace to excite and
quicken the spirit of prayer and praise amongst
some of my parishioners, over whose spiritual
progress I was anxiously watching.</p>
          <p>I accordingly obtained his master's leave that he
should attend me to one of my cottage assemblies.
His master, who was thoroughly convinced of the
extraordinary change in conduct and disposition
which religion had produced in his servant, was
pleased with my attention to him, and always
spoke well of his behaviour.</p>
          <p>I set out on the day appointed for the interview.
The cottage at which we usually assembled
was near four miles distant from my own residence:
the road lay along the foot of the hill
mentioned in my last account of the Negro, from
the summit of which so luxuriant a prospect was
seen. On my right hand the steep acclivity of the
hill intercepted all prospect, except that of numerous
sheep feeding on its rich and plentiful produce.
Here and there the nearly perpendicular
side of a chalk-pit varied the surface of the hill,
<pb id="rich173" n="173"/>
contrasting a dazzling white to the sober green
of the surrounding bank.</p>
          <p>On the left hand, at the distance of near half a
mile, the tide flowed from the sea into a lake or
haven of considerable length and breadth. At one
end of it, several fishing and pilot vessels lay at anchor:
at the other appeared the parish church
amongst the adjoining woods and fields. The
bells were ringing; a gently swelling sound was
brought along the surface of the water, and an echo
returned from a prominent part of the hill, beneath
which I was riding. The whole scene was
delightful.</p>
          <p>I passed some rural and beautifully situated cottages,
which seemed to be formed as fit residences
for peace and tranquillity; each was surrounded
by a garden, and each had a little orchard or field
adjacent, while the husbandman's cow enjoyed
her own pasture, and at the same time prepared
rich provision for her owner's family. Such was
the wise and considerate allotment which the
landlords and farmers had <hi rend="italics">here</hi> made for the labouring
poor. The wholesome vegetable, the medicinal
herb, and the sweet-scented flower,
intermingled as they grew round these little
dwellings; and reminded me, as I looked upon
<pb id="rich174" n="174"/>
them, a comfortable lot is that of the industrious
poor, whose heart have learned the lesson
of gratitude, in the school of heavenly wisdom!
For them, as mercifully as for their richest neighbour,
the sun shines, the rain descends, the earth
brings forth her increase, the flower blossoms, the
birds sing; their wants are few, and contentment
makes them less. How great the blessing of being
poor in this world, but rich in faith, and a chosen
inheritance in a better!</p>
          <p>I knew that this was the character of some,
whose humble, but neat and cleanly cottages I
passed. A few such features in a prospect render
it most lovely. Peace be to their memory, both
as pilgrims and strangers here; and as ransomed
souls, whom I hope to meet in glory hereafter!</p>
          <p>The house to which I was travelling was situated
at the corner of an oak wood, which screened
it both from the burning heat of summer suns, and
the heavy blasts of winter south-west storms. As
I approached it, I saw my friend the Negro sitting
under a tree, and waiting my arrival. He held in
his hand a little tract which I had given him: his
Bible lay on the ground. He rose with much
cheerfulness, saying, “Ah! Massa, me very glad to
see you: me tink you long time coming.”</p>
          <pb id="rich175" n="175"/>
          <p>“William, I hope you are well. I am going
to take you with me to a few of my friends, who, I
trust, are truly sincere in their religious pursuits.
We meet every Wednesday evening for conversation
about the things that belong to our everlasting
peace, and I am sure you will be a welcome visitor.”</p>
          <p>“Massa, me not goot enough to be with such
goot people. Me great sinner. Dey be goot
Christian.”</p>
          <p>“If you were to ask them, William, they would
each tell you they were worse than others. Many
of them were once, and that not very long
ago, living in an openly sinful manner, ignorant of
God, and the enemies of Jesus Christ by thought and
deed. But divine grace stopped them in
their wicked course, and subdued their hearts to
the love and obedience of him and his Gospel.
You will only meet a company of poor fellow-sinners,
who love to speak and sing the praises of
redeeming love: and I am sure, William, that is a
song in which you will be willing to join them.”</p>
          <p>“O! yes, Sir dat song just do for poor
Negro.”</p>
          <p>By this time we had arrived at the cottage garden
gate. Several well-known faces appeared in
and near the house, and the smile of affection
<pb id="jwl176" n="176"/>
welcomed us as we entered. It was known that the
Negro was to visit the little company this evening,
and satisfaction beamed in every countenance
as I took him by the hand and introduced
him among them, saying, “I have brought a brother
from Africa to see you, my friends. Bid him
welcome in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ.”</p>
          <p>“Sir,” said an humble and pious labourer,
whose heart and tongue always overflowed with
Christian kindness, “we are at all times glad to
see our minister, but especially so to-day,
with such a companion as you have brought with
you. We have heard how merciful the Lord has
been to him. Give me your hand, good friend
(turning to the Negro). God be with you here and
every where: and blessed be his holy name for
calling sinners, as I hope he has done you and me,
to love and serve him for his mercy's sake.”</p>
          <p>Each one greeted him as he came into the
house, and addressed him in very kind and
impressive language.</p>
          <p>“Massa,” said he, “me not know what to say
to all dese goot friends: me tink dis look a little
like heaven upon earth.”</p>
          <p>He then, with tears in his eyes, which almost,
before he spoke, brought responsive drops into
<pb id="rich177" n="177"/>
those of many present, said, “Goot friends and
bredren in Christ Jesus, God bless you all, and
bring you to heaven at de last.”</p>
          <p>It was my stated custom, when I met to converse
with those cottagers, to begin with prayer,
and reading some portion of the scriptures.</p>
          <p>When this was ended, I told the people present,
that the providence of God had placed this young
man for a time under my ministry; and believing him to
be very sincere in his religious profession, I had
resolved on baptizing him agreeably to his own wishes.
I added, that I had now brought him with me
to join in Christian conversation with us; for, as in
old times, they that feared the Lord spake often
one to another, in testimony that they thought upon
his name, (Mal. iii. 16.) so I hoped we were
fulfilling a Christian and brotherly duty in thus
assembling for mutual edification.</p>
          <p>Addressing myself to the Negro, I said, “William,
tell me who made you?”</p>
          <p>“God, de goot Fader.”</p>
          <p>“Who redeemed you?”</p>
          <p>“Jesus, his dear son, who died for me.”</p>
          <p>“Who sanctified you?”</p>
          <p>“De Holy Ghost, who teach me to know de
goot Fader, and his dear Son Jesus.”</p>
          <pb id="rich178" n="178"/>
          <p>“What was your state by nature?”</p>
          <p>“Me wicked sinner, me know noting but sin,
me do noting but sin, my soul more black dan my
body.”</p>
          <p>“Has any change taken place in you since
then?”</p>
          <p>“Me hope so, Massa, but me sometime afraid
no.”</p>
          <p>“If you are changed, who changed you?”</p>
          <p>“God de goot Fader; Jesus his dear Son; and
God de holy spirit.”</p>
          <p>“How was any change brought about in you?”</p>
          <p>“God make me a slave, when me was young
little boy.”</p>
          <p>“How, William, would you say, God made you
a slave?”</p>
          <p>“No, Massa, no: me mean, God let me be made
slave by white men, to do me goot.”</p>
          <p>“How to do you good?”</p>
          <p>“He take me from de land of darkness, and
bring me to de land of light.”</p>
          <p>“Which do you call the land of light; the
West India Islands?”</p>
          <p>“No, Massa, dey be de land of providence,
but America be de land of light to me, for dere
me first hear goot minister preach. And now dis
<pb id="rich179" n="179"/>
place where I am now, is de land of more light
for here you teach me more and more and more
how goot Jesus to sinners.”</p>
          <p>“What does the blood of Christ do?”</p>
          <p>“It cleanse from all sins: and so me hope from
my sin.”</p>
          <p>“Are then all men cleansed from sin by his
blood?”</p>
          <p>“O no, Massa.”</p>
          <p>“Who are cleansed and saved?”</p>
          <p>“Dose dat have faith in him.”</p>
          <p>“Can you prove that out of the Bible?”</p>
          <p>“Yes, Sir: ‘He dat believeth on de Son, hath
everlasting life; and he dat believeth not de Son,
shall not see life, but de wrath of God abideth on
him.” (John, iii. 36.)</p>
          <p>“What is it to have faith?”</p>
          <p>“Me suppose dat it is to tink much about Jesus
Christ, to love him much, to believe all he
says to be true, to pray to him very much; and
when me feel very weak and very sinful, to tink
dat he is very strong and very goot, and all dat
for my sake.”</p>
          <p>“And have you such a faith as you describe?</p>
          <p>“O Massa! me tink sometime me have no faith
at all.”</p>
          <pb id="rich180" n="180"/>
          <p>“Why so, William?”</p>
          <p>“When we want to tink about Jesus Christ,
my mind run about after oder tings: when me
want to love him, my heart seem quite cold;
when me want to believe all to be true what he
says to sinners, me den tink it is not true for me:
when me want to pray, de devil put bat, very bat
toughts into me, and me never tank Christ enough.
Now all dis make me sometime afraid I have no
faith.”</p>
          <p>I observed a very earnest glow of attention and
fellow-feeling in some countenances present, as
he spoke these words. I then said,</p>
          <p>“I think, William, I can prove that you have
faith, notwithstanding your fears to the contrary.
Answer me a few more questions.</p>
          <p>“Did you begin to think yourself a great sinner,
and to feel the want of a Saviour, of your
own self, and by your own thought and doing?”</p>
          <p>“O! no; it came to me, when me tink noting
about it, and seek noting about it.”</p>
          <p>“Who sent the good minister in America to
awaken your soul by his preaching?”</p>
          <p>“God, very certainly.”</p>
          <p>“Who then began the work of serious thought
in your mind?”</p>
          <pb id="rich181" n="181"/>
          <p>“De goot God; me could not do it of myself
me sure of dat.”</p>
          <p>“Do you not think that Jesus Christ and his
salvation is the one thing most needful and most
desirable?”</p>
          <p>“O! yes, me quite sure of dat.”</p>
          <p>“Do you not believe that he is able to save
you?”</p>
          <p>“Yes, he is able to save to de uttermost.”</p>
          <p>“Do you think he is not willing to save you?</p>
          <p>“Me dare not say dat. He so goot, so merciful,
so kind, to say, he will in no wise cast out any
dat come to him.”</p>
          <p>“Do you wish, and desire, and strive to keep
his commandments?”</p>
          <p>“Yes, Massa, because me love him, and dat
make me want to do as he say.”</p>
          <p>“Are you willing to suffer for his sake, if God
should call you to do so?”</p>
          <p>“Me do tink me could die for de love of him:
he not tink it too much to die for wicked sinner;
why should wicked sinner tink it much to die for. 
so goot and righteous a Saviour?”</p>
          <p>“I think and hope I may say to you, William,
thy faith hath made thee whole.”</p>
          <p>Thus ended my examination for the present.
<pb id="rich182" n="182"/>
The other friends who were in the house listened
with the most affectionate anxiety to all that
passed. One of them observed, not without evident
emotion,</p>
          <p>“I see, Sir, that though some men are white
and some are black, true Christianity is all of one
colour. My own heart has gone with this good
man every word he has spoken.”</p>
          <p>“And so has mine” gently re-echoed from
every part of the room.</p>
          <p>After some time had passed in more general conversation
on the subject of the Negro's history,
I said, “Let us now praise God for the rich and
unspeakable gift of his grace, and sing the hymn
of ‘redeeming love’:”
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>Now begin the heavenly theme</l><l>Sing aloud in Jesu's name, &amp;c.</l></lg></q>
which was accordingly done. Whatever might
be the merit of their natural voices, it was evident
there was spiritual melody in all their hearts.</p>
          <p>The Negro was not much used to our way
of singing, yet joined with great earnestness and
affection, that showed how truly he felt what he
uttered. When the fifth verse ended,
<pb id="rich183" n="183"/>
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>Nothing brought him from above,</l><l>Nothing but redeeming love;</l></lg></q>
he repeated the words, almost unconscious where
he was,</p>
          <p>“No, noting, noting but redeeming love, bring
him down to poor William, noting but redeeming
love.”</p>
          <p>The following verses were added, and sung by
way of conclusion:—</p>
          <lg type="verse">
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>See, a stranger comes to view;</l>
              <l>Though he's black,<ref targOrder="U" id="ref6" n="6" rend="sc" target="note6">*</ref> he's comely too;<note id="note6" n="6" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref6"><p>* Song of Solomon, i. 5.</p></note></l>
              <l>Comes to join the choirs above,</l>
              <l>Singing of redeeming love.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Welcome, Negro, welcome here,</l>
              <l>Banish doubt, and banish fear;</l>
              <l>You, who Christ's salvation prove,</l>
              <l>Praise and bless redeeming love.</l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
          <p>I concluded with some remarks on the nature
of salvation by grace, exhorting all present to press
forward in the heavenly journey. It was an evening,
the circumstance of which, had they never
been recorded on earth, were yet doubtless registered
in the book of remembrance above.</p>
          <pb id="rich184" n="184"/>
          <p>I then fixed the day for the baptism of the
Negro, and so took leave of my little affectionate
circle.</p>
          <p>The moon shone bright as I returned home, and
was beautifully reflected from the waters of the
lake: harmony and repose characterized the scene.
I had just been uniting in the praises of the God
of grace and providence; and now the God of nature
demanded a fresh tribute of thanksgiving for
the beauties and comforts of creation: as David
sang, “When I consider thy heavens the work of
thy fingers, the moon and the stars which thou
hast ordained; what is man that thou art mindful
of him, or the son of man that thou visitest him?”</p>
          <p>In a few days the Negro was baptized; and
not long after he went on a voyage with his master.</p>
          <p>Since that time I have not been able to bear
any tidings of him: whether he yet wander as a
pilgrim in this lower world, or whether he has
joined the heavenly choir in the song of “redeeming
love” in glory, I know not. This I do know,
he was a monument to the Lord's praise. He bore
the impression of the Saviour's image on his heart,
and exhibited the marks of divine grace in his life
<pb id="rich185" n="185"/>
and conversation, with singular simplicity and
unfeigned sincerity.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <trailer>Give to God the glory.</trailer>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div1 type="end section">
        <argument>
          <p>My interviews with the Negro suggested the
following lines, which are here subjoined, under
the title of</p>
        </argument>
        <lg type="verse">
          <head>The Negro's Prayer</head>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Jesus, who mak'st the meanest soul</l>
            <l>An object of thy care,</l>
            <l>Attend to what my heart would speak—</l>
            <l>Hear a poor Negro's prayer.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>For thou, when bleeding on the cross,</l>
            <l>My sins and griefs didst bear;</l>
            <l>Wherefore, my Lord, thou'lt not refuse</l>
            <l>To hear the Negro's prayer.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>I am a helpless Negro boy,</l>
            <l>That wander'd on the shore:</l>
            <l>Thieves took me from my parents' arms—</l>
            <l>They saw their child no more.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>And yet the lot which seem'd so hard,</l>
            <l>God's faithfulness did prove;</l>
            <l>For I was carried far from home</l>
            <l>To learn a Saviour's love.</l>
          </lg>
          <pb id="rich186" n="186"/>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Poor and despised though I was,</l>
            <l>Thine arm, O God! was nigh;</l>
            <l>And when thy mercy first I knew,</l>
            <l>Sure none so glad as I.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>In ign'rance long my soul and dwelt,</l>
            <l>A rebel bold I'd been:</l>
            <l>But thy kindness, O my God!</l>
            <l>Sav'd me from all my sin.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Mine was a wretched state, expos'd</l>
            <l>To men and angels' view;</l>
            <l>A slave to man, a slave to sin,</l>
            <l>A slave to Satan too.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>But if thy Son hath made me free,</l>
            <l>Then am I free indeed;</l>
            <l>From powers of darkness, sin, and hell,</l>
            <l>Thy love my soul has freed.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Lord, send thy Word to that far land,</l>
            <l>Where none but Negroes live:</l>
            <l>Teach them the way, the truth, the life,</l>
            <l>Which thou alone canst give.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>O! that my father, mother dear,</l>
            <l>Might there thy mercy see;</l>
            <l>Tell them what Christ has done for them,</l>
            <l>What Christ has done for me.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Whose God is like the Christian God?</l>
            <l>Who can with him compare?</l>
            <pb id="rich187" n="187"/>
            <l>He hath compassion on my soul,</l>
            <l>And hears a Negro's prayer.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Lord Jesus, thou hast shed thy blood</l>
            <l>For thousands such as me;</l>
            <l>Though some despise poor Negro slave,</l>
            <l>I'm not depis'd by thee.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>This is my heart's first wish below,</l>
            <l>To prove thy constant care:</l>
            <l>Keep me from sin and danger, Lord,</l>
            <l>And hear a Negro's prayer.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>In heaven the land of glory lies:</l>
            <l>If I should enter there,</l>
            <l>I'll tell the saints and angels too,</l>
            <l>Thou heard'st a Negro's prayer.</l>
          </lg>
        </lg>
      </div1>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI.2>