<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % external-entities SYSTEM "./extEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY % internal-entities SYSTEM "./intEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY boentp SYSTEM "boentp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>Anecdotes and Memoirs of William Boen, a Coloured Man, Who
Lived and Died Near Mount Holly, New Jersey. </emph><emph>To which is
Added, <hi rend="italics">The Testimony of Friends of Mount Holly Monthly 
Meeting Concerning Him</hi>:</emph> Electronic Edition.</title>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Tom Horan</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Image scanned by</resp>
          <name>Tom Horan</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Lee Ann Morawski and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>2000</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca.     40K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>2000.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and 
personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="title page"> Anecdotes and Memoirs of William Boen, a Coloured Man, Who
 Lived and Died Near Mount Holly, New Jersey. To which is Added, The Testimony of 
Friends of Mount Holly Monthly Meeting Concerning Him</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>   18   p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
            <publisher>John Richards</publisher>
            <date>1834</date>
            <authority/>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="yes">Call number    Bd. Pam. 326.92 Z99 ( Rare Book, Manuscript, and
 Special Collections Library, Duke University Libraries)</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Boen, William, 1735-1824.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- New Jersey -- Mount Holly --
Religion.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- New Jersey -- Mount Holly --
Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- New Jersey -- Mount Holly -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Religious life -- New Jersey -- Mount Holly.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- New Jersey -- Mount Holly -- History -- 18th
century.</item>
            <item>Society of Friends -- New Jersey -- Mount Holly.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2000-09-15, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2000-01-14, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2000-01-09, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Lee Ann Morawski</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-12-29, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Tom Horan</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="title page">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="boentp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">ANECDOTES AND MEMOIRS<lb/> OF <lb/>WILLIAM BOEN,<lb/> A COLORED MAN,<lb/>
WHO LIVED AND DIED NEAR MOUNT HOLLY, NEW JERSEY.</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="subtitle">TO WHICH IS ADDED,<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">The Testimony of Friends of Mount Holly<lb/>
monthly meeting concerning him.</hi></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <docImprint><pubPlace>Philadelphia:</pubPlace>
<publisher>PRINTED BY JOHN RICHARDS,</publisher><pubPlace>No. 129 North Third Street.</pubPlace><docDate>1834.</docDate></docImprint>
      </titlePage>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb id="boen3" n="3"/>
      <div1 type="text">
        <head>MEMOIRS AND ANECDOTES OF <lb/>WILLIAM BOEN</head>
        <p>William Boen was a coloured man, who resided
near Mount Holly, New Jersey. Like many of his
brethren of the African race, in those days, he was
from his birth held as a slave. But though poor and
ignorant, in his early days, he was cared for, as all
others are, by the universal Parent of the human
family. He became a pious, sober, temperate, honest,
and industrious man; and by this means, he obtained
the friendship, esteem, and respect of all classes
of his fellow-men, and the approbation and peace of
his heavenly Father.</p>
        <p>His industry, temperance, and cleanliness, no
doubt, contributed much to his health and comfort;
so that he lived to be a very old man, with having
but little sickness through the course of his life. His
character being so remarkable for sobriety, honesty,
and peace—that it  induced some younger people to
inquire by what means he had arrived to such a state,
and attained such a standing in the neighbourhood
where he lived. Ever willing to instruct, counsel,
and admonish the youth, he could relate his own
experience of the work of grace in his heart, which
led him into such uprightness of life and conduct.
For his memory did not appear to be much impaired
by reason of old age.</p>
        <p>To a friend who visited him in the eighty-sixth
year of his age, he gave the following account of his
<pb id="boen4" n="4"/>
early life, and religious experience. On being asked,
whether he could remember in what way, and by
what means, he was first brought to mind and follow
<hi rend="italics">that,</hi> which had been his guide and rule of faith
and life, and which had led and preserved him so
safely along through time? William answered as
follows: “Oh! yes; that I can, right well. In the
time of the old French war, my master (for I was a
poor black boy, a slave) my master sent me to chop
wood, on a hill-side, out of sight of any house; and
there was a great forest of woods below me; and he
told me to cut down all the trees on that hill-side.
When I went home, in the evenings, I often heard
them talking about the Indians killing and scalping
people: and sometimes, some of my neighbours would
come in, and they and my master's family talked of
the Indians killing such and such,—nearer and nearer
to us. And so, from time to time, I would hear
them tell of the Indians killing, and scalping people,
nearer and nearer: so that I began to think, like enough,
by and by, they would kill me. And I
thought more and more about it; and again would
hear tell of their coming still nearer. At length, I
thought, sure enough they will get so near, that they
will hear the sound of my axe, and will come and
kill me. Here is a great forest of woods below me,
and no house in sight:—surely, I have not long to
live. I expected every day would be my last;—that
they would soon kill me, a poor black boy, here all
alone.”</p>
        <p>“A thought then came into my mind, whether I
was fit to die. It was showed me, and I saw plain 
enough, that I was not fit to die. Then it troubled
me very much, that I was not fit to die; and I felt
<pb id="boen5" n="5"/>
very desirous,—very anxious that I might be made
fit to die. So I stood still, in great amazement; and
it seemed as if a flaming sword passed through me.
And when it passed over, and I recollected myself
(for I stood so, some time) it was showed me how
I should be made fit to die: and I was willing to do
any thing, so I might be made fit to die.”</p>
        <p>“Thus, I was brought to mind and follow <hi rend="italics">that,</hi>
that has been the guide and rule of my life,—<hi rend="italics">that
within me,</hi> that inclined me to good, and showed
and condemned evil. Now I considered I had
a new master—I had two masters; and it was showed me
(in my mind) by my new Master, a certain tree
on the hill-side, that I must not cut down. I knowed
the tree well enough. I had not come to it yet.
But I did not know what I <hi rend="italics">should</hi> do; for my old
master had told me to cut all the trees down, on that
hill-side. My new master forbids me to cut a certain
one. So I thought a good deal about it. I cut
on; and by and by I came to the tree. I cut on by
it, and let it stand. But I expected, every day, my
old master would come, and see that tree standing,
and say, ‘What did thee leave that tree standing
for? Did I not tell thee to cut all the trees down, as
thee went? Go, cut that tree down.’ Then, I <sic corr="didn't">did'nt</sic>
know what I <hi rend="italics">should</hi> do. But he never said any
thing to me about it. I cut on, and got some distance
by it; and one day my old master brought out
his axe, and cut the tree down himself; and never
said, William, why didn't thee cut that tree down?
never said anything to me about it. Then I thought,
surely my new Master will make way for me, and
take care of me, if I love him, and mind him, and
am attentive to this my guide, and rule of life. And
<pb id="boen6" n="6"/>
this seemed an evidence and proof of it, and strengthened
me much in love, and confidence in my Guide.”</p>
        <p>After the respectable and goodly old man, had
given this interesting account of the way and
manner in which he was brought to follow the guide
of his life, the following question was put to him:
“Well, William, has thee, from that time, till now,
been so careful and attentive to my guide, as never
to say or do amiss?” To which he replied, “Oh!
no: I have missed it—I have several times missed
it.” He was then asked, “Well, William, in that
case, how <hi rend="italics">did</hi> thee get along?” He answered, “Oh!
when I missed it,—when I found I had said, or done
wrong, I felt very sorry. I tried to be more careful,
for time to come;—never to do so any more: and I
believe I was forgiven.”</p>
        <p>Another inquiry was made of William, how he
and his old master got along together, after his
change. He said, “Very well. Some time afterwards,
one of his neighbours said to me, one day,
‘William, thy master talks of setting thee free.’ I
<sic corr="didn't">did'nt</sic> think much about it—<sic corr="didn't">did'nt</sic> expect there was
any thing in it; though I heard others say he talked
of setting me free;—till, after some time, as my
master was walking with me, going to my work, he
said, ‘William, <sic>would'nt</sic> thee like to be free?’ I
<sic corr="didn't">did'nt</sic> say any thing to it. I thought he might know
I should like to be free. I <sic corr="didn't">did'nt</sic> make him any
answer about it, but then I thought there was
something in it. So after awhile, sure enough, he did
set me free.”</p>
        <p>There is no doubt his old master observed a great
change in him; for his guide taught him to be dutiful,
industrious and diligent in his business, careful
<pb id="boen7" n="7"/>
in his words and actions, and sober, steady, and
exemplary in all he said, and in all his conduct.</p>
        <p>William Boen's guide, and rule of life and conduct,
his <hi rend="italics">new Master,</hi> as he called him, that did so
much for him, and raised him from the state of a
poor slave, to be a free man, in good esteem—thro'
habits of temperance, sobriety, honest industry and
integrity,— whereby he was enabled to become the
respectable head of a family, and to acquire a house,
and property of his own, sufficient for the comfortable
accommodation of himself and his family;—and who
forsook him not when he became old, and grey-headed;
—his new Master was the same Light that appears
unto all; and it would guide every one in the
right way, as it did him, if they would take it for
their Master, and mind and obey it, as he did. It
was the guide of his youth,—because his Lord and
Master,—preserved him from evil,—and conducted
him safely through the trials of life, to a good old age.</p>
        <p>William Boen's new Master was, and is the same
thing that the apostle Paul, in his Epistle to Titus,
bears testimony to, in these words; “the grace of
God, that bringeth salvation, hath appeared to all
men;—teaching us, that, denying all ungodliness
and worldly lusts, we should live soberly, righteously,
and godly in the present world.” Now, surely,
if we don't take it for our master, and mind its
teachings, we cannot <hi rend="italics">know</hi> it to bring our salvation,
or <hi rend="italics">save us</hi> from <hi rend="italics">all ungodliness</hi> and <hi rend="italics">worldly lusts,</hi>
as he did, and as all do, that are obedient to this
grace of God, <hi rend="italics">the Light of Christ, within.</hi></p>
        <p>In William Boen's simple account of the way and
means, by which he was showed how he should be
<pb id="boen8" n="8"/>
made fit to die;—that is, by minding and following
<hi rend="italics">that within</hi> him, which inclined him to good, and
that showed and condemned him for evil,—the goodness,
mercy, and condescending care of the Almighty
Father, are strikingly manifest. How graciously he
suits his dispensations to the weak and ignorant
states of his children, who sincerely seek him, and
inquire what they shall do to be saved! When William
Boen thought of death, something showed him
he was not fit to die. He “saw it plain enough,“ and
was troubled. In his anxiety to be prepared to die,
he became still and quiet—and then he felt condemnation,
as a flaming sword, pass through him. When
this had its effect to bring him to a state of humility
and watchfulness, the Divine Light in his soul showed
him the way in which he should walk, in order to
become fit to die. He became willing to do any
thing required of him: so, to prove his obedience,
it was showed him, by his new Master, that he must
leave a certain tree standing, where he was felling
timber. He began to reason upon consequences,
but resolved to obey his new Master, in preference
to his old one. It was sufficient to test his faith and
love; and though a simple circumstance, it was probably
of great use to him ever after; as by it he was
taught to be faithful in little things, and thus became
ruler over more.</p>
        <p>It may be useful to survivors, who, like William,
are desirous so to live, as that they may become fit
to die,—to bring into view some anecdotes of his
life, that show the principles by which his mind and
conduct were regulated.</p>
        <p>In his conversation among men, he was very careful
to keep to the plain language,—the language of
<pb id="boen9" n="9"/>
truth and sincerity—yet, through the help of his
guide, he detected himself in deviation from it, in
the following circumstances. A wealthy neighbour,
a white man, frequently availed himself of William's
obliging dispositions, by using his grindstone, instead
of procuring one for himself. On an occasion of this
kind, his neighbour told him he was obliged to him
for the use of his grindstone: to which, William
returned the usual compliment of saying he was
welcome. After the man was gone, William became
uneasy in his mind, with his reply, as being insincere.
He therefore went to his neighbour, and made
an acknowledgment, that although he had told him
he was welcome, yet it was only in conformity with
custom, and was not the case; for he thought his neighbour
was better able to keep a grindstone of
his own, than he was.</p>
        <p>How many customary compliments, by-words,
and common expressions, would be dispensed with,
as idle words, for which we must give an account in
the day of judgment,—if a strict regard to truth and
sincerity, were the ruling principle or guide of all
our words and actions!</p>
        <p>William Boen appears to have been as strictly
careful in his adherence to the principles of justice,
and the rights of property, as he was in regard to
truth and sincerity in his communications. Being
employed, with several others, to mow the meadows
attached to the place called Breezy Ridge, on
Lomberton creek,—William, with his scythe, accidentally
struck a partridge that was concealed from his
view, in the grass, and killed it. As it appeared to
be in good order, his companions proposed that he
should take it home, for his own use. William,
<pb id="boen10" n="10"/>
however, was not easy to do so: he said the partridge
did not belong to him, but to the owner of
the meadow.</p>
        <p>On another occasion, he manifested the acuteness
of his feelings, in regard to the rights of property.
With other labourers, he was employed to cut timber
in the pines, at a distance from the settlements.
They took provisions with them, to encamp for a
week or two in the woods; and, finding an empty
cabin on lands that did not belong to their employer,
they made use of it. William's mind, however,
was not quite satisfied. He had been using the property
of another, without leave. So, after his return,
he took an early opportunity to represent the
case to the owner of the cabin, who lived some miles
distant from him.</p>
        <p>William Boen believed in Christ, as the Prince
of peace; and that those who professed to be Christians,
and lived in his peaceable spirit, could have
nothing to do with war, in any shape. He therefore
had a testimony to bear against the spirit of
war, and the love of money that stands in connexion
with it. Not far from William's habitation, there
lived a storekeeper, a man of considerable note, who
had been an officer in the army, during the time of
the American revolution. Some time after the peace
was concluded, this storekeeper traded largely in
buying up soldiers' certificates, for much less than
their nominal value. By this means, he made considerable
profits to himself, with which he engaged
in building a large and fine house. While thus employed,
William Boen called on him, and told him
he had been much concerned for him, on account of
his traffic in what he considered no better than the
<pb id="boen11" n="11"/>
price of blood, and that the money with which he
was building his house, was unrighteousness gain. He
also quoted that passage of scripture, as applicable
to the case, respecting Judas, who betrayed his Master
for the sake of money; and mentioned the manner of his
death.</p>
        <p>His reproof and admonition were delivered with
so much honesty and tender feeling, and the kind
and friendly motives that influenced him thereto,
were so apparent, that his neighbour, through a
high-spirited man, received his communication, in a
respectful manner;—and, on a subsequent occasion,
upon hearing some persons remark, that they wondered
that William was not ridiculed by boys, and
light, vain persons, on account of his singular appearance,
and wearing his beard so long,—he stated,
that William Boen was a religious man; and that his
well known piety impressed the minds of such people
with awe and respect towards him; and thus
they were prevented from manifesting that levity
which the singularity of his dress and appearance
might otherwise have produced.</p>
        <p>For it is to be observed, that he thought it right
to have all his clothing of the natural colours, and
made very plain and simple. As he was very clean
in his person, his wearing apparel became very white,
by washing—his hair and beard also became
white through age: and these, contrasted with his
dark skin, gave him a very venerable appearance.
He was affable, modest, and respectful, in his manners
and deportment; while the mildness and gravity
of his countenance, indicated a mind governed
by the precepts of the gospel, and often impressed
lessons of serious reflection on those who beheld
<pb id="boen12" n="12"/>
him;—especially in the solidarity and reverence, with
which he sat in religious meetings.</p>
        <p>It was probably on account of his dress, that some
person remarked to him, that he appeared to be endeavoring
to walk in the footsteps of John Woolman,
—a Friend with whom he had been intimately
acquainted. After a pause, he said, “I am endeavouring
to follow the footsteps of Christ.”</p>
        <p>William Boen, by attending to his Guide, and
faithfully following Christ, his <hi rend="italics">new Master,</hi> was
brought to believe in his doctrine, in relation to
gospel ministers: “Freely ye have received, freely
give.” He therefore did not approve of hireling
ministry, or paying men for preaching. This testimony
to a free gospel ministry, he carried so far,
in order to keep a pure conscience towards his Divine
Master, that on one occasion, after he had sold
some woods to a person, who was called a clergyman,
—he felt scrupulous about receiving money
from him, which was obtained by preaching: as it
would not be, in his apprehension, bearing a faithful
testimony against hireling ministry. So he went to the
man, and asked him whether he got his money
by preaching. On being answered in the affirmative,
William told him, he was not free to take his
money in pay for the wood, as he did not approve
of making money by preaching, contrary to the command
of Christ.</p>
        <p>Yet his mind was clothed with Christian charity
towards his fellow-creatures, who had not been
brought to see and walk in the way which he
apprehended to be required of him. William was not
free to use any thing either in food or clothing, that
he knew to be produced through the labour of slaves.
<pb id="boen13" n="13"/>
On its being asked him, whether he thought so well
of his friends that used the products of slavery,
as he would do, if they did not use such articles;
he replied, “<hi rend="italics">Obedience is all, with me.</hi> I believe
it is required of me, not to use these things: and if
it has never been required of them, not to use these
things, then they are as much in the way of their
duty, in using them, as I am in the way of my duty,
in not using them.”</p>
        <p>When William was drawing near the close of his
long and exemplary life, his bodily powers failed
through weakness, and the decay of nature; but his
mind was preserved clear and tranquil. At this season,
he was frequently visited by a friend, who, on
one occasion, made some remarks respecting the
calm and peaceful state of mind, which he appeared
to enjoy, and inquired of him by what means he
had attained to such a happy state. William, in
accordance with his common expression of trying all
things by the mind, gave this short and comprehensive
answer: “By keeping the mind easy,—and resisting
every thing that made it uneasy.”</p>
        <p>Soon after his death, the following obituary notice,
appeared in one of the public papers:</p>
        <q direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1>
                <p>“Died, near Mount Holly, on the 12th instant,
in the ninetieth year of his age, William Boen,
(alias Heston) a coloured man.</p>
                <p>Rare, indeed, are the instances that we meet with,
in which we feel called upon to record the virtues
of any of this afflicted race of people. The decreased,
however, was one of those who have demonstrated
the truth of that portion of scripture, that “of a
truth God is no respecter of persons; but in every
<pb id="boen14" n="14"/>
nation, they that fear him and work righteousness,
are accepted with him.”</p>
                <p>He was concerned, in early life, “to do justly,
love mercy, and walk humbly with his God;” and
by a close attention to the light of Christ within,
and faithfully abiding under the operation of that
blessed spirit of Divine grace in his soul, he was
enabled, not only to bear many precious testimonies
faithfully, to the end of his days, but also to bring
forth those fruits of the spirit which redound to the
glory of God, and the salvation of the soul. He
was an exemplary member of the religious Society
of Friends; and as he lived, so he died,—a rare pattern
of a self-denying follower of Jesus Christ. He
had no apparent disease,—either of body or mind;
but, as he expressed himself a short time before his
death, he felt nothing but weakness: which continued
to increase, until he gently breathed his last;
and is, no doubt, entered into his heavenly Father's
rest.</p>
                <p>“Mark the perfect man, and behold the upright:
for the end of that man is peace.”</p>
                <closer>
                  <date>6<hi rend="italics">th month</hi>, 1824.</date>
                </closer>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
      </div1>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div1 type="text">
        <head><hi rend="italics">Memorial of Mount Holly monthly meeting of<lb/>
Friends, concerning William Boen, a coloured
<lb/>man. Read in the Yearly Meeting of Friends,
<lb/>held in Philadelphia,</hi> 1829.</head>
        <p>As the memory of those who have followed the
leadings of that Teacher which leadeth into all truth,
and enables its votaries to become, by example,
<pb id="boen15" n="15"/>
preachers to righteousness, is precious, we feel
encouraged to give the following testimony concerning
our deceased friend, William Boen, a coloured man.</p>
        <p>He was born in the year 1735, in the neighbourhood
of Rancocas. Being a slave from his birth, he had
very little opportunity of acquiring useful
learning; yet by his own industry and care, he succeeded
in learning to read and write.</p>
        <p>His mind became seriously impressed while very
young, and he was induced in early life, to attend
to the monitions of light and life in his own mind,
being convinced from what he felt within him, of
the existence of a Supreme Being; and also of the
manner of his visiting the children of men, by the
inward peace which he felt upon a faithful performance
of what he thus apprehended to be his duty.</p>
        <p>About the twenty-eighth year of his age, he contracted
for his freedom; and having entered into
marriage engagements with a woman in the
neighbourhood, but not being, at that time, a member of
our society, he was straitened in his mind how to
accomplish it; as he was fully convinced of our testimony
in that respect.</p>
        <p>In this difficulty, he made known his situation to
our friend, John Woolman, who, to relieve him, had
a number of persons convened at a friend's house,
where they were married after the manner of our society,
and a certificate to that effect, furnished them
by those present.</p>
        <p>About this time he made application to become a
member of our society; but way not opening in
Friend's minds, he was not received, but encouraged
to continue faithful; which we believe he did, from
the account we have of nearly his whole life.</p>
        <pb id="boen16" n="16"/>
        <p>He was concerned above all things, to walk in the
path of truth and righteousness; and according to
his measure, to be faithful to every opening of duty,
by which means he obtained the esteem of all who
knew him.</p>
        <p>As he thus continued steadfast to the light in his
own mind, he was favoured to see the necessity of
a daily cross to all the gratifications of self, and that
the cause of truth cannot grow in us, while we are
governed by a worldly spirit.</p>
        <p>By yielding full of obedience to that light, which it
was his chiefest joy to follow, he became truly convinced
of the necessity of maintaining the various
testimonies which we, as a people, have been called
upon to bear; and, in some respects, he had to bear
a testimony against things in which many of his
white brethren indulge, particularly in regard to
slavery; refusing to wear, or use in any shape,
articles which come through that corrupted channel.
And, we believe, it was through dedication to the
Lord, and an unreserved surrender of his will, to
the Divine will, that he was brought to see these
things in that light, which deceiveth not. Thus,
evincing by his conversation and example, the truth
of that scriptural declaration, “All thy children shall
be taught of the Lord, and great shall be the peace
of thy children; in righteousness shalt thou be established.”</p>
        <p>It appears, not only from his own words, but also
from his weighty example, that his great concern
was to keep his mind easy, believing that right and
wrong actions would result either in peace or pain
within; hence, his great care was to “try all things by
the mind,” as he expressed it, or the light of Christ
<pb id="boen17" n="17"/>
within; with which he was, no doubt, through faithfulness,
in a remarkable manner favoured; esteeming
it right to be obedient to every manifested duty,
however in the cross, or insignificant to the carnal
mind, these small duties might appear; and as he
was found, like the servant in the parable, “faithful
in the little,” he was strengthened to rule over the
carnal propensities of his nature, bringing his words
and actions into the obedience of Christ. His humility
was such, that although in low circumstances,
he appeared to be content, and even refused to indulge
himself in rich food or clothing, saying that
“bread and water was good enough for him.” In
1814, he was, on application, received into membership
with us, and continued to the last, when able,
a steady attender of our meetings, both for worship
and discipline.</p>
        <p>He enjoyed reasonable health and strength until
about his eighty-seventh year, when his strength
began to fail, but the faculties of his mind remained
good until his end.</p>
        <p>Some weeks previous to his death, he spoke of it
with the utmost composure, and recounting his past
trials and experiences said, “he had thought he was
alone with regard to his testimony against slavery.”
But, as though he had fresh evidence thereof, said,
“he believed it would grow and increase among
Friends.” He appeared perfectly resigned to death,
having no will therein; as he expressed himself,
“that some died hard and others easy, but for himself,
he had no wish for either, being fully resigned
to the Divine will in all things.”</p>
        <p>To a friend present, the day previous to his death,
he stated “that he felt himself going very fast; but
<pb id="boen18" n="18"/>
that he had no wish to stay.” His weakness increasing,
and having no desire to take any nourishment,
he was asked if he was sick, or felt any pain; to
which he answered, “that he felt neither pain nor
sickness, but weakness, and a total disrelish for every
thing of this world.” His weakness continued to
increase until he passed quietly away, on the night
of the 12th of the 6th month, 1824, in the ninetieth
year of his age; and we doubt not, he has entered
into his heavenly Father's rest.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute>Read in, and approved by, Mount Holly monthly
meeting of Friends, held 11th month 6th, 1828.</salute>
          <signed>AMOS BULLOCK, Clerk.</signed>
        </closer>
        <closer><salute>Read in, and approved by, Burlington Quarterly
meeting of Friends, held at Chesterfield, on the 25th
of the 11th month, 1828, and directed to be forwarded
to the Yearly Meeting.</salute>
<signed>ANDREW C. RIDGWAY, Clerk.</signed></closer>
      </div1>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI.2>