<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY eliotvs SYSTEM "eliotvs.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY eliotfp SYSTEM "eliotfp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY eliot60 SYSTEM "eliot60.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY eliottp SYSTEM "eliottp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>The Story of Archer Alexander.</emph><emph>From Slavery
 to Freedom, March 30, 1863:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Eliot, William Greenleaf, 1811-1887</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities  supported
the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name>Aletha Andrew</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by</resp>
          <name>Aletha Andrew</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns"> Joshua McKim and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1999</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca.     150K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1999.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note anchored="yes">Call number  E444 A37 1885 (University of Virginia Library)</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The story of Archer Alexander. From slavery to freedom, March 30,
 1863</title>
          <author>by William G. Eliot</author>
          <imprint>
            <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
            <publisher>Cupples, Upham and Company</publisher>
            <date>1885</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>All footnotes are moved to the end of paragraphs in which the reference 
occurs.</p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ 
and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using 
Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Alexander, Archer.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Fugitive slaves -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Freedmen -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Eliot, William Greenleaf, 1811-1887.</item>
            <item>Lovejoy, Elijah P. (Elijah Parish), 1802-1837.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- Missouri -- History -- 19th century.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- United States -- History -- 19th century.</item>
            <item>Western Sanitary Commission.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Monuments.</item>
            <item>Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865 -- Monuments.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>1999-11-01, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-07-19, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-07-16, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Joshua McKim</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-07-12, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Aletha Andrew</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="frontispiece">
        <p>
          <figure id="frontis" entity="eliotfp">
            <p>[Frontispiece Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="title page image">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="eliottp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="verso">
        <p>
          <figure id="verso" entity="eliotvs">
            <p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">THE STORY
<lb/>
OF
<lb/>
ARCHER ALEXANDER</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="main">FROM SLAVERY TO FREEDOM
<lb/>
MARCH 30, 1863</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>BY</byline>
        <docAuthor>WILLIAM G. ELIOT
<lb/>
A MEMBER OF THE WESTERN SANITARY COMMISSION
<lb/>
ST. LOUIS, MO.</docAuthor>
        <epigraph>
          <q direct="unspecified">“No sea 
Swells like the bosom of a man set free: 
A wilderness is rich with liberty.”</q>
          <bibl>WORDSWORTH</bibl>
        </epigraph>
        <docImprint><pubPlace>BOSTON</pubPlace>
<publisher>CUPPLES, UPHAM AND COMPANY <lb/>Old Corner Bookstore</publisher>
<docDate>1885</docDate></docImprint>
        <pb n="verso"/>
        <docImprint><hi rend="italics">Copyright, by</hi>
WILLIAM G. ELIOT,
<hi rend="italics">1885.</hi>
<lb/>ELECTROTYPED
BY C. J. PETERS &amp; SON, BOSTON.</docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="dedication">
        <pb id="alexa1" n="1"/>
        <opener>
          <salute>TO<lb/>
MRS. JESSIE BENTON FRÉMONT,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p>WITHOUT WHOSE PERSONAL SYMPATHY AND ACTIVE INFLUENCE<lb/>
THE WORK OF THE WESTERN SANITARY COMMISSION<lb/>
COULD NOT HAVE BEEN BEGUN NOR<lb/>
SUCCESSFULLY PROSECUTED,</p>
        <closer><salute>This Little Book is Most Respectfully Inscribed<lb/>
BY<lb/>
HER SINCERE AND OBLIGED FRIEND,</salute>
<signed>WILLIAM GREENLEAF ELIOT.</signed>
<dateline>ST. Louis, Mo., Aug. 5, 1885.</dateline></closer>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="contents">
        <pb id="alexa3" n="3"/>
        <head>CONTENTS.</head>
        <list type="simple">
          <item>FREEDOM'S MEMORIAL . . . . . <ref target="alexa11" targOrder="U">11</ref></item>
          <item>I. KALORAMA, ARCHER'S VIRGINIA HOME . . . . . <ref target="alexa17" targOrder="U">17</ref></item>
          <item>II. THE DEPARTURE . . . . . <ref target="alexa30" targOrder="U">30</ref></item>
          <item>III. LIFE IN MISSOURI.—1833-63 . . . . . <ref target="alexa39" targOrder="U">39</ref></item>
          <item>IV. THE ESCAPE . . . . . <ref target="alexa47" targOrder="U">47</ref></item>
          <item>V. THE CAPTURE  . . . . . <ref target="alexa54" targOrder="U">54</ref></item>
          <item>VI. THE RESCUE . . . . . <ref target="alexa67" targOrder="U">67</ref></item>
          <item>VII. SAFETY . . . . . <ref target="alexa74" targOrder="U">74</ref></item>
          <item>VIII. LOUISA . . . . . <ref target="alexa78" targOrder="U">78</ref></item>
          <item>IX. FREEDOM AND REST . . . . . <ref target="alexa83" targOrder="U">83</ref></item>
          <item> X. SLAVERY IN THE BORDER STATES . . . . . <ref target="alexa90" targOrder="U">90</ref></item>
          <item>XI. ELIJAH P. LOVEJOY . . . . . <ref target="alexa107" targOrder="U">107</ref></item>
          <item>APPENDIX . . . . . <ref target="alexa117" targOrder="U">117</ref></item>
        </list>
      </div1>
      <div1>
        <pb id="alexa5" n="5"/>
        <head>PREFACE.</head>
        <p>THE following narrative was prepared without
intention of publication; but I have been led to think
that it may be of use, not only as a reminiscence of
the “war of secession,” but as a fair presentation of
slavery in the Border States for the twenty or thirty
years preceding the outbreak of hostilities. I am
confirmed in this view by the fact, that, on submitting
the manuscript to a leading publishing-house in a
Northern city, it was objected to, among other
reasons, as too tame to satisfy the public taste and
judgment. But, from equally intelligent parties in a
city farther south, the exactly opposite criticism was
made, as if a too harsh judgment of slavery and 
slave-holders was conveyed, so that its publication
<pb id="alexa6" n="6"/>
would be prejudicial to those undertaking it.</p>
        <p>I therefore asked the opinion of several friends,
who, like myself, had lived all those years under the
shadow of the “peculiar institution,” in one or other
of the northern tier of the slave States, and who
labored faithfully for its abolition, giving the best
service of their lives to the cause of freedom, “possessing 
their souls in patience” while contending
against what seemed to be an irresistible power. Their
concurrence has confirmed me in the opinion, that,
however feebly drawn, a true picture, so far as it goes,
is given in these pages of the relation between master
and slave, and of the social condition of slave-holding
communities. Without claiming to be more than a
plain story plainly told, it shows things as they were,
and how they were regarded by intelligent and
thoughtful people at the time.</p>
        <p>Only those who lived in the border slave States
during that eventful period from 1830
<pb id="alexa7" n="7"/>
to 1860, can fully understand the complications and
difficulties of the “irrepressible conflict,” and how
hard it was fully to maintain one's self-respect under
the necessities of deliberate and cautious action; to
speak plainly without giving such degree of offence as
would prevent one from speaking at all. Yet it was in
these States that the first and hardest battles for
freedom were fought, and where the ground was
prepared upon which the first great victories were
won.</p>
        <p>It is a subject upon which I speak with deep
feeling; for I have known many cases in which those
who worked with faithful and self-denying energy
have been severely censured for their “temporizing,
time-serving policy.” Perhaps, upon mature thought,
it may appear that the man who stands at safe
distance from the field of battle, though he may have a
better general view of the conflict, is not always the
best judge of the hand-to-hand fight of those to whom
the struggle is one of life or death.
No city or State in the Union has greater
<pb id="alexa8" n="8"/>
reason to be proud of its record in the late
war of secession than St. Louis and Missouri.</p>
        <p>Gradually the mists of partial knowledge
clear away; but it will be many years yet before 
the North and South will thoroughly
understand each other, either as to the past
history of slavery or the present relations of
the negro and white races. Meanwhile mutual
forbearance may lead to increasing mutual
affection and respect.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1>
        <pb id="alexa11" n="11"/>
        <head>FREEDOM'S MEMORIAL.</head>
        <head>ABRAHAM LINCOLN.—ARCHER ALEXANDER.</head>
        <epigraph>
          <q direct="unspecified">“And upon this act I invoke the considerate judgment 
of mankind and the gracious favor of Almighty
God.”—</q>
          <bibl>PROCLAMATION OF FREEDOM, Jan. 1, 1863.</bibl>
        </epigraph>
        <p>IN the capitol grounds at Washington, D.C.,
there is a bronze group known as “Freedom's 
Memorial.” It represents President
Lincoln in the act of emancipating a negro
slave, who kneels at his feet to receive the
benediction, but whose hand has grasped the
chain as if in the act of breaking it, indicating 
the historical fact that the slaves took
active part in their own deliverance.</p>
        <p>A brief history of this memorial, taken from
the full account published at the time of its
dedication when unveiled by President U. S.
Grant, April 14, 1876, is as follows.</p>
        <p>Soon after Mr. Lincoln's assassination, Charlotte 
Scott, an emancipated slave, brought five
dollars to her former master, Mr. William P.
<pb id="alexa12" n="12"/>
Rucker, then a Union refugee from Virginia, and
residing in Marietta, O. It was her first earnings as a
free woman, and she begged that it might be used “to
make a monument to Massa Lincoln, the best friend
the colored people ever had.” Mr. Rucker placed it in
the hands of General T. H. C. Smith, who forwarded
it to Mr. James E. Yeatman, president of the Western
Sanitary Commission of St. Louis, with the following
letter:—</p>
        <q direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1>
                <opener><dateline>ST. LOUIS, April 26, 1865.</dateline>
JAMES E. YEATMAN, Esq.</opener>
                <p><hi rend="italics">My Dear Sir,</hi>—A poor woman of Marietta, O.,
one of those made free by President Lincoln's proclamation, 
proposes that a monument to their dead friend
be erected by the colored people of the United States.
She has handed to a person in Marietta five dollars as
her contribution for the purpose. Such a monument
would have a history more grand and touching than any
of which we have account. Would it not be well to
take up this suggestion, and make it known to the freed-men?</p>
                <closer><salute>Yours truly,</salute>
<signed>T. H. C. SMITH.</signed></closer>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <p>The suggestion was cordially accepted, and a
circular letter was published inviting all freedmen to
send contributions for the purpose to the
Commission in St. Louis. In response, liberal sums
were received from colored soldiers under command
of General J. W.
<pb id="alexa13" n="13"/>
Davidson (headquarters at Natchez, Miss.),
amounting to $12,150, which was soon increased
from other sources to $16,242. Then came a revulsion
of feeling, from various causes, after the accession of
President Johnson, which checked the movement, and
it could not afterwards be renewed. The amount was
entirely inadequate to the accomplishment of any
great work; but it was put at interest, and held with
an indefinite hope of its enlargement.</p>
        <p>In the summer of 1869, I was in Florence,
Italy; and at the rooms of Thomas Ball, sculptor, 
I saw a group in marble which he had
designed and executed immediately after President 
Lincoln's death. It had been done under
the strong impulse of the hour, with no special
end in view, except to express the magnificent
act which had given new birth to his country,
and for which the beloved and heroic leader
had suffered martyrdom. When I told him
what we were trying to do, and of our temporary 
failure, he said at once, with enthusiasm,
that the group was at our service if it suited
us, and that its cost should be only for the
actual labor of reproducing it at the royal
foundry in Munich, in bronze, colossal size, all
<pb id="alexa14" n="14"/>
of which he would gratuitously superintend himself.
When told of the sum actually in hand, he said it was
amply sufficient.</p>
        <p>Accordingly I had photographs taken, and carried
them home with me. The Commission thankfully
adopted them, with one suggestion of change, that
instead of the ideal figure of a slave wearing a liberty
cap, and receiving the gift of freedom passively, as in
the original marble group, the representative form of a
negro should be introduced, helping to break the chain
that had bound him. Mr. Ball kindly assented.
Photographic pictures of ARCHER ALEXANDER, a
fugitive slave, were sent to him; and in the present
group his likeness, both face and figure, is as correct
as that of Mr. Lincoln himself. The ideal group is thus
converted into the literal truth of history without
losing its artistic conception or effect. A duplicate of
the group was given by Moses Kimball to the city of
Boston, and stands in Park Square. It was dedicated
Dec. 11, 1879, having been cast in Munich at the
royal foundry, under direction of the same persons
who cast the original group. But, from some cause, it
is by no means equal in artistic effect to that in
Washington.</p>
        <pb id="alexa15" n="15"/>
        <p>The story of Archer, given in the following 
pages, is substantially a correct narrative of 
facts as learned from him, and in all the important
particulars as coming under my own immediate
knowledge. He was the last fugitive slave captured
under civil law in Missouri.</p>
        <p>It is written at the request of my children, for the
benefit of my grandchildren, that they may know
something of what slavery was, and of the negro
character under its influence.</p>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="main text">
        <pb id="alexa17" n="17"/>
        <head>THE STORY
<lb/>
OF
<lb/>
ARCHER ALEXANDER.</head>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
          <head>KALORAMA, ARCHER'S VIRGINIA HOME.</head>
          <p>ABOUT twenty-five or thirty miles from
Richmond, Va., in the year 1828, a family was living
in the old-fashioned hospitable Virginia gentleman-farmer 
style, on a place of some three hundred acres,
which the young folks called Kalorama, because of
the beautiful outlook from the old homestead,
although the name was not used except in the
immediate neighborhood.</p>
          <p>The proprietor was a man of some consequence,
the Rev. Mr. Delaney, who had been, before his
marriage, in active discharge of his duties as a
Presbyterian minister, but had retired from all except
occasional services of special interest, although still
familiarly called parson or doctor by his neighbors.
His wife, who brought him the property, was a lady
of
<pb id="alexa18" n="18"/>
great excellence, belonging to one of the best
families of the State,—a warm-hearted, devout
woman, a good manager, a faithful wife and
mother. At the time of which I write, two
sons and three daughters were growing up, the
oldest of them eighteen years of age. There were ten
or twelve families of slaves, numbering, in all, about
seventy “head,” old and young.</p>
          <p>Upon one subject Mrs. Delaney was absolutely
fixed. While believing that slavery was a divine
institution, sanctioned by scripture from the time
when “Cursed be Ham” was spoken, down to the
return of the fugitive slave Onesimus by the apostle
Paul,—subjects on which her husband had
eloquently preached,—yet she felt deeply through
her whole nature, as most of the well-born Southern
women did, that there was a trust involved for which
the slave-owner was responsible to God almost as
sacredly as for his own children. To all separation of
families, therefore, except at their own choice or as a
penalty for wrongdoing, she was firmly opposed. It
had seldom occurred on the place, and she said it
never should occur if she could help it. She had also
succeeded in convincing, or at least in
<pb id="alexa19" n="19"/>
persuading, her husband to the same effect. But he
wavered sometimes, under the pressure 
for money, and had even suggested the wisdom of
selling off a few so as better to provide for the
remainder.</p>
          <p>Only once, however, had he distinctly overstepped
the line, and that was a signal instance. 
It was in the case of a man named Aleck, a full
black, forty-five years old, strong, stalwart,
intelligent; in fact, his very best “hand.” Somehow or
other, this fellow had learned to read. Nobody knew
how, but probably from the children and by chance
opportunities. A good deal of discussion about
slavery was going on at the time, which was not very
far from the Missouri compromise days; and Aleck
had got some advanced notions of which he was rather proud, talking
them out rather freely among his fellows. In fact, “he
made himself altogether too smart.” At a colored
prayer-meeting he had gone so far as to say that “by
the 'Claration of 'Dependence 
all men was ekal,” and that “to trade in men
and women, jess like hogs and hosses, wasn't 'cordin'
to gospel, nohow.”</p>
          <p>Of course, such talk as this would not do. It
spread among the colored folk, and the
<pb id="alexa20" n="20"/>
white people began to hear of it. One of Mr.
Delaney's neighbors came to see him about it, and
after a while a committee of church-members called
upon him with a formal expostulation. They urged
upon him that his duty as a Christian man required
that he should send Aleck South; “that it was not
doing to his neighbors as he would be done by, to
keep such a mischief-maker there; that a slave
insurrection would be the next thing.”</p>
          <p>Mr. Delaney, being a good Christian, and believing
in the divine authority for slavery, saw the justice of
what was said. He knew that such notions as Aleck's
were fanatical, and subversive of social order. 
“Servants, obey your masters,” was good scripture;
and he was Greek scholar enough to know that, in the
original, “servant” meant bond-servant or slave. So
he talked with Aleck and threatened him, but it did
little good. Aleck kept at his work, but his mind was
working too. He was getting spoilt for slavery. As
Deacon Snodgrass emphatically said, “he was a
demoralized nigger.”</p>
          <p>Still his kind mistress pleaded for him.
“Don't sell him if you can help it. Chloe will go
distracted if you do; and her boy
<pb id="alexa21" n="21"/>
Archer, that his young master thinks so much of, will
take it so hard!” Even she wavered, as her manner of
pleading showed. She had begun to think of this sale
as a necessity.</p>
          <p>Unfortunately, Mr. Delaney was in debt. He owed
a good deal of money, for the farm had not been well
managed. His neighbors said he was “too easy on his
niggers,” for that. A suit had gone against him for
fifteen hundred dollars, on which judgment was given
and execution issued. He went to Richmond to
arrange it and Aleck drove him down, as he had often
done before; for he was a fine-looking fellow and his
master was proud of him. They stopped on Grace
Street, at the house of his creditor, who came to the
door, praised the horses and, with an eye to business,
closely scrutinized the driver. When they went in and
had pledged each other, according to the
hospitable notions of the times, in stiff glasses of
good old whiskey, Colonel Jones poured out a
glassful and took it with his own hands to Aleck,—an
unusual courtesy, at which the chattel was
astonished; but it gave the colonel a good
opportunity of satisfying himself that the man was
sound in life and limb. “Well, Aleck,” he said, “your
master hasn't sold you
<pb id="alexa22" n="22"/>
yet. I've heard talk of it.”—“No, <hi rend="italics">sir</hi>,” said he.
“Massa ain't a-goin' to do it, nudder. He'd most as lib
sell one of his own chilluns.”—“All right,” said the
colonel, “you just hold on to that.” Aleck showed his
teeth, and looked greatly pleased.</p>
          <p>As soon as the colonel went in, Mr. Delaney began
to apologize for delays, and to ask for further time.
But the colonel had made up his mind, and answered
abruptly, “Now, I tell you what, parson [creditors
with law on their side are apt to take liberties], there
ain't no use in this kind of talk. Cash is the word. But
I tell you how we <hi rend="italics">can</hi> fix it, short metre. You just
give me a bill of sale for that nigger Aleck out there,
and it's done. He's a sassy boy and will get you into a
big scrape some day; and you'd better get shet of him,
anyway, for your own good and for the good of the
country. There now, parson, the way I
look at it, your religion and your pocket are on the
same side. What do you say? But one thing's sure:
money or its equiv-a-lent I'm a-going to have, down
on the nail. There ain't no two ways about that.”</p>
          <p>Mr. Delaney hesitated and pleaded. He concluded
to stay over night with his considerate
<pb id="alexa23" n="23"/>
friend. His duty seemed to him plain enough;
but his feelings rebelled, and the thought of his wife
increased the weakness.
But he prayed over it at night, and again in the
morning. His mind gradually cleared up, especially 
when, after breakfast, the accounts
were laid before him and the necessity of
speedy action became plain.</p>
          <p>“What are you going to do with Aleck?”
he asked, unconsciously betraying that the decision
was already made. “Why, now,” answered 
the colonel with an emphatic gesture,
“that's just where it is. There's a kind of
prov-i-dence in it. Here's my neighbor, Jim
Buckner, that's making up a gang to go South, and he
wants a fancy nigger for a customer in Charleston,
and he knows Aleck and told me to get him and he'd
pay judgment <hi rend="italics">and</hi> costs. It's an awful big price, but
he's as rich as creases and don't care. Such a chance
wouldn't never happen again in a lifetime,
and Aleck would have a first-rate master besides. 
But he'll have to hold his impudent
jaw down there, <hi rend="italics">I tell you</hi>.” </p>
          <p>It came hard, but the bill of sale was signed,
and the debt paid. Every thing was done as
Colonel Jones said, quiet and civil, and without 
<pb id="alexa24" n="24"/>
fuss. What's the use of hurting the boy's feelings,
and your'n too, when it's got to be done?” So Aleck
was sent on a pretended errand to a place near the
slave-jail, taken quietly by Jim Buckner and his men,
handcuffed, carried South the same evening, and
<hi rend="italics">nobody at Kalorama ever heard of him again</hi>. It was
his death and burial.</p>
          <p>The next day Mr. Delaney returned home, arriving
late in the evening. Great was the excitement when it
was known that Aleck had been sold South “to pay
massa's debts,” and had gone off with Buckner's gang.
Poor Chloe, his wife, was dumfounded. She sat down,
rocked her body backward and forward, and groaned
aloud, “O, Lord God, oh, dear Jesus, what has ole
massa gone and done! O Lord Jesus, whar was you
when he done it!” But there was no help for it, no
hope for her. The next day's work must go on: so she
cooked and washed as usual, heavy-hearted but silent.</p>
          <p>“You see how it is,” said Deacon Snodgrass; “these
niggers don't have no feelings
like white folks. Anyhow, it's only as if her old man
had died. The thing happens every day, and has got
to happen. It's the order of Prov-i-dence.”</p>
          <pb id="alexa25" n="25"/>
          <p>Mrs. Delaney was deeply grieved. The young
master, Thomas, took it hardest at first, and said right
out, “it was a damned shame.” But his father rebuked
his profanity, and explained the case to him as one of
unavoidable Christian duty. Aleck's son Archer was
too young to understand it; but he kept close to his
mother, who, after that, never liked to lose sight of
him. The neighbors generally said it was a good thing;
“that Delaney's niggers had got too upppish, and
would now be brought down a peg. It was high time
for an example.”</p>
          <p>Two years had already passed since that “taking
down a peg” had occurred; but, on the whole, things
had not improved. The farm kept deteriorating in
value, worn out by exhausting crops of corn and
tobacco. One of the hands ran away and escaped.
Another who tried it, with his wife and child, was
caught and brought back; but they had suffered so
much from exposure and in the struggle with their
captors, <hi rend="italics">who had an unmanageable dog with them,</hi>
that they were never of much account afterwards.
From such experience the rest could not fail to learn
the wisdom of submission and contentment. Yet a spirit of
<pb id="alexa26" n="26"/>
uneasiness prevailed, so unreasoning is the African
mind. The increasing probability of being sold South,
and the difficulty of running away, did not seem to
have a soothing influence.</p>
          <p>In 1831 Mr. Delaney died suddenly, leaving no will
and many debts. The estate was administered upon,
and about one-half the land, with three or four families
of slaves, were sold to pay the pressing debts. The
rest of the property was divided, under the law,
among the widow and children. In this division Chloe
fell to the widow's share; her boy Archer, now
eighteen years old, to the “young master,” Mrs.
Delaney's oldest son. But Chloe, Aleck's “widow,”
had run down very sadly. It really seemed almost as
if she had had feelings like white people, and Aleck's
being sold South was in some way or other very
different to her from a divine dispensation of
bereavement. A clergyman talked with her; but when
he said, “The Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken
away; blessed be the name of the Lord,”—she said with
sobs, “O Lord, massa! please don't talk dat way! I can't
see it, nohow!” She was no longer cheerful and full of
jokes, but stolid and heavy-hearted,
<pb id="alexa27" n="27"/>
taking no interest in any thing except
her boy Archie. It was not long before she had to lose
him too, though not by death.</p>
          <p>Mrs. Delaney's oldest son, Thomas, whom Chloe
had nursed in his infancy, made up his mind to
emigrate to Missouri, the new land of promise in the
West. His mother and the rest of the family would
stay in the old place. He quietly made all his arrangements, 
sent part of his valuables forward to Guyandotte to
wait for him there, and when quite ready, one day
after dinner, told Archer, his foster brother, to saddle
up the horses and get ready for a start, so as to make
twenty miles before night set in.</p>
          <p>Of course, the old tradition of not separating
families had been broken up, in the settlement of the
estate. The law is no respecter of persons or feelings.
It allows little place for 
sentiment, and the family plate is worth the silver in
it; no more. Every thing had been
appraised at its value, slaves included; and, if families
could not be kept together, it was nobody's 
fault. They were sold under the hammer, “to
the best advantage.”</p>
          <p>It is a great mistake to suppose that the chief
hardships of slavery consisted in acts of
<pb id="alexa28" n="28"/>
severity or cruelty. Such did frequently occur,
for irresponsible power over an inferior race is
sure to result in its abuse; but they were the
comparatively rare exceptions, and in no part
of the South were they the rule. The vast
majority of slave-owners ameliorated the condition 
of slavery ; that is, so far as they conveniently could, 
consistently with their own
interests, the maintenance of subordination,
and a friendly regard to the rights of their
neighbors. They looked carefully after the
comfort of their “families” up to a certain
point, treated them with humanity and sometimes 
with indulgence and tenderness. Nevertheless 
they were “chattels” (Anglice, “cattle”),—in 
the eye of the law, property subject
to seizure and sale. The exigencies of debt,
so common in the unthrifty Southern management; the 
death of the owner, and consequent
necessity of dividing the estate; the commission of
faults of impudence or petty criminality, to say
nothing of the whims and caprices of the master or
mistress,—all were common and lawful causes of
trouble. Over the best and most pampered slave the
sword of uncertainty always hung, suspended by an
invisible hair; from which it came to pass, that, under
<pb id="alexa29" n="29"/>
the best of circumstances, the best condition of
slavery was worse than the worst condition of
freedom. The blacks are a docile and easily controlled
race. Subordination does not come hard to them. But
at this moment,—twenty years after they have had the trial
of freedom, trammelled as it has been by not a few
hardships and social oppressions, and by greater
cruelties in some sections than slavery itself
witnessed,—I doubt if a man or woman could be
found who would exchange freedom, such as it is, for
the old relation under the best master that ever lived.</p>
          <p>Six months after Archer's going, Chloe, his mother,
died. There was no special disease; but “she kind-a fell
off,” as the colored people expressed it. “She didn't
take no hand in nothin', like she used to;” did her
work faithfully, but “seemed to be a thinkin' about
somethin', and <hi rend="italics">prayed powerful.</hi>” Her kind-hearted
mistress said she never got over Aleck's being sold
South, and just grieved herself to death; but Deacon
Snodgrass, who “understood niggers,” said that she
was “the obstinatist nigger-wench he ever knew.”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <pb id="alexa30" n="30"/>
          <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
          <div3 type="section">
            <head>THE DEPARTURE.</head>
            <p>THE sudden bustle of the final getting-ready
stirred up the household. The family
partings were made between Mrs. Delaney and
her son. Very sad and bitter they were; but
the old lady knew it was best for Thomas, and
so she gave him her blessing and was resigned.
Then “young massa” went out and shook
hands with all the people, every one of whom
loved him, for he had been kind to all of them.
He gave them some trifling gratuities, and told
them to behave themselves first-rate till he
came back. Then, last of all, he looked for his
old nurse Chloe, who was at the door of her
cabin, and shook hands with her, and promised
to take good care of Archie, and to fetch him
back some day to see her. He gave her a new
calico gown, for which she “thanked him
kindly.” In fact, she had no hard feelings
towards him. He was only doing what he had
a right to do; and “mebby it's the best thing
<pb id="alexa31" n="31"/>
for the boy; and de good Lord, he knows best what's
good for all on us.” She seemed to feel very much as
Mrs. Delaney did, though of course no one would
have ventured to make so absurd a comparison
between a slave woman and her lady mistress. But
there she stood; and, when her young master turned
away, the tears were running down her cheeks.</p>
            <p>As for Archie, boylike, he was full of excitement.
He ran up to kiss his mammy, told her he was going
to ride “Shirley,” the old master's favorite horse, and
Master Thomas was to ride “Major,” and they were
most ready to start. She tried to look pleased, but the
tears kept coming. “Well, go way, chile; come back to
see de ole place ef you kin. Mebby you'll fine me
here.” She sat down on the stoop, and he was off in a
minute on a run.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="section">
            <head>A MOTHER'S LOVE.</head>
            <p>Forty-eight years after that day, Archer himself
told me of it. He was then nearly seventy years old,
failing very fast, about three months before he died. I
had often talked with him about his old home; but he
had said almost nothing about his mother, until one
day, as he was half-working on my grass-plot
<pb id="alexa32" n="32"/>
with his sickle, I asked him if he remembered her.
“Yes, sir,” he answered very slowly and solemnly,
first looking at me, and then higher up, with his face
raised. “Yes, sir, I remembers her like yesterday.
Seems like I never forgets her, nohow. 'Specially
when trouble comes, and I've had a heap of that,—
thank the Lord,—seems like she allays come to me—
not close up to me, but jess like she was when I seed
her the last time; and she's allays a-prayin' for me.
That's what keeps me up.”</p>
            <p>There was something peculiar in his manner, for to
the pious negro there are no realities like those of
faith; and I asked him to tell me more about it. He
hesitated a moment, and then said, “Yes, sir, I think I
kin. I can't allays talk about it, but it 'pears like it
would do me good now.” He sat down on his
wheelbarrow, while I stood by him, under the shade
of a tree that he had helped me to plant ten years
before.</p>
            <p>“You see, sir, after ole Mr. Delaney died, and the
family was all broke up, like what I was tellin' you
one day, the place wasn't big enough to keep all on
us; and young Mr. Thomas he thote to come West,
and he was bound to take me, 'cause he liked me, and I
<pb id="alexa33" n="33"/>
liked him; and I belonged to him, anyhow, as a part of
his sheer. Well, one day, on a suddent-like, he up and
quit. He said good-by to eberybody, and I kissed my
mammy, and was most crazy with 'citement 'kase
Massa Tom had chose me to go along wid him, and to
ride his favorite hoss ‘Shirley;’ and I didn't know
what a big fool I was.</p>
            <p>“I leff my mammy—that ar was Chloe, the ole
missus' favorite cook—a-settin' on the door-step,
and I didn't seem to keer no more about it than ef I
was goin' away for a week. But she keered. Then,
when we went down to the gate that one of the boys
was thar to open, suthin' came inside of me, right here
[laying his hand on his breast], and said to me,
‘Archie, you're leaving your mother for good. You
won't neber see her no mo'.’ Then I turned round to
see whar she was. And thar she stood, front of her
own white-washed cabin, whar I was born; and both
her hands was raised up, this way; and she was
lookin' up, and the sun shined on her, and I could see
her face plain, and it looked bright-like round her
head, and I knowed she was a-prayin' for me. I
knowed it jess as well as ef I heerd it. I kep' looking
so long that Massa Tom got a
<pb id="alexa34" n="34"/>
good bit away; and he turned and spoke up sharplike,
‘Come, hurry up thar! What you lookin' at thar like a
stuck pig?’ So I turns round and rode up to him, but
my 'citement was all gone. 'Peared like I weighed
twice as much on the hoss as I did before, and I
could'nt say nuthin'. ‘Why, what's up, Archie?’ young
massa said: ‘have you seen a ghost?’—‘No, sir, I ain't,’
I said to him; ‘but I seen my mammy, and she was a-prayin' 
for me.’—‘Well,’ said he, keerless-like, ‘that's
all right. Your mother will pray for you, and mine will
pray for me.’—‘Yes, Massa Tom, that's so.’</p>
            <p>“You see, sir, my young massa was mighty good to
me. He knowed I felt bad, and wanted to keep my
heart up. But I couldn't do it, nohow. That night we
stopped at Jake Appler's tavern, and I dreamed all
night of my pore ole mammy. But arter that I didn't
think hardly no mo' about it. I was drefful busy all
the time, and when we got to the river at Guyandotte,
and on the boat, there was a heap to see. But at
Louisville, whar we stopped two days, I seed her
agin.”</p>
            <p>He paused for a moment as if to collect his
thoughts. He was evidently telling what was to him
literal and sacred truth.</p>
            <pb id="alexa35" n="35"/>
            <p>“Massa Tom, he leff me waitin' for him in a
bar-room,—you see he trusted me anywhar,—and
some men thar was mighty civil, and give me a drink,
and got me to laughin', and I was goin' it strong. All at
once sumfin come over me. I looked out of the winder
(it was jess beginnin' to be darkish), and thar, plain as
I see you—thar she was, away off, stanin' front of her
whitewash door, de light shinin' on her face and all
aroun' her, and her hands up, a-prayin' for me,—seemed like I heerd 
her,—‘Lord Jesus, save my boy.’ I sot down the glass. 
‘Gentle<hi rend="italics">men</hi>, 'skuse me. I speck
my massa's callin' for me, and I'se bound to go.’ When
I tole Massa Tom how kind them men was to me, he
was orful mad. He said
they was <hi rend="italics">dealers</hi>, the damn rascals, and, ef they had
only got you drunk, they'd 'ducted you in no time,
and sole you South. But I didn't
tell him it was my mammy that saved me.” It is
impossible to express the tenderness with which he
said this.</p>
            <p>“Well, sir, it was a long time after that afore I thote
serious about any thing; for, arter we got to St.
Louis, I was worked in the brickyard, and nothing
much went wrong wid me. But there come round thar
a 'vival Metherdus
<pb id="alexa36" n="36"/>
preacher, and I went to hear him. He talked mighty
strong, persuadin' to come to Jesus; but somehow it
didn't 'press me much. He called for them as wanted
to be prayed for to come forrard, but I got up to go
home. Jess then, seemed like I heerd my mammy a-prayin', 
‘Lord Jesus, don't let him go!’ Shore enough,
right out in the dark night I seed her, plain as day, her
hands like they was befo', prayin' for me. I jess give
in and went straight up to the altar, and afore the
week was gone I found Jesus; and, bless the Lord, I'se
stuck to him ever sense. But it was my mammy that
done it.</p>
            <p>“It's a long time ago, and I haven't seen her plain
till lately; but now, ebery night mose, she comes in
my sleep, allays a-prayin' for me, and her looks is
pleasant. She's dead long ago, and gone to glory. I
never heerd nuthin' certain about it; but, sir, I'm
thinkin' I sha'n't be here long now. Please the Lord,
she's waitin' for me. I'se ready to go.</p>
            <p>“Mebby, sir, you think this is all fool talk. I'm a
pore ignerant man, ef I is free, thank the Lord! Kin
you tell me, sir, ef you please, was it my mammy all
this time, shore enough? Or is I 'ceivin' mysef ? I see
you don't make
<pb id="alexa37" n="37"/>
fun of me, and you's the fust one I ever tole it all to.”</p>
            <p>“No, Archer,” I said, “I don't feel like laughing. I
could never laugh at a man for loving his mother.
What you saw I don't know; but one thing is sure,
that it is your mother's love, and your memory of
her, that has saved you.”</p>
            <p>“Thank you, sir; that comforts me and 'courages
me. We don't know much, nohow, but I'll go
along steadier for what you say. I'm gettin' powerful
weak, and my mammy is a-waitin' for me.”</p>
            <p>I left him sitting there. It was his last day of work.</p>
            <p>All of this may seem trivial, childlike, superstitious, but it is
illustrative of the uneducated negro character, when
sincere piety has taken possession of it. The strength
and weakness of the African nature as seen in
American slavery came from its implicitness of faith.
We may smile at it, but from it often came the most
excellent results. I have given the narrative in this
place, because it furnishes the key to Archer's
subsequent history,
<pb id="alexa38" n="38"/>
and shows the spirit of love and faith in which
he lived. A childlike or even childish faith may give
birth to the most manly character. Unbelief, however
learned, is barren of such fruit.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <pb id="alexa39" n="39"/>
          <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
          <head>LIFE IN MISSOURI.—1833-63</head>
          <p>THE life of Archer for the next thirty years
varied but little in its general tenor from
that of the majority of well-behaved slaves held
in bondage by kind masters. The treatment
of slaves in Missouri was perhaps exceptionally   
humane. All cruelty or “unnecessary”
severity was frowned upon by the whole community. 
The general feeling was against it.</p>
          <p>Archer's young master, Mr. Thomas Delaney, 
was not only kind and considerate, but he 
was personally attached to his servant, who was 
nursed at the same breast, and
had been his constant playmate in boyhood. He was
also under promise to his own mother and to Archer's
mother to do what was right by the boy.</p>
          <p>For three or four years, while in St. Louis,
Archer was hired out and worked in a brick-yard 
(Letcher &amp; Bobbs), at the end of which
time Mr. Delaney bought a farm in the western
part of St. Charles County, and moved there
<pb id="alexa40" n="40"/>
to live. Soon after being settled in his new home, he
married a lady from Louisiana, who brought him some
considerable property. About the same time, Archer
“took up” with a likely colored woman named Louisa,
and was regularly married to her with religious ceremony,
according to slavery usage in well-regulated Christian
families. Louisa belonged to a thrifty farmer named
Hollman, in the near neighborhood, on the border of St.
Charles and Warren Counties. This gentleman had
learned what a faithful fellow Archer was, and when, a
few years later, Mr. Delaney, who was any thing but
thrifty, concluded to move South, where his wife's
property was, he was easily induced to sell Archer at a
high price to his neighbor, particularly as neither of
them was willing to separate man and wife, to whom
several children had now been born. In fact, this was
Mr. Delaney's chief reason for selling Archer, to whom
he was more and more attached. It happened, too, that
Mrs. Delaney wanted the money, and took pains to
convince her husband that it would be wrong to
separate the family, and that “Archer would be sure to
run away if they did.” So, from these mixed motives, the sale
took place; and the slave husband and wife
<pb id="alexa41" n="41"/>
were comfortably settled in their cabin, with a
growing family of children, for more than twenty
happy years. Their master was a religious and
humane man. He looked upon slavery as a patriarchal
institution, sanctioned by divine law, in no way
inconsistent with the republican principles of a free
country, and that it was the only condition for which
the colored race were providentially fitted. A strange
creed,—but if all slave-owners had put it in practice as
kindly as he did, we might possibly in some small
degree understand the delusion. Even on his place,
however, the bad behavior of husband or wife, of
parent or child, was sometimes punished by “sending
the offender away,” which was a virtual decree of
divorce, and so recognized, not only by usage, but by
the deliberate decree of the churches.<ref id="ref1" n="1" rend="sc" target="note1" targOrder="U">1</ref></p>
          <note id="note1" n="1" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref1">1 See Appendix I.</note>
          <p>For Archer no such suffering was in store. He was
a faithful man, and was trusted accordingly. As the trust
was increased, so was the trustworthiness. He
became a sort of overseer, and, as he said, “Mr.
Hollman trusted me every way, and I couldn't do no other than 
what was right.” Some of his children behaved
badly, being over-indulged, and were “sent
<pb id="alexa42" n="42"/>
away;” but he didn't seem to blame his master for it.
The heart learns to bear inevitable burdens.</p>
          <p>But in all this time the political and social condition
of Missouri was gradually and rapidly changing.
The boldly proclaimed Free-Soil doctrines of Thomas
H. Benton were taking possession of the public mind.
As early as 1854, Francis P. Blair, jun., to whom the
whole nation owes a debt of gratitude which has never
been adequately acknowledged, stood up in the
General Assembly at Jefferson City, avowing himself
a disciple of that school. He plainly said (although it
seemed at the time like taking his life in his hand to
say it) “that all the best interests of Missouri
demanded the extinction of slavery; that, even if it
could be defended as right and profitable in States
farther south, it was simply a blight and a curse here.”
As time passed on, the truth of such ideas
appeared<sic>-</sic>more plainly, and the unprofitableness if not
the wrong of slavery was more generally admitted.</p>
          <p>The slaves themselves, or the more intelligent of
them, began to feel that there was something in the
air affecting their relation with their masters, and that
in some way or 
<pb id="alexa43" n="43"/>
other it might soon be changed altogether. Many of
them were removed, either with their
masters or by being sold to the Southern
States. Many ran away and found secure refuge in the
neighboring Free States and Territories. Even on the
best-managed farms a sense of uneasiness began to prevail, and the
uncertainty of slave property to be felt. The slaves
felt it no less than their masters.</p>
          <p>Then came the Kansas conflict, the great
struggle for the extension or restriction of slave
territory, the turning-point of true Republican
progress, by which the whole country was thrown
into a paroxysm of excitement. The terrible
complication of affairs as existing in Missouri,
especially on its western borders, was
not then, and is not yet, understood in the Eastern
States. Those on the right side, for freedom and
humanity, were guilty of many outrageous 
acts of wrong. The slavery advocates thereby
found excuses for themselves, and redoubled their
atrocities.</p>
          <p>John Brown of Ossawatomie, with his heroic
ideas of freedom and philanthropy, half blinded by
the wrongs he had suffered, forgot, he and his
followers, that to do evil that good may come is
under Christian law a forbidden policy.
<pb id="alexa44" n="44"/>
He said he would “fight the Devil with fire,” and did
so; but that is not the law of the Lord Jesus, though
God may sometimes overrule it for good.</p>
          <p>A true history of that fierce struggle will probably
never be written. There were no impartial judges, no
unprejudiced witnesses, to observe or record the
facts. Right-minded men could hardly tell where the
lines of right and wrong crossed each other. Living in
St. Louis the whole time and long before, and
knowing many of those engaged in the strife on either
side, I thought I saw both sides as they really were,
but, in truth, I saw neither. The complications of
action and motive, both right and wrong, were past
finding out. One thing, however, is sure: that the right
prevailed at last. Thank God for that.</p>
          <p>But it will be readily understood that in the
progress of a strife that affected, for good or ill, all
social interests, every household would be disturbed.
The more intelligent negroes, both free and slave,
were pretty well informed as to the tendency of
public thought, and, when the die was cast by the
election of Lincoln, a vague but strong hope was
everywhere spreading that the day of freedom was at
hand.</p>
          <pb id="alexa45" n="45"/>
          <p>At Archer's home, in St. Charles County, close by St.
Louis, the centre of Free-Soil strength, the current of
thought circulated freely. Trusted as he was, he heard
from day to day, from those who talked freely in his
presence, what was going on. He heard it without full
comprehension, but with a growing conviction that
freedom was his rightful inheritance, under the law of
Christ. He may have inherited something of that feeling
from his father Aleck, the story of whose hard fate he
well remembered. In fact, he had remained contented in
the condition of slavery more from religious motives, as
being the will of God, than from consent to human law.
At my first acquaintance with him I could not help
seeing this. He spoke of his former employer as <hi rend="italics">Mr.</hi>
Hollman, not master, and never used the latter term at
any subsequent time, except when speaking of his
Virginia boyhood life. He had pretty well outgrown the
spirit of bondage, and was already entered upon that of
freedom. He was quite prepared to do his part in
breaking his chains.</p>
          <p>Mr. Hollman was “a Union man with slavery,”
not without it. He was what afterwards came to be
called a “Haystack Secessionist,” 
<pb id="alexa46" n="46"/>
staying at home with his property, but
sympathizing with the South and helping it whenever
he could without too great risk. After Camp Jackson,
in St. Louis, was broken up (10th of May, 1861), and
Union troops were on their way to Jefferson City, he
joined a band to cut down or burn bridges and
encumber the roads, to intercept or delay their
progress. Archer knew of this, and began to make up
his mind that the time for action was near; but more
than a year passed before it came.</p>
          <p>In the month of February, 1863, he learned that a
party of men had sawed the timbers of a bridge in
that neighborhood, over which some companies of
Union troops were to pass, with view to their
destruction. At night he walked five miles to the
house of a well-known Union man, through whom
the intelligence and warning were conveyed to the
Union troops, who repaired the bridge before
crossing it.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <pb id="alexa47" n="47"/>
          <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
          <head>THE ESCAPE.</head>
          <p>IN some way the suspicion arose that Archer
was the “traitor.” Mr. Hollman did not believe
it, but promised to bring Archer before the committee
for examination. He threatened Archer, and
commanded him to keep in the house unless he
wanted to be shot, and the poor fellow saw plainly
what was coming. He was in a terrible dilemma,—
without money, without arms, with nobody to
consult, afraid to speak even to his own wife, in
momentary danger of being killed. What could he do?</p>
          <p>In the middle of the night he got up quietly from
his bed, and went out into the open air, cold and
cheerless in the wintry wind, “to ask the good Lord
what this pore forsaken nigger should do.” He walked
on for nearly a mile; and then turned to retrace his
steps. Then, to use his own words, “The Lord he
answered me! It came on me like a flash of lightnin'.
<hi rend="italics">I felt like I was stripped.</hi> Suthin' said inside
<pb id="alexa48" n="48"/>
of me, ‘What you goin' back for, like a fool idgyut, to
be shot or whipt to death like those fellers whipt
Sam last week? Go for your freedom, ef you dies for
it!’”</p>
          <p>So he held on his way right southward, until he had
crossed the river at early daylight, and then lay down
for a short sleep in the woods. Soon after starting
again, he fell in with a party of six or eight negro men,
who, like himself, were making for freedom; but at
noon they were overtaken by a band of mounted
pursuers, who compelled them to go back as
runaways, to a tavern on the south bank of the
Missouri, which they reached before dark. There the
party concluded to stay over night.
They were in high glee, for there was “a big prize”
offered for the runaways, whom they stowed safely
in a room up stairs, gave them cornbread and bacon
and some bad whiskey, and told them to take it easy
and no harm would come to them. Then they went
themselves into the bar-room for a grand carouse,
which they kept up till midnight. The negroes were
completely disheartened. They eat their cornbread
and bacon and drank all the whiskey, and, laying
themselves down on the floor, were soon fast asleep.</p>
          <pb id="alexa49" n="49"/>
          <p>All except Archer. He sat down on a box by the
window to think. He had noticed that box when he
first came into the room, for a strong cord was
wrapped round it several times, and he thought it
might help him to escape. So he unwrapped it, and
took the cover off the box, which was filled with
wood. He found a knot-hole, through which he put
one end of the rope, and tied it to a stick so as to keep
it from slipping when he should let himself down by
it, if he got the chance. Then he knelt down and said
his prayers, and “begun to have some hope.” He had
drunk no whiskey, but had eat all he could, and put “a
chunk of cornbread” in his pocket.</p>
          <p>As soon as it was all quiet down stairs,—“I
thote they would never be done swarin' and singin',”—
he softly got up and examined the windows. They
were nailed down tight; but fortunately he had a small
claw-hammer in his pocket,—“I allays had it with me,
and it was mighty good luck,”—and without any noise
he drew the nails carefully. It was a bright moonlight
night, clear and fresh, and he could see perfectly to do
his work. Waiting a few minutes to be sure that all
was quiet, he raised the window “soft and easy.”
“Then,” to use
<pb id="alexa50" n="50"/>
his own words, “I puts my head fru de winder to see
what kind of a chance I had. The moon it was shinin'
bright as day, and, ef you'd believe me, thar was the
biggest kind of a dawg a-walkin' backerd and forrerd,
and he jess looked up at me, a-kind o'winkin', as ef he
said, ‘<hi rend="italics">No, you don't!</hi>’ I had thote them slave-ketchers
had been mighty keerless, leavin' us up thar without a
watch, but now I onerstood it all. I sot down on the
box jess flustrated. I hadn't no more hope, not a mite.
Sure enough, the Lord had done forsook me. I leaned my head 
down on the winder-sill and cried like a chile. How long it was
I don't know, but I 'speck I cried myself asleep, for
when I looked up again I felt fresher and more cheery-like. 
The moon had gone down behind the trees, and
the shadders was black, but over to the east I seed the
fust little show of daylight. I put my
head out agin, and thar was the dawg settin' down and
watchin' of me. He knowed his business sure. There
didn't seem no way out of it, nohow.”</p>
          <p>But a way did open itself most unexpectedly, in
accord with the nature of dog and of man; for
suddenly he heard off in the woods, three or four
hundred yards away, the barking of a coon.
<pb id="alexa51" n="51"/>
The dog heard it too, and that was too much even for
his faithfulness. To tree that coo was his first and
most earnest vocation, and off he started as fast as his
legs would carry him. “Now's my chance,” said Archer to himself:
“the Lord pints the way.” He took strong hold of the
rope, dropped himself down gently to the ground.
The box was heavy, but so was Archer; and it
“wobbled,” and when he let go it gave a “ker-thump”
on the floor.</p>
          <p>He knew that this must wake up the slave-catchers,
and he slipped quickly round the corner of the house
in the shadow of it, and waited. Sure enough, the door
opened and one of the men came out. He looked up at
the window and saw the rope hanging down. Then he
heard the dog over in the woods, and called out to his
mates, “The niggers have got away, and the dog is after
them!” They all rushed out, not very clear-headed
after their night's carouse, and, without stopping to
look, “made tracks for the timber.” When Archer saw
this, negro-like he “couldn't help larfin, though
skeered to death, to see them men fooled so bad by
their own dawg.” But he wasted no time, and, keeping
the house between him and them, he ran “like a
skeered dawg,” until he
<pb id="alexa52" n="52"/>
was well out of sight before they could have
discovered their mistake. At about a half-mile's 
distance he came to some “slashes,
where it was all wet and mashy,” and he “put
right through the swamp so as to kill the scent.”
He was at that time close to the St. Louis
road; but it was getting light, so that he could
see the tavern that he had left, and he was
afraid to keep on. He found a place where the bushes
were thick, and lay down among
them so as to be completely concealed.  “Ef
you'd believe it,” he said, “I dropt right off
asleep like a chile in its cradle.  I was jess
tired out and mose dead.”</p>
          <p>His hiding-place was well chosen, for when
he waked, about ten o'clock, he peeped through 
the bushes and saw the “slave-ketchers and
their gang” on their way from the tavern to
the ferry-boat. They had failed or had not
attempted to trace him. Still he was afraid
to start out on the open road, for some of the
men might be around, watching for him; and,
although he was “drefful hungry,” he “kept
right thar until dark came.” “As soon as it
was clear dark I got a-goin', and walked steady
all night along the road, till I come to whar
the houses begin outside of St. Louis. The
<pb id="alexa53" n="53"/>
daylight was jess comin' on, and I didn't know
what to do nor whar to go, but jess loafed
along until some how or another I struck that
market-house close to Bumont Street. I asked
the butcher-man, that was a Dutchman, for a
job. He asked me ef I was a runaway nigger.
I tole him I 'speck so. He larfed and said,
‘You wait thar and I'll give you a chance.’ In
about an hour he call me and said thar was a
lady who wanted me to take her basket home. I
looked at the lady, and she seemed so kind and
pleasant that I knowed she wouldn't be hard on a
poor feller like me; and then when she spoke up and
said, ‘Uncle, if you will take this basket home for me,
it isn't far, I'll give you a dime and a good breakfast,’ it
seemed like a angel was a-callin' of me.” Nor was 
he far from right.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <pb id="alexa54" n="54"/>
          <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
          <head>THE CAPTURE.</head>
          <p>IN the month of February, 1863, I was living with
my family at Beaumont Place, in what was then
the western suburbs of St. Louis. It was a lovely
spot, containing about four acres, with a grove of
forest-trees, a small but choice orchard, a vegetable-garden 
and lawn, with an old-fashioned one-story
farmhouse upon it. There were long porches, a
wide hall, and rambling outhouses, that made the
homestead altogether capacious enough for a large
family. In the months of April and May, with
trees in full glory, it seemed like a sort of paradise,
in contrast with the noisy and disturbed city. It
had formerly been occupied by one of my oldest
and dearest friends, Dr. William Beaumont of the
United States army, a man of great skill and wide
celebrity, whose death I do not yet cease to
mourn. Previously to his occupancy, it was the
residence of Gov. Hamilton Gamble, by whom the
house was built.</p>
          <pb id="alexa55" n="55"/>
          <p>We had ourselves moved there in May, 1861, just
after the war of the Rebellion had broken out. In St.
Louis it was indeed a civil war, a fratricidal strife. I
well remember when the news came that the United
States ship “Star of the West” had been fired upon,
and Fort Sumter attacked by Beauregard (I am glad
that it is not an American name), in Charleston harbor,
what intense excitement and animosities were aroused.
The nearest neighbors were set against each other, and
brothers against brothers. Parents and children,
husband and wife, were enlisted on different sides. I
had taken my stand firmly and plainly, and, in my
peaceful way, had enlisted for the war. After having
done my poor best to prevent it, there was no
alternative but to fight it through. Many of our friends
advised us not to go outside of the city to live, as
being unsafe in such a disturbed condition of affairs:
and before we had been in our new home many days
we were half of that opinion ourselves; for Camp
Jackson, organized to favor State secession, was but a
half-mile from us, and, when broken up by General
Lyon and the Home Guards, the rifle-bullets came
close to our fences. Afterwards the large buildings
known as “Uhrig's Cave” were occupied
<pb id="alexa56" n="56"/>
by volunteer troops under General B. Gratz
Brown. In their clumsy manœuvres and musketry
discharges, the balls whistled across our grounds to
the no inconsiderable danger and discomfort of the
family. Yet through all the four years of strife I
walked to and from the city at all hours of day and
night, generally alone, without the slightest annoyance
or cause of fear.</p>
          <p>The place was in a sadly neglected condition when
we went there; and all we could do in the first years
was to clean up the grounds, trim the trees, and make
things generally look as if somebody lived there. But at
the end of the second year, my boys and myself
thought we must have a garden and other
improvements, which prompted us to the extravagance
of a man-servant, if we could find one at low wages.
Accordingly, when my wife went to market one
morning, at the corner of Jefferson Avenue and
Market Street, she inquired of the butcher if he knew
of any colored man who wanted such a place. He
answered, “Yes, madam, I think I do. That boy
standing there came to-day, about two hours ago, and
seems clever and willing. It would be charity to
employ him. I'll tell him to take your basket to your
house, and you can
<pb id="alexa57" n="57"/>
see what you think of him.” So he called the “boy,” being a
man of full fifty years, who came forward with an uneasy,
timid look, but was ready enough to take the basket and go
with the lady. She spoke to him once or twice on the way,
and he gradually got courage as he looked at her, as well he
might. When they were inside the gate, he glanced round
with a brightening face and said, “Did I onerstand, madam,
that you is wanting a man to take keer of this place?”
She answered, “Yes, can you tell me of one?” He looked
at her earnestly, with the peculiar expression of the
negro face, keeping his eyes steadily upon her while his
head rolled round, and answered beseechingly, “I should
like sech a place oncommon well myself, ef you please,
madam, and I'd serve you faithful.” Following the lady to
the house, he waited in one of the outbuildings, where my
son Thomas went to see him and find out what he could
do.</p>
          <p>“Take care of horse and 
cow?”—“Yes, sir.”—
“Keep the grass and trees in good order, and lay out a
garden?”—“Yes, sir, I kin.”—
“Can you plough?”—“Plough, sir! why, my name's for 
ploughin'. In fac', sir, I'se a farm hand, and there ain't
nothin' 'bout a farm that I
<pb id="alexa58" n="58"/>
don't know, and ef your father tries me he'll be
satisfied sure.”</p>
          <p>As to who he was and where he came from, he was
rather shy. His name was “Aleck, and he didn't
edzackly belong to the city,”—that was all he would
say. He was shown into the kitchen, where the good-natured 
Irish cook put before him, as she said,
enough breakfast for three men, but he eagerly eat it
all. Poor fellow! he seemed half famished.</p>
          <p>In about half an hour I went down to see what I could
make of him. He studied my face very closely,
keeping all expression out of 
his own, for several minutes; but by the instinctive
perception which the negro seems to have,
just as the dog has it, he saw that I was not likely to
betray him, and soon opened his mind more freely.
He had come—carefully avoiding the word “runaway”—
from his old home up in the State, because of some
disturbance there. He left without telling anybody
where he was going. He was sometimes called Aleck,
but his right name was Archer Alexander. All he
wanted was a quiet place to work. He would take just
what wages I pleased, and he “jess wanted to keep
close to his self.”</p>
          <p>Evidently a fugitive slave, one of the thousands
<pb id="alexa59" n="59"/>
who, with or without reason, had taken their
chance for freedom. The events of the previous years
in Missouri had shaken society to its centre. More
than sixty battles or skirmishes had taken place in the
State beside local strifes, resulting in over five
thousand killed and wounded, so that the bitterness of
war was everywhere felt. On every farm and in every
household the possibility of emancipation was
discussed, and its almost certainty began to appear.
General Frémont's proclamation of freedom to all
slaves of rebel masters, although unfortunately and
unwisely revoked by President Lincoln, only
foreshadowed what was coming. Martial law, extended
over the State, practically placed all fugitive slaves
under protection of the military authorities. No one
but a loyal master could successfully reclaim a
fugitive, and then only under regular civil process.
Such was the condition of things in the spring of 1863,—
unsettled, revolutionary, with nothing clearly
defined, neither slave nor slave-holder having any rights
which they felt bound mutually to respect. But the
whole tendency was towards freedom, and all
thoughtful persons saw that it must there reasonably
end.</p>
          <p>When the fugitive Archer had disclosed the
<pb id="alexa60" n="60"/>
facts, therefore, I was not a little puzzled what to do.
He said his master was “the worst kind
of Secesh,”and had helped to burn down bridges
with his own hands to stop Union troops, though he
had never enlisted; but I had only his word for it. I
had always been an advocate for obedience to law,
and prided myself upon it, though an equal advocate
for freedom. When the fugitive-slave law had been
enacted by Congress, that great judicial blindness of
the South, I had said openly in the pulpit that I, for
one, could not obey it, but should be ready to bear the
penalty of paying the price of the non-surrendered
slave or of the adjudged imprisonment. What, then,
was I to do? I told him to stay for the present, and I
would let him know by evening whether he could
have the place permanently.</p>
          <p>Accordingly I went at once to the provost-marshal's
office, where I found an old friend, Lieutenant-Colonel 
Dick, in command, and told him the case. He
said he could do nothing to interfere with the civil law
in its regular process, but could secure me from
violent intrusion, so that the man should have
whatever advantages the mixed condition of civil and
martial laws could rightly afford. That was
<figure id="ill60" entity="eliot60"><p>OLD JAIL, FORMERLY AT THE CORNER OF SIXTH AND CHESTNUT STREETS,<lb/>
TO WHICH ARCHER WAS TAKEN.—Page 61.</p></figure>
<pb id="alexa61" n="61"/>
all I wanted, and he gave me the following permit:—</p>
          <q direct="unspecified">
            <text>
              <body>
                <div1>
                  <p>The colored man named Archer Alexander, supposed
to be the slave of a rebel master, is hereby permitted to
remain in the service of W. G. Eliot until legal right to
his services shall be established by such party, if any, as
may claim them. Not to exceed thirty days unless extended.</p>
                  <closer><signed>F. A. DICK, <hi rend="italics"> Lt. Col., Prov. Mar. Gen.</hi></signed> 
<dateline>FEB. 28, 1863.</dateline></closer>
                </div1>
              </body>
            </text>
          </q>
          <p>Returning home, I told Archer that he could stay
at work until his master legally claimed him, and one
of the outhouses was made comfortable for his use. I
doubt if there was a happier man than he in St.
Louis when he heard the decision. He went right to
work, and by the end of two or three weeks the
whole family were attached to him. He was quiet,
gentle, diligent, and sufficiently intelligent. The
stable, garden, and the whole grounds soon felt the
difference. In fact, he was one of the very best
specimens of the negro race I had ever known, and I
began to think if I couldn't in some way secure for
him a legal right to freedom. So I asked him more
about himself, the name of his master, where he had
lived, and what made him run away. He told me,
among other things, that Judge Barton Bates
<pb id="alexa62" n="62"/>
and family knew his people, and had often been at his
master's house. I then went to Judge Bates, who said
that Archer's master was a good Christian man,
always kind to his “hands,” and that he would most
likely do what was just and right, though he “was not
<hi rend="italics">particularly</hi> what one would call a <hi>loyal man.</hi>” He
promised to write to him at once, and give him my
message; viz., that Archer was at my place, and that I
was willing to pay his full “market value” for sake of
setting him free.
I told the judge that I would go as high as six
hundred dollars if necessary; but he answered that it
would be twice too much, as things were.</p>
          <p>The following is the letter he sent, a copy of
which he gave to me a few days after:—
<q direct="unspecified"><text><body><div1><opener><salute>MR.—.</salute></opener><p>SIR,—A gentleman of this city to-day stated to
me that he would like to buy your man Archer, or
Archie, if it could be done for a small sum, in order to
emancipate him. He states that Archie is determined
not to return to you, and that he believes he could not
be compelled to return. If you choose to sell him, and
will inform me of the amount that you will take for
him, I will see that the gentleman is informed of it. I do
not presume to advise or recommend any thing in the
premises, and have no further agency in the matter.</p><closer><salute>Yours, etc.,</salute>
<signed><name>BARTON BATES</name></signed></closer></div1></body></text></q></p>
          <pb id="alexa63" n="63"/>
          <p>The cautious wording of this letter shows the
delicacy of the subject handled, at that time. No
written answer came, but it served perhaps to give a
hint to Archer's master where to find him.</p>
          <p>After this I told Archer that I was trying hard to
keep him, and, in fact, my mind was easy on the
subject. I had no doubt that my offer would be
accepted, as it would have been, under all the
circumstances, by any reasonable man. But human
passion is uncalculating of interest or right, and the
verbal answer as reported to me, I hope incorrectly,
was “that he didn't mean to play into the hands of
any Yankee Abolitionist; that he'd have the nigger
yet, and take it out of his black hide.”</p>
          <p>As time passed I became anxious, and told Archer
to keep close about the house. The children were
always following him when at work. He was very
kind to them, and by the end of the month we were
all as earnest to keep him as he was to stay. And so
it came about, but not as I hoped and expected.</p>
          <p>One lovely day, the last but one for which my
provost-marshal protection was good, at about ten
o'clock, I went out as usual to attend to my regular
duties at “Washington University,”
<pb id="alexa64" n="64"/>
and as I walked towards the Locust-street
gate I stopped a moment to look at
Archer with his plough, and the children at his
heels. The plough he had found somewhere on
the premises, had rigged it up in some fashion,
so that my carryall-horse and harness could be
put to service, and was busy to his heart's content. 
The two boys, Christy and Ed., seven
and five years old, and the one-year-old baby,
sister Rose, in the arms of Ellen her nurse, were
the company. As they came towards me, and,
reaching the limit of the garden lot, the horse
was turned and the plough swung round with a
scientific flourish, Archer bowed, and said,
“Good-morning, sir,” looking as happy as freedom 
could make him. Then they pushed on
to make another furrow, the children shouting 
with pure enjoyment; and with the fruit-trees 
in full blossom, the birds singing in the
branches, it was as pretty a rural picture as
one can well imagine, close to a crowded and
restless city. Looking just beyond and adjoining 
my grounds, I saw in the barrack-rooms
of Uhrig's Cave the Union troops at the windows, 
within almost speaking distance, and the grand
old flag flying over them. That gave me a feeling of
satisfaction and safety.</p>
          <pb id="alexa65" n="65"/>
          <p>As I lifted the gate-latch, a butcher-built man, whip
in hand, accosted me, and asked if I hadn't a calf for
sale, as he saw a cow in the pasture. He had a hang-dog, 
sneaking look, not in keeping with the day nor
with my thoughts, and I answered him curtly that I
had not, nor was I likely to have. At the same time I
observed a close-covered wagon and two men
standing by it, just across the street, with a rather
suspicious appearance, and I paused for a minute; but
as the butcher-looking man joined them and they
seemed to be getting ready to move, and as I was in
haste, I walked off with Hamilton's “Metaphysics”
under my arm, and my mind intent upon the “law of
the conditioned“” and “excluded middle,”—how to
explain it to a dozen not too eager youths, especially
when I only half understood it myself.</p>
          <p>At about one o'clock I returned, and found the
whole family in terrified condition. The boys were
crying, the nurse half distracted, and my wife calm, as
she always is in troubled times, but with a
suppressed excitement that startled me. They thought
Archer was killed. As soon as I was well out of sight,
the three men had come in, with clubs in hand, and,
getting close to where Archer was working, said, “Is
<pb id="alexa66" n="66"/>
your name Archie?”—”Yes, sir, I've no 'casion to deny
my name.“—”Well, let go that horse, you runaway
rascal, and come with us.“—”No, sir, I'se here under
pertection of the law."</p>
          <p>He had no sooner said the word than one of them
raised his bludgeon and knocked him down with a
blow on the head. The others pulled out knives and
pistols, and kicked him in the face. Then they
handcuffed him and forcibly dragged the helpless man
to their wagon, pushed him in, and drove off at the
top of speed towards the city. The children and nurse
ran to the house to tell the story. That was all I could
learn. They had caught him, sure enough, and had
probably got him far beyond my reach already. But, if
so, it should not be for want of effort, on my part, to
rescue him.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <pb id="alexa67" n="67"/>
          <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
          <head>THE RESCUE.</head>
          <p>FORTUNATELY the military protection was still in
force, and, without taking off my hat or waiting for
dinner, I started with quick step for the provost-marshal's 
office; no more abstractions in my mind, nor
“law of the conditioned,” but a plain duty to rescue
the captive. Captain Dwight, who was on duty, heard my
statement with great indignation.
The nephew of Catherine Sedgwick was no friend of
slavery. He looked at the “permit,” questioned me
closely, and then exclaimed, “I'll show these fellows
what it is to defy this
office!” Two detectives were summoned, one of them
named John Eagan, to whom I shall
always feel grateful; and Captain Dwight said, “I
want you to listen to Dr. Eliot's statement.” I
repeated it carefully. “Now,” said he, “have
you got your pistols? me see them. Six-shooters?
Well, are they loaded? All right.
Now, one of you go down to the river and watch
<pb id="alexa68" n="68"/>
every boat that leaves or is ready to leave.—
You, Eagan, go with this gentleman to his house, find out
all you can, follow up the hunt until you take those
scoundrels and release the man, placing him again
where he was taken from.”</p>
          <p>“What shall we do, captain, if they refuse to give
him up?”</p>
          <p>“Shoot them on the spot.”</p>
          <p>“We are to understand that, Captain Dwight,
shoot them on the spot?”</p>
          <p>“Yes, shoot them dead if necessary. Here is your
written authority to take the men.”</p>
          <p>“All right, sir,” said Eagan: “we understand.”</p>
          <p>Eagan then walked out with me. It seemed ten
miles instead of two to the gate where the men had
spoken to me in the morning. While I was describing
them and their wagon, one of my neighbors, Mr.
Kelley, crossed the street and said, “I can tell you
something about that. One of the men had a
policeman's star on his coat, and the wagon was a
numbered city wagon. The poor devil was mauled to
death, and they drove off quick. I heard one of 'em
say ‘jail.’ I was afraid to interfere, and so were the
soldiers, because of the star.”</p>
          <pb id="alexa69" n="69"/>
          <p>Eagan took down the wagon number, and, quietly
turning to me, said, “Make yourself easy, sir. I'll
have them before night. They can't get away. Where
shall I bring your man?”</p>
          <p>“I shall be at the Western Sanitary Commission
rooms, No. 11 5th Street, opposite the court-house,
until ten o'clock this evening; after that, here.”</p>
          <p>“Oh, I'll have him long before that.” And so we
separated, my mind a little more at ease, but with
only a half-hope at best.</p>
          <p>At nine o'clock in the evening I was at the Sanitary
Commission rooms, with Mr. Yeatman and other
members, busy in opening several boxes of new
garments just received from No. 13 Somerset Street,
Boston.<ref id="ref2" n="2" rend="sc" target="note2" targOrder="U">*</ref> We were in urgent need of them at the
hospitals, and the rooms were in a blaze of light, so
that we could work to advantage. Some one knocked
loudly at the street door, and, looking up, I saw the
two police-officers coming in with a colored man
between them. It was Archer. He came forward, half
blinded by the sudden glare of gaslight, and
completely dazed, for he had not known where they
were taking him.
<note id="note2" n="2" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref2">* See Appendix II.</note>
<pb id="alexa70" n="70"/>
I came from behind the boxes, and, as he suddenly
caught sight of me, he stopped, and, raising both his
hands, exclaimed, “O Lord God! it's all right,” and
sank down on the floor helpless. “O Lord Jesus, it
was you that done it!”</p>
          <p>It seems, as I learned afterwards, that Eagan,
having some clew in his search for Archer's captors,
had traced them to the city jail, and then, posting his
companion at a little distance outside, went into the
outer office of the jail on Sixth Street, as if he had
business there, and “in a promiscuous manner” began
to talk to the jailer. The men whom he was looking
for were right there, sitting at a table, drinking. They
evidently had no fear of being followed, and perhaps
thought they had the law on their side, for they were
talking about their successful day's work. Eagan
listened for a few minutes, and then, telling the jailer
who he was, and that he had a military warrant to
take those men, he stepped up to them and said,
“Where is that nigger you are talking about?”—
“Oh, he's in the jail there all right. He's 
off for Kentucky tomorrow. You never saw 
any thing slicker than the way we got him, right 
under the nose of that little abolition preacher. 
He was fooled completely.”—“Well,” said
<pb id="alexa71" n="71"/>
Eagan, “that man was under military protection, and
I want him. And, what's more, I've got a provost-marshal's 
warrant to take you: so come along.”</p>
          <p>They started to run, for, half tipsy as they were,
they saw that they “had given themselves away.”
But just as they were getting out of the door, Eagan
drew his pistol and exclaimed, “You are dead men if
you take another step!”
Just then the other police-officer came forward, and,
seeing that they were trapped, they gave themselves
up quietly. Eagan told the
jailer to keep Archer safe until his return, and then
took the captors down to the military prison, 5th and
Myrtle Streets, where they were locked up for the
night, not a little chop-fallen, and cursing their luck.</p>
          <p>The officers then went back to the jail, and
found Archer handcuffed, lying on the stone floor of a
cell, dead asleep. They pushed him roughly, and as he
raised his battered head, only half awake, they said, 
“Come, get up here, old man, you've got to go out of
this.”—“Lord, massa, what you goin' to do wid
me? I'se mose dead, anyhow.”—“Never you mind,
you've got to go, and that quick. Come, get up.” He
rose with difficulty. They took off
<pb id="alexa72" n="72"/>
his handcuffs and led him out into the dark without a
word of explanation. It would seem as if they meant
to give him a sort of dramatic surprise; at least, that
was the effect. The city jail was at that time only one
block distant from the Commission rooms, and when
in less than five minutes, not knowing whether he
was in the hands of friends or enemies, he came into
the strong light of safety, it was to him like passing
from the blackness of despair into the shelter of
heaven.</p>
          <p>“Why, Archer,” I said to him, “you'd clean given
yourself up for lost, hadn't you?”—“No, sir,” he
answered solemnly, with tears running down his
bruised and swollen face. “No, sir, I hadn't quite give
up. I trusted in the Lord. And <hi rend="italics">I sort a knowed you'd
follow me up and find me.</hi>” By ten o'clock he was
quietly in his bed at his usual quarters, and I thanked
God with all my heart that the captors were captured
and their prisoner free.</p>
          <p>The next day I obtained, by Captain Dwight's
advice, an unconditional protection for Archer, which
placed him in perfect safety, so far as he could be in
that uncertain time. I offered to pay the police-officers 
for their efficient services, having obtained
permission to do so;
<pb id="alexa73" n="73"/>
but Eagan said, “No. They had done no more than
their duty, and should be glad to do as much every
day.”<ref id="ref3" n="3" rend="sc" target="note3" targOrder="U">*</ref> The captors of Archer were released as
having acted ignorantly under the civil law, not
knowing that he held a provost-marshal's permit.</p>
          <note id="note3" n="3" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref3">* I am glad to record the name of this faithful
officer. His death occurred in the month of May, 1885,
and I visited him at his home a few days previous to
that event. He was a devout Catholic, an honest man, a
good citizen. Some years ago, as his son informed me,
he held in his custody a very wealthy man, a noted gambler, 
charged with aggravated crime. The prisoner
offered him large sums of money, up to fifty thousand
dollars, if he would connive at his escape and suppress
the evidence. John Eagan refused to do it, preferring to
remain comparatively poor, but thoroughly honest.</note>
          <p>In speaking of it the next day, Archer said to me, 
“I don't feel hard against them, sir, though
they was rough and most killed me. But what hurt
my feelins the most was to see that young man that
showed them the way to me. I've toted him many a
time about the field on my back when I was ploughin'
and doin' my work on his father's place, whar was
my home. I didn't think he could 'a'done it, sir. It
wa'n't right in him, nohow. But the Lord forgive him for it.
I'se free.”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <pb id="alexa74" n="74"/>
          <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
          <head>SAFETY.</head>
          <p>BUT notwithstanding the full protection papers
which I held, the state of social and political affairs
was such that there could be no feeling of security to
any runaway slave. Missouri was still a slave State,
and the conflict between civil and martial law was at
its height. I therefore made one more attempt to quiet
the “legal claim to Archer's services” by getting a bill
of sale from his master, and addressed the following
letter to him:—</p>
          <q direct="unspecified">
            <text>
              <body>
                <div1>
                  <opener>—,<hi rend="italics">Esq.</hi></opener>
                  <p>SIR,—About a week ago I sent a message to you by
Judge Bates, that your man Archie was at my house, and
asking you to set a price on him. Since that time he
was forcibly taken from my place, but immediately
brought back by order of the provost-marshal, under
whose protection he has been since he first came to
me, more than a month since. He has now papers which
will protect him as long as martial law continues. But I
prefer to obtain full legal title to his services if I can,
<pb id="alexa75" n="75"/>
and am still ready to buy him from you if you will fix a
fair price, under the circumstances. I should emancipate
him on the day of purchase. As to the price, I am 
willing to leave it to Governor Gamble and Judge Bates.
My desire has been and is to do what is right in the
premises. </p>
                  <closer><salute>Yours, etc.,</salute>
<signed><name>W. G. ELIOT.</name></signed></closer>
                </div1>
              </body>
            </text>
          </q>
          <p>This note was sent through Governor Archibald
Gamble, but no answer or notice of it ever came in
return.</p>
          <p>Our anxiety, therefore, continued, and we thought
it best for Archer to be removed to a free State until
the evidently coming freedom was fully established
as the law of the land. As soon, therefore, as he was
recovered from his hurts, I gave him a complete outfit
of new clothes, which he had fairly earned, and took
him by steamer to Alton, Ill. There he obtained a
good place as farm-hand at the country home of one
of my best friends, William H. Smith, whose hand
and heart are and always have been open for every
good work. Archer served him faithfully for six or
seven months, at liberal wages, and when ready to
return he had a hundred and twenty dollars to deposit
in the Provident Savings Bank. But he had been
anxious to get back to Missouri: for he looked to my
place as home, and it was nearer
<pb id="alexa76" n="76"/>
to his wife and children. As soon, therefore, as things
were sufficiently settled under the State gradual
emancipation law, enacted June, 1863, he returned to
Beaumont Place, theoretically, 
though not quite yet practically, on
free soil. I still held myself ready to pay
ransom-money to his master, to give perfect
rest to the poor fellow's body and soul, but
the opportunity was not offered. We had
all by this time become so attached to him,
and felt so great respect for his manly, patient
character, that we would have spared neither
cost nor pains to secure his freedom beyond
all possible contingency. He settled down
quietly to his work, earning his wages well,
and taking care of every thing on the four-acre
lot as if it were all his own. I never knew a
man, white or black, more thoroughly Christian, 
according to the measure of light enjoyed,
in all conduct and demeanor. He went regularly 
with me to the Church of the Messiah, of
which I was pastor, and where I obtained for
him the place of organ-blower. Every month
he took his place with us at the Communion-table. 
But generally he kept close at home.
He mixed very little with “his people,”—
that is, the colored people of the city,—and
<pb id="alexa77" n="77"/>
scarcely ever went out alone, because he was
not yet quite over the fear of being again kidnapped.
But he was contented, happy, and
grateful.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <pb id="alexa78" n="78"/>
          <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
          <head>LOUISA.</head>
          <p>FROM time to time Archer had word from his old
home, through Germans who lived in the
neighborhood, and early in November (1863) he
managed to send messages to his wife Louisa. He
wanted her to find out if they would sell her at a low
price, and sent word that he had money to pay for
her if they would. One day he brought a long letter
from her for me to read to him. It had been dictated,
and was in a lady's handwriting, as follows:—</p>
          <q direct="unspecified">
            <text>
              <body>
                <div1>
                  <opener>
                    <dateline>NAYLOR'S STORE, Nov. 16, 1863.</dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>MY DEAR HUSBAND,—I received your letter
yesterday, and lost no time in asking Mr. Jim if
he would sell me, and what he would take for me. He
flew at me, and said I would never get free only at the
point of the Baynot, and there was no use in my ever
speaking to him any more about it. I don't see how I
can ever get away except you get soldiers to take me
from the house, as he is watching me night and day. If I
can get away I will, but the people here are all afraid to
take me away. He is always abusing Lincoln, and calls
him an
<pb id="alexa79" n="79"/>
old Rascoll. He is the greatest rebel under heaven. It is a
sin to have him loose. He says if he had hold of Lincoln
he would chop him up into mincemeat. I had good
courage all along until now, but now I am almost heart-broken. 
Answer this letter as soon as possible.</p>
                  <closer><salute>I am your affectionate wife,</salute>
<signed><name>LOUISA ALEXANDER.</name></signed></closer>
                </div1>
              </body>
            </text>
          </q>
          <p>I asked him what he was going to do about it, and
he said he'd just seen a German farmer that lived close
by where Louisa was, who said he'd manage to get her
away if she had anywhere to come to. “You see, sir,
we've been married most thirty years, and we'se had
ten chilluns, and we want to get togedder mighty
bad.” He said that three of the children, one of them a
married woman, had already managed to get to St.
Louis; and the youngest, Nellie, was with her mother,
and would come too. His point was to know whether,
if they <hi rend="italics">should</hi> get off, they might come there to stay
with him. “They wouldn't give no trouble, and there's
plenty of room, and they could take keer of
theirselves.” I answered him that, if they were well
treated, it would probably be best for them to stay
where they were; in a few months freedom was
almost sure, and then they could come and go as they
pleased; but if they
<pb id="alexa80" n="80"/>
came I should not drive them away, though they'd
have to take their chances. He said he knew that, but
the German had told him, “Louisa was having the
roughest kind of a time, and, now that they
suspicioned her, her life wasn't safe if they got mad at
her.” There it rested for a week or two, when it was
reported one Sunday morning at breakfast-table, that
Louisa and Nellie had arrived just before daylight.</p>
          <p>The German farmer had kept his word. He had told
Louisa that on Saturday evening, soon after sunset, he
should be driving his wagon along the lane near her
cabin, and that if they could manage to get down
there, he would pick them up, and put them on the
road. So at dusk they strolled down that way
separately, without bonnets or shawls, so as not to
attract notice. Nellie was thirteen years old, a smart
girl, and well understood the
plan. Meeting at a place agreed upon, they only had
to wait two or three minutes before their deliverer
came. He was driving an ox-team, his wagon being
loaded with corn shucks and stalks loosely piled.
Under these, arranged for the purpose, he made them
crawl, and covered them up with skilful carelessness,
so that they
<pb id="alexa81" n="81"/>
had breathing-place, but were completely concealed.
He then drove on very leisurely, walking by the oxen,
with good moonlight to show the way. When they
had gone about a mile, one of their master's family, on
horseback, overtook them, and asked the farmer if he
had seen “two niggers, a woman and a gal,” anywhere
on the road. He stopped his team a minute, so as “to
talk polite,” and said, “Yes, I saw them at the
crossing, as I came along, standing, and looking scared-like,
as if they were waiting for somebody; <hi rend="italics">but I have
not seen them since.</hi>” Literal truth is sometimes the
most ingenious falsehood.</p>
          <p>The man looked up and down the road, turned
quickly, and went back to see if he could find the
trace in another direction.</p>
          <p>The farmer, chuckling to himself, drove on as fast
as his oxen could travel, and before daylight was at
the place where he had promised to bring his human
freight. Archer paid him twenty dollars for his night's
work.</p>
          <p>After all, it was but small loss to the master, for on
the eleventh day of January, 1865, the immediate and
total Emancipation Law was passed by the State
Convention at St. Louis, and Missouri was a free
State. I was present
<pb id="alexa82" n="82"/>
at that grand consummation, and remember it with
unspeakable gratitude. (See <hi rend="italics">Am. Cyclop.,</hi> art. “Missouri.”)</p>
          <p>But Louisa's coming brought peace of mind to
Archer, who seemed to hold his wife and children in
as tender regard as if he had been free from the
beginning. Two others of his daughters soon found
him out. He also learned of the death on the battle-field 
of his son Tom (named for his young master,
Thomas Delaney), who had enlisted in the Union
army, among the first colored recruits, and was killed
in a brave charge by negro troops at Tilton Head. I
subsequently obtained full record of his enlistment
and services and death, and, on application to the
proper authorities, his back pay and bounty-money
were paid to Archer. Very proud was he that his son
had served and died in the cause of freedom. “I
couldn't do it myself,” he said, “but I thank the Lord
my boy did it.”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <pb id="alexa83" n="83"/>
          <head>CHAPTER IX.</head>
          <head>FREEDOM AND REST.</head>
          <p>FOR two years after the war of secession had ended,
Archer remained in my service; he then set up
housekeeping for himself. His wife, Louisa, had died
nearly a year before, under somewhat peculiar
circumstances. She became anxious to visit her old
home “to get her things;” that is, her bed and
clothes, and little matters of furniture, that “Mr. Jim”
sent word she could get <hi rend="italics">if she would come for them.</hi>
We advised her not to go, as they were not worth
much, and there might be some risk involved;
but she “honed” for them, and went. Two
days after getting there, she was suddenly
taken sick and died. The particulars could
not be learned, but “the things” were sent
down by the family. Archer mourned for her
not quite a year, and then married a young
woman named Judy, twenty-five years old, with
whom he moved to his own hired house, feeling,
no doubt, that it was one more step of freedom.</p>
          <pb id="alexa84" n="84"/>
          <p>Their housekeeping was on a very small scale. A
good part of his earnings came from my family; and
there were times of close poverty, though never of
distress. A long life of slavery had unfitted him for
the sharp competitions of freedom in a city life, and
in many things he was only a grown-up child. As a
mere matter of physical comfort, his slavery days
were better, his work less wearing, his daily bread
more easily earned, his sickness better cared for. But
he felt the manliness of freedom, and was happy in it.
He used it, too, without abusing it, was strictly
temperate, kept out of debt, and was always ready to
help others, even beyond the limit of prudence.
Shiftless and worthless negroes imposed upon him,
and not a few claimed kindred to himself or wife. But
he had in his humble sphere a dignified and happy
life, and was never unfaithful to his Christian faith
and principles.</p>
          <p>At the funeral of his second wife, Judy, whose
death occurred only a year before his own, when I
was conducting the services, I observed, in the lap of
one of the colored women attending, a child about
three years old, perfectly white and very pretty, and
inquired afterwards whose it was.</p>
          <pb id="alexa85" n="85"/>
          <p>It appeared that three months before, the little one
had been left entirely destitute by her mother, who
had, on her death-bed, given her up by a written
paper to Archer and Judy. She was therefore, after a
manner, their legally adopted child, and Archer was
sadly at loss how to provide for her. I assumed care
of her, and Archer had the satisfaction, some months
before his death, of seeing her well provided for in a
home where she would be educated and trained for a
useful life. I also learned concerning her that on her
mother's side she could claim descent from a very
respectable Scotch family; but unfortunately the
number of marriage ceremonies had not kept quite
equal pace with the genealogical steps, and the waif
was unacknowledged.</p>
          <p>Six months afterwards, when she was under care of
a lady who treated her with a mother's tenderness,
Archer asked permission to visit her. He went with
his negro heart full of love and pride, expecting a
loving welcome. But it happened that in all those
months the little one, who was only four years old,
had seen no colored persons, and she had quite
forgotten her kind benefactor. So when he came into
the room with a broad smile, saying to
<pb id="alexa86" n="86"/>
her, “Oh, here she is! Come to your old daddy!” she
did not know him, but, half scared, made up a lip, and
ran for shelter to her lady protector. Then she turned
and looked at him with big eyes, with no shadow of
recollection. He paused, tears ran down his cheeks,
and he soon left quite heavy-hearted. “It cut into me,”
he said when I next saw him: “it cut sharp into me
like a knife. My feelins was hurt drefful bad. She'd
clean done forgot me, and was skeered at me. Many a
time I had hugged her in my bosom. But I ain't of
much account, nohow.”</p>
          <p>It was a real grief to him, poor fellow, and I cannot
think of it now without pain. He ended by saying, “I
thank the Lord she's got good friends, and will grow
up to be a lady.” It is a small incident, too trifling
perhaps for mention; but to that humble, loving heart
it was a real and abiding grief.</p>
          <p>The remainder of Archer's troubled life was
marked by sadness and suffering, without possibility
of relief. The infirmities of age were upon him, and an
internal rupture prevented him from any work except
what a child might have done. At a time when I was
absent from the city with my family, he had a severe
attack,
<pb id="alexa87" n="87"/>
and it became absolutely necessary for him to be
taken to the city hospital for the best surgical 
treatment. At this the simple-hearted fellow was
sorely mortified. His pride was as
much hurt as if he had been sent to the almshouse as
a pauper. But he found himself so kindly and
generously treated by Dr. Dean
and assistants, that he soon became reconciled, and
understood that all was done for the
best.</p>
          <p>On my return he was removed, comparatively
restored, to comfortable rooms near my residence,
where he was well nursed and cared for. I believe that
he wanted for nothing that kindness could supply.
But the end soon came.
He gave me verbal directions for disposal among his
kindred of his little property, a few articles of
furniture of small value, and his last words were a
prayer of thanksgiving that he
died in freedom.</p>
          <p>His funeral, at which I officiated, took place from
the African Methodist Church, on Lucas Avenue, and
was largely attended. He was decently buried in the
Centenary Burial-Ground, near Clayton Court-House, 
followed to his last resting-place by many
friends. A part of the expenses of his long sickness,
and all the
<pb id="alexa88" n="88"/>
funeral charges, were defrayed from the funds of the
Western Sanitary Commission.<ref id="ref4" n="4" rend="sc" target="note4" targOrder="U">*</ref></p>
          <note id="note4" n="4" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref4">* See Appendix III.</note>
          <p>It is the record of a humble life, but one which was
conformed, up to the full measure of ability, to the
law of the gospel. I have felt as proud of the long-continued 
friendship and confidence of Archer
Alexander as of any one I have known.</p>
          <p>He was, I believe, the last fugitive slave taken in
Missouri under the old laws of slavery. His freedom
came directly from the hand of President Lincoln, by
provost-marshal authority, and his own hands had
helped to break the chains that bound him. His oldest
son had given his life to the cause.</p>
          <p>When I showed to him the photographic picture of
the “Freedom's Memorial” monument, soon after its
inauguration in Washington, and explained to him its
meaning, and that he would thus be remembered in
connection with Abraham Lincoln, the emancipator of
his race, he laughed all over. He presently sobered
down and exclaimed, “Now I'se a white man! Now
I'se free! I thank the
<pb id="alexa89" n="89"/>
good Lord that he has 'livered me from all my
troubles, and I'se lived to see this.”</p>
          <q direct="unspecified">
            <lg type="poem">
              <l>“No sea</l>
              <l>Swells like the bosom of a man set free!</l>
              <l>A wilderness is rich with liberty.”</l>
            </lg>
          </q>
          <p>A monumental stone will soon be placed to mark
the spot where he was captured as a fugitive slave,
with this inscription:—</p>
          <q direct="unspecified">
            <p>ARCHER ALEXANDER.<lb/>
FROM SLAVERY TO FREEDOM, March 30, 1863.</p>
          </q>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <pb id="alexa90" n="90"/>
          <head>CHAPTER X.</head>
          <head>SLAVERY IN THE BORDER STATES.</head>
          <p>I HAVE spoken of slavery in Missouri as existing in
its mildest form, and under many alleviations, by
force of prevailing public opinion.</p>
          <p>In saying this, however, I do not mean that no
cruelties, and no acts of gross injustice, were
committed under the slavery system as I have seen it
in St. Louis, nor that the public mind was so elevated
as to condemn all such wrongs by open censure. That
would be untrue, and I speak only comparatively in
my reference to the subject. It would be pleasant to
forget all that is painful in the past, and to say of the
institution of slavery and all connected with it, let the
dead past bury its dead. But such forgetting would be
unwise, and would have the effect of debarring the
rising generation from many of the most important
lessons that the past teaches. It would also prevent
us from forming a just estimate,
<pb id="alexa91" n="91"/>
both of the evils from which as a people we have
been delivered, and of the national blessings we now
enjoy. The prophet Isaiah, when calling the attention
of his people to the glory of the present and future,
says, “Look to the hole of the pit whence ye were
digged;” and equally may we say, when men are
complaining of political and social wrongs, and of the
evils that so greatly abound, Remember what your
fathers bore; remember the fearful wrongs, formerly
so common, defended by law, sustained by public
opinion, regarded as incurable, which have now
become impossible, the record of which is now
almost beyond belief.</p>
          <p>Notwithstanding the comparative humanity of
slavery as an institution in Missouri, I can truthfully
say that there is nothing in all the scenes of “Uncle
Tom's Cabin” as given by Mrs. Stowe, to which I
cannot find a parallel in what I have myself seen and
known in St. Louis itself, previously to the war of
secession. Let me enter here on record a few of the
details.</p>
          <p>On my coming to St. Louis, 27th of November,
1834, one of the first things I heard was of
<pb id="alexa92" n="92"/>
a colored girl who had been whipped so severely by a 
“gentleman” who lived not far from where I lodged, that
she died before night. The gentleman was in the very
best circles as to wealth and surroundings, an officer in
the United States army, high in rank, distinguished in
appearance, and of Herculean strength. The girl was
suspected of having stolen a key with intention of
rifling the bureau-drawers of her mistress, and was
whipped to compel her to confess. The gentleman was
indicted and thrown into jail, where he was visited by a
fellow-officer of the United States army (his
subordinate), who afterwards became my intimate
friend, and told me the particulars. By change of venue
the case was carried into St. Charles County, and a
verdict of <hi rend="italics">not guilty</hi> was rendered, although of the facts
there could be no dispute. The “public” were shocked,
but the feeling was of no endurance. The gentleman's
standing was not permanently, if at all, affected. No
notice of the transaction was taken by the military
authorities. It did not impede his advance to still higher
grades of military service in after years.</p>
          <p>Forty-five years afterward, when thinking of the
events as narrated, I could hardly trust my
<pb id="alexa93" n="93"/>
memory, so atrocious did they seem, and I wrote to
the friend above referred to for confirmation. He
replied as follows:—</p>
          <q direct="unspecified">
            <text>
              <body>
                <div1>
                  <opener>
                    <dateline>JUNE 17, 1880.</dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>MY DEAR SIR,—Major—did whip a negro woman
so brutally that she died from the effects of the whipping. 
My recollection of the matter is that she did not
die under the lash, but was so lacerated and beaten that
she was barely alive, and died within a day or two after
the whipping: . . . was indicted by the grand jury for
murder or manslaughter, I do not remember which.
He was put in the jail in St. Louis to await his trial, and
I visited him in jail. I am strongly of the impression
that the indictment was for murder, and that bail was
refused; and the fact that he was put in jail is confirmatory 
of that impression. Whether this was in 1834 or
before that, I do not remember. He did not dare to
come to trial in St. Louis, and got a change of venue to
St. Charles County. The woman was the slave of his
wife or his wife's sister, and was accused of having
stolen a key, which she denied, and he whipped her to
make her confess it. Several years afterwards, in conversing 
with a lady, now Mrs. Major —, about “Uncle
Tom's Cabin,” I said, “You and I know parallel cases to
every one in that book.” She said, “Yes, except the
case of Legree.”—“Ah, madam,” I said, “you forget” <milestone n=" . . . " unit="typography"/>and she assented.</p>
                  <closer>
                    <signed>
                      <name>N. J. E.</name>
                    </signed>
                  </closer>
                </div1>
              </body>
            </text>
          </q>
          <p>In the following year, a free mulatto man, who had
committed some petty offence, and
<pb id="alexa94" n="94"/>
was known to be a troublesome fellow, was in charge
of two police-officers on the way to jail, which was
then on Sixth and Chestnut Streets, when he suddenly
drew a knife, stabbed one of his captors fatally, and
the other dangerously. He attempted escape; but it
was on the open street, by the court-house, and the
cry for help brought a crowd who caught and carried
him to jail. One of his victims died on the spot. The
other, known as a faithful officer, was thought to be
dying. Intense excitement prevailed; and a mob,
headed by many good citizens, went to the jail,
forcibly took the negro out, carried him to a tree
which stood where the Public School Polytechnic
building now stands, and were proceeding to hang him.
Some one cried out, "BURN HIM!"
The word was immediately taken up by the crowd.
The man was tied to the trunk of the tree; fence-rails
and dry wood in abundance were brought and piled
up around him. Several leading and prominent men,
whom everybody knew, were active in bringing the
rails with their own hands. There was no secrecy or
disguise attempted. The deed was accomplished, the
man was burned to death, and his body (or the
remnant of it) was left there
<pb id="alexa95" n="95"/>
until the next day. Fortunately for me, I knew
nothing of all this until the morning, after breakfast,
when I was sent for by the family of the wounded
officer.</p>
          <p>The show of judicial investigation was gone
through; but, although the names of a dozen of the
actors were known to everybody, it was passed over
as the act of an irresponsible mob, and was freely
spoken of by many as a good warning to free negroes.</p>
          <p>It was the same year when William Lloyd
Garrison, whose name is now the pride of
Massachusetts, was hounded almost to death, and
dragged through the streets of Boston with a rope
round his body, good citizens looking on, because of
his too bold attacks on the patriarchial institution of
the Southern States. The roots of slavery had struck
very deep, and its branches were wide-spread, casting
dark shadows over the whole land. Thank God, it
was cut down, and its roots have withered away!</p>
          <p>Several years later, in 1839-40, I was living on
Market Street, near Third, just back of the National
Hotel. My “study” was over the dining-room in the
back building, the windows
<pb id="alexa96" n="96"/>
looking out upon the yard of a neighbor, whose
house fronted on Third Street. One day I was startled
by a terrible scream, and, going to the window, saw
under an open shed a young mulatto woman tied up
to the joist by her thumbs, so that her feet scarcely
touched the ground, stripped from her shoulders to
the hips, and a man standing by her with cowhide-whip 
in hand. He had paused for a moment from his
scourging to see if she would “give in.” I opened the
window and called out to him. He told me “to shut up
and mind my own business.” But he feared publicity
just enough to untie the victim and stop his brutality
for the time. I shut up my book and went straight
before the grand jury, which was then in session, and
entered complaint against the man, who was a person
of fair respectability. A true bill was found, and he
was brought before the criminal court for trial. The
court was at the time held in the basement room of the
Unitarian Church, where I was pastor, having been let
for the purpose while the court-house was undergoing
repair. (Those were primitive days in St. Louis.) I was
called as witness, and the case was fully proved. The
offence of the colored girl was her unwillingness 
<pb id="alexa97" n="97"/>
to “submit to the wishes” of her
master. The judge charged accordingly, and
there was no room for acquittal. Nevertheless 
the verdict was “not guilty,” because, as
afterwards declared, the penalty fixed by law
was thought to be too severe. It had been
strongly so represented by the counsel for
defendant. Attempt was also made to invalidate 
my testimony as that of a sentimental
young preacher who knew nothing about slavery.
That was a strong point to make.</p>
          <p>Not many years before the outbreak of the war,
when public opinion had very much
advanced, an old colored man came to see me to ask if
I could not do something to get his
daughter Melinda out of the slave-jail, and prevent
her from being “sold South.” Her master and mistress
were persons of high respectability, members of an
Orthodox Church,
and until lately she had always been treated kindly,
as an indulged servant who had grown up with the
children of the household. As a child she had been
their playmate, almost on equal terms, as was not an
uncommon case in Southern-educated families. But as the girls 
grew into young ladies, the slave-girl had not
<pb id="alexa98" n="98"/>
been sensible enough to see the growing distinction
between herself and them, and had become “sassy.”
She had been several times very impudent to her
mistress, who became angry with her, and insisted
upon her being sold; and not only so, but that she
should be sent out of the city. Her husband assented,
and had placed her in one of the slave-jails, at corner
of Sixth and Locust Streets, to go with the next
“gang” Southward, where her “attractive appearance
would command a high price.”</p>
          <p>The old man said all he wanted was <hi rend="italics">time</hi>; that he
had bought his own freedom, and had just finished
paying for himself; that the house where he was
porter would help him to pay for Melinda, if Mr. —
would only let him have her and “pay up gradual,”
but that Mr. — had said she'd got to be sold out of the
city. I told him that I didn't know what to do about it,
but that, although I was not acquainted with Mr. —, I
would go and see if there was any chance. This I did,
and found the gentleman in his counting-room on
Main Street, a wholesale store of leading importance.
He received me very politely; and when I had
explained my purpose, telling
<pb id="alexa99" n="99"/>
him the condition of things, I asked him if he
would not sell the girl on my guaranty, so that
her father could have her, either in his own name
or that of some friend. He said no; that he
had promised his wife to sell her <hi rend="italics">away from
the city</hi>, where she would give her girls no
trouble; and that she was not for sale here.
“Well,” I said, “if that is your fixed determination, 
I can't help it, for under the law you have
a right to do as you please. But one thing
I can do: I can make the facts known. I
therefore now offer you the price, whatever it
is, that you expect for the girl, so that she may
stay with her father.”—“All right,” he answered 
as I rose to leave, “if you will come in
to-morrow morning, I'll let you know.” In the
morning he agreed to the proposal; stipulating,
however, that the bill of sale should be made
out <hi rend="italics">to me</hi>, eight hundred dollars as the price,
one-third cash, and balance with eight per cent
interest, and my indorsement to the notes. It
was arranged in an hour's time, and for two
hours thereafter I was Melinda's legal owner. I
went directly to the jail, showed to the slave-dealer 
my bill of sale and an order for delivery
of the chattel, and went in to see her. She
was waiting, forlorn and cheerless, a good-looking 
<pb id="alexa100" n="100"/>
girl of eighteen years, knowing nothing of the
transfer. Glad enough was she to go to her father,
who received her thankfully. <hi rend="italics">She was then already a
free woman.</hi> He raised the cash payment at once, and
I never heard a syllable of the notes, which must have
been duly provided for by him.</p>
          <p>The transaction, however, as it was near being
completed, was in substance not an uncommon one.
“Likely young mulatto gals” were apt to be impudent,
and impudence or unmanageableness was punishable
as a crime. St. Louis was fast becoming a slave-market, 
and the supply was increasing with the
demand. Often have I seen “gangs” of negroes
handcuffed together, two and two, going through the
open street like dumb driven cattle, on the way to the
steamboat for the South. Large fortunes were made by
the trade; and some of those who made them, under
thin cover of agency, were held as fit associates for
the best men on 'change.</p>
          <p>These illustrations of slavery as it was, and as I
have seen it, are given in their simplest outline. Let
them be dramatized,—not exaggerated, but brought out
in the colors of real life, with suffering and helpless
human beings
<pb id="alexa101" n="101"/>
as the victims of legalized brutality, ungoverned
passion, and unbridled lust,—and there is nothing
worse to be found, in the “Fool's Errand,” by
Tourgee, or in the historical pictures of Harriet
Beecher Stowe.</p>
          <p>One other instance of the same character, the truth
of which I know, although not personally interested
in its details, is given here.</p>
          <p>In the year 185-, Mr. M., a well-known citizen of
St. Louis and a man of family, held as slave a mulatto
woman, personable and well-mannered, with whom
his relations were intimate, and two children were
born to them. He then gave to her “free papers,”
renouncing all claim to her services. She left the city
soon after; and being arrested in Peoria, Ill., on
suspicion as a fugitive slave, he sent a written
statement of her freedom, on strength of which she
was released. Subsequently he induced her to return
to St. Louis, and then proposed to renew his former
relations with her. She refused, pleading that she was
a church-member, a reformed woman, and wished to
keep free from her former sins. He then asked her to
bring her manumission papers to him, that he might
correct some informalities
<pb id="alexa102" n="102"/>
in them, so as to save further trouble. She did so,
and he put them in the fire. It seemed that they were
informal, had never been entered on record, and had
no legal validity. Judge Gamble, to whom the matter
was referred by some humane persons who knew the
facts, gave his opinion that there was no legal remedy,
although it was an outrageous wrong.
“The claim was legally perfect, and the power of
the master was absolute.”</p>
          <p>He took her, accordingly, by the sheriff, and placed
her and her children in Lynch's slave-jail, with orders
to send them South for sale. They were, however,
temporarily released, and held under security bond for
their return, for several months, when, after the best
legal counsel had exhausted every means of rescue or
reprieve, the law compelled their being again placed in
the jail, subject to their owner's will. His legal wife,
who knew all the facts, refused to hear of any thing in
their favor, and urged their immediate sale to 
“a Southern plantation, where they should be well
worked.” But fortunately her own son, the half-brother 
of the negro woman's children, either through
compassion or shame, insisted upon their being sold
to a gentleman who had been active in
<pb id="alexa103" n="103"/>
their behalf, and by whom this narrative is given to
me. He sent them, legally manumitted, to a free State;
and so, as by special providence, they were snatched
from a fate worse than death. No thanks to the laws
of slavery. I believe no members of Mr. M.'s family
now live in Missouri.</p>
          <p>As an illustration of the almost impossibility of
securing the slave from the worst hardships of the
system, I give the following extract from the letter of
a personal friend, a man of great intelligence, and, so
far as my acquaintance goes, of unequalled humanity.</p>
          <q direct="unspecified">
            <text>
              <body>
                <div1>
                  <opener>
                    <dateline>ST. LOUIS, Feb. 16, 1885.</dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p> . . . .I have read your manuscript carefully, and can
testify of my own knowledge that it is a perfectly true
and fair delineation of slavery as it existed from the
forties down. I could easily confirm all you have said,
and much more. My experience commenced in
Tennessee, on a farm, before I attained my majority, as
the owner of some twenty-five or thirty negroes, men,
women, and children, all of whom were purchased, with
one or two exceptions, in families, from one man. For
each family I built a separate house, and taught all who
were willing, to read, although the same was forbidden
by law. Four years later it became necessary for me to
remove, to take charge of a city business-house. I sold
my farm, and disposed of all my negroes, to a
gentleman who had
<pb id="alexa104" n="104"/>
been a lifelong friend of my family, taking for them a
mere nominal sum, in order to secure them a good
master, who would keep them all together. My friend
placed the negroes on a plantation that he had purchased
in the neighborhood. He put it in charge of a kinsman
from a free State, in whom he had confidence, and who
was to receive, as compensation for his services, one-fourth 
of the net earnings. But the overseer proved to be
a hard task-master; and four or five years later, in
visiting my old home, I called to see the purchaser of my
old servants, to ask about them. He had a sad tale to tell.
Many of the negroes had died from overwork and bad
treatment from “the Yankee overseer.” The place was
brought in debt, and the rest of them were sold under the
hammer, singly, for the best price they would bring, and
scattered far and wide. So all my efforts, and the
pecuniary sacrifice which I made to keep them together,
were of no avail<corr sic=",">.</corr></p>
                  <p>It was this experience that first taught me the inherent 
evils of slavery, although I had always been a gradual 
emancipationist. The perpetration of other wrongs
that I witnessed as I advanced in life so impressed me
that I gave freedom to all the domestics whom I owned,
which was some years before the presidential election
of 1856.</p>
                  <p>I hope to see your manuscript in print. Many
persons of this day have no conception of what slavery
was, and how it was regarded by very many very good
people. Your description is just and appreciative.</p>
                  <closer>
                    <signed>
                      <name> J. E. Y.</name>
                    </signed>
                  </closer>
                </div1>
              </body>
            </text>
          </q>
          <pb id="alexa105" n="105"/>
          <p>Nearly all of those to whom reference has been
made, either directly or indirectly, in this chapter,
have passed away, and personal interest in the
special facts given has well nigh ceased. But
everywhere in the former slave States the memory of
like cases of hardship and suffering remains. In every
precinct, city, village, or town, with whatever
diversity of details, the same general record might be
made.</p>
          <p>Therefore it is that in the Southern even more than
in the Northern States, the prayer of thanksgiving
continually ascends that by the over-ruling
providence of God the days of Slavery have ended. In
the previous pages I have said that no freedman
would consent to return to the best conceivable
condition of bondage; equally true is it that no former
slave-holder, of any intelligence, can be found who
would consent again to become a “master.” And this,
not chiefly because of the growing conviction that
free labor is most profitable, but far more because of
the moral and social deliverance which freedom has
conferred. If it were within the range of possibility to
re-establish the institution of slavery as it was thirty
years ago, and if such change were proposed,
<pb id="alexa106" n="106"/>
the resistance of the Southern States would be
the most emphatic. It is true that “they have been led
by a way they had not known” to this great
deliverance, but they now understand that, in every
sense, it has become a supreme benediction.</p>
          <p>There are many conflicting interests, both
political and financial, to be settled between
the North and South, for which there will be
abundant need of patience and mutual forbearance. 
But the one great cause of contention
has been forever removed, and before the
present  generation has passed, the North and
South, East and West, will be the most closely
united people on the face of the earth.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <pb id="alexa107" n="107"/>
          <head>CHAPTER XI.</head>
          <head>ELIJAH P. LOVEJOY.</head>
          <p>IN Missouri the social struggle between freedom
and slavery began with the persecution
and martyrdom of Elijah Parish Lovejoy, between 
the years 1833 and 1837. It was a 
tragic beginning, but less than thirty years 
later it ended with the triumphant emancipation 
decree of a convention of the State, Jan. 11, 1865,
adopted by almost unanimous vote (only two votes
in the negative), as follows:—</p>
          <q direct="unspecified">“<hi rend="italics">Be it ordained by the people of the State of
Missouri, in convention assembled,</hi> That hereafter in
this State there shall be neither slavery nor involuntary
servitude, except in punishment of crime, whereof the
party shall have been duly convicted; and all persons
held to service or labor as slaves are hereby declared
free.”</q>
          <p>It is worthy of note that Missouri was the only
slave State in the Union, which, of its own accord,
thus gave freedom to its slaves. President 
Lincoln's proclamation of freedom was a war
measure, taking effect only in the seceded States, and
even there of doubtful legal validity,
<pb id="alexa108" n="108"/>
until a constitutional amendment had been
adopted by a two-thirds vote of the whole Union.
Then Kentucky and Maryland became free States.
But Missouri had already been established as a free
State by her own acts,—first by a gradual
emancipation ordinance, June, 1863; and finally by
the conclusive act of January, 1865.</p>
          <p>The contrast is all the greater when we look back
to the days of Elijah P. Lovejoy; and a few pages of
that record may here not be out of place. I am
indebted for nearly all the details to several recent
articles in the  “Globe Democrat” of St. Louis, and in
the “St. Louis Republican,” the latter of which are
from the pen of Mr. Thomas Dimmock, one of the
ablest editors of that well-known and influential
journal.</p>
          <p>Mr. Lovejoy first came to St. Louis in 1827, being
at the time twenty-five years of age. “Having a
decided taste and talent for journalism, he naturally
drifted into it, and in 1828 became editor of the long
since forgotten ‘Times,’ then advocating the claims of
Henry Clay. His editorial work made him quite
popular with the Whig party, and might have opened
the way to political advancement; but
<pb id="alexa109" n="109"/>
in the winter of 1831-32, during a religious revival, his
views of life underwent a radical change, and he united
with the Second Presbyterian Church, then in charge
of Rev. W. S. Potts. Believing he had a call to the
sacred office, he entered the Princeton Theological
School in the spring of 1832, where he remained until
April, 1833, when he received his ministerial
credentials. In the autumn of the same year he returned
to St. Louis, then a city of seven thousand inhabitants,
and, yielding to the solicitations of many friends,
established a weekly religious newspaper, called the
‘Observer,’ the friends furnishing the necessary funds,
and the entire management being intrusted to him. The
first number appeared Nov. 29, 1833. In the spring of
1834 he publicly announced his anti-slavery
principles, and thus began the bitter warfare, which
finally cost hirn his life. He was not, however, what
was then popularly known as an abolitionist. He
favored gradual emancipation, with the consent,
compensation, and assistance of the slave-owners; and
this should be considered in our estimate of the
character and conduct of the man, and of those who
hounded him to death.”</p>
          <pb id="alexa110" n="110"/>
          <p>In October, 1835, an earnest and affectionate
letter was addressed to Mr. Lovejoy, signed
by nine of his principal supporters, all of whom
were men of commanding influence in St.
Louis. Among them were Archibald Gamble,
W. S. Potts, Hamilton R. Gamble and Beverly
Allen. They represented in every sense the
best citizens of the city and State. They
pleaded with him as Christians and patriots,
ending with this appeal: “We do not claim to
prescribe your course as an editor, but we hope
that the concurring opinions of so many persons
having the interests of your paper and of
religion both at heart may induce you to distrust
your own judgment, and so far change
the character of the ‘Observer’ as to pass over
in silence every thing connected with the subject
of slavery.”</p>
          <p>What his reply was may be understood,
says the “Globe Democrat,” Nov. 16, 1884,
from the following memorandum on the back
of the original letter, made only two weeks before
his death:—</p>
          <q direct="unspecified">
            <text>
              <body>
                <div1>
                  <p>I did not yield to the wishes here expressed, and in
consequence have been persecuted ever since. But I
have kept a good conscience in the matter, and that repays
me for all I have suffered, or can suffer. I have
<pb id="alexa111" n="111"/>
sworn eternal opposition to slavery, and, by the blessing
of God, I will never go back.</p>
                  <closer><signed><name>E. P. L.</name></signed>
<dateline><date>OCT. 24, 1837.</date></dateline></closer>
                </div1>
              </body>
            </text>
          </q>
          <p>In July, 1836, the patience of St. Louis was
exhausted, and Mr. Lovejoy having announced
his intention of removing to Alton, Ill., a mob
of citizens entered his office, and destroyed
the furniture, and scattered the types, by way
of a parting expression of hatred and contempt.
As I remember it, very few persons,
even among the best citizens, expressed either
regret or condemnation.</p>
          <p>He fared no better in Alton. His first press
was destroyed as soon as landed, and a second
one met the same fate in the following August.
The whole population was stirred up against
him, as would have been the case at that day
in any town of the United States. Meeting
after meeting was held, at which his proceedings
were denounced. At one of these meetings,
standing quite alone, he said,—</p>
          <q direct="unspecified">“But, gentlemen, as long as I am an American citizen,
and as long as American blood runs in these veins, I
shall hold myself at liberty to speak, to write, and to
publish, whatever I please on any subject, being
amenable to the laws of my country for the same.”</q>
          <p>“For these immortal principles,” says Mr.
<pb id="alexa112" n="112"/>
Dimmock, “Lovejoy laid down his life. His perfect
honesty and honor were never doubted, nor was his
superb moral and physical courage. He was a rare
combination of bravery and tenderness; as brave as a
lion, as tender as a woman.” In what may be justly
regarded as his dying appeal, five days before his violent 
death, in presence of a crowd of incensed enemies, he
spoke as follows:—</p>
          <p>“MR. CHAIRMAN,—I plant myself down on my
unquestionable <hi rend="italics">rights</hi>, and the question to be decided is,
whether I am to be protected in the exercise and
enjoyment of those rights,—<hi rend="italics">that is the question, sir,</hi>—
whether my property shall be protected; whether I shall
be suffered to go home to my family at night without
being assailed and threatened with tar and feathers, and
assassination; whether my afflicted wife, whose life has
been in jeopardy from continued alarm and excitement,
shall, night after night, be driven from a sickbed into
the garret to escape the brickbats and violence of the
mobs,—<hi rend="italics">that, sir, is the question.</hi>[Here the speaker
burst into tears.] Forgive me, sir, that I have thus betrayed 
my weakness. It was allusion to my family that
overcame my feelings; not, sir, I assure you, from any
fears on my part. I have no personal fears. Not that I
feel able to contest the matter with the whole
community: I know perfectly well I am not. I know, sir,
you can tar and feather me, hang me, or put me in the
Mississippi, without the least difficulty. But what then?
Where shall I go? I have been made to feel that if I
<pb id="alexa113" n="113"/>
am not safe in Alton I shall not be safe anywhere. I
recently visited St. Charles to bring home my family. I
was torn from their frantic embrace by a mob. I have
been beset day and night in Alton. And now, if I leave
here and go elsewhere, violence may overtake me in
my retreat, and I have no more claim upon the
protection of any other community than I have upon
this; and I have concluded, after consultation with my
friends and earnestly seeking counsel of God, to remain
at Alton, and here insist on protection in the exercise
of my rights. If the civil authorities refuse to protect me, I
must look to God; and if I die, I am determined to make
my grave in Alton.”</p>
          <p>Five days later, Nov. 7, 1837, a citizen mob
took him at his word, beset him at his printing-office, 
and murdered him. His body was
privately interred, pains being taken to conceal
the place of burial, from fear that the
mob violence would desecrate his grave. But after
the lapse of many years, Mr. Dimmock succeeded
in finding the spot, and having purchased 
the ground, he has presented it, in trust
for the colored people of Alton, to Mr. Isaac H.
Kelley. It will be hereafter properly cared for;
and at an early day a suitable monument will be
erected, in memory of the proto-martyr of
freedom, in the United States, who at the early
age of thirty-five years gave his
life in vindication of the great cause to which he
had consecrated it.</p>
          <pb id="alexa114" n="114"/>
          <p>I place the record here, partly as illustrative of the
times when the events occurred, but still more
because I think that it helps to explain the rapid
growth, in St. Louis and Missouri, of public opinion
on the subjects of domestic slavery and freedom of
speech. The blood of the martyr is the seed not only
of the Church, but of truth and liberty. Hundreds of
those who half approved of the outrages as they took
place, were led by sober second thought not only to
condemn them, but to hate the cause for which they
had been committed.</p>
          <p>In the great national exodus from slavery to
freedom, Elijah P. Lovejoy was a pioneer, and his
memory should be held in special honor to the last
day of our national existence.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
    <back id="alexa">
      <div1>
        <pb id="alexa115" n="115"/>
        <head>APPENDIX.</head>
        <div2>
          <pb id="alexa117" n="117"/>
          <head>APPENDIX I.</head>
          <head>RELIGIOUS MARRIAGE OF SLAVES.</head>
          <p>THE time will come when this statement will seem
almost incredible. The usage, considered as a barbarism 
for which no religious defence would be possible, is
bad enough. But to give it the sanction of religion, the
religion of Jesus Christ, and to invoke the Divine
blessing upon a marriage which was no marriage at all,
but simply a concubinage which the master's word might
at any moment invalidate, seems at first beyond all
manner of excuse. Yet it was done, and that not only by
individual ministers of Christ, but by authority of
ecclesiastical conventions. The resolutions to that
effect went upon record in Methodist, Baptist, Presbyterian
churches, declaring that the separation of husband and
wife under the laws of slavery, by the removal of either
party, was to be regarded as “civil death,” sundering the
bonds, and leaving both parties free to make another
marriage contract. Slavery, by necessity of the case,
abolished all family ties,—of husband and wife, of
parents and children, of brothers and sisters,—except
so far as the convenience of the master might be suited
by their recognition. Legal sanction there was none.
But the sham-service which the law scorned to recognize
was rendered by the ministers of the gospel of Christ. I
have witnessed it, but could never bring myself to
take part in such pretence.</p>
          <pb id="alexa118" n="118"/>
          <p>And yet I feel compelled by truth to say that, among
all the alleviations of slavery, there was none greater
than this. While the nominal relation continued at all,
it was made sacred to the slave husband and wife, and
the affectionate African nature was comforted and
sustained by it. It was a strong motive to good behavior,
it promoted decency in social intercourse, it tended
towards keeping the slave-family together, and was
some restraint upon masters—a great restraint upon the
better class of them—against arbitrary separation by
sale: in short, it was one of the fearful anomalies of a
brutal and barbarous social system existing among a
civilized, Christian people.</p>
          <p>The question was fully discussed by the Savannah
River Baptist Association of Ministers in 1835; and the
decision was, “that such separation, among persons
situated as slaves are, is civilly a separation by death,
and that in the sight of God it would be so viewed. To
forbid second marriages in such case would be to expose
the parties to church censure for disobedience to their
masters, and to the spirit of that command which
regulates marriage among Christians. The slaves are not
free agents, and a dissolution by death is not more
entirely without their consent and beyond their control
than by such separation.”</p>
          <p>Truly the logic of slavery was the destruction of
humanity. </p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <pb id="alexa119" n="119"/>
          <head>APPENDIX II.</head>
          <p>SOON after the battle at Wilson's Creek, Missouri, in
which the Union troops under General Lyon sustained a
seeming defeat but gained a real victory, the sufferings
of our soldiers in the field and hospitals were very great,
and an appeal for relief was published in the St. Louis
papers by the Western Sanitary Commission. Attention
was called to this in the Boston “Transcript” by my
sister, Mrs. Hannah Dawes Lamb, who volunteered to
receive at her home, No. 13 Somerset Street, all funds
and new clothing or goods, to be forwarded by Adams's
Express to St. Louis, free of charge. A most liberal
response was made, not only in Boston, but from every
part of New England. Every week large boxes were
packed, and remittances of money daily came in,
without special agencies or solicitation. In course of the
war the full value, in money or new goods, of  $40,000,
came to us through that channel. Many thousands of
the sick and wounded, including prisoners, who were
treated exactly as our own men, had reason to thank
God for the kindly patriotism of New England women.
Every Boston box made our eyes glad, for every article
sent was the best of its kind.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <pb id="alexa120" n="120"/>
          <head> APPENDIX III.</head>
          <p>THE Western Sanitary Commission, originally
established by order of Major-General Frémont, and
afterwards recognized and made permanent by the
secretary of war, Edwin M. Stanton, is still in active
working existence. All of its members—James E.
Yeatman, J. B. Johnson, George Partridge, Carlos S.
Greeley, and W. G. Eliot—are yet living. It has a
residuum of its funds, amounting to over $50,000, well
invested, by use of which children and families of 
“Union soldiers,” and at times other persons, are
reminded of the kindly charities that grew out of the
fearful fratricidal war.</p>
          <p>The total amount in cash and sanitary stores received
by the Commission during the war, was officially
reported at $4,270,998.55, the whole of which was used
for the humane and sanitary purposes for which it was
given, the total costs of distribution having been less
than one per cent. The surplus above named was a part
of the interest earnings which accrued from the
excellent management of the treasurer, Carlos S.
Greeley.</p>
          <p>Besides the hospital work for the sick and wounded,
the Western Sanitary Commission was intrusted by the
authorities with the care and relief of Union refugees,
and of fugitive slaves from the South. Many thousands
of both these classes of sufferers thronged to St. Louis,
generally in wretched condition, not only
impoverished, but thriftless and inefficient. In one way
or another they were taken care of until some sort of
<pb id="alexa121" n="121"/>
work was found by which they could earn their bread.
Special funds were liberally contributed, chiefly from
New England, for such uses.</p>
          <p>Throughout the war, quite up to its close in 1865,
many of the orders issued by the president of the
Commission were signed, “By order of Major-General J.
C. Frémont,” being regarded by his successors as outside
of army regulations, and beyond the authority usually
exercised by generals in command. In fact, when I first
submitted the form of organization to Dr. De Camp,
United States medical director, Sept. 5, 1861, he
promptly said that it was unusual and irregular, but that
it would be of great service if authorized by the
commanding general, and that he would in that case
gladly co-operate with the Commission, all the
members of which were known to him. With this
indorsement, I took it directly to headquarters, where,
at my request, it was copied by Mrs. Frémont, and taken
by her to the general's office. He was surrounded by
earnest and excited friends, having just received the
countermand of his proclamation of conditional
emancipation in Missouri; but he examined it, and, after
learning that it met the approval of the medical
director, he submitted it to the examination of his chief
of staff, and then signed it. I have that original copy, in
Mrs. Frémont's handwriting, now.</p>
          <p>When General Halleck succeeded in command, I took
it to him, having first fortified myself by letters from
President Lincoln and Secretary Chase, to prevent an
immediate veto. He read it, and said that, although he
could not have originated such an order, he saw how
useful it would be if in good hands, and should not
countermand it unless sufficient reason should appear;
<pb id="alexa122" n="122"/>
that the Commission could go on with its work under
the order already obtained. From that time forward,
under General Halleck and all his successors in
command, the services of the Commission were freely
used. The funds rapidly increased, and sanitary supplies
were freely distributed wherever needed, from Missouri
to Chattanooga, and far beyond. By the wonderful
efficiency of the president, James E. Yeatman, who
devoted his whole time and strength to the work, results
were obtained which would at first have seemed
impossible. The cordial testimony of Generals Grant
and Sherman and Curtis, and many others, was
frequently and publicly given to this effect.</p>
          <p>It may be that General Frémont overstepped the
limits of army regulations in authorizing the
Commission. When the rough draught was prepared, I
knew nothing about such regulations, and know but
little now. But I knew the need of our suffering men,
and the deplorable inadequacy of the means for their
relief. In making provision for such relief under existing
exigencies, General Frémont acted under the dictates of
humanity and common sense.</p>
          <p>It is my confident opinion, from familiarity with all
the facts at the time, that if his emancipation order had
been equally sustained, notwithstanding its alleged
irregularity, instead of being countermanded with
censure, the State of Missouri would have been saved
from more than two years of destructive guerilla
warfare. Even as it was, that order was the first keynote
to the emancipation policy, which soon after prevailed.
Time sets all things right, and honor will ultimately be
given to whom honor is due. The whole administration
of General Frémont in Missouri has been severely criticised
<pb id="alexa123" n="123"/>    
But I anxiously watched it from beginning to end,
and after carefully reading the scrutinizing report of the
Congressional Committee, the members of which were by
no means partial to Frémont, interpreting the testimony
by my own knowledge of the facts as they transpired,
I would sum up the whole record in a single sentence:
Whatever criticism of details may be just, he found Missouri 
trembling in the balance, between loyalty and secession, 
with alarming probabilities in the wrong direction; 
at the end of three months he left it, although with
great difficulties yet to be encountered, as secure to the
Union as Massachusetts itself, with slavery already
foredoomed. To whom the credit belongs, let
impartial history show.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI.2>