<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>Recollections of My Slavery Days:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Singleton, William Henry, 1835-1938</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Lee Ann Morawski</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Chris Hill  and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>2000</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca.  55K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>2000.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching 
and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="title page"> Recollections of My Slavery Days</title>
            <author>William  Henry  Singleton</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent> 10  p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace/>
            <publisher/>
            <date>1922</date>
            <authority/>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="yes">Call number E444 S56 1922a  (North Carolina Collection, J.Y Joyner Library, 
East Carolina University)</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>This electronic edition has been transcribed from a photocopy supplied by  the 
North Carolina Collection, J.Y Joyner Library, East Carolina University</p>
        <p id="id1">Images from the photocopy are not included in this electronic edition.</p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) 
and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Singleton, William Henry, 1835-1938.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- North Carolina -- New Bern --
Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- North Carolina -- New Bern -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Fugitive slaves -- North Carolina -- New Bern --
Biography.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- North Carolina -- New Bern -- History -- 19th
century.</item>
            <item>New Bern (N.C.) -- History -- 19th century.</item>
            <item>United States. Army. North Carolina Colored Infantry
Regiment, 1st
(1863-1864)</item>
            <item>United States. Army. Colored Infantry Regiment, 35th
(1864-1866)
Company G.</item>
            <item>North Carolina -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 --
Participation, Afro-American.</item>
            <item>United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 --
Participation,
Afro-American.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2000-04-03, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2000-02-18, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2000-02-10, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Chris Hill</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2000-02-08, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Lee Ann Morawski</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">RECOLLECTIONS
<lb/>
OF
<lb/>
MY SLAVERY DAYS</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>BY</byline>
        <docAuthor>WILLIAM HENRY SINGLETON</docAuthor>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="image">
        <p>Photograph of honorable discharge of the author from the Union Army, June 1, 1866. <ref target="id1" targOrder="U">[Illustration is not available]</ref></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="main section">
        <pb id="sing1" n="1"/>
        <head>Recollections of My Slavery Days.</head>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>I</head>
          <p>I have lived through the greatest epoch in history, 
having been born August 10, 1835, at Newbern, North 
Carolina. That was not so many years, you see, after the 
adoption of the Declaration of Independence and the winning 
of the Revolutionary War. But in the country of the 
Declaration of Independence I was born a slave, for I was 
a black man. And because I was black it was believed I <sic corr="(extra letter)">I</sic> 
had no soul. I had no rights that anybody was bound to 
respect. For in the eyes of the law I was but a thing. 
I was bought and sold. I was whipped. Once I was whipped 
simply because it was thought I had opened a book.</p>
          <p>But I lived to see the institution of slavery into which I 
was born and of which I was for many years a victim pass away. 
I wore the uniform of those men in Blue, who through four 
years of suffering wiped away with their blood the stain of 
slavery and purged the Republic of its sin. I met, too, that 
great man who led those men as their great Commander-in-Chief; 
he shook hands with me, yes, talked to me. I can still see his 
sad, tired worn face as he spoke to me that day. And in those 
days since I was whipped simply because it was thought I had 
opened a book. I have seen the books of the world opened to 
my race. And with the help and sympathy of God's good people 
I have seen them make a beginning in education. And in my 
old age when a nation across the seas sought to enslave the 
world as once my race was enslaved, I saw the boys of my race 
take their place in the armies of the Republic and help save 
freedom for the world.</p>
          <p>Comparing my position now, living in a good home, with my 
wife, with friends, respected in my community, with the 
same rights that every other man has, those days of my 
boyhood seem like a dream. But folks who know 
my story like to hear me tell about those days, how we lived, 
what we thought about, how we were treated, what kind of 
people our masters were. So I recall them for my friends 
and for other folks, who, though they do not know me, might 
like to hear a true story that may seem as strange to them, 
however, as a fairy tale.</p>
          <p>Now, although I was born black and a slave, I was not all 
black. My mother was a colored woman but my father was the 
brother of my master. I did not learn this until some years 
later. It caused me much trouble. They were a high, proud 
family, the Singletons. My master's estate was one of the
largest in Craven county, North Carolina, and he had more 
slaves than any other planter thereabouts. The first thing 
I remember is playing on the plantation with my little 
brothers and with the other slave children. While the men 
and women slaves were in the cotton, corn and potato fields 
working during the day, we children were taken care of by an 
old slave lady at a central house. She had grown too old to 
work and so acted as a kind of nurse for the slave children 
during the day. I was about four years old at that time.
I had two brothers younger than I and one two years older. 
Nights we went home with our mother. The slaves lived in a 
row of houses a ways from the
<pb id="sing2" n="2"/>
main house where our master lived. Of course my mother was 
supplied with all the food we wanted and we did not need 
much clothing because the weather was warm. I had nobody 
that I called father. I only knew my mother. Her name was 
Lettis Singleton. All the slaves on a plantation had the 
same name as their master. The slaves on Singleton's 
plantation, for instance, were known as Singleton's men and 
women. John Winthrop had a plantation adjoining ours and all 
the slaves on that plantation were called Winthrop's slaves. 
When a plantation changed owners the slaves changed their 
names. Our plantation had formerly been owned by a Mrs. 
Nelson, a widow. The slaves were then known as Nelson's 
slaves. When Singleton married Mrs. Nelson he succeeded to 
the plantation and all of the slaves, including my mother, 
were called from that time on Singleton.</p>
          <p>I can remember my mother used to tell us about our great 
grandmother. She, like my grandmother, was the slave of a 
family living in the city of Newbern. I cannot remember the 
name of this family now. My great grandmother had a hand that 
was burned and I can remember my mother telling us about it. 
It evidently made a great impression upon me, for that is 
about the only thing I can remember from my first years on 
the plantation, that and the days we spent together in the 
central house in charge of the old nurse while our mother 
was away with the other slaves at work in the fields.</p>
          <p>One day when I was about four years old a strange man came to 
this central house where all us children were and asked me if 
I liked candy. I told him yes. So he gave me a striped stick 
of candy. Then he asked me if I liked him. I said, yes, sir, 
because he had given me the candy. There was a colored woman 
with him and he asked me then how I would like to go and live 
with him. Of course I did not know him nor the woman, but 
without saying any more the man took me away with him and 
gave me to the strange woman who took me to Atlanta, Georgia, 
and delivered me to a white woman who had bought me. That 
night when my mother came to get me and my brothers I was not 
there. I had been sold off the plantation away from my 
mother and brothers with as little formality as they would 
have sold a calf or a mule. Such breaking up of families and 
parting of children from their parents was quite common in 
slavery days and was one of the things that caused much 
bitterness among the slaves and much suffering, because the 
slaves were as fond of their children as the white folks. But 
nothing could be done about it, for the law said we were only 
things and so we had no more rights under the law than 
animals. I believe it was only the more cruel masters, 
however, who thus separated families. I learned afterwards 
that the reason I was sold was because there had been trouble 
between my master and his brother over me and as my presence 
on the plantation was continually reminding them of something 
they wanted to forget my master sold me to get me out of the 
way. I suppose they sold me cheap for that reason. I was 
bought by a white woman in Atlanta, a widow, who ran a slave 
farm. That is, she would buy up young slaves whose pedigrees 
were good and would keep them till they grew up and sell them 
for a good price. Perhaps she would have them taught to do 
something and thus add to their value. These slave farms were 
quite common. Most of the work of the South in those days was 
done by slaves. Slaves were ginners, that is, they knew how 
to run cotton gins; they were carpenters, blacksmiths, ship 
carpenters and farmers. An ordinary slave sold for from 
$500 to $600 to $700, but a slave of good stock who was a 
good carpenter or a good ginner would be worth from $1,000 
to $1,500. And when such a slave got on a plantation he would 
not be apt to be sold. They would keep him on the plantation 
to do their work. So it was to a slave's advantage to learn 
to do some work, because then he would be treated better and 
would not be sold. A slave like that would have his wife and 
he would be of higher standing among the other slaves. But 
his children, of course, would belong to his master and he 
would have no legal right to keep his wife if his master 
chose to take her away from him. But a slave that was lazy or 
shiftless or inclined to run away would not be wanted on a 
plantation and he would be sold for almost nothing.</p>
          <p>Young as I was when I was sold the first time I did not like 
the idea of leaving my mother and brothers. And I did not 
like my new mistress, either. Not that she treated me so 
very bad. I was too young to work much so I stayed around 
the house. I had all I wanted to eat. Of course I had hardly
<pb id="sing3" n="3"/>
any clothes, but then I did not need many clothes to keep me 
warm. I did not have any bed to sleep on, simply slept on the 
dirt floor by the fireplace in the house like a little dog. 
But my mistress had a great habit of whipping me. Some 
slave owners used to have a custom of whipping their slaves 
frequently to keep them afraid. They thought it made them 
more obedient. My mistress had a bundle of twigs from a 
black walnut tree with which she used to whip me. My 
particular work was in running errands and in carrying
things from one place to another, and if I did not come back 
from doing what she told me to do as soon as she thought I 
should, she would whip me. One day when I was about seven 
years old she sent me on an errand. I must have been gone 
entirely too long for when I returned she started for the whip 
to whip me again. I suddenly decided to run away, and I did. 
After I had started I was afraid to come back. My mistress's 
farm was a little ways outside of Atlanta and I ran into the 
city. There on the streets I ran across an old colored man 
who asked me my name and what part of the country I was from 
and what my mother's name was. When I had told him, he said:
“I know your people. I was sold from that part of the 
country.” Then he told me about my great grandmother and her 
burned hand and how she lived at Newbern. He pointed out the 
road that led to Newbern and said I might get a ride on the 
stage. “But don't tell anybody your name,” he said, “If they
ask you your name, you don't know, and keep agoing.” Not long 
afterward, I saw a stage standing up before a building. So I 
waited around to see when it would start. Finally I saw a 
white lady with a carpet bag coming toward the stage and I 
went and took her carpet bag and helped her in the stage.
The colored man who drove the stage thought I belonged to the 
white lady, because of that fact. It proved that the lady was 
going by stage route from Atlanta to Wilmington, North 
Carolina. Of course the same horses and driver that started 
from Atlanta did not make the whole journey to Wilmington.
The horses were changed and the first driver went back, and 
a new man took the stage until the next change was made. But 
as all the drivers thought I was with the white lady and as 
she seemed to be willing to help me by letting them think so, 
I got to Wilmington in that manner. There the white lady
said to me, “Little boy, I have got to stop here and I do not 
go any further.” She did not want me to go with her any 
further. I suppose she knew I was running away and sympathized 
with me, but she did not want to get in any difficulty 
herself, for she did not ask me my name and cautioned me 
that I did not know anything about her.</p>
          <p>From Wilmington I walked and caught rides the rest of the 
distance to <sic corr="Newbern">Newburn.</sic> It was a city I should judge about as 
large as Peekskill is now, perhaps a little larger. I 
remembered what the old colored man in Atlanta had told me 
to do when I reached there, ask for an old colored woman with 
a burned hand. My great grandmother must have been quite a 
well known character in the city, for I soon was directed to 
where she lived. When I knocked at the door the old colored 
woman who came to the door wanted to know what I wanted. I 
told her I was looking for my great grandmother She asked me 
who I was. I was afraid to tell her and so said, “I don't 
know.” She said, “You little fool, how is anybody going to 
know what you want? Are you the little runaway boy that the 
white people were here looking for?” I said, “I don't know.” 
While we were talking there we heard some men coming. My great 
grandmother said, “You better get away.” Her house was
next to the jail. She was owned by a man named Jacobs at that 
time. I afterwards learned that he was a great friend of 
colored people. So I ran and hid myself back of the jail 
until the men were gone<corr sic="no punctuation">.</corr> Then I started from Newbern down the 
road to the plantation where my mother was. That was on the 
Neuse river, about 35 miles from Newbern. I walked in the 
road, but if I heard any one coming I would go in the woods 
and wait until they passed. As it happened nobody molested me 
and I made the journey from Newbern to the plantation in 
about a day and a night. In order to reach the plantation I
had to cross a creek, Adams Creek. When I reached there a 
little before dusk, I saw a man fishing a little ways from 
the shore. I knew he must be a colored man, because the white 
people as a rule did not fish, they generally got their
fish without taking that trouble. So I hailed the man and 
asked him if he could put me across the creek. He said he 
could and pulled to the shore and I got in. When he saw how 
young I was he said, “Look here, little boy, where
<pb id="sing4" n="4"/>
are you going.” I said, “I don't know.” He said, “How am I 
going to tell where to put you?” I said, “Put me over across 
the creek? This is Adams Creek?” He said, “Yes.” “I want to 
go down to the Singleton plantation. Do you know where that 
is?” He said “Oh, yes.” He was a colored man, as I had 
supposed. I said, “My mother's name is Lettis.” He said, “Oh, 
yes. I know Aunt Let. I know her well, you go right straight 
down the road until you get to the school house and when you 
get there keep to your left hand. The road will take you right 
into the Singleton plantation.” So he put me ashore on the 
other side of the creek and I followed his directions and in 
a little while I came to the school house and then after that 
it was not long before I was running down the road that led 
to the plantation and home. It was the only home I knew. It 
was where my mother was.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>II</head>
          <p>Luckily the first door I knocked at when I reached the 
Singleton plantation happened to be the door of my mother's 
house, but of course I did not know my mother, so when she 
opened the door and asked me what I wanted, I made my usual 
reply, “I don't know.” I did not know my mother and she did 
not know me. She said, “What do you want, little boy?” I said, 
“I am looking for my mother.” “Your mother?” “Yes, ma'am.” 
Just then my older brother, Hardy, came to the door and he 
said, “Mamma, that's Henry.” My mother said, “No, it isn't; 
that child wouldn't know how to get back hero alone like that. 
When he went from here he was nothing but a baby.” But Hardy 
said, “Mamma, that's Henry, that's our Henry.” Hardy was two 
years older than I and so was about nine years old then. He 
was big enough to be working on the plantation. My mother 
said, “I won't believe it's Henry except I can see a scar on 
the back of his neck where he was burned; I burned him when I 
was smoking my pipe one night and when he went away that scar 
was plain on the back of his neck. If it is there now, I will 
believe it is Henry.” But when I heard her say that I was 
afraid because I did not know that I had a scar there and I 
thought it was a trap to catch me and turn me over to the 
white people. So I ran, but Hardy ran me down and caught me 
and mother found the scar and then I was all right. We went 
in the house and I was telling them about my trip when we 
heard the patrol coming. The patrols were something like our 
mounted police, they were men who rode around the country and 
if they found any colored people off the plantations where 
they belonged, they would lash them and turn them over to 
their masters. Nights they would go around to the houses 
where the slaves lived and go in the houses to see if there 
was anybody there who had no right to be there. If they found 
any slaves in a house where they had no right to be, or where 
they did not have a permit to be, they would ask the reasons 
why and likely arrest them and whip them. My mother had a 
board floor to her house and underneath that a cellar. It was 
not exactly a cellar, but a hole dug out to keep potatoes and 
things out of the way. When she heard the patrol coming she 
raised up one of the boards of the floor and I jumped down in 
the cellar and when the men on the patrol came in they did 
not find me. That cellar was my hiding place and sleeping 
place for three years. My mother fed me and looked out for me, 
and although the white people suspected me and looked for me 
they could not find me. They got me finally, however, by a 
trick. One Sunday morning my mother and brothers went to a 
camp meeting and left me in the cellar. There were cracks in 
the cellar through which I could see out of doors. Looking 
out I saw there were some biscuits on a fence not far away. 
That was one of the tricks the masters had to catch slaves 
who were in hiding. They would put food on the fences where 
a slave they suspected of being in hiding could see it in the 
hope that he would get hungry and venture out and take it and 
thus reveal himself. That is what happened to me, for no 
sooner did I go out after the biscuits than I heard a horn 
blow and soon I was surrounded and caught. They sold me that 
time to the overseer on the plantation, John Peed. But he did 
not buy me to keep me on the plantation, he bought me to send 
me to Jones County, North Carolina, to his folks. He paid $500 
for me. But when he sent me to my mother's house to get my 
clothes to take with me I ran to the woods. They tried to 
find me, but they could not. Nights I came back to my 
mother's house and to the cellar and very early in the 
morning before the sun was up I would go to
<pb id="sing5" n="5"/>
the woods and watch the men go to their work. I would stay 
in the woods all day and then come back at night. Of course I 
could not have done this if the colored people had not been 
friendly to me. Finally my mother got notice that if I would 
come back and give myself up they would put me to work on
the plantation, helping the boys feed the horses and things 
of that kind, that Mr. Peed did not own me any more for they 
had given him his money back when I ran away. So I gave 
myself up, but very soon the folks up at the big house began 
to find fault about my being on the place, so my master sold 
me the third time. He virtually gave me away, for he received 
only $50 for me and sold me to a poor white woman of the 
neighborhood. She was very good to me. She had a little farm 
and was what might be called one of the “poor whites.” The 
plantation owners considered any one who did not own a good
deal of property and slaves poor. She was named Mrs. Wheeler. 
But she got tired of me for some reason and sold me to a 
party who was to come for me. But before they could come to 
take me away I ran away. I went to the city of Newbern and 
hired out as a bell boy at the Moore Hotel. Of course
they did not know that I was a runaway slave and they did not 
know my name, either, for I would not tell them. They called 
me the “Don't know” boy. But they gave me three dollars a 
week and my food. I was then about ten years old. I stayed at 
the Moore House three years. I left because some of the other 
colored boys about there had found out who I was and said 
they were going to give me away. So I went back to the 
plantation again to my mother's house. She told me that they 
had promised not to sell me any more if I would give myself 
up and go on the plantation and go to work. And she
wanted me to do that, because she was very tired of my 
foolishness, as she called it, in running away and going 
about the country. So I did give myself up. I went to the 
big house and saw my master and told him I had come
home to stay now. He was a tall, raw-boned, black faced man, 
quite old then, too old to go to war when the war came. He 
said, “All right, go out to the barn and go to work and it 
will be all right. Go out and help the men take care of the 
horses and stay home.” And I did. I learned to plow and to do
all kinds of work about the plantation and in the cotton and 
corn fields. I was not given any chance to learn a trade, 
though. And of course I was given no opportunity to learn to 
read. There was no school for the slaves to attend. I would 
not have wanted to go to school any way for my only 
experience with a book was not a pleasant one. One day my 
master's son, who was just my age, had a bag coining home 
from school and he gave me the bag to carry. The bag had 
books in it. I slung the bag over my shoulder but did not 
take any of the books out. But Edward said I took one of his
books out of the bag and opened it. When his father heard 
that, he said he would teach me better things than to do that, 
and he whipped me very severely. I cried and told him that 
I did not take the book out, and then he whipped me all the 
harder for disputing his word. He whipped me with a
harness strap. That was not the first time my master whipped 
me, however. Whipping with him was a very common thing. He 
was one of the masters who believed in whipping their slaves 
to keep them in subjection. If you looked cross at them, 
they would whip you. They did not see the propriety of 
treating their slaves well to get more out of them. </p>
          <p>It was shortly after this that I learned that my master was 
not only my master but my uncle and that his brother was my 
father. I learned this first from my aunt. She heard about 
my master whipping me and she said, “It is a great note for 
him to whip you for that, because you are his own nephew.” 
That surprised me very much. I had heard the men about the 
plantation before that speak about my being half white, but 
I did not know why. My aunt also told me that once my master 
and his brother had had a quarrel about it up at the big 
house. But by that time I had settled down on the place
and so there was no more said about it. Except once my 
master's daughter, who very much resembled her mother for 
her good disposition, referring to the fact said there 
oughtn't to be so much trouble about it anyway, because
we were one family and the time would come when the black 
people would be free. This made her father very angry. She 
had heard those things, I think, from her mother. It was her 
mother who had owned the plantation originally, as I have 
before mentioned. Upon her husband's death she later 
married John Singleton, and he then became the master of 
the plantation. But I
<pb id="sing6" n="6"/>
think they never agreed upon the question of having slaves. 
She did not like the idea of owning slaves. She was a good 
Christian woman and she believed the Bible did not teach 
that it was right to own slaves. Shortly before her death 
an incident occurred which made a very great impression upon 
all of us for more reasons than one. She was very sick and 
one day she called Frank, the carpenter, and who as the head 
slave had charge of the others, and told him to bring into 
her room all the slaves he could find on the plantation. They 
were shelling corn at the time, getting it ready to ship to 
the market, and he brought in as many as he could get 
together, I suppose, in a short time. I was not one of them, 
but I was later told by the others what happened. She said 
to them, “Be good and do your work and the time will come 
when you will all be free. The North is not satisfied with 
slavery.” My master's brother was present and heard this and 
after that we were treated very much worse than before. 
Whenever they saw a group of us standing together they would 
come up and make us disperse for fear we were going to raise 
against them. Shortly after that our mistress died and on 
the day of the funeral all of us slaves on the plantation, 
between seventy-five and a hundred, men, women and children, 
followed her body to the cemetery, about five miles away, 
where she was buried.</p>
          <p>It was a very sad occasion, for all the women were crying and 
most of the men too, as well as the children. We knew that 
she was the best friend we had and that now our lot would be 
harder. Shortly after that my master married again, but our 
new mistress did not have the kind heart our old mistress 
had had.</p>
          <p>I do not remember just the year our mistress died and told us 
that we would some time be free, but I think it was about 
1858. At any rate, it was not long before we began to hear 
talk of a war. Our masters were afraid that there would be 
a war. They kept talking against the North. They told us that 
the white people in the North were nothing but shop slaves. 
That the white girls were slaves who did the house work for 
the Northern people and that the Northern people were not 
considered as high class people as the Southern people. It 
was about this time, too, that we first heard of a man named 
Lincoln. They said he was a bad man and that he had horns. 
Another man we heard about was John Brown and the underground 
railroad. Of course we did not understand what the 
underground railroad was. We thought it was some sort of a 
road under the ground. We only knew, of course, what we were 
told. We could not read or write and if any of us had tried 
to learn to read or write we would have been severely 
punished. One reason for the prejudice which the plantation 
owners had against the poor white people in every community 
was that these poor white people naturally sympathized with 
us and the plantation owners were afraid that because of this 
they might teach us to read or might give us some information 
about what the North was trying to do. So we learned little 
about the outside world. We did learn, however, that a man 
named Wendell Phillips and a man named Garrison were getting 
slaves into Canada and we were told that once you got into 
Canada they could not get you back again, that you were free. 
Of course the slaves as a whole wanted to be free. Many of 
them were not treated well and the thought of being sold was 
a very burdensome thing. The slaves on our plantation had 
been told that they were going to be free, and they were 
looking for what their mistress had said to come true. Then 
Colonel Nelson, who owned an adjoining plantation, set all 
his slaves free by his will when he died and they were all 
sent to Liberia. There were about seventy-five of them. And 
we were anxious to be free too. </p>
          <p>I do not mean by all this that our life was altogether bad. 
We had enough to eat and we had certain pleasures. It was a 
common thing for the slaves to have parties where the slaves 
from adjoining plantations came together and danced and sang 
and played. The masters encouraged these parties for the 
purpose of getting the young men and women slaves acquainted 
with one another. They were looked forward to with pleasure, 
for they were the chief social events.</p>
          <p>Another thing we liked to do was attend the camp meetings. We 
liked the singing and speaking. And then it was something for 
us to go to. One of the worst features of slavery was that 
the slaves on a plantation were virtually in prison. They 
could not leave the plantation except with the
<pb id="sing7" n="7"/>
consent of their masters. Then no matter how hard they worked 
they had nothing which they could call their own. Even their 
children did not belong to them. And they themselves were 
liable to be sold away to a distant part of the country to a 
master whom they did not know and who might be very cruel to 
them. Then as there were no schools for us and as we could 
not read you can see how we would want to go to camp meetings 
or to church. So we were always glad when Sunday came. On 
Sunday, masters and slaves all went to church together.</p>
          <p>Our master was a very religious man, being a local preacher 
in the Methodist church. Once every three months the 
Presiding Elder used to visit the church and hold a quarterly 
meeting after he had preached. On one of those visits an 
incident occurred that I still remember even after so many 
years. It showed how bitter our masters were toward any one 
who sympathized with us. And it marked, too, the breaking off 
of religious association between our part of the South and 
the North.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>III</head>
          <p>I cannot remember when the church incident with relation to 
the Presiding Elder occurred, but it could not have been so 
very long before the beginning of the war. We slaves used to 
go to the same church our master and the other plantation 
owners attended. Of course we used to sit back by the door 
by ourselves while they sat up front. The church was about 
five miles away from our plantation. We slaves used to walk 
while our masters rode. This Sunday for some reason they 
left me at home. But after they were gone I happened to 
think of a donkey I often rode and the thought occurred to me 
that I might ride him to church. So I got on his back and 
started off. He carried me to church in good style but when 
we reached there instead of waiting for me to get off he 
threw me off. I had no rope to tie him, so I left him outside 
and went in the church. The result was that he got in a fight 
with another donkey while the church services was in progress 
and created such a disturbance that I was later given a 
severe whipping for it.</p>
          <p>But another thing happened during that service which caused 
a greater commotion than my donkey. Mr. Ayers, the Presiding 
Elder, called upon a colored man named Ennis Dilamar to pray. 
Ennis was a slave who had recently been purchased by my 
master and who had quite a local reputation as a religious 
man. The fact that Mr. Ayers should call upon a slave to pray 
caused great offense to the plantation owners and after the 
service was over and while the masters and their families 
were arranging themselves on the ground to eat their dinner, 
my master called Ennis to him and asked him what he meant by 
asking God to send the time when Ethiopia should stretch 
forth her arm like an army with banners, and said that he 
would teach him better than to use such words as that. Of 
course Ennis could not make any reply to this. He had simply 
been repeating what he had heard some white man say, because 
he himself could neither read nor write. However, they gave 
him a severe whipping right then and there. This seemed to 
disturb Mr. Ayers very much. He withdrew from the company and 
went over to where the slaves were preparing their dinner and 
told them that he did not see why a Christian man could not 
be allowed to use his gift of prayer even if he was black. 
In some way this remark got to the white people. So when the 
afternoon meeting was called my master told Mr. Ayers that 
his service was no longer wanted and that he need not visit 
the church any more. From that time on my master had charge 
of the meetings as local preacher and we never saw Mr. Ayers 
again.</p>
          <p>This incident, as I say, must have happened a short time 
before the beginning of the war, because shortly afterwards 
Samuel Hymans, a young man from our community who was 
attending West Point, came home for a vacation, but when the 
vacation was over he did not return to West Point. Instead 
he commenced to organize a company of soldiers. I was very 
anxious to go with him as his servant and my master, at his 
request, let me do so. The reason why I was anxious to go 
with Hymans was because I wanted to learn how to drill. I did 
learn to drill. In fact I learned how to drill so well that 
after a while when he was busy with other matters he would 
tell me to drill the company for him. After Fort Sumpter
<pb id="sing8" n="8"/>
was fired upon. Hyman's company went to form with other 
companies in Newbern, the First North Carolina Cavalry. This 
regiment was stationed at Newbern until the 14th of March, 
1862, when Burnside and Foster captured Newbern and drove our 
regiment to Kinston. At Kinston, I ran away from the regiment 
and made my way to Burnside's headquarters at Newbern. I 
secured employment as the servant of Col. Leggett, of the 
10th Connecticut Regiment. I told the Colonel my story, but I 
found out later that my story was not believed and that they 
thought I had been sent by the rebels to secure information 
for them about the Union troops. I soon had an opportunity, 
however, to convince them of my honesty. A stranger was 
brought in to the camp and brought to headquarters as a 
suspicious person. He would give no information about himself 
and no one, of course, knew anything about him. Finally I was 
sent for and asked if I knew the man. I replied that I did, 
that he was Major Richardson of the First North Carolina 
Cavalry. After giving this information I was sent out of the 
room and later the adjutant on General Foster's staff came to 
me and told me I must not be too positive about this man 
because he was a Union man. My reply was, “If I am not 
correct, you can cut my throat.” He told the guard to keep a 
watch over me, that they had not got through with me. So I 
was held until they could secure further information. They 
secured information the next day that I was a slave and had 
been a servant for one of the officers in the First North 
Carolina Cavalry and that it was a fact that I had run away 
from there. This information was <sic corr="secured">securred</sic> from Colonel 
Leggett, for it was by his sentries that I was picked up when 
I came into the Union lines. Then I was taken to General 
Burnside's headquarters and asked the best way to reach the 
rebels at Wives Forks, before you could get into Kinston. I 
laid the route out for them the best I knew how, but said 
that if I were going to command the expedition I would give 
them a flank movement by the way of the Trent river, which 
was five miles farther from Wives Forks than the Neuse river. 
But they did not accept my proposition and attacked directly, 
with the result that they were repulsed.</p>
          <p>I took part in that attack as a guide and had a horse shot 
from under me. A few days later I told Colonel Leggett that 
I would not fight any more unless I was prepared to defend 
myself. He said, “We never will take niggers in the army to 
fight. The war will be over before your people ever get in.” 
I replied, “The war will not be over until I have had a 
chance to spill my blood. If that is your feeling toward me, 
pay me what you owe me and I will take it and go.” He owed me 
five dollars and he paid me. I took that five dollars and 
hired the A. M. E. Zion church at Newbern and commenced to 
recruit a regiment of colored men. I secured the thousand men 
and they appointed me as their colonel and I drilled them 
with cornstalks for guns. We had no way, of course, of 
getting guns and equipment. We drilled once a week. I 
supported myself by whatever I could get to do and my men did 
likewise.</p>
          <p>I spoke to General Burnside about getting my regiment into 
the federal service but he said he could do nothing about it. 
It was to General Burnside, however, and my later association 
with him, when I was with him for a time as his servant, that 
I owe what I now regard as one of the great experiences of my 
life. It was one day at the General's headquarters. His 
adjutant pointed to a man who was talking to the general in 
an inner room and said, “Do you know that man in there?” I 
said, “No.” He said, “That is our President, Mr. Lincoln.” In a few minutes the conference in the inner room apparently 
ended and Mr. Lincoln and General Burnside came out. I do not 
know whether they had told President Lincoln about me before 
or not, but the General pointed to me and said, “This is the 
little fellow who got up a colored regiment.” President 
Lincoln shook hands with me and said, “It is a good thing. 
What do you want?” I said, “I have a thousand men. We want to 
help fight to free our race. We want to know if you will take 
us in the service?” He said, “You have got good pluck. But I 
can't take you now because you are contraband of war and not 
American citizens yet. But hold on to your society and there 
may be a chance for you.” So saying he passed on. The only 
recollection I have of him is that of a tall, dark 
complexioned, raw boned man, with a pleasant face. I looked 
at him as he passed on in company with General Burnside and 
I never saw him again.</p>
          <pb id="sing9" n="9"/>
          <p>On January 1, 1863, he signed the Emancipation Proclamation, 
which made me and all the rest of my race free. We could not 
be bought and sold any more or whipped or made to work 
without pay. We were not to be treated as things without 
souls any more, but as human beings. Of course I do not
remember that I thought it all out in this way when I learned 
what President Lincoln had done. I am sure I did not. And the 
men in my regiment did not. I had gone back to Newbern then. 
The thing we expected was that we would be taken into the 
federal service at once. It was not until May 28, 1863, 
however, that the thing we had hoped for so long came to pass, 
when Colonel James C. Beecher, a brother of Henry Ward 
Beecher, that great champion of our race, came and took 
command of the regiment. I was appointed Sergeant of Company 
G, being the first colored man to be accepted into the 
federal service and the only colored man that furnished the 
government a thousand men in the Civil War. The regiment was 
at first called the First North Carolina Colored Regiment. It 
later became known as the 35th Regiment, United States 
Colored troops. Soon afterwards we were armed and equipped 
and shipped to South Carolina and stationed at Charleston
Harbor. From that time until June, 1866, when we were 
mustered out at Charleston, South Carolina, I was in active 
service, ranking as First Sergeant, Company G, 35th U. S. 
Colored Infantry. J. C. White was the Captain of that company 
and Colonel James C. Beecher was the commander of the 
regiment. We saw active service in South Carolina, Florida 
and Georgia. I was wounded in the right leg at the battle of 
Alusta, Florida. After the war ended we were stationed for a 
time in South Carolina doing guard duty and were finally 
mustered out of the service an June 1, 1866. My honorable 
discharge from the service dated on that day, although it is 
worn and not very legible now, as you can see, is one of my 
most prized possessions. Some years ago a man from the 
government service in Washington made out for me in a 
detailed form a record of my war service. It is in much more 
complete form than I have set it down here, but I think such 
details are of more interest to one's family than to the 
general public.</p>
          <p>My life since the war has been the ordinary life of the 
average man of my race. I have not so many accomplishments to 
boast of, but I have done the best I could to prove myself 
worthy of being a free man. I came North shortly after the 
war and settled in New Haven, Connecticut. I secured a 
position as a coachman with a very estimable family, the 
Trowbridges. I worked for six years for Henry Trowbridge and 
then after his wife died I went to work for his brother, 
Thomas R. Trowbridge, for whom I worked for twenty-five years.</p>
          <p>Shortly after the war ended I was converted in a Methodist 
church, of the A. M. E. Zion connection, in North Carolina, 
so when I came to New Haven I joined the A. M. E. Zion church 
of that city. It was in that church that I learned to read, 
although I had learned the alphabet and how to spell simple 
words while I was in the army. I became ambitious to learn 
all I could and so read as many books as I could and availed 
myself of all the opportunities that presented themselves to 
educate myself. I saved some money from my salary, too. After 
the war my mother and brothers remained near Newbern and 
hired a little place known as the Salter place. When I had 
money enough I bought this place. But there was such a strong 
feeling against me at Newbern for the part I had taken in the 
war, that I could not go back there. The <sic corr="Ku">Klu</sic> Klux Klan said 
they would shoot me. My mother lived on the place until her 
death some years later. But I could not even go back to see 
her buried. My brothers remained on the place after that, but 
they did not live very long after my mother. Then I sold the 
place through a Mr. Wheeler of Newbern. I sold it for $200 
more than I gave.</p>
          <p>As a result of my study and interest in religious things I 
gradually began to speak in the church in New Haven. Finally 
I was ordained a deacon and later I was ordained a local 
elder. I conducted for some years the religious services at 
the jail in New Haven and took part in the city mission work 
as assistant to the preacher in charge of that work. After my 
thirty-one years of service with the Trowbridges, I entered 
the itinerant ministry, devoting all my time to it for three 
years as a preacher in the A. M. E. Zion church in Portland, 
Maine.</p>
          <pb id="sing10" n="10"/>
          <p>It was in New Haven, too, that I married my wife. She was a 
Northern girl, Maria Wanton. Our married life was very happy. 
We had one daughter. She is married and lives in New Haven. 
Her husband's name is Chart Fitch. She is the mother of eight 
children, two of whom died in infancy. The other six are all 
active, healthy boys. My wife died in 1898. Later I married 
my present wife. She was Charlotte Hinman, also a Northern 
girl, a resident of Staten Island. She has made we a good 
wife and we have been very happy.</p>
          <p>At the end of my three years as pastor of the church in 
Portland, I resigned from the itinerant work and came to New 
York City, where I worked until about 1906, when I came to 
Peekskill, New York, which has since been my home. I worked 
first at the LeBaron place on Main street. Later I was 
employed by Mr. George F. Clark, an Crompond street, for whom 
I worked thirteen years. During the World War I was for a 
time engaged in work with the local Y. M. C. A. and the War 
Camp Community service. Since the war I have been employed by 
Mr. George W. Buchanan of Peekskill. I have been extremely 
fortunate in my employers. From all I have received kind and 
considerate treatment, vastly different front the rough, 
sometimes brutal treatment I received from my slave masters. 
It is as different, in fact, as freedom from slavery. It is 
impossible, I think, for those have always been free to 
realize the difference. Now I feel that I am a part of the 
country, that I have an interest in its welfare and a 
responsibility to it. As a slave I was only property, 
something belonging to somebody else. I had nothing I could 
call my own. Now I am treated as a man. I am a part of 
society. I am a member of Admiral Foote Post. G. A. R. of New 
Haven, Connecticut, which I joined in 1879. I was for a year 
chaplain of the Post, resigning when I went to Portland. I 
also a member of Oriental Lodge, F. and A. M., of New Haven, 
Connecticut. Since coming to Peekskill I transferred my 
church membership to the Mt. Olivet Baptist Church of 
Peekskill. And I am a citizen of this great country and have 
a part in directing its affairs. When election day comes I go 
to the polls and vote, and my vote counts as much as the vote 
of the richest or best educated man in the land. Think of it! 
I, who was once bought and sold, and whipped simply because 
it was thought I had opened a book. And it is not only I who 
have this privilege, but millions of other men of my race. 
Ah, we can truly say, “Old things are passed away: behold, 
all things are become new.”</p>
          <p>I feel that I am greatly indebted to the government and to 
the American people for what they have done for me and for 
my race. I can not find words to express properly what I 
feel. But my heart is overflowing with gratitude, when I 
think of my situation and the situation of the people of my 
race now, and think of all the blessings we enjoy, compared 
with our former situation. I feel that as long as I live an 
honest life, do my work and conduct myself properly, I have 
the respect and the good wishes of the community. And this
is true, I believe, not only of myself but of every man of 
my race. As long as we are honest and obey the law, seek to 
educate ourselves and to show ourselves worthy of freedom, we 
will have the respect of the American people and fair 
treatment from them.</p>
          <p>It is a great thing to have lived to see this day come. It is 
great to feel that the people of my race understand something 
of the debt they owe this great country and are showing their 
appreciation by trying to be good citizens.</p>
          <p>God has been very good to me. I have preached His Gospel. I 
can read His book. America has been very good to me. I am one 
of its citizens. There is no stain on the Flag now. I once 
fought under its banner. The Great Emancipator is loved by 
the world now. He once shook hands with me.</p>
          <p>Truly I can say with the psalmist, “The lines are fallen 
unto me in pleasant places; yea, I have a goodly heritage.”</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <trailer>(Copyrighted, 1922, by William Henry Singleton)</trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>