<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
<emph> Life on the Old Plantation in Ante-Bellum Days</emph>
<emph>OR</emph>
<emph> A Story Based on Facts:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Rev. Irving E. Lowery,  b. 1850</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Fiona Sewell</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by</resp>
          <name>Fiona Sewell</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Carlene Hempel  and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1999</date>
</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca. 300 K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1999.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Call number E443 .L91 1911a         
(Davis Library, UNC-CH)</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc default="NO">
        <bibl default="NO">
<title>Life on the Old Plantation in Ante-Bellum Days</title>
<title>Or, A Story Based on Facts</title>
<author>Lowery, Rev. I. E.</author>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>Columbia, S.C.</pubPlace>
<publisher>The State Co., Printers</publisher>
<date>1911</date>
</imprint>
</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc default="NO">
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South, Beginnings to 1920.</hi>
</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl default="NO">
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl default="NO">
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass default="NO">
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Lowery, I. E. (Irving E.), b. 1850.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- South Carolina -- Sumter County --
Biography.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- South Carolina -- Social conditions.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- South Carolina -- Sumter County -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- South Carolina -- Social conditions -- 19th
century.</item>
            <item>Freedmen -- South Carolina -- Biography.</item>
            <item>South Carolina -- Social conditions -- 19th century.</item>
            <item>South Carolina -- Social conditions -- 20th century.</item>
            <item>South Carolina -- Social life and customs -- 19th century.</item>
            <item>South Carolina -- Social life and customs -- 20th century.</item>
            <item>United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.</item>
            <item>Plantation life -- South Carolina -- Sumter County -- History $ y
19th century.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- South Carolina -- Sumter County -- History -- 19th
century.</item>
            <item>Southern States -- Race relations -- History -- 20th centur</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>1999-06-25, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Steve Kelley </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-04-29, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-04-27, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Carlene Hempel</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-04-14,</date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Fiona Sewell</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="Image of frontispiece" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <p>
          <figure id="frontis" entity="lowerfp">
            <p>THE AUTHOR<lb/>[Frontispiece Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="Image of title page" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="lowertp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">Life on the Old Plantation
<lb/>
in Ante-Bellum Days,</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="main">OR
<lb/>
A Story Based on Facts,</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>BY</byline>
        <docAuthor>REV. I. E. LOWERY</docAuthor>
        <docEdition>With Brief Sketches of the Author by the Late Rev. J.
Wofford White of the South Carolina Conference,
Methodist Episcopal Church
<lb/>
AND
<lb/>
An Appendix</docEdition>
        <docImprint>
<pubPlace>Columbia, S.C.</pubPlace>
<publisher>THE STATE CO., PRINTERS</publisher>
<docDate>1911</docDate>
</docImprint>
        <pb id="loweryverso" n="verso"/>
        <docImprint>Copyright, 1911
<lb/>
By
<lb/>
THE STATE COMPANY</docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="epigraphs" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <lg type="verse" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <l part="N">“Backward, turn backward, O Time in your flight;</l>
          <l part="N">Make me a child again just for tonight.”</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>MEMORIES.</head>
          <l part="N">O mystic Land of Smiles and Tears,</l>
          <l part="N">O Land that Was and Is,</l>
          <l part="N">Alone—unchanging with the years—</l>
          <l part="N">The Land of Memories.</l>
        </lg>
        <bibl default="NO">—John Trotwood Moore.</bibl>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="contents" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="lowery5" n="5"/>
        <head>CONTENTS</head>
        <list type="simple">
          <item>BRIEF SKETCHES OF THE AUTHOR.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER I.<lb/>
THE OLD PLANTATION.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER II.<lb/>
THE PROPRIETOR OF THE OLD PLANTATION.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER III.<lb/>
GRANNY, THE COOK, ON THE OLD PLANTATION.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER IV.<lb/>
A 'POSSUM HUNT ON THE OLD PLANTATION.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER V.<lb/>
A WEDDING ON THE OLD PLANTATION.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER VI.<lb/>
CHRISTMAS ON THE OLD PLANTATION.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER VII.<lb/>
SUNDAY ON THE OLD PLANTATION,</item>
          <pb id="lowery6" n="6"/>
          <item>CHAPTER VIII.<lb/>
A FUNERAL ON THE OLD PLANTATION.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER IX.<lb/>
A LOG-ROLLING ON THE OLD PLANTATION.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER X.<lb/>
A CORN-SHUCKING ON THE OLD PLANTATION.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER XI.<lb/>
LITTLE JIMMIE, THE MAIL BOY, ON THE OLD PLANTATION.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER XII.<lb/>
A LOVE STORY ON THE OLD PLANTATION.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER XIII.<lb/>
THE BREAKING UP OF THE OLD PLANTATION.</item>
        </list>
        <pb id="lowery7" n="7"/>
        <list type="simple">
          <head>PART SECOND<lb/>
<emph rend="bold">APPENDIX</emph>
<lb/> SIGNS OF A BETTER DAY FOR THE
<lb/>NEGRO IN THE SOUTH 
<lb/>By I. E. LOWERY</head>
          <item>I.<lb/>
INTRODUCTION.</item>
          <item>II.<lb/>
WHITE PATRONS OF NEGRO BUSINESS ENTERPRISES.</item>
          <item>III.<lb/>
WHITE CONTRIBUTORS TOWARD THE BUILDING OF
NEGRO CHURCHES.</item>
          <item>IV.<lb/>
WHITE CONTRIBUTORS TOWARD THE BUILDING OF
NEGRO CHURCHES.—Continued</item>
          <pb id="lowery8" n="8"/>
          <item>V.
<lb/>
WHITE CONTRIBUTORS TOWARD THE BUILDING OF
NEGRO SCHOOLS.</item>
          <item>VI.
<lb/>
CURRENT INCIDENTS OF NEGRO INDUSTRIAL
ACHIEVEMENTS.</item>
          <item>VII.
<lb/>
FRIENDLY EXPRESSIONS OF SOUTHERN WHITE
PEOPLE FOR THE NEGRO.</item>
          <item>VIII.
<lb/>
FRIENDLY EXPRESSIONS OF SOUTHERN WHITE
PEOPLE FOR THE NEGRO.—Continued.</item>
          <item>IX.
<lb/>
THE WHITE PEOPLE'S CARE OF THE OLD BLACK
MAMMIES.</item>
        </list>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="preface" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="lowery9" n="9"/>
        <head>PREFACE</head>
        <p>I have no apology to make, and no excuse to
offer for writing this book—“Life on the Old
Plantation in Ante-Bellum Days.” It is not the
result of vanity, neither is it a desire for notoriety,
that prompted me to write it. No, my
reasons are higher, and my purposes are nobler.
My only desire has been to do good. The religious
element runs through the entire story.</p>
        <p>It has been a work of faith and a labor of love
to me. I cannot express the pleasure I have had
in sitting down, and recalling the incidents of
my childhood and youth. In doing so, it has
enabled me to live my life over again. I only
hope that the reader will experience something
of the same pleasure in reading the book that I
have had in writing it.</p>
        <p>The “Brief Sketches of the Author” were
written just twenty years ago by the late Rev.
J. Wofford White. He was a colored man, and a
close friend of mine, and was born and reared in
the same neighborhood with myself. These
sketches were printed in <hi rend="italics">The Christian Witness</hi>,
a Boston (Mass.) newspaper, and were clipped
and carefully pasted in my scrapbook. I republish 
them in this connection without changing a
<pb id="lowery10" n="10"/>
single word. I would ask the reader to peruse
them carefully, and compare them with Chapter
XI, entitled “Little Jimmie, the Mail Boy,” and
note the similarity of characters.</p>
        <p>I have written this book because there is no
other work in existence just like it. No author,
white or colored, so far as I know, has traversed,
or attempted to traverse, the literary path which
I presume to have trodden in writing this book.
We are now about forty-five years away from the
last days of slavery and the first days of freedom,
and the people who have any personal
knowledge of those days are rapidly crossing the
mystic river, and entering the land that knows
no shadows; and soon, there will not be one left
to tell the story. And it is the author's thought
that a record of the better life of those days
should be left for the good of the future generations
of this beautiful southland. Others have
written of the evil side of those days, but the
author felt it to be his mission to write of the
better side.</p>
        <p>Before the war, the relation that existed
between the master and his slaves was, in most
cases, one of tenderness and affection. There
was a mutual attachment between them, which
has commanded the admiration of the world.
But since the war, an estrangement between the
colored and the white races has sprung up, which
<pb id="lowery11" n="11"/>
has resulted in a feeling of intense bitterness and
alienation. But I am glad to say that things are
now taking a turn for the better. I can see signs
of a better day ahead; and if this book should, in
any way, contribute to, and help on this much
desired day, the author will be satisfied.</p>
        <p>I conclude this preface with the following clipping:</p>
        <div2 type="excerpt" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>WANT TO HONOR OLD SLAVES.</head>
          <p>An appeal to erect a monument to the former
slaves of the South was issued in New Orleans a
few days ago from the headquarters of the United
Confederate Veterans by Gen. George W. Gordon,
commander-in-chief of the veterans.</p>
          <p>The appeal is in the form of a general order,
which quotes the resolutions favoring such a monument
adopted at the Birmingham reunion in 1908,
and adds:</p>
          <p>“Only those familiar with the beautiful <sic corr="patriarchal">patriarchial</sic>
life on the Southern plantations previous to
1865 know of the devotions of the slaves to their
owners and the children of the family. They were
raised more like members of a large household.</p>
          <p>“The children of the owners and the slaves 
associated most intimately together, and enjoyed alike
the pleasure of the home, all receiving the care and
attention of the heads of the family, who had a
feeling of tender affections for these departments.”</p>
          <p>The devotion of these slaves during war time
in caring for the plantations, in sharing dangers at
<pb id="lowery12" n="12"/>
the front and nursing the wounded is noted, and the
order concludes with an appeal to the U. C. V., the
U. D. C., the U. S. C. V., and the C. S. M. A., to
see “that some evidence is given to the world of
their appreciation of the faithfulness and affection
of this devoted people.”</p>
          <closer>
<signed>I. E. LOWERY.</signed>
<dateline>Columbia, S. C., <date>September 13, 1910.</date>
</dateline>
</closer>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="introduction" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="lowery13" n="13"/>
        <head>BRIEF SKETCHES OF THE AUTHOR.</head>
        <div2 type="sketch" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>I.</head>
          <docAuthor>BY THE LATE REV. J. WOFFORD WHITE.</docAuthor>
          <p>When one has accomplished something of good
for his fellowman, and performed work worthy
of praise, people become interested not only in
what he has done, but also in the history of the
person himself. As fulsome praise is invidious,
and heartless flattery no less damaging than
unjust, we shall not make the mistake of
committing the blunder of doing either, but shall
state the facts as they exist.</p>
          <p>The Rev. Irving E. Lowery, A. M., was born in
the County of Sumter, State of South Carolina,
September 16th, 1850, and is, therefore, 37 years
old. His parents were born slaves; it was in this
condition, too, that he came into this world. His
father lives today [He has since died—THE
AUTHOR] at the ripe age of almost four-score
years. He has been known always as a man of
integrity, strict honesty, and possessed of much
energy and industry, and withal a man of much
natural ability. Long before the war, by economy
and frugality, he had saved enough in hard-earned wages to purchase his own freedom. He
succeeded also in purchasing the freedom of his
<pb id="lowery14" n="14"/>
mother, and when Abraham Lincoln issued the
famous Emancipation Proclamation he was
making herculean efforts to purchase his wife.
Under the new order of things, by dint of
perseverance and hard labor by night as well as day,
he managed with shrewdness to secure an excellent
farm, and although today the hoar-frost of
seventy-eight winters is clearly observable, he
superintends his business, is observant of passing
events, and takes a lively interest in the questions
of the day. The mother has been noted
always for her modesty, piety, and Christ-like
demeanor. To her the children are indebted for
all the home training they received that pertains
to the Christian life.</p>
          <p>Years ago, when the subject of these sketches
was a mere boy, this pious mother, without a
dream of freedom, with faith in the God she
served, prayed that He would call one of her
sons to be a preacher of the Gospel, which then
meant to be an exhorter or class-leader. “Only
this and nothing more.” Wonderful as 
mysterious are the ways of God! Long years
afterward that mother's prayers were signally
answered in a way wonderful to speak of—a way
she could not have appreciated at the time the
prayers were offered. It is an example worthy
of being followed by all Christian parents, who
should unfalteringly commit their children by
<pb id="lowery15" n="15"/>
faith and prayer to the Lord. After they are
dead, in answer to the prayers on behalf of their
children, God will in some way bring about
the desired results. How these prayers were
answered will be related further on.</p>
          <p>Brother Lowery had better advantages than
most of the boys on the plantation. Being of a
lively, quick and sprightly disposition, his owner
took him “into the house” when he was quite
young. In the same room, on a little pallet, he
slept with his master and wife. He made the
fires in the early winter mornings, blew the
signal at the break of day for the feeding of the
horses and beginning the preparations for the
labor of the day. As the master was a Methodist
of the old-fashioned type common “in ye olden
time,” there was a family altar in that house, and
this little slave boy was one who bowed at it in
devotion. A little pony for his exclusive use to
ride for mail and do errands, was furnished him.
In going to the county-seat on business, or when
visiting alone or with his family, this boy was
invariably the companion of his master; thus he
saw more than the other boys, came in contact
with more people, obtained a better knowledge
of men and things, and as a result, he became
more observant, more inquisitive, and more intelligent.
Thus, even in a condition of abject thralldom, 
God was making the wrath of men to praise
<pb id="lowery16" n="16"/>
Him by causing them thus to sow the seeds of
usefulness in the heart of one whom He 
determined, in answer to the prayers of a pious
mother, to lead into paths of holiness, usefulness
and peace, and to become a preacher of the Gospel
of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ. As to
church privileges, he had but few, although the
best of such as were allowed slaves. Anon he
was permitted to go to public service at the
church, but more frequently the slaves were
gathered together in old master's yard, and some
exhorter or leader was allowed to come, under
the surveillance of a white man, lest something
insurrectionary be said—and conduct a service
of prayer and praise.</p>
          <p>As this was the limit of their liberty to worship,
it is not to be wondered at that they entered
into their services with a zeal and fervency, and
to this day it is said of the negro that they pray
more, and naturally sing better, than any other
race. We say nothing of slavery, since it is
accursed of God and man, but even with the best
possible circumstances under such a condition
and environment, no one could become efficient
and useful in the highest sense of the term. That
system had no elements to draw out the best in
any one, be he master or slave. It was calculated
to bring out the worst in both, and develop it to
an unlimited degree. This proved to be the
<pb id="lowery17" n="17"/>
invariable result. True, many were saved, and we
know of many good people that lived in those
days, but it must be remembered that God's love
is so far-reaching that it accomplishes what is
impossible to man. Of itself, what did slavery
do for any? What did it do for our brother?
Absolutely nothing. Dear readers, when the
morning of January first, 1863, dawned upon
this fair but then blighted land, and the first ray
of hope—the Proclamation of Emancipation—
burst forth from a leaden sky, he who has ere
this become a familiar name in your household,
had not learned his alphabet, was in blissful
ignorance of his high calling, had dreamed
naught else than a life of slavery; in this condition
because of his training from infancy, he was
contented to live, and worse than all, he had not
tasted of Jesus's blood that purifies our sinful
hearts.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>BRIEF SKETCHES OF THE AUTHOR.</head>
          <head>II.</head>
          <p>More than two years passed after that
immortal document had been made public. Not
till the South had stacked arms at Appomattox,
and agents of the Government sent to every
plantation to effect a legal contract between master
<pb id="lowery18" n="18"/>
and slaves, did the great mass of negroes learn
that they were indeed freed men. When this was
thoroughly understood, old men and women
jumped for joy, young men and maidens clapped
their hands and shouted. The old masters submitted,
apparently, to the new order of things.
When the agent came around, Brother Lowery
was then a boy in his teens, and he signed the
contract to remain that year.</p>
          <p>He continued, till one day he was approached
by his old master's son with a whip in one hand
and a gun in the other. Without any provocation,
he began to thrash the servants unmercifully.
Seeing that his turn would soon come, he
said to a companion, older than himself, “I will
not stand this; I will go to Sumter and complain
to the Provost Marshal.” He leaped over the
fence, and into the dense forest ran, followed by
the friend referred to. Night was fast approaching;
they wandered and traveled through
swamps, and waded branches, till, after a ramble
of fifteen miles, they got to the railroad that runs
by the county-seat. Here they stopped to rest,
as it was late at night, with the damp earth for a
bed and the heavens for a covering. When the
sun arose they aroused themselves, and shivering
with cold, affrighted and hungry, they hurried
toward their destination, about twenty miles
away. They reached the place, inquired their
<pb id="lowery19" n="19"/>
way to the proper office, and were ushered into
the presence of the Provost Marshal. Their
complaint in simple language was made.</p>
          <p>This was Brother Lowery's first public address,
which was a statement of the grievances
he had been made to suffer. After he had
finished the reaction came, and the untutored
youth melted into tears. The redress he sought
was granted in part. A writ from this office
turned him over to the custody of his father.
With him, on a rented farm, he labored. At the
end of that year the family was all reunited. In
the year 1866, through the philanthropy of an
educational society of New England, a free
school, the first ever opened in that community
for negroes, began its session. At the age of sixteen
he was entered by his father and began the
arduous task of mastering the alphabet after the
manner pursued by teachers in ye olden time.
He readily took to learning, and very soon was
reading. His hunger for knowledge became
intense. His father, according to his training,
thought that work stood first in importance, and
schooling was something to attend when farm
work was over. This doctrine was very distasteful
to one who had begun to drink from the
fount of knowledge, so he ran away from his
father, hired his time to work on the railroad;
but the father, with an eye to business, waited
<pb id="lowery20" n="20"/>
patiently till the month was ended, was promptly
on hand when the pay-train arrived and claimed
the wages of his son—he being a minor. When
the youth realized that thus it would be at the
end of each succeeding month, he willingly
returned to the home of his father.</p>
          <p>The father, recognizing the exceeding anxiousness
of the son to become educated, concluded to
send him to school. As this stage marks the
most important change in his life, pardon a little
digression.</p>
          <p>In 1865 the Rev. Timothy W. Lewis was sent
to South Carolina to reorganize the Methodist
Episcopal Church. He was soon strengthened by
the Rev. A. Webster, D. D., recently deceased.
Baker's Institute was established in Charleston
for the training of young men for the ministry.
One of the first to enter it was a brother full of
zeal and the Holy Ghost. This brother belonged
to the same community wherein lived Brother
Lowery, and was widely known for his piety,
having managed, with great secrecy, to obtain a
fair knowledge of English branches. He spent
one year at this institute. As the field was white
and but few laborers, he was sent out to gather
the people and assist in the organization of the
church. This brother swayed great influence
over the old, and especially the young. Among
<pb id="lowery21" n="21"/>
the young men who frequented the church under
his ministry was the subject of our sketch.</p>
          <p>Just about the time his father concluded to
give every available advantage to enable him to
prosecute his studies, he was happily converted
under the pastorate of the sainted Joseph White,
the brother referred to above. He joined the
Methodist Episcopal Church in the year 1867.
His conversion was sound and thorough, and
although he hesitated to obey, he felt the irresistible
call of God to preach the gospel of His Son.
Thus the mother's prayers offered years before,
when her son was a boy, were most singularly
answered in the conversion of this son, and his
being called to the ministry. He was licensed to
exhort in the year 1868, and as the way was
opened, he was directed by his pastor to Baker's
Institute, which he entered and remained two
years—1868 and 1869. He was the first student
that registered at Claflin University. This was
October, 1869.</p>
          <p>There he continued till the latter part of 1870.
In December of that year he was made a local
preacher, joined the South Carolina Conference,
was ordained deacon by Bishop Simpson and
stationed by him at Cheraw. He remained there
two years; he was then, at the beginning of 1873,
sent to Columbia, where he remained till August.
He then went to Wilbraham, Mass., to complete
<pb id="lowery22" n="22"/>
education in the Wesleyan Academy, then
under the presidency of Rev. Dr. Cooke. In the
spring of 1874 he completely broke down in
health and was forced to return home for the
year. Influences, strong and powerful, were
brought forward to induce him to enter politics.
He was offered the nomination for School
Commissioner, then equivalent to an election.
Although the temptation was seductive, the
inducements great and offers flattering, he
turned neither to the right nor the left. He 
commanded Satan to get behind him, and he was
obeyed, for the weakest Christian is stronger
than the devil, because God dwelleth in him.
Until the meeting of the Conference in January,
1875, he taught school in Sumter and was 
principal of the high school. It was here that he met
the young lady who afterward became his wife.
She is of noble and pious parentage, well educated,
and, from peculiar advantages, was reared
in the best colored society and influences in
Charleston. It is a blessed union to both, and
much of Brother Lowery's success in the ministry is due to the industry, energy and helpfulness
of his wife. Five children enliven the interest
of their home life, and they are carefully
instructed in the way of life by their parents.
Theirs is a model, Christian home, where the
family Bible occupies a conspicuous place, and
<pb id="lowery23" n="23"/>
wherein is an altar erected to the Lord of Hosts,
around which, twice a day—morning and evening
—the family gather for worship, prayer and
praise.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>BRIEF SKETCHES OF THE AUTHOR.</head>
          <head>III.</head>
          <p>Rev. I. E. Lowery commenced again his active
work in the ministry in the year 1875, soon after
his return from Wesleyan Academy. He was
appointed to Summerville by Bishop Wiley, an
appointment high in grade, both because of the
intelligence of the local membership and of its
proximity to Charleston, many of whose best
citizens, both white and colored, own homes and
spend the summer there. With satisfaction to
the people he remained there two years, and was
by Bishop Harris appointed to the station of
Greenville, with a membership of about 700,
whose acquirements socially, intellectually and
religiously are equal to that of any membership
of any community or city in the State.</p>
          <p>Soon after this young brother's arrival at his
new field of labor he discovered that the people
he was to serve were not only religious, but were
Christians of a very pronounced and advanced
type, many of whom were blessed with the grace
<pb id="lowery24" n="24"/>
of sanctification. Such openly professed, and,
better still, lived it.</p>
          <p>The Rev. True Whittier is one of the noble
band of Christian missionaries that came to the
South after the war. He was zealous for the
Master. He preached sanctification all over the
upper part of the State, where he served as 
presiding elder, and as a result numbers sought till
they found full peace and cleansing of heart.</p>
          <p>Greenville, of which we now write, was the
principal hot-bed of this phase of Christian experience.
Many here had enjoyed this fullness long
before Brother Whittier's time, but they did not
proclaim it as a distinct blessing. It is possible
that they knew it not. He preached it, it was
believed and many experienced it. This was the
condition of the church when Brother Lowery
took charge. He had not up to this time given
much thought to this subject. Now he was made
to face it. What could he do with a membership
largely in advance of him in Christian experience?
You can imagine the answer to such an
inquiry more easily than it can be given. What
did he do? He did what all ought to do who
have not yet received it. Confessed his lack in
that experience, earnestly solicited the prayers
of the faithful, sought by meditation, prayer and
faith until he found to his joy the blessed
experience of sanctification, a second, separate and
<pb id="lowery25" n="25"/>
distinctly different blessing to that experienced
in regeneration. He began then to preach as
never before. His pulpit efforts were filled with
a holy unction. Hitherto he had with all faithfulness
preached the gospel, but now he preached
a full gospel. While he does not make the subject
a specialty, yet he hesitates not in claiming
it as his own experience, and proclaiming the
necessity of this experience not only to complete
that of all Christians, but until it is sought and
found the whole duty is not performed,
requirements of spiritual life are not met, the danger
line still in sight, and indeed not passed; for
sanctification means, if anything, not only the
pardon of sins, assurance and the other divine
evidences of acceptance; it includes also the idea
of the change in our nature of a proneness,
inclination or natural bent to do evil, to a proneness
or natural bent in us to do that only which
pleases God. From the time of his experience of
sanctification he has been, and is today, a different
preacher altogether. The change is almost
as marked between sanctification and regeneration
as that between the highest type of moral
living and regeneration. For three full years to
an ever-increasing congregation and membership,
he acceptably served the church at Greenville.
It was with greatest reluctance that the
people gave him up.</p>
          <pb id="lowery26" n="26"/>
          <p>By Bishop Simpson, in the year 1880, he was
appointed to Wesley, one of the three important
stations in the city of Charleston. Under him
the membership grew rapidly. Here he remained
three years, full of labors for the Master, and
when he was moved by expiration of the time-limit,
he carried with him the good wishes of the
membership of the church he had served so
faithfully and well. Recently he visited Charleston,
and as an illustration of the hold he has on the
people, the church was crowded to overflowing to
hear his sermons, and by careful computation
1,200 came to hear his lecture, “The Twenty
Years' Progress of the Colored Race.” Bishop
Merrill then appointed him to Cheraw, his first
appointment—an illustration of the theory of the
eternal cycle that brings things back to the same
condition of former times. The people were
jubilant over the appointment. They received
their old pastor with open hearts. Here he
remained three years. Here he was again
wonderfully blessed of the Lord. The charge
prospered beyond that of any administration since he
had left there years before. Here he and his
family were bereaved of the favorite of the
house—a bright 2-year-old boy—who departed
this life and took up residence in Zion, city of
our God. How this bereavement tried their
souls! Other than prayerful meditation and
<pb id="lowery27" n="27"/>
resignation, two incidents were providentially
sent as solaces. One in the person of the 
minister who conducted the burial services, who
selected as a text these beautiful words, “My
Beloved is Gone Down Into His Garden to
Gather Lilies”—<hi rend="italics">Song of Solomon</hi>. Such
suggestive words were to them fraught with the
fragrance of heaven. Ever after, in thinking of
their little boy, these words loom uppermost in
their minds. The other was from the pen of
Bishop Foster, while on the Red Sea, homeward
bound. When as a picture there loomed up
before him all of his life's work and experience
as a minister, he portrayed in graphic style his
trials, struggles and the loss of a child, the first
of that kind experienced by the young itinerant
(himself), etc., which was almost an exact
representation of the feelings and experiences of this
family. To them this article was a message of
condolence divinely sent. After serving a full
Methodistic term here, he was appointed by
Bishop Andrews to his present place of labor,
Aiken, S. C., which, because of the peculiar
circumstances surrounding it, is the most important
appointment, in the Conference at the present
time.</p>
          <p>Brother Lowery is tall and of commanding
appearance. Suave in manner, quiet in disposition
and devotional. His sermons are models of
<pb id="lowery28" n="28"/>
pulpit preparation. His style is more of the
exposito-textual than that of the topical. He
throws his whole soul into the delivery of a
sermon, and not <sic corr="infrequently">unfrequently</sic> somebody is either
converted or so deeply impressed that conversion
follows as a result of his powerful appeals.</p>
          <p>In recent years he has developed taste of a
literary nature. His papers in the columns of
<hi rend="italics">The Witness</hi> are widely read, and the readers of
that journal have formed their own opinions as
to their merits.</p>
          <p>Twice has he been named as anniversary orator
at Claflin University, and twice he has honored
the occasion by efforts that surpassed even the
expectations of his friends. He never sought nor
desired it, yet the university has honored itself
by conferring the degree A. M. upon him. If a
degree is a recognition of worth, then it has
been worthily bestowed in this instance. He is,
however, that same modest, unassuming preacher
of the gospel.</p>
          <p>As a writer, he is painstaking, careful, scrutinizing.
As a student, he is methodical, discriminating,
industrious. As a preacher, he is forcible,
logical, convincing. As a worker, he is indefatigable,
energetic, pushing. As a financier, he
is successful and skillful. As a Christian, he is
sympathetic, consistent and spiritually-minded.
God helping, we predict for him a career of
usefulness to the church, his fellow men and the
cause of Christ.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb id="lowery29" n="29"/>
      <div1 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
        <head>THE OLD PLANTATION.</head>
        <p>At a point about eight miles southeast of
Mayesville, S. C., and about the same distance
southwest of Lynchburg, is a settlement known
as “Shiloh.” There was a church located there
which was called “the Shiloh Church”; hence the
settlement took its name from the church. It
was a Methodist Church, and belonged to that
denomination known as the Methodist Episcopal
Church, South. Not far from the church was a
store owned by a man whose name was Chris.
Player. Mr. Player kept the postoffice, and here
the planters for miles around got their mail. It
was a convenient place for a church and also for
the store and postoffice, for they were located
near where the public road forked at two places.</p>
        <p>Just about two miles from this church, due
north across the swamp, called Pudden Swamp,
was the plantation which forms the scene of my
story. I do not know the number of acres this
farm contained (that is a matter of little consequence
any way), but suffice it to say that it was
a good sized plantation.</p>
        <p>But how shall I begin to describe this wonderful
old plantation? As I write the scene comes
<pb id="lowery30" n="30"/>
fresh before my vision. I imagine I can see the
old farm house, where the white folks lived,
nestled in the midst of a clump of stately old
water oaks. There was a front and back piazza
and there was a brick chimney at each end. It
was a one-story building, with an ell running
back, in which was located the dining room.
About thirty feet east of the building was the
kitchen, and about the same distance in the rear
of the dining room stood the smoke-house and the
store-room. That smoke-house was never without
meat and lard, and that store-room contained
barrels of flour, barrels of sugar, barrels
of molasses and sacks of coffee from one year to
another. And the corn, oh, there was no end to
that. There were several barns, some big and
some little, but when the corn was gathered and
the “corn-shucking” was over and the crop was
housed, the barns were full to overflowing. They
would remind one of Pharaoh's barns in Egypt
at the end of the seven years of plenty. There
was very little cotton raised on that plantation
in those days. Four or six bales were considered
a good crop. But the corn, peas, potatoes, hogs,
cattle, sheep and goats, there was no end to
these. It was a rare thing to buy anything to
eat on that plantation save sugar and coffee.
Shoes were bought, but the clothing for the white
folks and the slaves was made at home. It was
<pb id="lowery31" n="31"/>
the good old “homespun.” On rainy days, when
it was too wet to do outdoor work, the men and
boys got out corn, as they said in plantation language,
for the mill, while the women and girls
carded and spun cotton and wool. A task of so
many hanks of yarn was given them for a day's
work, which was a reasonable task, and when it
was finished they carded and spun for themselves.
They more or less completed their tasks
before night, and by working after night they
were enabled to do almost as much for themselves
as they did for the white folks during the
day. The weaving was almost invariably done
by the young white ladies, or by some one of the
servant girls who was taught especially to do it.
Thus everybody on the place was kept well
clothed, both the white folks and the slaves.
That which the slave women carded and spun at
night was their own, and they usually hired their
young missus, or some other white woman of the
neighborhood, to weave it into cloth for them,
and thus they always had good, clean clothing
for Sunday wear, so that they could go to
“meetin' ” without embarrassment.</p>
        <p>On the east side of the white folks' house was
the orchard. It occupied a space of about five
or six acres and contained a large number of
fruit trees of every description. There could be
found the apple in variety, the peach, the pear,
<pb id="lowery32" n="32"/>
the apricot and the plum. On the west side was
a large vegetable garden, which contained, in
addition to the supply of vegetables for the table,
several varieties of grapes. The arbors built for
these grapes were large, strong and, well cared
for. And the slaves got their portion of all these
delicious fruits. Of course, they were not
allowed to steal them (but this does not signify
that they never resorted to this method of obtaining
fruit), but they could, and did, get fruit by
asking for it.</p>
        <p>At some distance in the rear of the white folks'
house stood the barns and other outhouses, and
a little to the east of these was the large horse
and cow lot and the stables. In front was a
beautiful avenue skirted on each side with lovely
oaks of different varieties. And, strange to say,
about three hundred yards in front of the white
folks' house, and to the east of this beautiful
avenue, was located the “negro quarters.” On
most plantations in those days the “negro 
quarters” was located in the rear, or at least some
distance from the white folks' house. But not
so in this case, for these were located in front,
but a little distance from the house and from the
avenue. But there is another thing that goes to
show that the owners and managers of this
plantation were people of education, culture and
refinement, and that was even the fields were
<pb id="lowery33" n="33"/>
given names. At some distance eastward from
the “big house” was a large field called “Sykes
field.” In the midst of this field stood a large
and beautiful walnut tree. It was customary to
plant wheat, oats or rye in this field, and when
the crop was harvested, which usually took place
in June, the field was then made a pasture.
Every field of the plantation had a good fence
around it, and after the crops were taken off the
horses, cattle and sheep were turned in. It was
a charming sight to see these creatures during
the early morning grazing in different parts of
the “Sykes field,” and when the sun waxed hot
they would gather themselves together and lie
down under this tree and rest. And in the cool
of the afternoon they would start out again.
This was repeated day by day during the summer
season. Still east of the “Sykes field,” and
across the swamp, were two large fields called
the upper and lower “Forks.” North of these
was another called the “Island field.” Then there
were the “New Ground field,” the “Gin House
field,” the “Middle field,” the “Graveyard field”
and the “West field.” It was necessary that these
fields should all have names so that it could be
ascertained where the hands were working, or
where the horses or cows were being pastured.</p>
        <p>There were six horses and two mules on the
place, and they, too, all had names. There was
<pb id="lowery34" n="34"/>
“Old Reuben,” “Old Gray,” “Old Lep,” “Fannie,”
“John” and “Charlie.” John and Charlie were
young horses raised on the place. The mules
were “Jack” and “Ginnie.” Jack was a noble
fellow, but Ginnie was as wicked as she could
be. She had as many devils in her as did Mary
Magdalene before she met Christ. Ginnie did
very well when hitched to the wagon with Jack
or some other horse by her side, but under the
saddle she would not carry double to save your
life. And pull a plow, that depended on the state
of her mind. If she felt like it she would do it,
but if she did not she would kick things to pieces
in a jiffy. When that mule was foaled she was
as good as it is possible for a mule to be, but the
negro who plowed her spoilt her. And if Ginnie
had been granted the gift of speech as was the
good fortune of Balaam's ass, she doubtless
would have said to that negro and to the rest of
mankind in the language of Shakespeare: “Villainous company hath been the spoil of me.”</p>
        <p>It will be noticed that the word “old” precedes
the names of these horses. This does not
signify that they were naturally old, but it was
simply a designation given to them by the slaves,
and the white folks accepted it and so styled the
horses also. The slaves were <sic corr="adept">adepts</sic> at giving
nicknames to animals, to each other and even to
<pb id="lowery35" n="35"/>
the white folks. But the white folks seldom
caught on to the nicknames given to them.</p>
        <p>I cannot close this chapter without speaking
of the adjoining plantations. To the north was
Mr. Isaac Keels and his father, Mr. Billie Keels;
east was Mr. Alex. Lemons; south was Mr. Chris.
Player, and west was Mr. Fullwood and Mr.
Jack Player. The latter was a brother of Mr.
Chris. Player. These all were slaveholders, but
none of them were cruel to their slaves. They
knew that the slaves were valuable property, and,
therefore, took good care of them. Mr. Fullwood
died, leaving a widow and a number of small
children, and the estate could not be settled-up
until the youngest child became of age. This
made it necessary to put the plantation in the
hands of an overseer, and that overseer was Mr.
Rance Player, a brother of Mr. Chris. Player and
Jack Player. He was pretty strict in his discipline,
but not cruel. Such things as bloodhounds
and nigger traders were scarce in that community.
I will not say that they were never seen,
but they were scarce. It was a rare thing for
slaves to be bought and sold in that neighborhood. </p>
        <p>I quote a couple of verses from “Lyrics of
Love,” by Rev. Charles Roundtree Dinkins, a
negro poet. The book was published by <hi rend="italics">The
State Publishing Company of Columbia, S. C.</hi>:</p>
        <pb id="lowery36" n="36"/>
        <lg type="verse" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <l part="N">“Give me the farm, where grows the corn,</l>
          <l part="N">Shouting with tassel gold unworn,</l>
          <l part="N">While breezes roll;</l>
          <l part="N">Where smiles the fleecy staple, white,</l>
          <l part="N">Like snowy fields of Eden bright</l>
          <l part="N">Around the soul.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="verse" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <l part="N">“Give me the farm—the cabin dear,</l>
          <l part="N">With the fireplace so spacious there—</l>
          <l part="N">Full five feet wide—</l>
          <l part="N">With the backlog just burning down,</l>
          <l part="N">Potatoes sweet and 'possum brown</l>
          <l part="N">Right by my side.”</l>
        </lg>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="lowery37" n="37"/>
        <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
        <head>THE PROPRIETOR OF THE OLD PLANTATION.</head>
        <p>The owner of this farm was a remarkable
character. His name was Mr. John Frierson, but he
was called by his intimate friends “Jack Frierson.” There was another John Frierson, who
lived in the upper part of Sumter County, but
this one was sometimes alluded to as “John
Frierson on Pudden Swamp,” to distinguish him
from the other Mr. John Frierson. His age I
do not know, but he lived to be quite an old man.</p>
        <p>He was a Christian and was, perhaps, the leading
man in the Shiloh Methodist Church. I am
told that he was educated for the Christian ministry
in early life, but he never entered that holy
calling. But he became a class leader, and this
was the only sacred office he would accept, and
he filled it well and to the satisfaction of the
ministers and the members of the Shiloh Church.
It was said that he was the best educated man in
all that region of country. He was a very fine
elocutionist and one of the best readers that ever
opened a book or held a newspaper. During the
exciting times that led up to the War Between
the States, and during the four years of that
bloody struggle, the white neighbors—and many
<pb id="lowery38" n="38"/>
of them were men and women of wealth and
intelligence—used to come to the home of Mr.
Frierson to hear him read the papers and to discuss
with him the news and the burning questions of that day.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frierson was married three times. By his
first wife there was born but one child—a boy—whom he named Mack; by his second wife there
were born five children—three girls and two
boys, and by his last wife there was no issue.
The children by his second wife were named as
follows: Mary Ann, Isabella, Rush, Adolphus
and Janie. I have given them in the order of
their birth, as I remember it. These all grew up
to manhood and womanhood. The following
lived to be married off: Mack, Isabella,
Adolphus and Janie.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mack married a lady from Chesterfield
County whose maiden name was Miss Martha
Garland. Her father's name was Mr. Jesse Garland.
He was a farmer, owned a few slaves, but
his daughter—Miss Martha—was handsome and
considered a belle in society. Miss Isabella 
married Mr. Ransom Garland, the brother of Miss
Martha. Mr. Adolphus married the daughter of
Mr. Billie Keels, known as “Little Billie Keels.”
Miss Janie married a Mr. Kirby and afterwards
settled in Columbia, S. C., as I have been
informed. I also learned that she has some sons,
<pb id="lowery39" n="39"/>
and possibly grandsons living there now, and
are merchants in that city. Miss Mary Ann
never married, but lived to be a very pious and
happy old maid. She became housekeeper for
her father after the death of her mother and
until he married again, which was his third and
last marriage. Her own mother was a very
devout Christian, and spared no pains in training
up her children in the way they should go,
so that when they became old they did not depart
from it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rush grew up to a beautiful young manhood
and became quite a favorite among the
young ladies of the community, but the war
broke out and there was a call for volunteers,
and he was among the first to enter the Confederate
army. His leaving the old plantation to
go to the front was a sad occasion. Well do I
remember the morning. The handsome young
soldier in a beautiful new uniform of gray with
shining buttons bade the family and servants
good-bye, never to return. In less than two years
he fell on one of the battlefields of Virginia, and
sacrificed his life for the cause that is so dear
to every Southern white man. When the news
of his death reached the old plantation there was
mourning and weeping among the white folks
and the slaves. He was a good young man, and
was much beloved by all. His body was never
<pb id="lowery40" n="40"/>
brought home, but was buried in that far-off land
along with his comrades in battle. But he was a
Christian, having been brought up in a religious
atmosphere, and by devout parents, and, on the
other side of the mystic river, he has met them,
where peace forever abides and where happiness
is the lot of all such.</p>
        <lg type="verse" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <l part="N">“Asleep in Jesus! far from thee</l>
          <l part="N">Thy kindred and their graves may be;</l>
          <l part="N">But thine is still a blessed sleep,</l>
          <l part="N">From which none ever wakes to weep.”</l>
        </lg>
        <p>Mr. Mack, the oldest son, was also a devout
young man. Like Jacob of old, he was a man of
prayer. There was a place in the thicket in the
rear of the lot where he resorted for private
communion with his Maker every evening at twilight.
When the day's work was done, and when the
horses and mules were stabled and fed, he would
steal away to his sacred retreat and pour out his
soul in prayer. Many were the times when the
writer of these lines, then a boy of twelve, stood
in the road just a short distance away from his
place of prayer, when the stars were being
revealed in the heavens and the crimson gradually
fading away from the sunset skies, and
listened alternately to the plaintive sounds of
the whippoorwill and the audible voice of prayer,
which was tremulous with emotion and frequently
<pb id="lowery41" n="41"/>
accompanied with tears. The scene was
awe-inspiring to the inquiring mind and to the
reverent soul, such as mine was at that time. I
must confess that I scarcely knew what it all
meant. But I sure did love to hear Mr. Mack
pray and the whippoorwill hollo. But, thank
God, I have lived long enough to know what
prayer means.</p>
        <p>But let us consider our subject a little further.
Mr. Frierson invariably observed family worship
twice a day—morning and evening. The Scriptures
were read in course at each service. Singing
was usually omitted except on special occasions,
when perhaps there was a minister present,
one who could sing. But he was never in
such a hurry that he did not have time for family
devotions. It mattered not in what season of
the year and how busy they might be in the farm,
his prayers he would say. And it was always a
treat to hear that man read his Bible and then
to take the different members of his family to a
throne of grace. And his slaves were not forgotten
during these warm, fervent and eloquent
<sic corr="intercessory">intercessary</sic> prayers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frierson always looked carefully after the
morals of his slaves. I have already stated that
he did not allow them to steal if he could
possibly prevent it. He did everything he could to
teach them to be truthful, to be honest, and to
<pb id="lowery42" n="42"/>
be morally upright. He had it understood on
his plantation that there should be no little bastard
slaves there. He gave it out that they were
not wanted. When the boys and girls reached a
marriageable age he advised them to marry, but
marry some one on the plantation, and he would
see to it that they should not be separated. But
if they married some one from the adjoining
plantations, they might be separated eventually
by the “nigger traders,” as they were called in
that day and time. But Mr. Frierson was never
known to separate a man and his wife by sale or
by trading. Nor was he ever known to separate
mother and child. He did not believe in this
kind of business.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frierson was a good man and taught both
his children and servants to fear God and keep
His commandments. The Lord said of Abraham,
“For I know him that he will command his children and his household after him, and they shall
keep the way of the Lord, to do justice and judgment.”
These words may fitly be applied to our
subject—Mr. Frierson—for he certainly
emulated the example of the Father of the faithful.</p>
        <p>There were some free colored people in the
neighborhood. Some of these were free-born,
but others bought their freedom. But all of
them, according to the then existing laws, had
to have some white man to be their guardian.
<pb id="lowery43" n="43"/>
That is, some white man to look after their
interest to see that they got their rights, and to
protect them, if necessary. And Mr. Frierson was
chosen by some of these free colored people as
their guardian. He was a kind-hearted man and
never failed to respond to the call of distress. It
mattered not whether it came from the poor
slave or from the more fortunate freeman or
from the oppressed white brother, he had an ear
to hear the call, a heart to respond and hands to
help. As Alfred Tennyson said of the Duke of
Wellington, so I say of our subject: “The path
of duty was the way to glory.”</p>
        <p>He seemed not to care what men thought of
him, but his whole aim was to please his Maker.
He regarded the voice of conscience as the voice
of God, and to the warnings and mandates of
that voice he was always true.
He was greatly beloved by all his neighbors.
His children, his slaves and all his white 
associates loved and admired him. And when time
shall be lost in the brilliant dawn of eternity's
morning, many shall rise up and call him blessed.</p>
        <lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <lg type="verse" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">“Asleep! asleep! when soft and low</l>
            <l part="N">The patient watchers come and go,</l>
            <l part="N">Their loving vigil keeping;</l>
            <l part="N">When from the dear eves fades the light,</l>
            <l part="N">And the glad spirit takes its flight,</l>
            <l part="N">We speak of death as ‘sleeping.’</l>
          </lg>
          <pb id="lowery44" n="44"/>
          <lg type="verse" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">“Or when, as dies the orb of day,</l>
            <l part="N">The aged Christian sinks away,</l>
            <l part="N">And the lone mourner weepeth;</l>
            <l part="N">When thus the pilgrim goes to rest,</l>
            <l part="N">With meek hands folded on his breast,</l>
            <l part="N">And his last sigh a prayer confessed—</l>
            <l part="N">We say of such, ‘He sleepeth.’ ”</l>
          </lg>
          <signed>Lucy A. BENNETT.</signed>
        </lg>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="lowery45" n="45"/>
        <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
        <head>GRANNY, THE COOK, ON THE OLD PLANTATION.</head>
        <p>The number that constituted the body of
slaves on this plantation was not very large, but
they were a fine-looking set of human beings.
They were warmly clad, well fed and humanely
treated. And, as forty-two years have passed since
“the breaking up of the old plantation,” it is
hardly possible that the writer should remember
the name of every slave born and raised on that
place. And yet he can recall the most of them
and the image of their person still yet lingers
in his memory.</p>
        <p>Here they are: There were Uncle Fridie and
Aunt Nancy, his wife; Uncle Isom and Aunt
Tena, his spouse. There were two young women
on the plantation—Namie and Peggie—who,
after marriage, became very fruitful. Namie
married a man by the name of Tom and Peggie
a man by the name of Sam. Tom belonged to a
Mr. Durant, and Sam to a Mr. Singletary.
Namie became the mother of some nine children
and Peggie some twelve or thirteen. Namie's
children were Melton, Sam, Nellie, Tom, Kellie,
Jimmie, Vinie, Martha and Joe. Peggie's were
Prince, Caroline, Sydney, Mary, Henry, Elizabeth,
<pb id="lowery46" n="46"/>
Aleck, Sammie and four or five others
whose names I cannot now recall. Nearly all of
these grew up to manhood and womanhood and
<sic corr="married">marired</sic> off, and themselves became fathers and
mothers. And when the Emancipation Proclamation
was issued by Mr. Lincoln, there were
perhaps forty or fifty slaves on this plantation.</p>
        <p>But one of the most important characters
among them all was Granny, the cook. She was
slightly lame in one leg. When she was a little
girl she and other children were playing in a bed
of deep sand. She ran and jumped into the sand,
and as her feet sunk into it she suddenly turned
around and this twisted her leg at the knee. The
injury at first did not seem to be serious and no
doctor was called, but her leg grew crooked and
she became lame for life. Because of this lameness
she was favored to the extent that she was
not made a field hand, but was kept about the
house and taught to cook. And right well did
she learn her trade; for she became one of the
most expert cooks in all that region of country.
And she took special pride in her profession,
especially when company came to visit the white
folks. All they had to do was to give Granny
the materials and tell her what to do with them,
and it was done. She always carefully followed
the instructions given by Mrs. Frierson or Miss
Mary Ann, and all was right. When that breakfast,
<pb id="lowery47" n="47"/>
that dinner or that supper was sent into the
dining room, especially when company was “in
the house,” if the reader had been privileged to
look upon it, or to sniff its delicious odor, he
would have thought that there was a Parisian
caterer who presided over that kitchen.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frierson's house was the preacher's home.
Like the Shunammite of old, he set apart a room
in his house and denominated it the “Prophet's
chamber.” He never forgot to entertain strangers,
knowing that thereby some had entertained
angels unawares. Among the preachers who
served the Lynchburg circuit were: Rev. L. M.
Little, Rev. M. A. Connolly, Rev. W. L. Pegues,
Rev. W. W. Mood, Rev. P. F. Kistler, and Rev.
F. Auld. These were all members of the South
Carolina Conference of the M. E. Church, South.
There were two eminent local preachers who
preached acceptably to the people, namely: Rev.
Jesse Smith and Rev. William Smith. These two
ministers were brothers, and the latter, Rev.
William Smith, was the father of three distinguished
Carolinians, namely: the late Bishop A.
Coke Smith, Rev. Charles B. Smith, and the Hon.
E. D. Smith. But whenever these ministers
would preach at the Shiloh church they would
invariably come to Mr. Frierson's either for
dinner or to pass the night. And when Granny,
the cook, was notified that the pastor was
<pb id="lowery48" n="48"/>
coming, she would be delighted and made extensive
preparations in the kitchen and did her best. All
of Mr. Frierson's guests soon learned who the
cook was, and seldom failed to give expressions
of satisfaction when they left the dining room.
Because of Granny's skill, Mr. Frierson did not
have much trouble in persuading his pastors and
friends to accept the hospitality of his home.</p>
        <p>Granny could not be excelled in making and
baking bread. Her biscuits, her light bread and
her johnnie cakes were, to use a modern expression,
“just out of sight.” Reader, do you know
what a “johnnie cake” is? I am afraid that you
don't. If you have never inhaled the odor nor
tasted a johnnie cake I am sure I shall have some
difficulty in making you understand what it is.
It was not baked in an oven nor in a stove, but
before the fire.</p>
        <p>A board was made out of oak, hickory or ash
wood. It was about six inches wide and twelve
inches long, and highly polished. The ingredients
of the johnnie cake were: corn meal and
sweet potatoes for flour, butter for lard and pure
sweet milk for water. I think eggs were also
used and some other seasoning, which I cannot
now recall. These things were carefully mixed in
and then the dough was spread out over the johnnie
cake board and placed on the hearth before an
oak fire. The board was slightly tilted so as to
<pb id="lowery49" n="49"/>
throw the cake squarely before the fire. It
would soon “brown,” as they said, and when
Granny pronounced it done, the very sight, to
say nothing of the odor, would make anybody's
mouth water. Oh, how those preachers did like
johnnie cake! Sometimes they would send for
Granny to come into “the house” and shake her
hand and congratulate this dusky queen of the
kitchen.</p>
        <p>It is said that women have a horror for snakes,
and it is true. Ever since Mother Eve was
beguiled by a serpent, all of her daughters—it
matters not what their color may be, whether
white, black or brown—have an awful dread of
snakes. This intense hatred of the serpent tribe
on the part of the women is of divine origin. In
the Book it is written: “I will put enmity
between thee and the woman and between thy
seed and her seed; it shall bruise thy head and
thou shalt bruise his heel.” Thus spake the Lord
to the serpent in the Garden of Eden.</p>
        <p>But I want to tell the reader a story about
Granny and the snake. The kitchen where
Granny did the cooking was a small board building
that set some distance from the dining room.
It was about fifteen feet wide by twenty feet
long. It had two doors—the doors being in the
sides and opposite each other—and two windows. The building was unceiled. It was a
<pb id="lowery50" n="50"/>
mere shell. There was not even a loft overhead.
This made it a den for rats, and, in consequence
of this, a place for snakes. The rats came in
search of food and the snakes came in search of
rats.</p>
        <p>One evening just about dark Granny was getting
supper, and while stooping down at the fire-place
a great big chicken snake was chasing a
rat on the plate above. They turned the corner
and while passing over the fireplace where
Granny was stooping, the snake fell full length
across her neck and instantly wrapped itself
around her neck. It is needless to say that
Granny alarmed the place. She hollered, she
screamed; the dogs barked and the children
cried. The white folks and the colored folks all
came running to see what was the matter.
Granny left the kitchen and took the yard, and
the yard was a very large one, too. Doubtless the
snake would have fled from fright, but Granny
clutched it with both hands—one hand on each
side of her neck. The men folks could not catch
her to release her from the snake until she
fainted, then they killed the snake and Granny
soon came to. She was not bitten but greatly
frightened. The white women had to finish getting
the supper, while Granny tried to get herself
together again, which she eventually succeeded
in doing. But this was an experience
<pb id="lowery51" n="51"/>
which Granny never forgot. In subsequent years
she used to sit down with a dozen or more children
at her feet and relate to them, in graphic
language, her experience with that old chicken
snake. And oh, how the little ones used to ply
her with questions! But she answered all of
them to their satisfaction.</p>
        <p>But Granny was great along other lines and
for other things than that of cooking. It has
already been stated that when Mr. Frierson lost
his first wife she left a little motherless baby
behind. It was a little boy, and his name was
Mack. But Granny came to the child's rescue
and acted a mother's part. She raised him. She
prepared his food and fed him. She bathed him,
dressed him, took him on her lap, tied his shoes,
combed his hair and taught him his prayers. He
slept in Granny's own bed with his lily white
arms around her black neck. Little Mack loved
Granny and Granny loved little Mack. And
when he became a man he always entertained a
high regard for her, and loved her to the end.
Granny, though she was black, considered herself the mistress on that plantation. She thought
that her color was no fault of hers, but circumstances
(part of the time Mr. Frierson having
no wife) and efficiency, made her head of the
household. When Granny gave orders those
<pb id="lowery52" n="52"/>
orders had to be obeyed. White and colored
respected and obeyed her.</p>
        <p>Granny took great delight in caring for the
chickens and the turkeys. She also gave the pigs
about the yard some attention. All the waste
from the kitchen was carefully saved for them.
She saw that the cows were milked regularly.
She kept the milk piggins and pans clean and
nice, and did the churning herself. Consequently
Mr. Frierson always had a plenty of fatted fowls
for his table and a pig to roast whenever he felt
like it. He also had an abundance of nice milk
and butter. Granny took special pride in providing
these things, and her master felt grateful
to her for it.</p>
        <p>Granny lived to see Emancipation, and, after
becoming free, was taken by her son-in-law to his
own hired home, where she was tenderly cared
for until the angels came and escorted her soul
home to that “happy land far, far away.” She
lived the life of the righteous, and died in the
Christian faith.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="lowery53" n="53"/>
        <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
        <head>A 'POSSUM HUNT ON THE OLD PLANTATION.</head>
        <p>There was a good supply of fresh water fish in
Pudden Swamp in ante-bellum days. The varieties
known and caught in those days were suckers,
pikes, jacks, perches and catfish. But the
slaves hadn't much time for fishing; they had to
work during the day. But they were very fond
of hunting coons and 'possums, and even this
pastime had to be gratified at night.</p>
        <p>The flesh of these animals, when properly
prepared, makes a very savory and palatable dish.
The method of cooking the 'possum or coon
was this: They first parboiled it whole and then
roasted or baked it brown. Sweet potatoes were
also boiled and skinned and roasted around it.
The slaves were very fond of such dishes.</p>
        <p>As has already been remarked, the young men
had a natural fondness for hunting. Like the
sporting men of all races, there were some slaves
who possessed a natural fondness for the chase.</p>
        <p>There were four dogs belonging to the white
folks and perhaps one or two belonging to the
slaves. These were all trained by the slaves.
There was old Sumter, named for General Sumter
of Revolutionary fame, and old Bull, Rip and
<pb id="lowery54" n="54"/>
Tiz. The last two were full-blood fox hounds,
male and female. Better 'possum and coon dogs
never entered the woods. Then there was old
Toler. He was half bull and belonged to Tom.
He was the fighter. When the other dogs failed
he would swing to a 'possum or coon to the last.
A 'possum was not much at fighting, unless he
was caught in his den, then it took all the dogs
to bring him out, and often all failed but old
Toler. He would bring him out or die.
Consequently the boys seldom left him behind. His
presence was necessary to do the fighting.</p>
        <p>'Possums usually inhabit the woodland and
coons the swamps. The boys thought that they
would like to have a 'possum for their Sunday
morning's breakfast, and yet they had been told
by Uncle Fridie and Uncle Isom not to go hunting
on Saturday night, for, as the holy Sabbath
began at midnight and as they had no way of
telling when midnight came, they would be likely
to hunt on Sunday. They owned no watches,
but were told that when the seven stars reached
a point directly overhead that it was midnight.
Such was the case at that season of the year.</p>
        <p>After supper the boys started out. The only
things necessary to achieve a successful hunt was
the dogs and two or three good, sharp axes with
which to cut down the trees when the dogs would
tree the game. They first went to the woods for
<pb id="lowery55" n="55"/>
a 'possum hunt, but, after wandering away for
two miles, the dogs failed to strike a trail. They
then concluded to go to the swamp (Pudden
Swamp), for a coon hunt. Away <sic corr="they">then</sic> went,
holding in their hands bright pitch pine torches.
Now and then they would give to the dogs a keen
coon hunters' whoop, but there came no response
from them. On they went in the dark and dense
swamp, whooping up the dogs. Presently the
clear, full yelp of old Bull was heard. Sydney
said, “It is a rabbit, for old Bull likes to run
rabbits.” “Wait and see,” said Tom. Sam, who
was the oldest in the crowd, and who had more
experience in the hunting business than all the
others, said: “I am waiting on old Tiz, for she
never runs rabbits at night. If she barks then I
will know it's a coon.” Again the boys whooped
to the dogs. Just then a long, rolling bark was
heard, such as a full-blood fox hound would
make when it strikes a warm trail. Sam said:
“Boys, it is old Tiz, and I believe it is a coon.
Come on.” The torch-bearers snuffed their
torches and quickened their steps. Again the
boys whooped. By this time all four of the dogs,
as the hunters used to say, were speaking. Old
Bull, old Sumter, Rip and Tiz. The sound of
their barking and yelping was like different
voices singing the four parts of music. There
was the soprano, alto, tenor and bass. Again
<pb id="lowery56" n="56"/>
the boys whooped. On they went trying to keep
up with the dogs. The fellows got lively as they
thought of the fun just ahead of them, when they
would have the pleasure of witnessing a great
coon-dog fight. But all of a sudden every dog
ceased barking and the hunters stopped. They
did not know what to make of it. Again they
whooped, but there was no response on the part
of the dogs. They listened in silent wonder.
Presently the dogs came in, one by one, with their
tails drooping between their hind legs. The
boys noticed that their bristles were all upturned
and they whined at their feet. The hunters
became frightened and they began to think.
Tom said, “Boys, perhaps it is after midnight
and we are hunting on Sunday.” Instantly all
eyes were upturned as they peered into the
heavens looking for the seven stars, and to their
surprise the seven stars had passed the zenith
and swung far over into the western sky. Then
they remembered what Uncle Fridle and Uncle
Isom had told them about hunting on Sunday.
Immediately they all concluded that God was
angry with them for desecrating His holy day,
and allowed the devil to come after them. It
is needless to say that they left the swamp
unceremoniously, for such was the case. They
ran nearly every step of the way home, and when
they got their breath they awoke the whole negro
<pb id="lowery57" n="57"/>
quarters and related their wonderful but very
unpleasant experience. All the slaves believed
that it was the devil sent after those wicked
boys, but when the white folks heard of it they
said it was a bear, for Mr. Adolphus saw one just
a few days before while squirrel hunting in that
region. But the slaves all held to their belief
and still contended that it was the devil and that
he came in the form of a big black bear. Suffice
it to say that it cured the boys, and from that
time on there was no more 'possum and coon
hunting by the slaves on Saturday night in all
that part of the country.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="lowery58" n="58"/>
        <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
        <head>A WEDDING ON THE OLD PLANTATION.</head>
        <p>The slave young men and young women were
like the young people of all other races, they fell
in love and they married. Their love affairs,
their courtship and their marriage were of the
simplest form. They could not read nor write,
therefore notes and letters did not figure in their
love experiences. But they loved all the same.
Cupid managed to kindle the divine spark in
their breasts, and he had a way to fan it to a
flame.</p>
        <p>Love, as every one who has loved knows, has a
language peculiarly its own. And it is not a
language of words, but rather a language like that
of free masonry. It is a language of grips, of
signs and of symbols. When two young slaves
fell in love with each other the young man would
make it known on his part by a gentle pressure
of the young woman's hand as they shook hands.
Or he would give her a peculiar or affectionate
smile and accompany his action with a loving
gift. And in the majority of cases the gift
consisted in the most beautiful red apple that he
could secure from the orchard. The girl would
rarely eat the apple until the Sabbath was passed
<pb id="lowery59" n="59"/>
and until it had become mellow. The presentation
would likely be made on the Sabbath as they
went or returned from church, and the girl
invariably carried the apple in her hand or
wrapped it in her handkerchief. As she gazed
upon its beauty and inhaled its fragrance, she
would be reminded of the tender love of her
sweetheart.</p>
        <p>When the young man became satisfied that he
had won the heart of his girl, he then proceeded
gently and modestly to ask her to become his
wife. This was called among the slaves “popping
the question.” Having secured her consent, he
next secured the consent of her parents, if she
had any, and the consent of his master and her
master, if she lived on another plantation. This
ended it. He was considered married, and he
took her to be his wife. This was the usual way.
There was no religious wedding ceremony and
no marriage supper.</p>
        <p>But there were a few isolated cases where the
slaves were allowed to marry in due form and
were given a wedding supper. These were the
more prominent or favorite slaves, such as butlers,
coachmen, nurses, chambermaids or cooks,
sometimes enjoyed this privilege. Sam, the foreman on Mr. Frierson's plantation, was granted
such a favor. He married a girl whose name was
Bettie. She belonged to Mr. Isaac Keels, who
<pb id="lowery60" n="60"/>
owned the adjoining plantation just north of
Mr. Frierson's.</p>
        <p>The time was Saturday night and the occasion
was a great one. Careful and elaborate preparations
were made. The Friersons on Sam's side,
and the Keelses on Bettie's side, co-operated to
make the wedding a success. Also the relatives
of the bride and the groom came forward to
render assistance.</p>
        <p>There were six bridesmaids and six groomsmen.
The bridesmaids were all dressed in white
and the groomsmen in black. Most of these costumes
were borrowed—some from the white folks
and some from the colored. The marriage feast
was a bountiful affair. A good size shote, the
gift of Mr. Frierson, was nicely barbecued. Uncle
Tom, the father of the groom, was an expert at
barbecuing. He did a lot of it for the white
folks, especially on occasions of general musters,
weddings, picnics, etc. Dozens of chickens were
roasted, potted and fried. An abundance of
sweet potato custards, apple pies and cakes were
baked, and several large pots of rice were boiled.
Every plantation within a radius of five miles
was represented at that wedding. The marriage
took place at the bride's home, or, I might say,
in the negro quarters on Mr. Isaac Keels' place.
Several white folks were present, especially of
the Friersons and the Keelses. Uncle John
<pb id="lowery61" n="61"/>
Woods, an ante-bellum negro preacher, was
engaged to perform the marriage ceremony. He
was a very intelligent old man. He could read
well and talk fluently. He was considered a
great preacher by the slaves, and many of the
devout white folks were fond of hearing him. He
wore black pants and a black shad-belly or
pigeon-tail coat and white vest. It was a
secondhand outfit, and was the gift of his old master,
Mr. Woods. He also wore a black silk beaver
hat that looked rather seedy because of its
extreme age and exposure to the elements. He
wore a stiff standing white collar that spanned
his neck and touched his ear on each side, and a
white tie. But, withal, he had the appearance of
a distinguished negro clergyman of ante-bellum
days.</p>
        <p>The marriage ceremony took place in the yard.
At some distance in front of the door of the two-room cabin was placed a small table with a clean
white cloth over it and on which were two brass
candlesticks. In these burned two tallow dips
or candles. Behind this table stood the preacher.
Near him sat Jerry Goodman in a chair with a
fiddle, who played the wedding march. The
waiters, as they were called, filed out in couples, a
man and a woman walking together. The groom
and his bride followed in the rear, with the bride
gracefully leaning upon the arm of her beloved.
<pb id="lowery62" n="62"/>
As now, so then, everybody tried to gain a view
of the pair. Perfect silence reigned while Uncle
John read, in a full, clear voice, the Methodist
marriage ceremony. At the end the preacher was
the first to kiss the bride, the groom the second,
then followed kisses from all the bridesmaids and
groomsmen. This was the custom in ante-bellum
days among the slaves.</p>
        <p>The next thing in order was the supper. Two
tables had been built on different sides of the
yard, one for the white folks and the other for
the colored. The table for the white folks was
about twelve feet long and three feet wide; the
one for the colored was about twenty feet long
and three wide. Clean white cloths were spread
over these tables and plates were placed thereon
as close as persons could stand. Food was put
upon these tables until, if they were things of
life, they would literally have groaned under the
burdens of good things. Uncle John was placed
at the head of the colored people's table with the
groom and his bride on the right and the 
groomsmen and bridesmaids on each side down the line.
He asked the divine blessing, or said the grace,
for both tables. There were several tables full
of the guests, but, as the food supply was ample,
all had enough. The whole scene was a picturesque
one, and it was made more so by the
<pb id="lowery63" n="63"/>
glare of the big bonfire that was kept burning in
the yard.</p>
        <p>After supper the fiddle struck up, with the 
nimble fingers of Jerry Goodman on the bow,
and the dancing began and continued until a
very late hour of the night. Early in the next
week Sam, the groom, settled the marriage fee
by giving the preacher, Uncle John Woods, a
peck of clean-beat rice. Thus ended the wedding
festivities on the old plantation.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="lowery64" n="64"/>
        <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
        <head>
<sic corr="CHRISTMAS">CHRITSMAS</sic> ON THE OLD PLANTATION.</head>
        <p>Not many of the slaves knew the historical
significance of Christmas. They could not read
nor write, hence their knowledge of the important
events of history, even those of sacred history,
was exceedingly limited. Most they knew
about Christmas was that it meant a good time
for everybody. It was the custom on the
plantations in that region of the country to kill the
fattening hogs just before Christmas so that all,
white folks and slaves, might have plenty of fresh
meat to eat during this joyous season. This gave
rise to the expression, which originated among
the slaves, “a hog-killing time.” Backbones,
spare-ribs and rice were a favorite dish about
Christmas time.</p>
        <p>There is another thing to be considered about
the way and manner in which Christmas was
observed on the old plantation in ante-bellum
days, and that is this: Three days were usually
given to the slaves for Christmas. The day
before, generally called “Christmas Eve,” and
the day after; hence the slaves thought all three
days were Christmas. They frequently referred
to Christmas Eve as “the first day of Christmas,”
<pb id="lowery65" n="65"/>
to Christmas itself as “the second day of Christmas,”
and the day after as “the third or last day
of Christmas.” And this thought and this manner
of expression have been brought over into
freedom. Among the country colored people we
frequently hear similar expressions used even at
this day and time in speaking of Christmas.</p>
        <p>On some plantations it was the custom to have
all the slaves repair in a body to the white folks'
house on Christmas morning and receive a dram
as “a Christmas present.” Old and young, male
and female, came forward for the “Christmas
dram.” It was certainly a lively time with the
slaves on the old plantation. Those who came
early to the yard would have to wait until all
came. And while they waited they would whistle,
jig or dance, or
<q type="quote" direct="unspecified">
<lg type="quote" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
<l part="N">“They sat and sung</l>
<l part="N">Their slender ditties when the trees were bare.”</l>
</lg>
</q>
</p>
        <p>But this was not the case on Mr. Frierson's
plantation. He was a Christian man, and, therefore,
believed in and practiced the principles of
temperance. He, nor a single member of his
family, were ever known to indulge in strong
drink. Such a thing as whiskey was unknown on
that plantation. But it was freely used on some
of the adjoining plantations. On some of these
<pb id="lowery66" n="66"/>
there were drunkards to be found both among
the white folks and among the slaves. But not
so on Mr. Frierson's place. It was a plantation
where sobriety was strictly taught and practiced
by the white folks, and, consequently, the slaves
were greatly benefited.</p>
        <p>But Christmas was observed on Mr. Frierson's
place in a way that was highly enjoyable to all.
It was the custom on all the plantations around
to give at the beginning of the winter each male
among the slaves a new outfit, consisting of
shoes, pants, coat and a cap. The women and
girls got shoes and dresses. Mr. Frierson made
it a point to give out these on Christmas morning.</p>
        <p>On or about a month before Christmas the
right foot of each slave, male and female, was
measured and Mr. Frierson would get in his
buggy and drive to Sumter, the County seat, and
Sam would bring the two-horse wagon. The
purpose was to buy shoes for the slaves. The
town was only about twenty miles away, and by
starting before day they could, and did, make
the trip in a day, and do all their trading, too.
The topic of conservation during that day among
the slaves while they worked was the trip of the
old boss and Sam to Sumter. As the sun went
down and the time drew near for them to return
the slaves would listen for the rumbling of the
<pb id="lowery67" n="67"/>
wagon wheels and the sound of horses' hoofs.
That night their slumbers were filled with
dreams and visions of new suits, new shoes, new
caps and new dresses. But these things were not
given out until Christmas morning. And while
this glad day was perhaps only a month off, yet
the month seemed longer, the days seemed longer
and the nights seemed longer than at any other
season of the year. This was naturally and literally 
true of the nights, but it was not true of the
days nor the month, but so it seemed to the
slaves. The anxiety, the longing and the solicitude
for the dawn of Christmas morning is indescribable.
The thought of old Santa Claus
among enlightened people never could produce
such a feeling as that which animated the breasts
of these poor, ignorant slaves.</p>
        <p>But Christmas came. The sun arose without
a cloud to obscure his brightness. Breakfast is
over and all hands repair to the “house.”
Presently the yard is full of darkies with smiling
faces and joyous hearts. And there are as many
piles on that long front piazza of the white folks
house as there are hands on that place. In each
pile there are shoes, a suit, or dress, and a cap.
On each pile there is a tag with the name of the
person written on it for whom it is designed.
Now, imagine, if you can, the exquisite joy that
thrilled each heart as his or her name was called.
<pb id="lowery68" n="68"/>
And as each person filed out of that gate on their
return to the negro quarters they seemed to be
as happy as angels. And it is needless to say
that the white folks enjoyed the distribution of
the winter's outfit on Christmas morning as
much as the slaves, for such undoubtedly was
the case. Everybody felt that this was a better
way than having a dram on Christmas morning.
Such was Christmas on the old plantation in
ante-bellum days.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="lowery69" n="69"/>
        <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
        <head>SUNDAY ON THE OLD PLANTATION.</head>
        <p>Sunday was always a welcome day on the old
plantation, not only by the slaves, but also by
the white folks. It came in all right to break
the monotony of plantation life. The older and
more serious ones went to “meetin'” or visited
the sick, or made social calls, while the 
youngsters met other youngsters from the adjoining
plantations and spent the day in wrestling,
jumping, boxing, running foot races and 
sometimes fighting. In the summer season they
would sometimes roam through the fields
from plantation to plantation in search of watermelons and fruits. They would plunge into the
dark and dense swamp in search of wild muscadine
grapes or through the fields for blackberries,
or the pine woods for huckleberries.</p>
        <p>On some of the nearby plantations the younger
slaves were made to do light work on Sunday,
such as minding the birds and crows from the
corn, rice and potatoes. When these plants were
coming up the crows and rice birds were very
destructive. They would pull them up, and often
the whole crop would have to be carefully
replanted. But Mr. Frierson, who planted the
<pb id="lowery70" n="70"/>
same kinds of stuff as was planted on the other
plantations, did not put any of his slaves on
guard in the fields on Sunday, and yet he always
made good crops and had an abundance. He was
a God-fearing man, and held that the Sabbath
was a day of rest for man and beast. He kept
the day as sacred and required all his slaves, as
nearly as possible, to do the same.</p>
        <p>The Shiloh Methodist Church, to which Mr.
Frierson and his family belonged, formed a part
of the circuit known as the “Lynchburg Circuit.”
The parsonage was located at Lynchburg, a little
cross-roads village about eight miles away. The
minister was accustomed to preach in the Methodist
Church at Lynchburg Sunday morning at 11
o'clock and at Shiloh in the afternoon at 3:30
o'clock the same day. His appointment at the
Shiloh Church was once a month, but to keep the
slaves—and especially the younger ones—out of
mischief, Mr. Frierson had preaching in his yard
under the stately old water oaks on the regular
preaching day at Shiloh. This service was
conducted by some one of the old ante-bellum negro
preachers. There was also a Sunday school
conducted at the Shiloh Church in the afternoon
just before preaching. All this was done for the
spiritual and moral uplift of the slaves as well
as to keep them out of devilment, and from
desecrating God's holy day.</p>
        <pb id="lowery71" n="71"/>
        <p>But the service conducted in Mr. Frierson's
yard at 11 o'clock on the preaching day at
Shiloh was the centre of attraction in all that
region of country. The more pious from the
adjacent plantations, both white and colored,
came in large numbers. The services invariably
were conducted by ante-bellum negro preachers.
These preachers were: Uncle John Woods,
Uncle Daniel Gass, Uncle Daniel Hand, and
Uncle Joseph White. Some of these lived just
a few miles away, others again lived a considerable
distance. One, Uncle Daniel Hand,
lived across the Lynches River, over in 
Darlington, the adjoining county. They all had their
day, and they seldom failed to meet it. Of
course, they had to get the consent of their
masters to come, and they invariably brought a
ticket from their masters for their protection.
If they lived far away their masters would let
them have a mule to ride; or if it happened to
be in the work season and the mules were busy,
the master's saddle horse or buggy horse was
given instead. But Uncle John Woods lived the
nearest, and, therefore, was oftenest there.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frierson's front yard was a large one, and,
as has been stated heretofore several times, it
was well shaded with large and beautiful water
oaks. Under these oaks Mr. Frierson had very
comfortable seats placed. There was a seating
<pb id="lowery72" n="72"/>
capacity for possibly 250 or 300 people. They
were arranged so that the audience would face
the east and present a side view to the white
folks, who sat in the long front piazza. At the
east end of these seats, fronting the audience,
stood a small table with a clean, white cloth
thrown over it. On this table was placed a
pitcher of fresh water and a tumbler, a Bible and
a hymn book, and behind it a chair. All this for
the use and convenience of the speaker, who was
always a colored man. No white preacher was
ever known to stand behind that table, though
some of them very much desired to do so. That
long piazza was usually filled with devout white
worshippers, and the seats below with zealous
and enthusiastic colored Christians.</p>
        <p>The scene presented a very unique appearance.
Those who had religion in that day and time had
what is now called “the old time religion.”
Sometimes when the old preacher would warm up to
his subject and grow loud, if not eloquent, the
audience would break forth in shouts of joy and
praise. (While some colored sister would be
jumping out in the audience, some of the white
ladies were known to act in a similar manner in
the piazza. In those days both the White folks
and the colored folks had good religion. The
singing by the colored folks on such occasions
was an important feature of the worship. It
<pb id="lowery73" n="73"/>
was not done by notes nor always by words, but
it was from the heart, and the melody seldom
failed to stir the soul. Rev. Dinkins, the negro
poet quoted previously, describes it thus:</p>
        <lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <lg type="verse" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">“Give me the farm when Sunday comes,</l>
            <l part="N">When all the girls and all the chums</l>
            <l part="N">Meet at the spring,</l>
            <l part="N">When long-eared mules, ox-carts in droves,</l>
            <l part="N">Come sailing through the woods and groves,</l>
            <l part="N">Oh, how we sing!</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="verse" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">“The preacher reads the hymn divine,</l>
            <l part="N">And we remember not a line,</l>
            <l part="N">But sing right on;</l>
            <l part="N">When with the text we start to shout,</l>
            <l part="N">Forgetting shame, or pride, or doubt,</l>
            <l part="N">To heaven most gone.”</l>
          </lg>
        </lg>
        <p>Uncle John Woods was a good preacher, considering
his chances, and had an excellent command
of good English. He was a man of deep
piety, and had the love and respect of both white
and colored. The author herewith reproduces,
from memory, one of his sermons preached in
Mr. Frierson's yard.</p>
        <q direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                <head>A SERMON ON THE OLD PLANTATION.</head>
                <docAuthor>By Uncle John Woods.</docAuthor>
                <p>Text—“The men of Nineveh shall rise in judgment
with this generation and shall condemn it
<pb id="lowery74" n="74"/>
because they repented at the preaching of Jonas;
and, behold, a greater than Jonas is here.”—
Matt. xii:41.</p>
                <p>Brothers and Sisters: These words, which I
have taken for a text, were spoken by our Lord,
Jesus Christ. He spoke them to the people of
His day and time, but He commanded His servant,
St. Matthew, to write them down in a book
so that all the people in all the ages might have
them and take warning. So I bring them to you
today, and you will do well to listen and to take
heed.</p>
                <p>St. Matthew was a servant, brothers and
sisters, and he was a good servant and obeyed
Christ, his Master. Christ called him and he
came and followed Christ. Christ commanded
him to write the gospel and he wrote it. So
Christ wants you and me to obey Him in all
things. He says, “Repent, for the kingdom of
heaven is at hand.” Christ wants us to hear His
voice and obey His words. And if we don't obey
Him he will punish us, for He says in another
place: “He that knows his Master's will and
does it not shall be beaten with many stripes.”
Many of us know, in a two-fold sense, what this
means. But all who are not Christians will learn
to their sorrow one of these days what it means
in a spiritual sense. Christ is our Master, we
are His servants, and if we don't obey Him and
<pb id="lowery75" n="75"/>
repent, He will certainly apply the lash, and
apply it severely, too.</p>
                <p>But let us consider Jonah. He is the man
referred to in the text. Let me read it again;
perhaps you have forgotten it: “The men of
Ninevah shall rise in judgment with this
generation and shall condemn it, because they
repented at the preaching of Jonah; and, behold,
a greater than Jonah is here.”
Jonah was called just like Matthew. Matthew
was called to be an apostle and to write a book,
and he obeyed. Jonah was called to be a
prophet. He was sent to preach repentance to
the people of Ninevah, but he refused to go. It
is hard to tell, brothers and sisters, what were
his reasons for not obeying God and going to
preach to these people. But I remember that
Jonah was a Jew, and, according to his raising
and training, he did not want to have anything
to do with the people of another nation. He did
not wish to associate with them, he did not wish
to eat with them, nor sleep in their houses, nor
to preach the word of God to them. I can't say
Jonah was a wicked man, neither can I say he
was a bad man, for I don't believe that God
would call a wicked or a bad man to preach His
word to the people, no, not even to the heathen.</p>
                <p>Now, what did Jonah do? Let us see. He
ran away, or, at least, he tried to run away from
<pb id="lowery76" n="76"/>
God. He thought he would go down to Joppa,
buy a ticket for Tarshish and take shipping for
that place, as though there was no God in Joppa,
Tarshish or on the sea. My friends, I fear we
sometimes make the same mistake. We do
wrong and then try to run away from God. We
try to hide from His presence. Adam and Eve,
in the Garden of Eden, tried the same trick, but
it would not work. They sinned against God.
They disobeyed Him and ate the forbidden fruit,
and when they found that God was displeased
and angry with them, they hid themselves among
the bushes of the garden. But God came down
and sought them and found them. Right there
in the garden the judgment was set; the guilty
pair was convicted and the awful sentence was
pronounced. In great shame and disgrace they
were driven from that holy place out into a world
of sin, sorrow and misery. If a man breaks God's
holy law and sin against Him, though he may
run away and hide, God will find him and punish
him. The Bible says, “Be sure your sins will
find you out.”</p>
                <p>But Jonah came to Joppa, and, after paying
his fare, he went aboard that ship. He did not
feel good. He did not feel like a man taking a
pleasure trip, nor like a man going off on business.
He did not sit down on deck and converse
with the other passengers. No, under the burden
<pb id="lowery77" n="77"/>
of his terrible guilt he went down into the hold
of the ship among the freight and went fast to
sleep. He went to sleep! Sleep is all right when
it is taken in the right place, at the right time
and under the right circumstances. Otherwise
it is wrong, it is out of place. Hence you see,
brothers and sisters, it is possible for a man to
sleep with a great burden of guilt upon him, and
when he is in great and fearful danger. Jonah
was asleep, but God was wide awake with His
eyes on him. Jonah thought he was hiding, but
God saw him.</p>
                <p>By and by I hear loud thunders begin to roll.
I see dark clouds coming up. The lightnings
flash and play upon the bosom of these black
clouds. The sea roars and the waves rise like
mountains. The ship pitches and rocks and the
shipmaster and his crew become afraid. They
threw some of the freight overboard and every
man prayed to his god, and yet the storm was not
abated. It still raged. Then they thought that
they would cast lots to see on whose account this
terrible storm had come upon them. They felt
that somebody was guilty and they desired to
find the guilty man. And when the lot was cast
it fell upon Jonah. He was the guilty man. Then
the shipmaster went down in the hold and found
Jonah fast asleep. How that man could sleep in
the midst of such a storm is a mystery to me! I
<pb id="lowery78" n="78"/>
cannot understand it. But every sinner is doing
the same thing. He is dead asleep in his sins
while the storm of God's wrath is raging all
around him.</p>
                <p>The shipmaster said to Jonah: “What meanest
thou, O sleeper? arise, call upon thy God, if so be
that God will think upon us, that we perish not.”
When Jonah was awakened, the shipmaster,
his crew and the passengers all gathered around
him and asked him what was his occupation,
what was his country and what was his nation.
And Jonah answered and said: “I am a Hebrew
and I fear Jehovah, the God of heaven, who hath
made the sea and the dry land.” He then confessed
his guilt. He told them that he was trying
to run away from God, and begged them to
throw him into the sea. They did so. But God
had sent a great fish to swallow up Jonah. And
Jonah was three days and nights in the belly of
the fish. Then God told the fish to cast Jonah
out on land, and the fish did so. And when
Jonah got free from the fish he went to Nineveh
and preached repentance to the people, and the
whole city was converted and spared. Now,
Jesus says in my text: “The men of Nineveh
shall rise in judgment with this generation and
shall condemn it, because they repented at the
preaching of Jonah; and, behold, a greater than
Jonah is here.”</p>
                <pb id="lowery79" n="79"/>
                <p>Christ declares here in this text that He is
greater than Jonah. And so He is. This does
not need any argument to prove it. You all
believe that Christ is greater than Jonah.
Jonah was a man, Christ was God. Jonah was
guilty of the sins of disobedience and anger,
Christ yielded perfect obedience to God and was
without sin. Therefore He is greater than
Jonah. But the people of Ninevah repented at
the preaching of Jonah, while Christ, who is
greater than Jonah, came from heaven to earth
to preach to sinners, and they will not hear nor
repent. Therefore the people of Nineveh shall
rise up in the judgment and condemn them.</p>
                <p>My friends, there is going to be a judgment.
God has appointed a day when He is going to
judge the world. All the good angels will be
there. All the devils in hell and out of hell will
be there. All the good people saved in heaven
will be there, and all the bad people lost in hell
will be there. And you, my friends, all will be
there, and I will be there. And if you don't
repent the men of Nineveh will come forth as
witnesses against you. They shall condemn you,
because they repented at the preaching of
Jonah, and behold a greater than Jonah is here,
and that greater one is Christ.</p>
                <pb id="lowery80" n="80"/>
                <p>May the Lord help you all to get ready for
that awful day, for it will surely come!</p>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <p>This sermon, of which the above sketch is a
mere outline, was delivered with great energy
and power, and it produced a deep impression
upon the entire audience.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="lowery81" n="81"/>
        <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
        <head>A FUNERAL ON THE OLD PLANTATION.</head>
        <p>It may appear strange to the reader, but it is
true, nevertheless, that in some way or other the
slaves very often connected sickness and death
with voodooism or conjuration. This belief and
practice of voodooism and conjuration originated
in Africa, and was brought over to
America when the native African was brought
here and made a slave. The idea is deeply rooted
in the negro thought and life. Its history runs
back, perhaps, four thousand years among the
native tribes of that Dark Continent.</p>
        <p>I quote from the <hi rend="italics">University Encyclopedia</hi>:
“Voodoo, a name given by the negroes of the
West Indies and the United States to superstitious
rites and beliefs brought with them from
Africa, and to the sorcerer who practiced these
rites.</p>
        <p>“In the Southern States of the Union there was
at one time a widespread and deep-rooted belief
in the power of these sorcerers. As the negroes
advance in education the belief is dying away.
At one time, however, despite all efforts of religious
teachers to banish the mastery of this belief
from the minds of the slaves, the voodoo “doctor’
<pb id="lowery82" n="82"/>
was an almost omnipotent individual in the
estimation of his fellows. No slave could, under any
pretext, be persuaded to expose himself to the
vengeance or wrath of one of these conjurers.
In some cases there was a reasonable foundation
for these fears, for in not a few instances has it
been proven that some of the voodoos were skillful
poisoners, and while the great mass of their
professed art was a rank imposture, still they
possessed enough of devilish skill to render them
objects of wholesome dread.</p>
        <p>“Their methods were as varied and variable as
the winds. Anything that was mysterious or
likely to impress the ignorant mind with a feeling
of terror was eagerly seized on and improved
by them to their own advantage. Their services
were more often invoked in destructive than in
curative offices. If a negro desired to destroy an
enemy he sought the aid of the voodoo, who, in
many cases, would undertake to remove the
obnoxious one, and the removal was generally
accomplished through the medium of poison. No
doubt exists that in many cases the victim of a
voodoo died from sheer fright, for whenever a
negro had reason to think that he was possessed
by the spell of the voodoo, he at once gave up all
hope, thus hastening the accomplishment of the
end toward which the energies of the sorcerer
were directed. Their incantations and
<pb id="lowery83" n="83"/>
spell-workings were always conducted with the
greatest secrecy, no one being allowed to witness the
more occult and potent portion of their ritual.
They were frequently employed by dusky swains
to gain for them the affections of their hardhearted
inamoratas, and love powders and other
accessories for ‘tricking’ constituted their stock
in trade, and in some instances yielded them no
insignificant revenue. The field in which voodooism
flourished best was the far South, among
the rice, cotton and sugar plantations, where the
negroes were not brought into contact so closely
with their masters as they were further North.”</p>
        <p>The above quotation is a correct presentation
of the conditions as they existed on the Frierson
plantation, as well as on every plantation in the
Southern States. What was true of one as
regards voodooism and conjuration, was true of
all of them.</p>
        <p>Well, there was a girl on the Frierson plantation
by the name of Mary. She was a black girl
of medium size, but rather good looking. She
was quite a favorite among the young men of the
place and neighborhood. Several, so to speak,
were cutting after her. Mary was a daughter of
Aunt Peggie and Uncle Sam. But it came to
pass that she took sick, and, after a lingering
illness of possibly four or six months' duration,
she died, leaving behind her a little infant.
<pb id="lowery84" n="84"/>
During the entire period of her sickness it was
whispered around on the plantation, also on the
adjoining plantations, that Mary had been
conjured. Of course, this meant that she had been
poisoned. There was a woman who lived on a
plantation not far away, whose name was Epsey.
This woman was said to have been Mary's rival
in a love scrape, and, therefore, was accused of
being the one who administered the dose. Some
conjurer of the neighborhood prepared the dose
for her, so it was said. This thing—Mary's
sickness and death, and the talk of her being
conjured—stirred the negroes on all the plantations
for miles around.</p>
        <p>But the white folks took no stock in all these
rumors and gossip. They knew that Mary was
sick, therefore they sent for Dr. Adolphus Higgins
Frierson. He was a brother of the proprietor
of the old plantation, and was a graduate
of a medical college in Philadelphia, Pa. He
was a learned man and a very competent physician.
He was the family physician for the white
folks, and also attended the slaves.</p>
        <p>Dr. Frierson treated Mary, but the slaves did
not think that he understood the case perfectly
well. He said Mary had been “hurt” or “conjured,”
and that he alone could cure her. So he
<pb id="lowery85" n="85"/>
treated her secretly at the same time that Dr.
Frierson was treating her. But it came to pass
that Mary died and her funeral was the largest
ever held in all that region of the country.</p>
        <p>Death always made a very profound
 impression upon the slaves. They could not understand it. Their dead was invariably buried at
night or on the Sabbath, at which time the slaves
from the adjoining plantations attended in large
numbers. Mary's funeral took place at night.</p>
        <p>The coffin, a rough home-made affair, was
placed upon a cart, which was drawn by old
Gray, and the multitude formed in a line in the
rear, marching two deep. The procession was
something like a quarter of a mile long. Perhaps
every fifteenth person down the line carried an
uplifted torch. As the procession moved slowly
toward “the lonesome graveyard” down by the
side of the swamp, they sung the well-known
hymn of Dr. Isaac Watts:</p>
        <lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <l part="N">“When I can read my title clear</l>
          <l part="N">To mansions in the skies,</l>
          <l part="N">I bid farewell to every fear</l>
          <l part="N">And wipe my weeping eyes.”</l>
        </lg>
        <p>Mary's baby was taken to the graveyard by its
grandmother, and before the corpse was deposited
in the earth, the baby was passed from one
<pb id="lowery86" n="86"/>
person to another across the coffin. The slaves
believed that if this was not done it would be
impossible to raise the infant. The mother's
spirit would come back for her baby and take it
to herself. This belief is held by many of the
descendants of these slaves, who practice the
same thing at the present day.</p>
        <p>After this performance the corpse was lowered
into the grave and covered, each person throwing
a handful of dirt into the grave as a last and
farewell act of kindness to the dead, and while
this was being done the leader announced that
other hymn of Dr. Watts:</p>
        <lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <l part="N">“Hark! from the tombs a doleful sound</l>
          <l part="N">My ears, attend the cry;</l>
          <l part="N">Ye living men, come view the ground</l>
          <l part="N">Where you must shortly lie.”</l>
        </lg>
        <p>These hymns were sung with a spirit and
pathos which were sufficient to move the heart
of a savage. A prayer was offered, the doxology
sung and the benediction was pronounced. This
concluded the services at the grave. No burial
or committal service was read, for it was only
now and then that one could be found among
the slaves who could read well enough to do it.
At a subsequent time, when all the relatives and
friends could be brought together, a big funeral
<pb id="lowery87" n="87"/>
sermon was preached by some one of the
ante-bellum negro preachers. And this practice has
been brought over into the land of freedom, and
is still observed in some places and by some
colored people at the present day.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="lowery88" n="88"/>
        <head>CHAPTER IX.</head>
        <head>A LOG-ROLLING ON THE OLD PLANTATION.</head>
        <p>The slaveholders of ante-bellum days had some
customs that were very convenient, and, at the
same time, very helpful to each other. There
were no markets and butchers in the country,
where they could get fresh meats: hence they
formed a market among themselves, and each
man was his own butcher. That is, a number of
them formed themselves into a club, one of which
killed a fat young beef every Saturday, and a
choice piece was taken to each member of the
club. Thus they were supplied with nice fresh
beef every week. This beef was not sold, but was
distributed around among the members of the
club as a sort of an exchange arrangement. When
a member of the club killed, he put the whole
beef into the wagon (except his own choice or
piece) and sent it round to each member of the
club, and they made their own selection. When
the club was formed, each member subscribed to,
or promised to take so many pounds each week,
and it was done. This arrangement obtained all
through the country, and it worked very nicely.
There was another arrangement, which was
formed by the planters for mutual helpfulness:
<pb id="lowery89" n="89"/>
namely, the log-rolling. A day was set on which
the log-rolling was to take place, and then
invitations were sent out to the neighboring planters,
and each sent a hand. This work was returned
when the others had their log-rolling. A log-rolling
always meant a good dinner of the best, and
lots of fun, as well as a testing of manhood. This
testing of manhood was something that everybody
was interested in. The masters were concerned,
and consequently they selected and sent
to the log-rolling their ablest-bodied men; the
slave women were concerned: for they wanted
their husbands and sweethearts to be considered
the best men of the community. Then, too, the
men took great pride in the development of their
muscles. They took delight in rolling up their
shirt sleeves, and displaying the largeness of
their arms. In some cases, their muscles presented
the appearance of John L. Sullivan—the
American pugilist.</p>
        <p>The woodlands of the South were covered with
a variety of trees and undergrowth. Among the
trees, were to be found the majestic pine, the
sturdy oak, the sweet maple, the lovely dogwood,
and the fruitful and useful hickory. When a
piece of woodland was cleared up, and made
ready for planting, it was called “new ground.”
In clearing up new ground, the undergrowth was
<pb id="lowery90" n="90"/>
grubbed up and burned; the oaks, maples, dogwood,
and hickories were cut down, split up, and
hauled to the house for firewood; and the pines
were belted or cut round, and left to die. After
these pines had died and partially decayed, the
winter's storms, from year to year, would blow
them down: hence the necessity for the annual
log-rolling. These log-rollings usually took place
in the spring of the year. They formed an
important part of the preparations for the new
crop.</p>
        <p>On the appointed day, the hands came together
at the yard, and all necessary arrangements were
made, the most important of which was the pairing
or matching of the men for the day's work.
In doing this, regard was had to the height and
weight of the men. They were to lift in pairs,
therefore, it was necessary that they should be as
nearly the same height and weight as possible.
The logs have all been cut about twenty feet in
length, and several good, strong hand sticks have
been made. Now, everything is ready, and away
to the fields they go. See them as they put six
hand-sticks under a great big log. This means
twelve men—one at each end of the hand-stick.
It is going to be a mighty testing of manhood.
Every man is ordered to his place. The captain
gives the order, “Ready,” and every man bows to
<pb id="lowery91" n="91"/>
his burden, with one hand on the end of the
handstick, and the other on the log to keep it from
rolling. The next command given by the captain
is, “Altogether!” and up comes the big log. As
they walk and stagger toward the heap, they
utter a whoop like what is known as the “Rebel
yell.” If one fails to lift his part, he is said to
have been “pulled down,” and therefore becomes
the butt of ridicule for the balance of the day.
When the women folks learn of his misfortune,
they forever scorn him as a weakling.</p>
        <p>At 12 o'clock the horn blows for dinner, and
they all knock off, and go, and enjoy a good
dinner. After a rest, for possibly two hours, they
go to the field again, and finish up the work for
the day. Such was the log-rolling in the “days
before the war.”</p>
        <p>At a subsequent day the women and children
gather up the bark and limbs of these fallen trees
and throw or pile them on these log heaps and
burn them. When fifty or seventy-five log heaps
would be fully ablaze in the deepening of the
evening twilight, the glare reflected from the
heavens made it appear that the world was on
fire. To even the benighted and uneducated
slave, the sight was magnificent, and one of
awe-inspiring beauty.</p>
        <pb id="lowery92" n="92"/>
        <p>The custom of log-rolling, under the changed
condition of things, may be done away with, but
its name still lingers in the thought and language
of modern times. It is often heard in gatherings,
both religious and political, where everything
goes, or is<hi rend="italics"> made</hi> to go <hi rend="italics">one way</hi>. Such they say is
“log-rolling.” The idea comes from the fact that
in a log-rolling, every man does his part, and
every man goes the same way. There is unity of
purpose, and concert of action. <hi rend="italics">This</hi> is 
“log-rolling” in modern times.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="lowery93" n="93"/>
        <head>CHAPTER X.</head>
        <head>A CORN-SHUCKING ON THE OLD PLANTATION.</head>
        <p>All who have the good fortune to have been
born and reared in the country, can recall with
pleasing recollections the joy that welled up in
all hearts during the harvest. Rev. Dr. Henry
Duncan, an English writer of singular ability,
says: “The heart thus opened, is prepared for
that social enjoyment which we observe so
remarkably diffused over whole bands of reapers
engaged in the same toilsome but healthful
employment. The emotion spreads from heart to
heart, and the animation which prevails while
the work proceeds, is not less an indication of
gladness than the joke and song with which the
welkin resounds during the intervals of rest.
Who can view the joy which sparkles in the eye,
and bursts from the lips of the reaper while he
plies his daily tasks and not acknowledge a
beneficent Creator?”</p>
        <p>In the Book of Ruth we have a vivid and beautiful
picture given us of an oriental harvest. The
fields of Boaz teem with plenty. The golden crop
yields its stores to replenish his granaries. The
voice of the season calls for the reapers. They
take down their sickles and whet them until they
<pb id="lowery94" n="94"/>
are keen and bright. Then away to the
harvestfield they go, followed by the binders and
gleaners; among the latter is the lovely Ruth.
With patient industry they ply the sickle from
morn till noon, at which time they gather, master,
reapers, binders and gleaners, to partake of
their bountiful meal. This they do with a beautiful
simplicity and with great joy and gladness.
And this joy and gladness is not the result of
having a plenty to eat and drink, but the responsive
gratitude of the finer qualities of the heart
for the gracious and lavish gifts of a Divine
Providence. This sentiment—joy at the return
of the harvest—is characteristic of human
nature. This is the testimony of all ages the
world over. So it was with the ancient Egyptians,
Greeks, and Romans. And so it is with us
at the present day. The writer of these pages
can remember the time when, even in America,
the grain harvest was a time of great rejoicing.
Of course this was before reapers or harvesters
became so common. The neighbors for miles
around used to send each a hand, with the
old-fashioned “cradle,” to our house, to assist in
reaping down the harvest. And when ours was
all done, we sent to help each of them. This was
the custom in those days. With twenty hands
we could reap down nearly a hundred acres in a
<pb id="lowery95" n="95"/>
day. Each reaper had a binder to follow him,
and each binder had a little boy to gather up the
handfuls as fast as the reaper would let them
fall, and hand them to him or her. The writer
was one of those little boys. It was fun for us.
We always had a plenty to eat and drink of the
best the farm afforded. The fun, the sport, and
the joy we all had cannot be described. Only
those who have had some acquaintance with farm
life can imagine how we enjoyed it. What we ate
and drank, and the joy the harvest afforded,
constituted a considerable portion of our reward for
bearing the burden and the heat of the day in the
harvest field. This was wheat harvest, which
usually occurred in June.</p>
        <p>But the corn harvest came in the fall, and the
corn-shucking always took place at that season.
The fodder was generally pulled or stripped in
August and September, and the ears of corn were
left on the stock to dry until about the first of
November. But now the day has come, and the
corn breaking has begun. The hands all go to
the field, and they break off the ears and throw
them into piles. These piles are made in the
middle of the same row about twenty feet apart,
and contain the corn of some twelve rows. Two
wagons, each drawn by a pair of mules or horses,
with bodies the same size, are loaded level full of
<pb id="lowery96" n="96"/>
corn. At the barn yard it is thrown into two
piles preparatory to the corn-shucking. One
load is put on this pile, and the other on that,
and so on, until the entire crop is hauled in.</p>
        <p>Then the night is set for the corn-shucking: for
it was usually had at night, so that the slaves
from the adjacent plantations could come and
enjoy the sport. Invitations were sent far and
near, and they were readily accepted. Great
preparations were made in food and drink. The only
drink allowed at the corn-shucking was coffee,
but it was customary on some of the plantations
to have whiskey at corn-shuckings, but Mr. Frierson
never allowed it.</p>
        <p>It was often the case that from fifty to seventy-five
men, beside the women, came to the corn-shucking.
All these had to be fed. Great pots of
rice, meat, bread and coffee were prepared. It
was enough for all who came and took part in
the corn-shucking.</p>
        <p>When all the invited hands had arrived, the
first thing in order was the election of two men
to be captains, and these captains selected their
companies from the crowd present. It was done
alternately, something after the manner of school
boys when they make up their sides to play a
game of baseball. Captain Number One had the
first choice, and then his opponent, and so on,
<pb id="lowery97" n="97"/>
until the two companies were made up. These
preliminary matters having been arranged, they
then set in to shucking corn.</p>
        <p>The reader will remember that there are two
piles of corn of equal size, and now there are two
companies of shuckers of equal numbers, each
company having a captain. It was considered no
little honor to be elected captain of a corn-shucking
company. His hat or cap was invariably
decorated with the inside shucks of a large ear of
corn. He was delighted with the office, and
everybody—white and colored—did him honor.
In the election of these captains, regard was had
to their ability to sing: for the captains usually
led their company in singing while shucking
corn. At a given signal, each captain took his
seat on the top of his pile of corn, and his
shuckers surrounded it. While they shucked
corn they engaged in singing corn-shucking
songs. Much of the fun of the occasion depended
upon which side should win. It was a race that
grew more exciting as the piles of unshucked
corn grew less. They shucked, they sang, and
they shouted. Then they knew that a bountiful
supper awaited them just as soon as the work
was done. On they went—a jolly good set, singing, joking and laughing. In the midst of it all,
they could sniff the aroma of hot coffee, and the
<pb id="lowery98" n="98"/>
delicious odor of roasted meats and other nice
dishes. This, as well as the hope of victory, was
quite an inspiration to the boys. Well, the work
is done. The last ear of corn has been shucked,
and captain number one, with his company, has
won. See the boys, as they toss their hats into
the air! Hear them shout! The victory is theirs.
They are a happy set.</p>
        <p>Supper is now ready. Long tables—well laden
with good things—have been prepared. Fully
two score colored women are there to wait on
the table. And they eat, and eat, and drink, to
their satisfaction. The supper being over, with
the moon shining brightly (moon-light nights
were invariably selected for corn-shuckings) the
boys spend some time in wrestling, foot racing
and jumping before going home. And in all
these games they matched one's agility, strength,
and manhood against that of his fellow. This is
kept up until a late hour of the night, and then
they retire to the various plantations whither
they belong.</p>
        <p>Such was the corn-shucking on the old plantation
in ante-bellum days. It was very much
enjoyed by both the white folks and the slaves.
The incidents and the happenings of a corn-shucking were long talked of on all the
plantations represented. Nearly all the plantations
had their corn-shuckings, and they certainly kept
things lively during this season of the year in
those days.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="lowery99" n="99"/>
        <head>CHAPTER XI.</head>
        <head>LITTLE JIMMIE, THE MAIL BOY, ON THE OLD
PLANTATION.</head>
        <p>Little Jimmie was, perhaps, the most interesting
character on Mr. Frierson's plantation. He
was not a mulatto in the strict sense of that
word. Webster, who is an authority on the
meaning of words in the English language, says:
“A mulatto is the offspring of a negress by a
white man, or of a white woman by a negro.”
Jimmie was the son of Uncle Tom and Aunt
Namie. Both of them were mulattoes. Both of
their fathers were white and both of their
mothers were black.</p>
        <p>Jimmie's father—Uncle Tom—was a free
man. He was born a slave, but purchased himself
and his mother long before the first gun of
the Civil War was fired. He was a man of industry;
frugality, and wisdom. His wife—Aunt
Namie—possessed the same qualities as her
husband in an eminent degree, to all of which she
added another very desirable quality, and that
was a deep and sincere piety. Though a slave,
she was one of Zion's noblest daughters.</p>
        <p>Jimmie was not like Isaac, a child of promise;
nor like Moses, a goodly child; nor like Samuel,
<pb id="lowery100" n="100"/>
a child of desire and prayer; but like the
unnamed offspring of David and Bathsheba, he
was a child of affliction. According to the testimony
of his mother, his father, and his grandmother,
he came into the world a sorely afflicted
child. They never thought that they would ever
succeed in raising the little fellow. But they
did all in their power for the child, backed by the
efforts of the white folks; and God blessed the
means used, and the child lived, and grew to be
a bright and active little boy.</p>
        <p>Jimmie possessed a lively, sunshiny, and
frank disposition, which never failed to win
friends for him. Consequently, from his early
childhood, he became a general favorite on the
plantation among both the white folks and the
slaves. Just as soon as he became old enough,
his old master took him from his mother to be
his waiting-boy. This necessitated his eating at
the yard and sleeping in the white folks' house.
Family prayers were invariably had, evening and
morning, and Jimmie was always called in. The
family sat in a semi-circle around the fireside,
and Jimmie's little chair formed a part of that
semi-circle. The Bible was read in a most
impressive manner, and prayer was offered. The
memory of those days has always been helpful
and a source of inspiration to Jimmie.</p>
        <pb id="lowery101" n="101"/>
        <p>But Jimmie had many narrow escapes from
death. In the big house, he slept on a pallet
before the fire. One night, between midnight
and day, his bed took fire. And, strange to say,
it burned some considerable time before he
realized what was the trouble. It is true, he felt the
fire, but, in his sleep, he imagined himself being
toasted by a big oak fire on a cold winter's night.
However, he awoke, and to his utter astonishment,
found his bed to be on fire. He aroused
himself and tried to put the fire out, but failed.
By this time the large room was filled with
smoke, which became stifling. One of the young
ladies—Miss Mary Ann—awoke, and asked if his
bed was not on fire, and Jimmie told her, “Yes.”
She told him to take it out into the yard, which
he did. He then applied water, and put it out.
He sat up the balance of the night, but, like a
shipwrecked seaman, he wished for the morning.</p>
        <p>When Jimmie was about twelve years of age,
he had a narrow escape from death by drowning.
It was the custom among the slaves—both men
and boys—to go in swimming after dinner. The
place was a deep lake on the stream called Pudden Swamp. Up to this time Jimmie had not
learned how to swim. The edge of the lake was
shallow, but as you advanced toward the centre,
it became deeper and deeper until it reached
perhaps some twelve or fifteen feet. The boys
<pb id="lowery102" n="102"/>
of Jimmie's age and size bathed near the banks,
while the men, and those who could swim
plunged into the deep. Once Jimmie ventured
too far out, and got into water where he could
not touch bottom. Down he went: and when he
arose, he screamed. This attracted the attention
of all who were in bathing. He sank again, and
when he came up the second time, his oldest
brother Sam, who was an expert swimmer,
caught him and saved him. Thus he was rescued,
through the mercy of God, from a watery grave.
Had this occurred on an occasion when these
men were not present (for the boys often went
in swimming without them) Jimmie would
certainly have been drowned.</p>
        <p>This boy was full of mischief, and reckless
daring. He would venture to ride wild horses,
unbroken mules, and even untamed steers. Once,
while riding the little mule Jack, he was thrown
with violence and tremendous force to the
ground. It nearly killed him. After lying there
awhile, he came to, and got up, but no traces of
the little mule could be seen. In after years,
Jimmie thought on these narrow escapes from
death, and took comfort in the saying of an old
writer: “Second causes do not work at pleasure.
This is the bridle that God has upon the world.”
Lack of space prevents the writer from recording,
in detail, all the miraculous deliverances from
<pb id="lowery103" n="103"/>
death, which marked the life of this much favored
youth.</p>
        <p>Jimmie was something of a privileged character
on Mr. Frierson's plantation. It is true, he
had to work in the field along with the other
hands. Sometimes he dropped corn and peas;
sometimes he thinned corn and cotton; and sometimes he hoed or plowed. But when Mr. Frierson
would go off on business in his buggy, Jimmie
had to go along and drive him. When his
daughters went to church, or to make social calls,
he went to drive them, and to care for the horses.
So Jimmie had the privilege of attending all the
big meetings, the weddings, and the parties of the
white folks. All this proved to be of considerable
advantage to him in gaining knowledge and
information. Frequently on his return from
some of these trips, the slaves would gather
around him—old and young—to hear him tell
what he saw and heard. And for days these
things would be discussed by the body of slaves.
This helped also to break the monotony of
plantation life.</p>
        <p>But as Jimmie grew up to young manhood, he
became an expert horseman. There were none on
the place, even among those older than he, white
or colored, who could surpass him in this particular.
His old master—Mr. Frierson—was so
<pb id="lowery104" n="104"/>
well pleased with Jimmie's achievements along
this line that he gave him a pony named Charlie.
This horse was a chestnut sorrel, with a star in
his forehead, and a double mane, or a mane that
fell gracefully on both sides of his neck. He was
built exactly like a race horse. His body was
long and slim, and his legs long and slender. His
tail was of medium length, and inclined to be
bushy. Jimmie ran many a race with Charlie,
and had him so thoroughly trained that no horse
or mule on that plantation, or on the adjoining
plantations, could run with him. It was Jimmie's
duty—in addition to the work he did on the
farm—to go twice a week—Wednesdays and
Saturdays—to Mr. Chris Player's, two miles away,
for the mail, and to bring up the cows and sheep.
Hence Jimmie never made a full hand on the
farm, but worked when he was not needed for
other duties.</p>
        <p>But there is another interesting incident in the
life of this youth, which the author cannot fail
to relate. It occurred when he was about fifteen
years of age. In the spring of 1865 the War
between the States ended. The result was, all
the slaves became free. A contract was signed
by master and slaves to remain together the
balance of that year and finish the crop.</p>
        <pb id="lowery105" n="105"/>
        <p>It was now in the fall of that year, and the
crops were being gathered. The children and
young folks were sent to the field to pick peas.
Jimmie was one of the number. The field was in
sight of the white folks' house. From this house
the white folks had a splendid view of these
youngsters. They worked tolerably well until
toward sundown, when they became very playful
and frolicsome. From the house, the white folks
saw their pranks. But nothing was said, yet
they noticed that young “Mas Dolphus” was
coming toward them with his double-barrel
shotgun on his shoulder. They suspected nothing;
but supposed that he was going on a squirrel
hunt, as he was wont to do in the cool of the
afternoons. As a matter of course, the youngsters
all sobered down to work—seeing “Mas Dolphus”
coming. And not a word was spoken, until he
walked right up to Jimmie, and drew from under
his coat a long whip, and began to lay it on him.
The young master uttered these awful words as
he continued to hit Jimmie: “Run if you dare,
and I'll blow your brains out.” Of course, the
sight of the gun, and the threatening words of the
young master had a decided effect in taming this
young freedman. He stood and took it as good
naturedly as he possibly could. And when he
had gone the rounds (for he gave all a little) and
<pb id="lowery106" n="106"/>
left, Jimmie said: “I am not going to take this:
for I am going straight to Sumter, and report
this fellow to the Yankees.” Brave words these!
for a boy of fifteen, who was born and bred a
slave, and taught nothing but to obey. He left
the field immediately, jumped over into the
swamp, went around the plantation, entered his
mother's house, got his Sunday clothes, and
struck out for Sumter, twenty-five miles away.
He was followed by a boy called Henry, who was
six months his junior, but was somewhat larger
in stature. Henry had never been more than five
miles from home in his life, and knew nothing
but to work. Hence, it will be seen that Jimmie's
traveling companion was not calculated to
encourage him very much.</p>
        <p>From the white folks, Jimmie had learned that
the slaves were all free, and that the country had
been put under military government. From them
he learned that there was a garrison of Union
soldiers in the town of Sumter, and that there
was a provost marshal there, who heard and
settled difficulties between the freedmen and
their former owners. It was a knowledge of
these things that prompted him to do what
he did.</p>
        <p>Jimmie and Henry left the old plantation just
about dark. They told nobody of their departure,
<pb id="lowery107" n="107"/>
not even their mothers. How it must have pained
them, when they discovered, at supper time, that
these boys came up missing. Those were critical
times. The war had just closed, but the country
was still infested with lawless wanderers, who
did not hesitate to commit crimes of all kinds.
Robberies and murders were quite common. But
in the face of all this, they plunged into a long,
dark, and dense woods. Jimmie did not know
the way to Sumter by the way of the State road,
though he had traveled it several times with the
white folks. But he knew that the railroad coming from Wilmington, N. C.—which ran within
twelve or fifteen miles of Mr. Frierson's place—
and going to Kingville, S. C., went by Sumter:
for farmers from that section always crossed it
near Sumter, going into the town. Now, Jimmie's
plan was, to get to the railroad, and then
following the track in a westward direction, they
would be sure to reach Sumter. And, after persuing
their journey through these fifteen miles
of black forest, they struck the railroad about 11
o'clock in the night. Jimmie at once suggested
to Henry that they camp for the night. It was
agreed to. So they crossed the railroad, and
went about a hundred yards, raked up some pine
straw and oak leaves, and lay down to sleep close
by the side of each other. They slept as quietly
<pb id="lowery108" n="108"/>
and as sweetly as two little fawns. Sometime
during the night, Jimmie was aroused by a
passing train. As he raised up, and saw its glaring
headlight, and heard its thundering noise, which
shook the earth beneath him, he was so terribly
frightened until he could not call Henry. The
next morning he asked Henry if he heard or saw
the train in the night, and he said, “No.”</p>
        <p>They arose betimes, and began their long
journey for Sumter. They had no breakfast. In
fact, they had had no supper the night before.
They left home so unceremoniously until they
forgot to take provisions for the journey. It is
needless to say that they left in great haste: for
such was the case. They had no money, and
knew nobody by the way, and yet they did not
steal. They reached Sumter, and found their
way to the provost marshal's office before he
came down. And, to their surprise, they met a
crowd of other colored people there, who, like
themselves, had had difficulties with their
former owners, and came from all parts of
the country, seeking redress. They were heard
one at a time. And when these boys' turn
came, they entered the office as timidly as a hare.
This was their first sight of a Yankee soldier in
uniform. There were two of them, but the boys
could not remember their names. When Jimmie
<pb id="lowery109" n="109"/>
and Henry were asked in a most tender manner
what they wanted, the former's heart was so
touched, until he burst into a flood of tears. But
when his tears were brushed away, Jimmie
rehearsed the whole matter to them. This was
his first public speech, and he never forgot it.
The officers asked the boys if they had parents,
and they told them, “Yes.” But Jimmie told
them that his father was a free man, and was
living on a rented farm to himself. The provost
marshal wrote him a note—telling him that his
son was now free, and that he must take care of
him, and not allow him to return to the old
plantation. This was done. Henry was given a letter
to Mr. Frierson, which he took back to him, and
was not molested.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="lowery110" n="110"/>
        <head>CHAPTER XII.</head>
        <head>A LOVE STORY ON THE OLD PLANTATION.</head>
        <p>This love story is not a tale of fiction, nor is it
one of romance, but it is a real story of love
based on facts. It contains all the elements
necessary to the making of a fascinating novel
of two hundred or more printed pages. The
characters were both slaves—having been born and
reared in that condition. Nevertheless, they
were not so lowly as to escape Cupid's notice.
He aimed a dart at the heart of each of them,
and in each case it struck and stuck fast. The
flame that was kindled in these hearts by the son
of Mars and Venus was as pure, and burned as
fervently as in any human breast.
Jimmie, the bright little mail boy, fell in love
with Isabella. This young girl was a beautiful
quadroon. She was inclined to be tall, and somewhat slim, and possessed a lovely face. Her skin
was fair, her eyes were dark, and her hair was
black and fell in curls upon her shoulders. Her
teeth were white, and it seemed that nature took
special pains in making them in a uniform size,
and in adjusting them in such a way that they
would be attractive, and an object of admiration
<pb id="lowery111" n="111"/>
to all with whom she came in contact. Her
dresses were always neat and clean. They were
such as were worn by the nurses and chambermaids
of the well-to-do white folks of that day
and time. This beautiful girl—Isabella—
belonged to Mr. Charles Durant, who lived on
Lynches river, about five miles above Lynchburg,
on the main road to Bishopville. This put a
space of some twelve miles or more between
Jimmie and his lover. And while he loved her
dearly, yea, with all his heart, yet he could not
go to see her. The distance was too great, and
he was too shy and young. Therefore he had to
wait until the spring season, when the quarterly
meeting took place at the Methodist church at
Lynchburg, or until the fall, when the annual
camp-meeting was held at the old Tabernacle
camp ground on Lynches river about four miles
below Lynchburg.</p>
        <p>As already stated, the Methodist parsonage
was located at Lynchburg, and, perhaps, the
largest and most important church of the circuit
was at this point. And when the quarterly meeting
of this church took place, it brought together
many people from different parts of the circuit,
and among them were the Friersons and the
Durants. It was here that Jimmie would have
the privilege of meeting his sweetheart—Isabella.
<pb id="lowery112" n="112"/>
She was nurse and waiting maid for the Durants,
and was invariably brought along to care for the
baby. Jimmie was coachman, and came as driver
for the Frierson girls. While the services would
be going on in the church, and the minister would
be delivering one of his most eloquent discourses
to an intensely interested audience, Jimmie and
Isabella would be sitting out in the carriage talking love, and making plans which they could
never be able to execute. Being slaves—and
quite youthful at that—there were insurmountable
barriers in the way, which they did not
dream of. But it was a great pleasure for
them to meet on these big meeting occasions,
and look at each other, smile at each other,
and tell each other how much each loved
the other. One did not doubt the sincerity
and genuineness of the other's love. Each felt
that their love was reciprocated, and this, in a
measure, gave them satisfaction. These quarterly
meetings lasted only about two days—Saturday
and Sunday—and thus ended the interviews
of Jimmie and his beloved Isabella. These
meetings usually were held every three months
on the charge, but in the Lynchburg church it
took place in the spring of the year, and these
lovers would meet no more until the fall, when
the great Tabernacle camp-meeting came on.</p>
        <pb id="lowery113" n="113"/>
        <p>The location of this camp ground has already
been mentioned. The annual camp-meeting was
a great occasion. Everybody went to camp-meeting
—white and colored. Many of the prominent
farmers connected with the Lynchburg circuit,
were tent-holders at this camp ground. Mr.
Frierson and Mr. Durant had tents on the same
line. These tents were built of pine lumber, and
in cottage style. They were built with several
rooms, and with front piazzas. They formed a
large circle, with the tabernacle, or church, in
the center. Elevated scaffolds, about three feet
square, with earth thrown up on them, and a
bright lightwood blaze burning on the top,
constituted the lighting system of the encampment.
In addition to these scaffold-lights, there were
bonfires built on the ground in front and in the
rear of each tent. All culinary work was usually
done at this fire in the rear.</p>
        <p>When the trumpet would sound, which was a
signal for the commencement of the services at
the tabernacle, and when the white folks and
the more serious servants and slaves would repair
thither for worship, Jimmie would go over to Mr.
Durant's tent, and spend the evening with his
beloved Isabella, or at least until services at the
tabernacle were out. This was done each evening,
while the camp-meeting lasted, which usually
<pb id="lowery114" n="114"/>
was five or six days. These camp-meetings were
great occasions. In fact, they were the biggest
occasions that came within the experience of
plantation life, and were hugely enjoyed by all,
white and colored, old and young, male and
female.</p>
        <p>The last camp-meeting that Jimmie and Isabella
attended was in the fall of 1864. The
following year the white people who owned
Isabella moved away to parts unknown to
Jimmie. Hence he gave up all hope of ever
seeing his lover again, and doubtless Isabella did
the same. But while the sacred flame of love
burned down, it was never completely extinguished.</p>
        <p>In the fall of 1865, as has already been stated
in a previous chapter, Jimmie left the old plantation,
and went to the Yankees at Sumter. The
provost marshal returned him to his father, who
lived on a rented farm near Lynchburg. Here
Jimmie worked on his father's farm during the
summer months, and went to school at Lynchburg
in the winter. After completing the course
in this school, his father sent him to a school of
a higher grade at Sumter. About this time
Jimmie was converted, and became a Christian.
He also felt that he was divinely called to preach
the Gospel to his people. Consequently his
<pb id="lowery115" n="115"/>
father sent him to Charleston, S. C., to study
divinity in the Baker Theological Institute, and
afterwards to Claflin University at Orangeburg.</p>
        <p>In December, 1870, at the age of 20, he joined
the South Carolina Conference of the Methodist
Episcopal Church, and was sent to Cheraw. He
arrived at this historic old town on a Saturday
night, and, was met at the station by one of the
officers of his church by the name of Johnson.
This brother accompanied the young pastor to
his own home, where he spent the night.</p>
        <p>The next morning, which was the Sabbath, the
young preacher repaired to the church in
company with Brother Johnson. There was a large
congregation present to see, and hear the new
preacher. Expectation, born of genuine curiosity,
was at its height. This was true of both the people
and the preacher.</p>
        <p>At the close of the services, the people—both
the brothers and the sisters—gathered around
the chancel to become acquainted with the new
pastor, and to extend to him a warm welcome.
Among the sisters, who came forward, Jimmie
noticed one who exhibited traces of having been a
most beautiful woman. She was tall, with fair
skin; dark eyes, and straight black hair. But
Jimmie also noticed that her teeth had been
shattered, and some of the front ones were gone.
<pb id="lowery116" n="116"/>
But he suspicioned and suspected nothing.
Jimmie was an innocent and inexperienced young
fellow. But this woman, like every other member
of her sex, possessed a woman's instinct.
While the other folks withdrew from the altar,
she still lingered, and once more brought herself
face to face with the young stranger.</p>
        <p>Then she ventured to say to him: “I think I
have met you somewhere before.” “I do not
remember,” said the young pastor. “But where
are you from?” said the woman. “Lynchburg is
my home,” answered the preacher. “Well, please
pardon me, were you ever a slave?” asked the fair
inquirer. “I was,” he replied. “Well, to whom
did you belong?” she asked. “I used to belong to
the Friersons on Pudden Swamp.” “Well, please
tell me what might be your first name.” “My
first name is James, but all my friends call
me ‘Jimmie.’ ” “Oh, don't say so!” she said,
excitedly, while her beautiful black eyes filled
with tears. She then gently dropped her head,
and wiped her eyes with a handkerchief that was
well saturated with cologne. When she had
succeeded in getting her face straight, she looked up
and said in a very familiar way, “Jimmie, don't
you know me?” He replied, “I can't say that I
do.” Then came the astounding words, “I am
Isabella, that used to belong to Mr. Charles
<pb id="lowery117" n="117"/>
Durant.” Jimmie was stricken with dumbness,
and when he became able to break the silence, all
he could say was: “Well, well, well.” It is needless
to say that they were glad to see each other:
for their joy was inexpressible. For a few
moments, while they stood there, they gave a
brief account of their whereabouts during the six
or seven years since they last met at the old
tabernacle camp ground. During this period
Isabella had married, and she and her husband
both were members of Jimmie's church.</p>
        <p>About this time, he met a young woman of
education, a successful school teacher, whom he
courted and married. She was born of free
parents, and reared in one of the large cities of
the South. She is a woman of deep piety, and
sustains a high moral standard. She is a great
church worker, and much of Jimmie's success in
the ministry has been attributed to the aid she
has given him. She has proved herself to be a
helpmeet indeed. Isabella was beautiful, but
was not a woman of education, and therefore
could not have filled the bill, and God knew it,
and, in His wisdom, ordered otherwise. In discussing
this matter, Jimmie has often been heard
to repeat the lines:</p>
        <lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <l part="N">“In each event of life, how clear</l>
          <l part="N">Thy ruling hand I see!</l>
          <l part="N">Each blessing to my soul more dear,</l>
          <l part="N">Because conferred by thee.”</l>
        </lg>
        <pb id="lowery118" n="118"/>
        <p>But all through life Isabella continued to show
a fondness for Jimmie. Some years after this,
she moved away to the Land of Flowers, and, as
an evidence of her friendship for him, she
shipped him a crate of beautiful Florida oranges.
Since that they have lost sight of each other.</p>
        <p>N. B.—Since the above chapter was written,
Jimmie, in his wanderings, chanced to meet a
sister of Isabella, and from her he learned that
she (Isabella) moved from Florida to New
Jersey, where she died. Thus ended the earthly
career of a beautiful woman, and a lovely
character. But Jimmie is still alive, and is doing
active work as a gospel minister.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="lowery119" n="119"/>
        <head>CHAPTER XIII.</head>
        <head>THE BREAKING UP OF THE OLD PLANTATION.</head>
        <p>On the morning of April 12th, 1861, the first
gun of the great Civil War was fired. It was
fired on Fort Sumter from a Confederate battery
located in Charleston harbor. It was a terrific
bombardment of thirty-four hours' duration.
This was the beginning of a struggle which
resulted in the emancipation of 4,000,000 <sic corr="repeated word">of</sic>
slaves. On the 1st day of January, 1863,
President Abraham Lincoln issued his famous
Emancipation Proclamation, and it completely swept
away the institution of African slavery, which
had had an existence on the American continent
for two hundred and forty-four years. But this
Proclamation did not go into universal effect
until General Lee surrendered at Appomattox
Courthouse on the 9th of April, 1865.</p>
        <p>At this time—April 9th—the farmers in the
South had pitched their crops. The corn, the
cotton, and the potatoes had been planted, were
up, and growing nicely. And now comes the
emancipation of all the slaves, and if they all
leave the old plantation at once, what would be
the result? It meant starvation and death both
<pb id="lowery120" n="120"/>
for the white folks and the newly made freedmen.
But the authorities at Washington relieved the
situation by advising the landlords and the ex-slaves
to enter into contracts to remain together
until the following January, to work the crops,
and to divide them at the harvest in the fall.
This was done.</p>
        <p>We come now to the most pathetic part of our
story, namely: “The Breaking Up of the Old
Plantation.” And well do I remember it. I do
not remember the day of the week—whether it
was Monday, Tuesday, or some other week-day—
but most vividly do I remember the scene.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frierson—on a certain day—requested all
the hands on the plantation to come to the
“house.” The men, the women, and the children
were included in his order. And some of the free
colored people of the neighborhood heard of the
order, and they also came to see and hear. In
those days of excitement, curiosity reached a
high degree of feverish expectation and desire for
knowledge, for information, and for light. The
slaves had heard of the Emancipation Proclamation,
which had been issued a little more than two
years before, but which had never changed their
condition. They had also heard of the surrender
of General Lee, which put an end to the war. Mr.
Adolphus—a Confederate soldier—had returned
<pb id="lowery121" n="121"/>
home, and there he sat at a small table on the
front piazza, writing. The paper which he was
writing afterwards proved to be the contract
between the landlord and the ex-slaves, which
they were called together to sign.</p>
        <p>It was a beautiful spring day. There was not
a cloud in the heavens to obscure the brightness
of the sun. The yard in front of the piazza, and
in front of the east end of the same, was crowded
with negroes. Their faces were all turned toward
Mr. Frierson, who stood on the piazza with the
contract in his hand. Their eyes were fixed on
him, and their ears were attentive. But before
he read the contract, he made to them a speech.
He spoke, in part, as follows:</p>
        <p>“My Servants: I call you together today, to
read this contract to you, and have you all to sign
it. This is the order issued by the Government
at Washington. The North and the South have
been engaged in a four-years' bloody war. As
you all know, I have had two sons at the front—
your Marse Rush and your Marse Adolphus.
Your Marse Rush was killed in battle by those
cruel Yankees, and is buried in an unknown
grave in that far off land. Your Marse Adolphus
—through a kind Providence—passed through
the awful struggle without receiving as much as
a scratch, and has been permitted to return home
<pb id="lowery122" n="122"/>
to us again. I know you all are glad, and rejoice
with me in his safe return.</p>
        <p>“But I must now tell you that you all are no
longer my slaves. All the colored people who
have been held in the South as slaves are now
free. Your freedom is one of the results of the
war, which has just closed. I do not know what
you all are going to do after this year. I do not
know whether you intend to leave me, and go out
to seek homes elsewhere, or whether you will
remain. But I want to assure you that I will be
glad to have you all remain—every one of you.</p>
        <p>“There is not one among you that was not
born in my house, save four, namely: Uncle
Fridie and his wife, and Uncle Isom and his wife.
These four came into my possession by inheritance. They were my father's slaves, and when he
died, at the division of his estate, they fell to me.
I have kept them through all these years, even
down to old age. And when they became so old
and feeble that they could not work, I have
kindly clothed, fed and cared for them. I have
made them as comfortable in their declining
years as it was possible for me to do.</p>
        <p>“Then again, I declare unto you that I have
not been cruel to any of you. I have not abused
you myself, and did not allow anybody else to do
it—not even my own sons, Mack, Rush, nor
<pb id="lowery123" n="123"/>
Adolphus. And all the neighborhood knew that
I did not wish to have my negroes imposed upon.
The patrols so understood it. And to avoid
trouble with them, and to keep them from slashing
your backs when they caught you away from
the plantation, I always wrote you a ticket or a
pass. But some of you have gone off without my
knowledge, and without a ticket, and have been
caught and whipped, but it was not my fault. I
was not to blame for that. You, yourselves, were
responsible for it.</p>
        <p>“There is another thing which I want to call
your attention to. I have never put an overseer
over you, neither have I employed a ‘nigger
driver’ on my plantation. I have owned no blood
hounds, and have not given any encouragement,
nor employment to those who have owned them.
I have never separated, by selling nor by buying,
a mother and her child; a husband and his wife.
Of the truth of this, you will bear me witness.
In all these matters, I have the approval of a
good conscience.</p>
        <p>“And now, I wish to say again, you are no
longer my slaves, but you all are now free. And
I want to say to you that I bear no ill-will toward
you. You are not responsible for the great change
that has come upon us, and for the separation of
master and servants. Others are responsible
<pb id="lowery124" n="124"/>
for these things. In the future let us be friends
and good neighbors. You all have been taught
to work, and to behave yourselves, and I hope
you will continue to lead such lives in the
future.”</p>
        <p>At the close of this talk, Mr. Frierson read the
contract, in which it was agreed that all the
slaves should remain on the plantation until the
first day of January, 1866, when the crop would
be divided. When he had finished reading, the
older heads of these ex-slaves filed in one by one,
and touched the pen in the hand of Mr. Adolphus,
and made their mark. They then left the yard,
and returned to their work.</p>
        <p>But what were their feelings? Ah! words are
inadequate to describe them. Their joy was
unspeakable. But they had good sense. They
imagined what were the feelings of the white
folks because of the loss of their slaves. They
knew that they were chafed in their minds, and
that an outward demonstration of joy on their
part would be unwise. Therefore their rejoicing
was a subdued rejoicing. Though they had been
kindly treated, and their relations to, and their
attachment for, the white folks had been one of
tenderness, yet they welcomed the change, and
were glad of the new order of things. But they
scarcely knew what it all meant. It was decidedly
<pb id="lowery125" n="125"/>
a new experience to them. They all
remained except Jimmie until January.</p>
        <p>During the fall the crops were harvested and
divided according to the provisions of the contract,
and when January came, there was a breaking
up, and a separation of the old plantation.
Nearly all the slaves left and went out and made
contracts with other landlords. A few remained
for one year, and then the last one of them pulled
out and made their homes elsewhere. Thus they
were all scattered, as it were, by the four winds
of the heavens, never to come together again
until the judgment.</p>
        <p>Sometime during the next spring (1866) Mr.
Frierson, the proprietor of the old plantation,
went out into the field to view his growing crop,
and fell with a paralytic stroke, and died soon
after. He was buried at the old family graveyard.</p>
        <p>In 1886, just twenty years after the breaking
up and separation of the old plantation, Jimmie,
the mail boy, (now the Rev.——) returned to
Lynchburg to visit his parents—Uncle Tom and
Aunt Namie. It was during this visit that Jimmie
proposed to his mother that they visit once
more the Friersons' at the old plantation on
Pudden Swamp. He thought he discovered in
himself a sorter hankering desire to revisit the
<pb id="lowery126" n="126"/>
place where he first saw the light, and view once
more the scenes of his childhood. He had heard
that Mr. Frierson—the old man—had gone to his
long home, so had Mr. Adolphus, but the girls
were still living, and occupied the old mansion
on the Frierson plantation, and Jimmie wanted
to see them once more in this life. Hundreds of
times Jimmie had driven those girls in the carriage
while attending “big meetings,” weddings,
and while making social calls. In those days
these girls were good to Jimmie, and he had not
forgotten it. Now, he wants to see them for the
last time, so he persuaded his mother to accompany
him to the old plantation. This she readily
consented to do.</p>
        <p>After breakfast one morning Jimmie hitched
up his father's horse and buggy and, with his
mother, started for Pudden Swamp. They drove
up into the yard at the Friersons' just as the old
clock in the “house” struck 12, and Jimmie
recognized the familiar tones of the old timepiece,
and it so filled him with glee that as he
alighted from the buggy, he said: “That is the
same old clock by which I used to rise at four in
the morning, and blow the horn for the boys to
come and feed the horses and the mules.” And
so it was.</p>
        <pb id="lowery127" n="127"/>
        <p>But the girls were filled with surprise. They
did not recognize Jimmie. They recognized the
woman who was with this young stranger. They
knew Aunt Namie very well. They had seen her
several times since she left the old plantation.
This was not the first time that she had visited
them, and once or twice the girls had driven up
to Lynchburg to see Aunt Namie. These girls
loved Aunt Namie, and Aunt Namie loved them,
and it was their delight to visit each other, and
talk over old times.</p>
        <p>When this young stranger helped Aunt Namie
from the buggy, the white girls rushed up to her
and kindly greeted her. It certainly was a warm
meeting. Jimmie then proceeded, as they used
to say on Pudden Swamp, “to loose out the
horse.” And while doing so, he carefully watched
the women folks as they embraced each other,
but he had nothing to say. But the girls were
pondering the expression which they heard this
young stranger make as he drove up into the
yard: “That is the same old clock by which I
used to rise at 4 o'clock in the morning, and blow
the horn for the boys to come and feed the horses
and the mules.” They closely eyed him, but there
was nothing about him that would enable them
to detect him. He was well dressed, and had an
air of refinement about him which they were not
<pb id="lowery128" n="128"/>
accustomed to see about the male darkies on
Pudden Swamp, notwithstanding they had been
free for upwards of twenty years.</p>
        <p>Now, the girls ventured to ask: “But, Aunt
Namie, who is this man you have with you?”
Aunt Namie replied: “Why, Miss Mary Ann,
you don't know who that is?” “No,” was the
response. “Why,” said Aunt Namie, “that is my
little Jimmie, don't you know him.” “Aunt
Namie,” said Miss Mary Ann, “do you mean to
say that that is Jimmie, our little mail boy and
our coachman?” “Yes, that is Jimmie.” “Come
here, Jimmie,” said the girls, “give us your hand.
How glad we are to see you. How have you been
all these years?” This was another glad meeting. The balance of the day was spent as a
reunion of the members of a family long
separated.</p>
        <p>The ladies showed Jimmie where to give the
horse water, and where to feed him. Then they
invited Aunt Namie and Jimmie into the house.
Dinner was about ready, and a side table was set
in the dining room for the visitors. It was the
same old dining room, and it was a real good old-fashion farmer's dinner. Aunt Namie and Jimmie
enjoyed it immensely.</p>
        <p>After dinner, Jimmie left his mother and the
girls to spend the afternoon talking about old
<pb id="lowery129" n="129"/>
times, while he alone roamed over that old
plantation. From field to field he went, without
seeming to grow weary, observing and noting every
change. He noticed that the fences, the gates,
the bars, and the bridges over the ditches were
all gone. And in many places the fields had
grown up with undergrowth and looked like
woods again. “Ah,” said Jimmie, “how cruel old
Time is. He has laid his decaying hand upon
everything on the old plantation. That which he
has not destroyed, he has left in a state of decay
and ruin. The colored folks are all gone, and
only two of the white folks are left to tell the sad
story.”</p>
        <p>But there is one thing that interested Jimmie
more than anything else, and that is the spot
where he first learned to sin. Jimmie located the
place as nearly as possible, owing to the changes
which time had wrought in the face of the
country. And when he had found it, he knelt
down and prayed to the God of heaven, and asked
forgiveness for all the sins that he ever had
committed on the old plantation, or anywhere else,
and then reconsecrated himself anew to God and
to His service. Then he arose, and returned to
the old mansion, and chatted with the girls until
it was time for him and his mother to leave for
home.</p>
        <pb id="lowery130" n="130"/>
        <p>This last separation was a very sad one, for the
reason that they all knew that they would never
meet on earth again. And so it came to pass.
They have all crossed the mystic river, save Jimmie, and have been gathered to their people on
the other side. Tears were shed by all—white
folks and colored folks—as they shook hands,
and said, “Good-bye.”</p>
      </div1>
      <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div1 type="appendix" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="lowery131" n="131"/>
        <head>APPENDIX.</head>
        <head>Signs of a Better Day for the Negro
in the South.</head>
        <head>Being the Reprint of a Series of Articles Written for
<lb/>
The Daily Record of Columbia, S. C.,</head>
        <docAuthor>by Rev. I. E. Lowery.</docAuthor>
        <div2 type="section" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <pb id="lowery133" n="133"/>
          <head>I.</head>
          <head>INTRODUCTION.</head>
          <p>After consulting the editor of The Record, and
obtaining his consent, the writer has concluded
to write a series of articles on the subject, “Signs
of a Better Day for the Negro in the South,” and
it is his wish that these articles be published in
the Saturday afternoon's paper, so as to form a
column of Sabbath reading for the members of
his race. This article is intended to be an introduction
to what is to follow.</p>
          <p>“Signs of a better day for the negro in the
South.” But the negro reader will ask: “Are
there any signs anywhere that foretell of a better
day in the South for the negro?” And the writer
answers, “Yes.” The trouble with the majority
of the colored people is, they look on the dark
side of the picture too much. They read the
daily papers and note the cases of lynchings,
burnings, murders and the outrages committed
on members of the race generally, and then they
grow discouraged, and say the future of the negro
in the South is dark, and is growing darker still.
But not so, could he but read aright. First of
all, the best white people of the South are
opposed to these crimes being committed against
<pb id="lowery134" n="134"/>
the members of our race. The best and most
influential papers of the South, both daily and
weekly papers, are opposed to it, and they speak
out in no uncertain sound against it. And what
is the result? These crimes have gradually grown
less. The facts prove that the brutal offense
against the purity of womanhood has diminished,
and the sickening crimes of lynchings, burnings,
murders and outrages have largely decreased.</p>
          <p>I herewith submit a clipping from a Northern
paper:</p>
          <p>“According to statistics, lynchings were fewer
in 1909 than the year previous. Seventy-eight
lynchings took place in the United States in
1909, a greater number than in any year since
1904, except 1908, with 100 summary executions.
In 1907 there were 63, and in 1906 there were 72.
The victims of the 1909 lynchings were 65
negroes and 13 whites. All but five negroes were
in Southern States. Illinois and Oregon were
the only Northern States to furnish instances of
mob law last year, and two cases were recorded
in the Territory of New Mexico.</p>
          <p>“Virginia barely missed a record of ‘no lynchings’ in 1909. On Christmas day a mob at Hurley
hanged a white man. Except for this tragedy,
Virginia would have been the only Southern
State with a clear record on lynchings for the
year.</p>
          <pb id="lowery135" n="135"/>
          <p>“In Oklahoma there was a quadruple lynching
of cattle men, and there were several double
lynchings in Southern States. Texas led with 13
cases and Georgia was a close second with 12.</p>
          <p>“Crimes and alleged crimes against white
women were the principal causes, and accusations
of murder and theft were responsible for
many cases. A charge of counterfeiting was the
incentive in one case and kidnapping in another.”</p>
          <p>A careful reading of the above clipping will
show that the crimes that incite to mob violence
are not as numerous now as they have been some
years in the past. This, evidently, is a sign of a
better day for the negro in the South.</p>
          <p>Not long since the writer was coming from
Florence to Columbia. He passed through the
gate at the union station into the yard where the
trains stood on the several tracks. There was a
stream of passengers following behind him.
Some were white people, and some were colored.
He, heard the voice of some one inquiring of the
gate keeper—in a joking way—if his ticket would
take him to “Lynchburg” and on which track
his train stood. Hearing the name “Lynchburg”
called (which is a small station only 20 miles
west of Florence), attracted the writer's attention;
for it is the place of his birth. He turned to
see the person who was speaking, and who was so
good-natured, and so full of life—and at once he
<pb id="lowery136" n="136"/>
thought he recognized the individual and waited
on the inside until he came through. He
approached the stranger and said to him, “Sir,
excuse me, but will you please tell me your
name?” He said, “My name is E. D. Smith,
junior United States senator from South Carolina.”
He then looked at the writer more closely
and said, “Is this Irving Lowery?” and the reply
was, “Yes.” We were both born and raised at
Lynchburg and played together when we were
boys. We stepped inside and chatted pleasantly.
Really we were boys again for a while.</p>
          <p>Now, here are some of the things he told me.
He first had something to say about 14 and 15
cents cotton. Everybody knows that that is
Senator Smith's favorite theme. But he went on to
say: “Lowery, the South is undergoing a change.
She is getting out of her old grooves of thought
and action. The motto of the South today is:
Every man, irrespective of race or color, shall
have a chance in the race of life.” The writer,
with his breast heaving with emotion, said:
“Mr. Smith, is not this great change which has
come over the South due to the young men and
to the young women of the South?” and he
answered, “Yes.” Thus ended one of the most
pleasant interviews the writer has ever had in his
life. It is to be taken for granted that Senator
Smith knows the South as well, or better, than
<pb id="lowery137" n="137"/>
any other man, for he travels all over the South,
and he is in a position to speak for the South
with authority. At any rate, his statement comes
to the negro like good news from a far country
and should fill him with hope and with aspiration,
for there is a better day ahead of him right
here in the land that gave him birth. Only let
him cease from crime; let him be industrious,
and let him educate his children and the white
people of the South will see to it that he shall
have fair chance in the race of life.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>II.</head>
          <head>WHITE PATRONS OF NEGRO BUSINESS ENTERPRISES.</head>
          <p>The industrial achievements of the negro race
in the South are signs of a better day. It is said
by those who claim to know, that in the North
the negro seldom engages in any independent
business. Up there most of the colored population
are cooks, chambermaids, nurses, laundry-women,
butlers, coachmen, elevator boys and
hotel waiters. This is all they can hope to be.
Of course, there are some colored ministers up
there, and here and there a lawyer, a physician
and a few mechanics. But in the South the negro
<pb id="lowery138" n="138"/>
fills all of these minor and higher callings, and,
in addition, he may become a farmer, a merchant,
or even a college president.</p>
          <p>I clipped the following from the editorial columns
of The News and Courier, of Charleston,
April 9th, 1907:</p>
          <p>“In Charleston all the laundry wagons are
driven by colored men, we believe. Nearly every
delivery wagon sent out by the dry goods, grocery
and other commercial establishments here is
driven by a colored teamster. Nearly all the
barbers in town are colored, many of them owning
their own plants. There have been colored men
on the Charleston police force for nearly forty
years. There are also colored firemen employed
here and paid by the city for their services. The
drivers of the carriages of our best people are
colored men. Quite a number of colored men are
doing business here on their own account, and
have been for years, and number among their
customers many of the best white people in the
town. There are four or five colored physicians
practicing here. There are in Charleston, besides,
colored lawyers and colored teachers. Many of
the best dressmakers are colored women, and
colored trained nurses are employed to attend
white patients. There are also colored farmers,
and one of the largest rose gardens in the South
is owned by a colored man at Charleston. There
<pb id="lowery139" n="139"/>
are also in this town colored mechanics and
colored contractors and colored labor unions.
The most of the house servants employed in
Charleston are colored, and now that the
automobile microbe is infecting this community it is
not an unusual sight to see these modern
machines operated by colored chauffeurs.”</p>
          <p>It is true, and every intelligent person knows
it, that every avenue of legitimate business is
open to the negro in the South. And there is
another thing that is true, and that is this: that
it matters not what might be the nature of the
business that a colored man may engage in, the
white people, and the best white people, of the
South, will patronize him. For instance, in
Charleston, the butcher's business is largely
controlled by colored men. This is true both in the
down-town market and also in the green grocery
business, as it is called, throughout the city.
Gilliard &amp; Fludd, T. S. Grant, John Stokien, Tom
Marshall, the Hoffman Brothers, and Trescott,
are among the leading colored butchers, and they
do a large business, and serve some of the best
white people of the city. C. C. Leslie, the colored
fish merchant, did a fine business for nearly
thirty years. He did a heavy business in supplying
the local market, and shipped large quantities
of fish to all parts of the State to both white
and colored customers. Really, Leslie has become
<pb id="lowery140" n="140"/>
rich, and last year he sold out his business to a
white man and retired, and is living in ease and
comfort on his income.</p>
          <p>Thaddeus Felon, of Summerville, owns a fine
brick store near the Southern depot, in which he
conducts a large dry goods store, employing
colored girls as clerks, and the white people—
gentlemen and ladies—trade with him. Of
course he is making money. In this same town
Dr. Allston practices medicine and conducts a
livery business. Hoffman also conducts a livery
business and runs a butcher shop. The Sasportas
Brothers are butchers on a large scale. All of
these colored business men have white friends
who patronize their business liberally.</p>
          <p>In Sumter, W. J. Andrews has been engaged in
business for more than 30 years. He kept a first
class restaurant for white and colored, having
separate rooms for each race, and sold fish,
oysters and ice. He did the largest business of this
kind of any man in Sumter. He made money
and is considered one of the wealthiest colored
men of the town. He made the most of his money
out of the white people, who thought that there
was no negro in Sumter like “Bill Andrews.”
They believed him to be honest, industrious and
truthful, hence they did not hesitate to trade
with him. In Camden, Eugene Dibble is the
best-to-do colored man of the town. When the writer
<pb id="lowery141" n="141"/>
visited that town last he owned and operated
three stores and several farms. He is also the
proprietor of several tenement houses. It is
evident to the casual observer that this accumulation
of property was not the result of colored
patronage alone, but the facts show that much of
it is the fruit of his white trade.</p>
          <p>The city of Columbia has produced some
successful colored business men, who have
accomplished much through the patronage of their
white friends. There was R. J. Palmer, who
conducted a business as a merchant tailor on
Main street nearly opposite the postoffice, and
made money. “Cap” Carroll, as he was
familiarly called by his friends (I mean C. R.
Carroll), conducted an up-to-date white barber
shop, and when he died he left his family in
comfortable circumstances. He made his money
out of the white people, and many of them, as
well as hosts of colored people, regretted his
death. And there is I. S. Leevy, a young man
of intelligence and thrift, who is doing a good
business as a tailor on Taylor street. He was
educated at Hampton Institute in Virginia,
where he learned the tailor's trade. He numbers
some of the best white people of Columbia as his
customers.</p>
          <p>A few years ago, Charles Stewart, the noted
negro newspaper correspondent of Chicago, was
<pb id="lowery142" n="142"/>
making a tour of the South, and spent a couple
of days in Newberry. In his letter to The
Afro-American Ledger, a negro journal, published in
Baltimore, Md., he speaks as follows of some of
the colored people of Newberry:
“We have some men in business here. T. A.
Williams &amp; Sons operate the grocery store right
in the business section of the city and spitting
distance of the court house. He owns 1,400
acres of land and some good property right in the
city.</p>
          <p>“G. C. Williams, who is brother to the one I
have mentioned, owns 600 or 700 acres of land
and is doing well. Robert Williams joins his
brother, Thomas Williams, in owning and operating
a brick yard; John D. Daniels perhaps is
the leading meat man in town. It is said that he
knows more about the meat business and has the
largest trade. Some of the best white people in
town buy meat from him. He also carries a full
line of groceries, and is a property owner.
W. W. Graham owns a grocery store, and is
doing good business; A. G. Neeley is a young
man in business. He has a grocery, and his wife
is in charge of the business while he attends the
farm. They are happy and are doing well. He
owns some good property himself. Mrs. Mattle
Neeley operates an eating house, and she does
a good business, while her husband beats out
<pb id="lowery143" n="143"/>
iron. He is one of the leading, blacksmiths of
the town. He has as his partner, John Morgan,
who knows how to operate, too.”</p>
          <p>In Anderson, a blacksmith, by the name of
David Dooly, has earned and saved a small fortune.
He works for the best white people of the
town and county. He is skilled as a workman,
is honest, truthful and perfectly reliable. He
owns several good houses, and his note is good at
any of the banks in town. But why go further
in naming others, for men like these are found in
almost every town and city in the South. Yes,
there are colored men all over the South engaged
in business and the white people do not hesitate
to patronize them. They know that some of these
negroes are making money, yet they are not
envious, but trade right along with them, and
thus help them up in the world. This is surely a
sign of a better day for the negro in the South.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>III.</head>
          <head>WHITE CONTRIBUTORS TOWARD THE BUILDING OF
NEGRO CHURCHES.</head>
          <p>There are thousands of white people in the
South who contribute liberally toward the building
of negro churches. This may be regarded as
<pb id="lowery144" n="144"/>
a hopeful sign of a better day for the colored
people in the South.</p>
          <p>During the days of slavery the colored people
were connected with the churches of their
masters. They were given the galleries, or a few
seats at the rear end of the church, or, if they
wanted to have their own services, the basement
was given to them, and sometimes the main
auditorium of the church proper was turned over to
them when not in use by the white people. Thus
all the slaves who were Christians in that day
and time had their church home. Their master's
church was usually their church. If he was a
Methodist, his slaves were Methodists; if he was
a Baptist, his slaves were Baptists; if he was a
Presbyterian, his slaves were Presbyterians; and
if he was an Episcopalian, his slaves were
Episcopalians. It mattered not what church the
master and his family were members of, the
slaves usually belonged to the same.</p>
          <p>But when freedom came, and when the newly
made freedmen broke away from the “old
plantation” and from their former masters, they left
their church home behind them. They went out
without spiritual leaders and without churches.
They were as sheep having no shepherd and no
fold. Just at this period of their history, the
Northern missionary and the Northern school
teacher came upon the scene. They had strong
<pb id="lowery145" n="145"/>
churches at their backs, which furnished them
with money. These missionaries and teachers
organized churches and established schools for
the uplift of the negro. But it is not to be supposed
that while the Northern white people did
much the Southern white people did nothing.
The truth of the matter is the benevolent and
charitable work of the Northern white people
have been magnified, while the same kind of work
by the Southern white, people has been minimized. In fact, no publicity scarcely has been given
to the Southern white people. But now has not
the time come to give the Christian white people
of the South the honor due to them for their good
and noble work in helping the colored people to
better their condition? If justice was allowed to
speak, she would answer “Yes.”
But let us bear what Booker T. Washington,
the greatest leader of the negro race, has to say
on this subject. He says: “It may not be known
outside of the South, and to the general public,
but it is true that every branch of the Southern
white church is assisting in some manner in the
educational, moral and religious development of
the negro through their college, Sunday school or
church work. This country owes a debt of
gratitude already to a group of brave, unselfish,
courageous Christian white men and women in
the South which it can never repay. It has been
<pb id="lowery146" n="146"/>
owing to the influence of this group, working in
co-operation with the educated negro, that peace
and harmony and good-will prevails in the South
to the extent that it does. The future for both of
our races is not dark.”</p>
          <p>I think the facts will bear me out when I make
the statement that during the 45 years of our
freedom there has not been a single church site
bought nor a single church building erected
anywhere in the South but what the Christian white
people of the South put money into it. In addition
to this, there are hundreds and thousands
of cases, where Christian white men and white
women of the South gave the land on which to
build churches for colored people. Nor has the
day of this mission work ceased. It is still being
carried on all over the South today.</p>
          <p>Now, I wish to give a few cases illustrating
the fact that the Southern white people have
helped and still are helping the colored people
to secure sites and to build their churches. There
is a remarkable case which occurred in the city
of Charleston at the close of the Civil War. The
history of this very interesting event was written
by the Rev. W. H. Lawrence, a Northern white
man, and published in a good-sized volume. The
writer secured a copy of this book through the
kindness of the Rev. James H. Holloway, a
prominent member of this church. The historian
<pb id="lowery147" n="147"/>
says: “The history of the purchase of Centenary
Church is an interesting evidence of God's care
for His work. The people worshipping in the
normal school early observed a day of fasting
and prayer, that God would supply them with a
suitable building. Bishop Baker heard of this
touching instance of faith; he promised the
brethren that the missionary society would assist
them to secure a church. It was discovered that
the Wentworth Street Baptist Church was for
sale. This society had been so crippled by the
war that it was determined to unite with the
congregation worshipping at the Citadel Square
Baptist Church. The Wentworth Street property
is an elegant brick structure in the Corinthian
style of architecture, with a fine lecture room
attached. Its estimated value is $75,000.</p>
          <p>“Negotiations were immediately begun, 
resulting, in a bargain at $20,000. This amount the
missionary society agreed to furnish. When the
Baptist brethren discovered that their church
was to fall into the hands of Northern brethren
for the use of a colored congregation, they
imposed further conditions, which seemed likely
to prevent the sale. They said the money must
be paid in gold, and during the banking hours
of an appointed day. Gold commanded a
premium of 50 per cent., which was an addition
of $10,000 to the stipulated price. The Charleston
<pb id="lowery148" n="148"/>
people must raise this $10,000. Meetings
were held, collectors appointed and an heroic
effort made. Some of the mothers in Israel even
contributed the money which had been sacredly
laid away for their burial.</p>
          <p>“As there was not $20,000 in available gold in
the city, a broker was authorized to purchase this
amount in New York. The box of precious metal
reached Charleston on the morning of the day
when the money must be paid, or the bargain
broken. The broker declined the draft of $20,000
of the missionary society, which the brethren
presented. Mr. Geo. W. Williams agreed to cash
the draft, but as exchange then commanded a
premium against the brethren, this involved an
additional outlay of a few hundred dollars. Mr.
Thomas Tulley and other well-to-do members of
the church were fortunately able to command
the needed amount. Mr. Williams' check was
accepted by the broker, and a dray carried the
box of gold to the lawyer's office, where the
papers were to be signed. Just as the 2,000
golden eagles were being rung upon the counter
the minute hand of the clock began to count off
the last half hour of the appointed time, and the
property passed forever into the hands of the
Methodist Episcopal Church. The deed was
made out, from motive of prudence, on account
of the unsettled condition of the country, to the
<pb id="lowery149" n="149"/>
Missionary Society of the Methodist Episcopal
Church, to be held in trust by Alonzo Webster,
Charles Holloway, George Shrewsberry, John
Gibbs, Jacob Mills, Samuel Weston, January
Holmes and Archibald Walker, trustees of the
Methodist Episcopal Church in Charleston. This
transaction took place on the 10th of April,
1866.”</p>
          <p>The point in the above piece of history, to
which the writer wishes especially to call the
reader's attention, is the part that Mr. Geo. W.
Williams took in the delicate transaction. If
he had not come to the rescue of this congregation
and cashed that draft, these people never
would have come into possession of that
magnificent property on one of the principal streets
of Charleston. Mr. Williams was a wealthy
banker and was highly esteemed and reverenced
by these people to the day of his death.
The church was bought in the centennial year
of the establishment of Methodism, and therefore
named Centenary. The Rev. M. M. Mouzon is
the present pastor, and the Rev. Jas. H. Holloway
is superintendent of the Sunday school.
The church has 1,300 members and 600 Sunday
school scholars.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <pb id="lowery150" n="150"/>
          <head>IV.</head>
          <head>WHITE CONTRIBUTORS TOWARD
 THE BUILDING OF NEGRO 
CHURCHES.—(Continued.)</head>
          <p>In my last article I spoke of the Southern
white people as contributors toward the building
of negro churches in the South. This I regard as
a “sign of a better day.” In that article I gave
a history of the purchase of the Centenary
Church in Charleston, which is considered one of
the finest negro churches in the South, and the
part that Mr. Geo. W. Williams—a wealthy
banker—took in the transaction. But for him
there would never have been a Centenary
Church.</p>
          <p>But in this article I wish to mention a few
other cases where the colored people were
assisted by their white neighbors. Take the Old
Bethel M. E. Church, located on the north side
of Calhoun street in Charleston. It is one of the
oldest and most historic buildings in the city. It
is certainly the oldest Methodist Church in the
fair “City by the Sea.” Bishop Asbury, the first
bishop of Methodism, preached in the building
now under consideration. It has been moved
twice, but now it has reached perhaps its last
resting place.</p>
          <p>It is a substantial wooden building and well
constructed. It was built in colonial days on the
<pb id="lowery151" n="151"/>
northwest corner of Pitt and Calhoun streets,
the site where the new Bethel M. E. Church now
stands. This is the church where Mr. F. J.
Pelzer, a very wealthy gentleman, holds his
membership. This old building stood on this corner
lot for a number of years, during which time the
congregation grew both in numbers and wealth.
About this time they felt the need of a better and
more modern building. This was long before the
Civil War. They decided to erect a new brick
building of Grecian architecture. A large number
of colored people were connected with this
church, as members, and some of them were
well-to-do free colored people. They occupied the
gallery during the services.</p>
          <p>Now, when these white folks were arranging to
build their new church, they told the colored
portion of the congregation that if they would give
them $1,000 toward the erection of the new
church they would roll the old one to the rear end
of the lot and give it to them. The colored people
were delighted and went to work to raise the
money—both the slaves and the free colored
people. The thousand dollars were raised, and
the old building was shoved to the rear and fitted
up. A beautiful new building took its place,
which stands there today. The old building
remained on its site until the close of the war,
when the colored people went over to the
<pb id="lowery152" n="152"/>
Methodist Episcopal Church. They also claimed
the building, but they could not claim the land
on which it stood. This belonged to the New
Bethel congregation, and this congregation asked
the colored people to move the building away, as
they wanted the lot to erect a Sunday school
room. They also promised the colored people to
give them $500 to assist them in defraying the
expense of moving the building. Luckily the
colored people found a very desirable lot for sale
just across the street (Calhoun) and they bought
it. In the purchase of this lot there was something
that the New Bethel congregation did not
like, and they refused to carry out their agreement
of giving the colored people $500 to help
them. They thought that they had good and
sufficient reasons for their decision in the matter,
but Mr. Pelzer differed from them, and stood by
the original agreement. He wrote his personal
check for $500 and gave it to the colored people.
The old building was moved and fitted up and
called “Old Bethel.” The writer had the honor
of serving this church as pastor for six years not
long since, and it was during this period that he
made it his business to see Mr. Pelzer in person
and get the facts from him. He gave them to me
as related above. Mr. Pelzer is a good man, but
he is not the only good white man in the South.
There are thousands just like him. Are not
<pb id="lowery153" n="153"/>
incidents like this a sign of a better day for the
negro in the South?</p>
          <p>But let us consider some other cases similar to
the one named above. During last year (1909) a
destructive storm passed over the little town of
Greeleyville on the Coast Line Railroad between
Sumter and Lanes, and blew down every colored
church in the place. The Rev. E. W. Stratton,
a native of Columbia, is pastor of the M. E.
Church, and he told the writer that the white
people of Greeleyville gave him $100 to assist
him in rebuilding his church. One white gentleman,
a member of the Baptist Church, gave $50
of that amount. There is a colored Baptist
Church in course of construction near Norway,
in Orangeburg County. This is a station on the
Seaboard Air Line Railway. A white gentleman
contributed $100 toward the building fund of
this church and endorsed a note at the bank for
$200, given by the officers.</p>
          <p>But take one more case. There is a colored
Methodist Church in Spartanburg called “Silver
Hill.” The building is of brick and was erected
just after the war in a very ordinary style, with a
school room on the first floor and the church
auditorium above. Some 15 years ago the Rev.
C. C. Scott was sent there as pastor, and he
undertook the tremendous job of remodeling the
church. He began the work, but was removed
<pb id="lowery154" n="154"/>
before it was finished. The writer was sent to
complete the work, and therefore had access to
the financial records. These books showed that
the white people of Spartanburg gave something
over $500 to complete the work. Among the
largest contributors were: Mr. John B. Cleveland,
Capt. Montgomery, Mr. Converse and Mr.
Twitchell. But a large number of the white
citizens contributed in smaller sums.
These are sample cases, the like of which can
be found throughout the South. If all the incidents
of this nature, which have occurred since
emancipation, could be written it would make a
large volume of many thousand pages.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>V.</head>
          <head>WHITE CONTRIBUTORS TOWARD
 THE BUILDING OF <lb/>NEGRO SCHOOLS.</head>
          <p>In two articles I discussed what the white
people of the South have done in helping the
colored people to secure sites for their churches,
and the assistance rendered them in erecting
buildings thereon. But before leaving this line
of thought, I wish to call the reader's attention
to the schools designed for the education of the
colored youth of the South. I do not refer to the
<pb id="lowery155" n="155"/>
common school system. These schools have been
provided by the State. The buildings, such as
they are, in most cases have been erected out of
public funds, raised by taxation. Aside from the
public schools located in the towns and cities
there is not much being done for the education
of the young negro. The terms are too
short-lasting only from two to three months. This is
a serious mistake, for the reason that it causes
hundreds and thousands of some of the best
colored families to leave the farms and move
nearer to or into the towns and cities for the
purpose of educating their children. Whereas
if the rural schools were made better and the
terms extended, the colored people would be
more willing to stay on the farms. In that case
the educational facilities of the country would
measure up to the standards of the towns and
cities, and this would make the negro farmer contented to stay where he is. These points are worthy of a careful consideration by the land
owners of the South.</p>
          <p>But at the close of the war the negroes of the
South were without school houses, as they were
without church buildings. But as their church
buildings multiplied, they were used in many
cases as school houses. Finding that the public
school was insufficient for the education of
their children, the colored people began to plant
<pb id="lowery156" n="156"/>
and build denominational or independent
schools. And even in this the Southern white
people have helped them. There is not a single
denominational or independent negro school in
the South but what the white people put money
into it, and helped to build it. And they are still
helping them along this line. Of course, the
Northern people have done much and are still
doing much, but in recent years they have begun
to tighten the strings of their purses. They are
not doing as much now as they have done in the
past. They seem to be growing tired of the negro.
They say he is a burden, and that they have
carried him long enough. Hence each year there
is a considerable falling off in the gifts of the
Northern people. This is the universal testimony
of those who are engaged in the work of
negro education under the patronage of Northern
philanthropists. But it must be a pleasing
thought to the close observer of passing events to
note that while the donations of Northern people
toward the education of the colored people are
annually decreasing, those of the Southern white
people are largely on the increase. The donations
of the Southern white people are given, in
most cases, to the secular or independent negro
schools. I will now proceed to mention a few
cases in South Carolina and some of the
adjoining States.</p>
          <pb id="lowery157" n="157"/>
          <p>Some time last fall it was the writer's privilege
to visit the town of Marion. While there I spoke
to the faculty and students of the colored graded
school, and noticed that an additional new building
on the campus was nearing completion. I
was told by some of the colored people of Marion
that that building was designed as an industrial
building, and that it was the gift of Judge
Woods, one of the Associate Justices of the
Supreme Court of South Carolina. The information
greatly impressed me, and I regarded it as a
“sign of a better day for the negro in the South.”
But to be sure that the information given me by
the colored people was correct, I wrote Mr. T. C.
Easterling, the superintendent of the city schools
of Marion, and this is what he said, touching that
new building: “Our colored industrial school
building and equipment cost something over
$1,100. Of this amount Judge Woods was one
of those who gave $200 each. The colored people
themselves gave $132. The balance was given
in amounts from $500 to $50. Nearly all of the
white citizens of Marion to whom I went for
money to build and equip our colored industrial
school responded willingly.” The above letter
needs no comment, but I would, in passing, ask
the reader to note the spirit of friendliness and
charity on the part of the white citizens of
Marion.</p>
          <pb id="lowery158" n="158"/>
          <p>But one of the most conspicuous monuments
of the charity of the Southern white people in the
education of the negro is the Paine Institute,
located in Augusta, Ga. The school was planted
by the M. E. Church, South, and named after
Bishop Paine, one of the great men of Southern
Methodism. This school, which is one of the best
in the South, established for the education of
negro youth, is presided over by the Rev. George
Williams Walker, D. D., a South Carolinian, a
man of God, and a true friend of the colored man.
He has devoted his best days to the uplift and
the betterment of the colored people of the South.
And thousands of the sons and daughters of Ham
will rise up in the judgment and call him blessed.
He deals with the hearts or morals of his pupils
as well as with the intellects. When they pass
through his school they do not only come out as
educated young men and women, but they come
out as Christians, prepared to fight the battles of
life.</p>
          <p>There is a school for the education of negro
youth at Denmark, S. C. It was founded by a
young colored woman by the name of Elizabeth
Evelyn Wright. She was born at Talbotton, Ga.,
on April 3, 1874, and graduated from Tuskegee
Industrial Institute, after which she came to this
State. They have a magnificent plant of more
than 380 acres of good farming land. These
<pb id="lowery159" n="159"/>
lands are dotted with five or six splendid buildings,
which are well equipped for school purposes.
The farm is well stocked with mules and
cattle and abundantly supplied with the latest
farming implements. A fine printing outfit has
been installed. The school is supplied with a
saw mill, and also a grist mill. The school plant
is worth about $75,000 and is out of debt. Mr.
Ralph Voorhees, of New Jersey, furnished the
money to found this school, but it could not be
done without the aid of the Southern white men.
I will quote just one sentence from their latest
catalogue, which will prove my statement:
“Ex-Senator Mayfield, who lives at Denmark, became
interested in her efforts, and has always been a
friend to the work. He helped her to secure this
large tract of land, and, all along, has he been a
tower of strength in behalf of this negro school.”
The Sterling Industrial College for negro
youth is an independent or undenominational
school located at Greenville, S. C., and the Rev.
D. M. Minus, D. D., is the founder and president.
Mrs. E. R. Sterling, of Poughkeepsie, N. Y., gave
the first money to establish this school, therefore
the school has been given her name. But Mrs.
Sterling died soon after the school was founded,
and the enterprise would have failed had not the
white people of Greenville and Anderson come to
its rescue. These good people have given thousands
<pb id="lowery160" n="160"/>
of dollars to the school, which kept it
going, and have put it on a firm basis. I quote
one paragraph from their recent catalogue:</p>
          <p>“Its growth has been so rapid until in 1903
the trustees found it necessary to sell the old
school site, on Choice street, and purchase larger
and more convenient quarters in West Greenville,
where better work, especially in the industries,
can be done. The school has now a large
farm, president's home with seven rooms, a main
building containing 19 rooms, a large and
comfortable dining hall, with other buildings, a
magnificent park with splendid springs of pure water
and large, open grounds for athletic purposes.
With God's blessing and guidance and the hearty
co-operation of our friends the school will
increase as a powerful agency in educating and
uplifting the young men and women of our race.”</p>
          <p>I have named only a few of the negro schools
in the South that have been fostered by donations
from the Southern white people. But similar
schools are found in every Southern State from
Virginia to Texas. Let the reader look, and see,
and consider for himself.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <pb id="lowery161" n="161"/>
          <head>VI.</head>
          <head>CURRENT INCIDENTS OF NEGRO INDUSTRIAL<lb/>
ACHIEVEMENTS.</head>
          <div3 type="subsection" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <p>The industrial achievements under Southern
conditions are a sign of a better day for the
negroes in the South.</p>
            <p>In January, 1866, the negroes left the old
plantation with nothing—absolutely nothing.
And they were ignorant, too. They had no
education. They only knew how to work. They
had been taught this in slavery. But recent
statistics show a marvelous accumulation of
property for a period of forty years. The figures
are almost incredible, but they are said to be
based on government authority. Here they are:
They own 137,000 farms and homes, which
consist of 40,000,000 acres.</p>
            <p>These farms and homes are valued at
$725,000,000. They have personal property to the
value of $10,000,000. The different colored
denominations own $41,000,000 of church,
parsonage and school property.
But I wish to give two or three current incidents
illustrating the possibilities of the negroes'
success along industrial lines. But similar cases
may be found everywhere in this beautiful
Southland.</p>
            <pb id="lowery162" n="162"/>
            <p>In Camden, S. C., there is a young man by the
name of George Washington Clarke, who is a
graduate of Tuskegee Institute, Booker
Washington's school. This negro is employed by one
of the wealthiest white gentlemen of that city as
a gardener, or horticulturist, at a fine salary.
He has charge of both his flower and vegetable
gardens, and, as a result, this white citizen has a
variety of nice, fresh vegetables the whole year
round.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subsection" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <p>Not long since, the writer was traveling and
came to a certain Southern city, and took the
trolley cars for his boarding place. And when
the car reached the junction, where all the cars
came together at intervals, a young colored man
walked in, got down on his knees and lifted a
trap-door in the middle aisle, and made a
thorough examination of the electric apparatus
beneath the car. The writer saw that he was a
car inspector, and when he had finished and
walked out, he followed him, and asked his
name and what salary he was paid. This
information was willingly and freely given, but
for prudential reasons, he requested that no
publicity be made of it. But the fact is, the young
negro was an electrician, and as such was given
employment by a wealthy corporation right here
in the South.</p>
            <pb id="lowery163" n="163"/>
            <p>The wealthiest negro in the city of Atlanta,
Ga., is A. F. Herndon. He owns and operates the
largest barber shop in the city; is the president
of a flourishing insurance company, and owns
and rents some 50 dwelling houses. He is said to
be worth $80,000, all of which has been made
since the Civil War.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subsection" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <p>Bishop L. J. Coppin, D. D., of the A. M. E.
Church, is considered one of the strongest and
safest leaders of the colored race in America. In
a recent lecture in Emanuel Church at Charleston,
in speaking of the progress that the negroes
are making in South Carolina, he said he saw in
a white paper of this State that 55 per cent. of
the farming lands of South Carolina is owned
by colored people. The bishop said he could
scarcely believe the statement, but he supposed
that it was true, for these papers generally know
what they are talking about. If it be true, said
the bishop, it is certainly encouraging to the
race.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subsection" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <p>To excel in any, line of work is worthy of the
effort. Alfred Smith, of Oklahoma, a negro, is
put down as the champion cotton raiser. He has
taken all the premiums offered in that State for
the first and best cotton received, also the blue
<pb id="lowery164" n="164"/>
ribbon at the World's Fair, and the first prize in
England. Smith is a native of Georgia, having
been born near Atlanta, and claims that when
Sherman passed through on his famous march to
the sea, he was in the field plowing with an old
gray mule. That this good brother should have
continued at the plow until he is able to receive
so many evidences of his ability as a cotton
raiser, ought to be a source of inspiration to
every negro in America. It shows that patient
industry also has its reward.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subsection" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <p>Robert C. Owens, of Los Angeles, Cal., has
been very fortunate in making investments in
real estate. He began with a small capital as an
option dealer, which has enabled him to amass
property valued at the enormous sum of $675,000.
He is a member of the Los Angeles Chamber
of Commerce, and in a short time will have
a monthly rent toll of $3,500.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>VII.</head>
          <head>FRIENDLY EXPRESSIONS OF SOUTHERN WHITE<lb/>
PEOPLE FOR THE NEGRO.</head>
          <p>On February 26, 1910, the writer was in Aiken
—having gone there to attend a farmers' conference.
<pb id="lowery165" n="165"/>
The early train from Augusta to Blackville
was derailed at the freight depot, just on the
outskirts of the town. Great crowds from the
town and the surrounding country visited the
scene of the wreck. Among these curious
sightseers were several small boys—white and
colored. It was Saturday, and, the schools being
closed, the boys were on hand in full force.
Near the track was a hole about as large
around as a barrel, and about as deep. This hole
was nearly full of water, and there was a frog
floating around in it. These boys soon lost
interest in the wreck and gathered around the hole.
They fished the frog out, and instantly a half
dozen boys gathered up rocks and brickbats to
kill it. They held in their hands missiles sufficient
to kill a good-sized animal, with proper
force behind them. The unanimous opinion of
the boys was that the frog should be killed.
Presently another little white boy came up and said:
“Boys, what are you all going to do with that
frog?” “Kill him!” cried a half dozen voices.
“No, don't do that,” said the newcomer. “That
frog has as much right to live as any of you.
Put him back in the hole and into the water.”
And, strange to say, this boy's advice was taken,
and the life of the frog was spared. It was
thrown back into its native element, the water.</p>
          <p>“Now,” said I, “there is the influence of one
<pb id="lowery166" n="166"/>
voice when it pleads for the innocent and the
helpless.” This story may be applied to the
negro and to his surroundings. There are voices
that cry against him, but I am glad to say that
there are some friendly voices that plead for him.
In this, and in my next article, I purpose to
mention some of these friendly voices.</p>
          <p>The Atlanta riot is still fresh in the minds of
the American people. It was a bloody affair,
during which human lives were sacrificed and
great damage done to the business of the city.
Some days after the riot, the best citizens among
the white people and among the colored held a
mass meeting, in which frank and outspoken
expressions were made. Some of these
expressions I herewith reproduce.</p>
          <p>Mr. Charles T. Hopkins, one of the ablest
lawyers at the Atlanta bar, a native of Tennessee
and a graduate of Williams College, made a
speech at this meeting, in which he said: “The
Negro race is a child-race. We are a strong race,
their guardians. We have boasted of our
superiority, and we have now sunk to this level—
we have shed the blood of our helpless wards.
Christianity and humanity demand that we treat
the negro fairly. He is here, and here to stay.
He only knows how to do those things we teach
him to do; it is our Christian duty to protect
him. I for one—and I believe I voice the best
<pb id="lowery167" n="167"/>
sentiment of this city—am willing to lay down
my life rather than to have the scenes of the last
few days repeated.”</p>
          <p>In the same meeting a colored man arose to
speak. He was timid and doubtful. It was Dr.
W. F. Penn, one of the foremost colored physicians
of Atlanta, and a graduate of Yale College.
He said the mob went to his house to kill him,
but he was saved by a white man, who spirited
him away in an automobile. When he had
finished, Col. A. J. McBride, a real estate owner
and a Confederate veteran, arose and said with
much feeling that he knew Dr. Penn, and that he
was a good man, and that Atlanta meant to protect
such men. “If necessary,” said Col. McBride,
“I will go out and sit on his porch with a
rifle.”</p>
          <p>Ex-Governor W. S. Northen, one of the best
known and most respected citizens of the State
of Georgia, recently made an eloquent speech in
that State in which he gave expression to these
noble sentiments: “We shall never settle this
(the race) question until we give absolute justice
to the negro. We are not now doing justice to
the negro in Georgia. Get into contact with the
best negroes; there are plenty of good negroes in
Georgia. What we must do is to get the good
white folks to leaven the bad white folks, and the
good negroes to leaven the bad negroes. There
<pb id="lowery168" n="168"/>
must be no aristocracy of crime; a white fiend is
as much to be dreaded as a black brute.”</p>
          <p>Mr. Washington Gladden, in the January
(1907) number of The American Magazine, says:
“There are many Southern men who are determined
that the negro shall not be reduced to serfdom;
who mean that he shall have a chance to be
a man—to make of himself what God meant him
to be.”</p>
          <p>President Kilgo, of Trinity College, North
Carolina, says: “The best Southern people are
too wise not to know that posterity will judge
them according to the wisdom they use in this
great concern. They are too just not to know
that there is but one thing to do with a human
being, and that is to give him a chance.”
Prof. Woodward, of the same college, says:
“What is to be done with the negro race? It
must somehow be built into this national fabric,
and organically incorporated with the national
life and character.”</p>
          <p>The Rev. Edgar Gardner Murphy, of Alabama,
says: “While the development of the higher life
of the negro may come slowly, even blunderingly,
it is distinctly to be welcomed.”</p>
          <p>Senator B. R. Tillman, in a debate in the
United States Senate on the discharge of the
negro troops of the Twenty-fifth Infantry, who
were summarily dismissed from the army by
<pb id="lowery169" n="169"/>
President Roosevelt, said that there were many
good negroes. He also said that he had had good
negroes working for him 30 years, and he
believed there were millions of good negroes.</p>
          <p>Says Mr. Washington Gladden, in the January
(1907) number of The American Magazine: “It
is idiotic to talk of deporting the negroes to some
other country; they are here, and here they must
stay; and their home will be in the southern
portion of the territory of the United States.
Whether the two races shall live there together
or live there separately is the only possible
question. They cannot live together unless both
races have full opportunity to live a complete
human life.”</p>
          <p>These friendly expressions from some of the
leading white men of the South are signs of a
better day for the negroes in the South.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>VIII.</head>
          <head>FRIENDLY EXPRESSIONS OF SOUTHERN WHITE<lb/>
PEOPLE FOR THE NEGRO.—(Continued).</head>
          <p>The friendly expressions of prominent Southern
white men are signs of a better day for the
colored people of the South.</p>
          <p>The Rev. Samuel Phillips Verner—a young
South Carolinian, who has consecrated his life to
<pb id="lowery170" n="170"/>
missionary work in Africa—pays an eloquent
tribute to the devotion of his faithful black followers
in that dark continent, and by this he was
reminded of the fidelity of the slave to his master
in this country. Ten of his devoted men sacrificed
their lives that Mr. Verner's might be
saved. He afterwards found an arm on the bank
of the river, and only an arm, which told the sad
story of their death in his defence. In speaking
of this incident Mr. Verner says: “As I looked
at it (the arm) through a mist of tears, there
rose to mind another scene, a far off and happier
land, but on a day of strife and battle, when,
amid the cannon's roar and the shriek of the
flying balls, an old man lay wounded and near to
death. But a black arm encircled him, and bore
him through the hell of battle raging around,
safely to the rear, and to the surgeon's care, and
then Uncle Quince stumbled himself from his
own sore wound, and fell, when old master was
safe. Here, it was again in Central Africa, as it
had been in Virginia, the same dumb, unquestioning
loyalty, the same blind fidelity even unto
death. As I stood over that severed limb, I saw
the African's people in that other land standing
faithful at the plough, while old master was away
at the war, that same black arm keeping the
wolf from old missus's door; I saw the African
arm, as it had borne the Cross, when the fainting
<pb id="lowery171" n="171"/>
Saviour could bear it no more; and here it was
again, lying all torn and gashed on that blood-stained
shore, mute witness to the heroic fidelity
with which they all had perished. But for me,
may Almighty God forget my people and me,
when I forget them and theirs!”</p>
          <p>Col. Henry Watterson, the famous Louisville
editor, delivered a brilliant speech in Carnegie
Hall, New York, in the interest of Tuskegee
Institute—Booker Washington's school. His
subject was, “The Future of the Negro.” From
that speech I quote as follows:</p>
          <p>“Nobody can go to Tuskegee, and see what I
saw there, and come away without being
impressed. Ever since I went there, now many
years ago, I have been filled with hope; for
though the institution of African slavery be
dead, and, thank the Lord of Hosts for that, the
negro is here; he is here in ever-increasing numbers,
and he is here to stay. All schemes for getting
rid of him are fantastic, and, if attempted,
would prove abortive. He must be developed on
new lines, educated to an anomalous situation
and resolved into the body of society, not as an
irritant, but as a natural, indispensable component part.</p>
          <p>“I want nothing for myself, or for my children,
which I am not ready to give to my colored neighbor
and his children. I live in a region peopled
<pb id="lowery172" n="172"/>
172
by many blacks, good, orderly, hard-working folk.
They know me, and they know that when I
declare this I mean it. We have had no race war
or serious racial conflict in Kentucky. The feudists
of the mountains, the night riders of the
tobacco belt, are all whites, not blacks. Reasonable
white people and reasonable black people
find it easy to get along much as if there existed
no color line. Each is inspired by a sense of
duty to the other, which, under the benign influence
of religion and humanity, may yet blossom
into the old domestic relations of confidence and
affection, the man-ownership clause succeeded by
a manhood clause, at once self-respecting and
reciprocally respected.</p>
          <p>“As, during the sectional war, they were faithful
servants, remaining at home, and tilling the
fields and taking care of the women and children,
so, since the war, according to their lights they
have tried to be good citizens. I glory in every
step of progress they have made—and they have
made many strides—from that day to this.</p>
          <p>“I stand here tonight to declare that the world
has never <sic corr="witnessed">withnessed</sic> such progress from darkness
to light as that which we see in those districts
of the South where the negro has had a
decent opportunity for self-improvement.
Nowhere on the habitable globe has the liberated
slave fared so well, nowhere has he so fair an
<pb id="lowery173" n="173"/>
outlook as in the Southern States of North
America.</p>
          <p>“Why? Because we know one another, and
because, no matter what anybody may say to the
contrary, there is a common bond of association
between us. Never can the white man of the
South forget what the black man did during the
war waged for his freedom, and what he might
have done. Never should the black man of the
South forget that he is the weaker in the race,
and for a long time to come must look to the
white man for help of many kinds. It is through
these reciprocal obligations and interests that the
two races will reach some institutional system of
living and doing entirely satisfactory to both.</p>
          <p>“The negro in Africa has scarcely burst the
chrysalis of the primitive state of man. In
America he is yet in a state of racial childhood.
As he realizes this, the faster he will grow, the
quicker he will learn, and the sooner he will
reach his racial manhood. In less than half a
century he has achieved wonders. Before the
century we have just begun is half over he will
have achieved greater still. He has yet, and
upon an extensive scale, to learn habits of
method and order; habits of tenacity and acquisition;
habits of sustained industry and sobriety,
without which no race—white, red, brown, or
<pb id="lowery174" n="174"/>
black—or any individual man—can get on and
prosper.</p>
          <p>“He is a bad white man who will not help his
neighbor black man, when that neighbor black
man shows the spirit to help himself. He is a
bad black man who cherishes hatred in his heart
against the white man because he is a white man.
He is a foolish black man who thinks because the
mirage of social equality, which would prove a
curse rather than a blessing, is denied him, that
the white man hates him. Social questions the
world over create their own laws and settle themselves.
They can not be forced. It is idle anywhere
for anybody to contest or quarrel with
them. No man should wish to go where he is not
wanted; true, self-respecting men dismiss the
very thought of it, going their own way, hoeing
their own row, and giving praise to God that
their happiness is within themselves, and beyond
the reach of any man, be he white or black, king
or vassal.”</p>
          <p>The Rev. Alexander Sprunt, D. D., pastor of
the First Presbyterian church of Charleston,
preached an able sermon to his congregation on
December 1, 1907. His subject was, “Give the
Negro the Gospel,” and he took for his text the
words, “For the Jews have no dealings with the
Samaritans.” Dr. Sprunt belongs to the Southern
Presbyterian Church, and we may take it for
<pb id="lowery175" n="175"/>
granted that in this sermon he voiced the sentiments
of that great denomination of Christians.
He said, in part:</p>
          <p>“The general assembly of the Presbyterian
Church in the United States, commonly known as
the Southern Presbyterian Church, appoints an
annual collection to be taken on the first Sabbath
in December for the evangelization of the colored
people of our Southland. There are some who
are very much prejudiced against this cause,
because they have no dealings with the negro,
and no sympathy for the work. They would
rather give to almost anything else. Let us see,
‘the Jews had no dealings with the Samaritans.’</p>
          <p>“Now and then some white man maintains that
the black man has no soul. As well doubt the
existence of the soul altogether. The Holy Ghost
says, ‘God hath made of one blood all nations of
men for to dwell on all the face of the earth, and
hath determined the times before appointed, and
the bounds of their habitation; that they should
seek the Lord, if haply they might feel after him,
and find him, though he be not far from every one
of us.’ Acts 17:26, 27.</p>
          <p>“Yet it is sometimes said that neither religion
nor education is a benefit to the race; but such
a statement carries its own contradiction. It
may be that some forms of religion are no benefit
to the negro, but neither are they beneficial to
<pb id="lowery176" n="176"/>
any others. Some kinds of education may not be
helpful to them either. But these forms are not
prescribed. We all know they are a very
religious people, and they will have some form of
religion. It is our part to give them a pure
religion, and the kind of education which will
elevate them, and make them the best of citizens,
and most enlightened Christians. The Commissioner
of Education reports to the United States
government that ‘from both a moral and religious
point of view, what measure of education the
negro has received has paid and there has been
no backward step in any State. Not a single
graduate of Hampton Institute or of the Tuskegee
Institute can be found today in any jail or
State penitentiary. The record of the South
shows that 90 per cent. of the colored people in
prison are without a knowledge of trades, and 61
per cent. are illiterate.’ In 1865 only a very
small proportion of the negroes of the South
could read. Today not less than 30,000 are professors and teachers in schools and colleges. A
vast number of well-read preachers, lawyers, doctors,
mail agents and clerks are at work today.
There are more than 150 newspapers edited by
negroes. The percentage of illiteracy has fallen
from 70 per cent. in 1880 to 56 per cent. in 1890,
and to 44 per cent. in 1900.</p>
          <pb id="lowery177" n="177"/>
          <p>“This race is susceptible to wholesome
religious training and useful education. It is
ours to give it to them. They have a right to the
Gospel of our Lord Jesus as much as we have.
What right have any of us to it? It is ours in
possession by the grace of God, but not ours to
hoard or keep to ourselves, but it is ours in trust.</p>
          <p>“These people are our neighbors, and the ‘second
great commandment’ leaves us no liberty
whatever in our obligations to them.</p>
          <p>“If, then, they are in such need, are susceptible
of the glorious benefits of the Gospel; if they
have a right to it, and are our neighbors, and we
have it to give them, surely it is our duty to give
it to them and to do so at once.”</p>
          <p>In these two articles, I have given a few
expressions from representative Southern white,
people for the negro. But there are white people
like these scattered all over the South. They are
a brave, courageous, and Christ-like band.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>IX.</head>
          <head>THE WHITE PEOPLE'S CARE OF THE OLD BLACK<lb/>
MAMMIES.</head>
          <p>The care that the Southern white people take
of the old black mammy is a sign of a better day
for the negro in the South.</p>
          <pb id="lowery178" n="178"/>
          <p>The old black mammy of ante-bellum days did
not pass away with the passing of that period.
And it is predicted that it is likely that they will
never cease to be in the South. It is a system
that is likely to spread to the North. There is a
mutual confidence and love that naturally
springs up between the colored cook, nurse or
maid on the one hand and the white people on
the other, let them be Southern or Northern
white folks. There are thousands of black mammies
in the South today who have almost the
entire charge of the children of some of the best
white families. Not only are the life and health
of these children in their hands, but the moral
and spiritual training of the little ones likewise.
And these children are not all motherless children,
either—in fact, very few of them are
motherless. Their parents are living, but because
of the faith and confidence they have in mammy's
integrity and religion, they turn the little ones
over to her. She is hired to care for their bodies,
but she does not neglect their other natures.
And among other things that she teaches them
she teaches them good manners. The molding
hand of the old black mammy tells on the life of
the child through all its future career, and even
into the life beyond.</p>
          <p>For all this work the old black mammy is
paid her wages. And when the infirmities of old
<pb id="lowery179" n="179"/>
age come on and she is not able to work any more
she is often granted a pension by her white folks,
or given a room in their house or yard, and fed
from their table. In sickness the best medical
attention is given at their expense, and often the
white ladies take their turn at watching and do
part of the nursing. Mammy's pastor and her
church brothers and sisters are not forbidden
to see her. And when death comes and mammy
is dead, the white folks bury her—paying all
funeral expenses, and frequently attend the
funeral at the church. Such cases happen
throughout the South. I will give two or three
instances.</p>
          <p>At Lake City, S. C., there is a white gentleman
—Mr. S. M. Askins—who had an old colored
woman who lived in his family for thirty years.
She raised his two children—Hoxie and Willie.
The old woman's name was Lozetta McFadden.
Mr. Askins gave her a very nice and comfortable
home. He gave her titles for the land and built
her a good house. He did this as a reward for
her faithfulness, and instructed his children that
they must never allow her to want for anything
while she lived. The children have carefully
obeyed their father's instructions. Mammy
Lozetta has always been considered as a member
of the Askins family, and does not hesitate to
<pb id="lowery180" n="180"/>
draw on them whenever in need. And her
requests for assistance are never denied.</p>
          <p>There is a very touching case of this nature
that came under the writer's own observation in
the city of Charleston. When he was pastor of
Old Bethel M. E. Church there was an old blind
sister connected with that congregation whose
name was Hagar Seabrook. She lived in the
yard of the late Mr. Holmes on Charlotte street,
the East Bay oil and paint merchant. The old
sister told the writer that she raised Mrs.
Holmes, the merchant's wife, and then assisted
her in raising her children. She was the cook
and nurse, and when she became old and blind,
Mrs. Holmes gave her a comfortable room in
her yard. All the wood she needed for fire was
given to her. It was cut, split and carried to her
room. Her meals were sent to her three times a
day and she told this writer that she ate just
what the white folks ate. All the servants in the
yard were instructed to look after mammy and
do for her whatever she wanted done. Every
Sunday afternoon one of the young ladies of the
house—one of Mrs. Holmes' daughters—would
go to mammy's room and spend hours with her
reading the Bible for her. And when the family
would go to the mountains to spend the summer,
Mrs. Holmes and her daughters would write
some very beautiful, touching and consoling letters
<pb id="lowery181" n="181"/>
to mammy. Many of these letters were read
by the writer on the occasion when he would be
making a pastoral visit to “Mother Seabrook,”
as she was affectionately called by her church
people.</p>
          <p>But, by and by, the old soul was paralyzed,
but Mrs. Holmes did not forsake her. Though
she was blind and helpless from paralysis, Mrs.
Holmes stood by her and cared for her to the
last. And when she died, Mrs. Holmes sent for
a colored undertaker and told him to give
mammy a respectable burial and send the bill to
her. This was done, and the writer, assisted by
the late Rev. Dr. J. H. Welch, who was at that
time pastor of the Emmanuel A. M. E. Church,
performed the burial services, Mrs. Holmes and
her daughters being present. There are thousands
of cases just like this in all parts of the
South.</p>
          <p>I clipped the following touching incident from
the American Magazine. It was written by Mr.
Ray Stannard Baker just after the Atlanta riot.
He says: “The mass of colored people still
maintain, as I have said, a more or less intimate
connection with white families, frequently a very
beautiful and sympathetic relationship like that
of the old mammies or nurses. To one who has
heard so much of racial hatred as I have since
I have been down here, a little incident that I
<pb id="lowery182" n="182"/>
observed the other day comes with a charm
hardly describable. I saw a carriage stop in
front of a home. The expected daughter had
arrived—a very pretty girl indeed. She stepped
out eagerly. Her father was half way down to
the gate, but ahead of him was a very old negro
woman in the cleanest of clean starched dresses.</p>
          <p>“ ‘Honey,’ she said eagerly. ‘Mammy!’
exclaimed the girl, and the two rushed into each
others' arms, clasping and kissing, the white girl
and the old black woman.</p>
          <p>“I thought to myself: ‘There's no negro problem
there: that's just plain human love.’ ”</p>
          <p>When Senator James Gordon, of Mississippi,
was leaving the United States Senate not long
since he read an original poem entitled, “The
Old Black Mammy.” I herewith reproduce it:</p>
          <lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <head>THE OLD BLACK MAMMY.</head>
            <lg type="verse" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
              <l part="N">'Tis easy to wander off from my theme</l>
              <l part="N">When traveling over the ground;</l>
              <l part="N">Thro' evergreen pastures across the bright stream</l>
              <l part="N">When in fancy I wander around,</l>
              <l part="N">And see in the picture which never grows older</l>
              <l part="N">Tho' age chills the blood which never grows colder.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb id="lowery183" n="183"/>
            <lg type="verse" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
              <l part="N">In fancy I see those good old negroes again</l>
              <l part="N">I loved in the days long ago,</l>
              <l part="N">As they worked in the fields of cotton and grain</l>
              <l part="N">And sung as they chopped with the hoe;</l>
              <l part="N">I can never forget, wherever I roam,</l>
              <l part="N">The scenes of my childhood and home.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="verse" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
              <l part="N">The dear old black mammy, so gentle and tender,</l>
              <l part="N">So faithful and true to her trust—</l>
              <l part="N">I loved her so well I dared not offend her;</l>
              <l part="N">She is gone, yet I honor her dust.</l>
              <l part="N">From the wells of my heart arise tears of regret;</l>
              <l part="N">Tho' she sleeps 'neath the sod, I can never forget.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="verse" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
              <l part="N">She was lovely to me in, her colored bandanna</l>
              <l part="N">With which she turbaned her head;</l>
              <l part="N">Her songs were far sweeter than flute or piano</l>
              <l part="N">As she put me to sleep in my bed;</l>
              <l part="N">Her soft, crooning voice I can never forget,</l>
              <l part="N">Like an angel, in dreams, she comes to me yet.</l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
          <p>A few years ago I clipped the following from
the New York World:</p>
          <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
            <text>
              <body>
                <div1 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                  <head>A SOUTHERN WOMAN'S PROTEST.</head>
                  <opener>
                    <salute>To the Editor of The World:</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Tired of the continual warfare upon the colored
race, I, a Southern woman, vigorously
<pb id="lowery184" n="184"/>
shout my protest. Accustomed to their kindly
faces from childhood, I fling my praise. The
negro pleads for justice. He does not crave
equality. They are grateful, trusting and sympathetic.
As to their patience, it reaches the
sublime. They exist against fearful odds, “Put
yourself in his place.” Heinous crimes are committed
only by the ignorant, hunted, starved desperado.
Such creatures frequently degrade
every nationality. For every rascally negro (I
am unbiased) score tenfold white demons, the
majority arrayed in fine cloth. Day and night
they await every opportunity (base human vultures,
fair-skinned) to drag innocent girl victims
in the meshes of gilded vice. Lavish expenditure
on wines, blandishments, deceit are
unblushingly used as a means to success. No
man can gainsay me. Remove the causes.
Stop this un-Christian crusade against the
poor, downtrodden black man and educate the
“white boss” to show him a better example.
Faithfully, I was rocked on the breast of a
saintly old black mammy in my babyhood. Today
her memory I still revere. I can not resist
defending her helpless race. Far better give him
a chance to earn his living than to despise and
execute without lawful sanction.</p>
                  <signed>LOUISIANA.</signed>
                </div1>
              </body>
            </text>
          </q>
          <pb id="lowery185" n="185"/>
          <p>If there could only be more people of the same
opinion, how much better the two races would
get along together. There's a truth in every sentence
of that person's generous letter, and we are
glad that there is some one who thinks as she
does about the situation.</p>
          <q direct="unspecified">
            <text>
              <body>
                <div1 type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                  <head>OLD BLACK MAMMY.</head>
                  <p>(Many of the Southern States propose erecting
a monument to the old black mammy of ante-bellum
days.—Daily Paper.)</p>
                  <lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                    <lg type="verse" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                      <l part="N">Away down South in Dixieland</l>
                      <l part="N">Where snowy fields of cotton grow,</l>
                      <l part="N">And live-oaks stand in mossy cloaks</l>
                      <l part="N">Like ghostly soldiers in a row,</l>
                      <l part="N">And banjos tinkle to the moon,</l>
                      <l part="N">And winds are heavy with the scent</l>
                      <l part="N">Of jasmine and magnolias,</l>
                      <l part="N">They want to raise a monument</l>
                      <l part="N">To old black mammy.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="verse" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                      <l part="N">The memory of her <sic corr="ebony">ebon</sic> face</l>
                      <l part="N">Beneath its scarlet turban gay,</l>
                      <l part="N">Is dear to all her babies yet,</l>
                      <l part="N">Though they are wrinkled, bent and gray.</l>
                      <l part="N">She rocked them in their loving arms,</l>
                      <l part="N">And crooned them off to happy rest,</l>
                      <l part="N">And all their childish griefs and pains</l>
                      <l part="N">Were soothed upon the ample breast</l>
                      <l part="N">Of old black mammy.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <pb id="lowery186" n="186"/>
                    <lg type="verse" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                      <l part="N">She peopled with her fancy quaint</l>
                      <l part="N">Each bush and tree with spectres bold,</l>
                      <l part="N">And while a son of Dixie lives</l>
                      <l part="N">Her folk-lore stories will be told.</l>
                      <l part="N">They dwell in every Southern heart,</l>
                      <l part="N">They roll from every Southern tongue,</l>
                      <l part="N">The mystic, droll, romantic tales</l>
                      <l part="N">Her children loved to hear when young</l>
                      <l part="N">From old black mammy.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="verse" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
                      <l part="N">Her loyal faith in things divine,</l>
                      <l part="N">Her simple creed of hope and trust,</l>
                      <l part="N">Survive the seasons as they fade,</l>
                      <l part="N">And rise triumphant from the dust.</l>
                      <l part="N">Her skin was black, her soul was white,</l>
                      <l part="N">Her many virtues justly claim</l>
                      <l part="N">The tribute of a sculptured stone</l>
                      <l part="N">To glorify the lowly name</l>
                      <l part="N">Of old black mammy.</l>
                    </lg>
                  </lg>
                  <bibl default="NO">MINA IRVING, McGirt's Magazine.</bibl>
                </div1>
              </body>
            </text>
          </q>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI.2>