<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY offletp SYSTEM "offletp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY offlecv SYSTEM "offlecv.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>A Narrative of the Life and Labors of the Rev. G. W. Offley, a Colored Man, 
Local Preacher and Missionary,</emph>
<emph>Who Lived Twenty-Seven Years at the
South and Twenty-Three at 
the North; Who Never Went to School a Day in His Life, and Only Commenced
to Learn His Letters 
When Nineteen Years and Eight Months Old; the Emancipation of His Mother
and Her Three Children; 
How He Learned to Read While Living in a Slave State, and Supported
Himself from the Time He Was
 Nine Years Old Until He Was Twenty-One:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Offley, G. W. (Greensbury Washington), b. 1808</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Fiona Mills</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by</resp>
          <name>Fiona Mills</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Bethany Ronnberg and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>2000</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>40KB</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>2000.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as 
long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="cover"> A Narrative of the Life and Labors of the Rev. G. W. Offley, A Colored Man, 
Local Preacher and Missionary.</title>
            <title type="title page"> A Narrative of the Life and Labors of the Rev. G. W. Offley, A Colored 
Man, Local Preacher and Missionary, Who Lived Twenty-Seven Years at the South and Twenty-Three at 
the North; Who Never Went to School a Day in His Life, and Only Commenced to Learn His Letters 
When Nineteen Years and Eight Months Old; the Emancipation of His Mother and Her Three Children; 
How He Learned to Read While Living in a Slave State, and Supported Himself from the Time He Was
 Nine Years Old Until He Was Twenty-One.</title>
            <author>Rev. G. W. Offley</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>24 p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>Hartford, Conn.</pubPlace>
            <publisher/>
            <date>1859.</date>
            <authority/>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="yes">Call number  Bd. Pam. 326.92 Z99  (Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections 
Library, Duke University Libraries)</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft
 Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Offley, G. W. (Greensbury Washington), b. 1808.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Maryland -- Biography.</item>
            <item>African American clergy -- Maryland -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Maryland -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Freedmen -- Maryland -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Religious life -- Maryland -- History -- 19th
century.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- Maryland -- History -- 19th century.</item>
            <item>Slaves' writings, American -- Maryland.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2000-07-20, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2000-01-14, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2000-01-11, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Bethany Ronnberg</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-12-16, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Fiona Mills</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="cover">
        <p>
          <figure id="cv" entity="offlecv"/>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="titlepage">
        <p>
          <figure id="tp" entity="offletp"/>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">A NARRATIVE
<lb/>
OF THE
<lb/>
LIFE AND LABORS
<lb/>
OF THE
<lb/>
G. W. OFFLEY,
<lb/>
A COLORED MAN, <lb/>Local Preacher and Missionary,</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="subtitle">WHO LIVED TWENTY-SEVEN YEARS AT THE SOUTH AND TWENTY-THREE<lb/>
AT THE NORTH; WHO NEVER WENT TO SCHOOL A DAY IN HIS LIFE,<lb/>
AND ONLY COMMENCED TO LEARN HIS LETTERS WHEN NINETEEN<lb/>
YEARS AND EIGHT MONTHS OLD; THE EMANCIPATION OF<lb/>
HIS MOTHER AND THEIR THREE CHILDREN; HOW HE<lb/>
LEARNED TO READ WHILE LIVING IN A SLAVE<lb/>
STATE, AND SUPPORTED HIMSELF FROM THE<lb/>
TIME HE WAS NINE YEARS OLD<lb/>
UNTIL HE WAS TWENTY-ONE.</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <docImprint><pubPlace>HARTFORD, CONN.,</pubPlace> <docDate>1859.</docDate></docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="introduction">
        <pb id="offley2" n="2"/>
        <list type="simple">
          <head>NAMES OF GENTLEMEN WHO SPEAK IN HIGH TERMS OF
HIS<lb/> MORAL WORTH:</head>
          <item><hi rend="italics">Ware, Mass., Feb., </hi>1852.</item>
          <item>REV<corr>.</corr> W. WARD.</item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italics">Hartford, Conn.,</hi> 1854.</item>
          <item>REV. DR. J. HAWES.</item>
          <item>“Dr. H. BUSHNELL.</item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italics">Worcester, Mass.,</hi> 1854.</item>
          <item>REV. O. SWEETSER.</item>
          <item>“E. SMALLEY.</item>
          <item>“GEO. BUSHNELL.</item>
          <item>“DR. A. HILL.</item>
          <item>Hon. JOHN DAVIS.</item>
          <item>REV. O. H. TILLOTSON.</item>
          <lb/>
          <item><hi rend="italics">Boston, Mass.,</hi> 1859.</item>
          <item>REV. JOHN W. DADMAN.</item>
          <item>REV. E. E. HALL.</item>
        </list>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="text">
        <pb id="offley3" n="3"/>
        <head>NARRATIVE
<lb/>
OF THE LIFE OF<lb/>
REV. G. W. OFFLEY.</head>
        <p>My mother was born a slave in the State of
Virginia, and sold in the State of Maryland,
and there remained until married, and became
the mother of three children. She was willed
free at the death of her master; her three children
were also willed free at the age of twenty-five.
But my youngest brother was put on a
second will, which was destroyed by the widow
and the children, and he was subjected to bondage
for life. My father was a free man, and
therefore bought him as a slave for life and
<pb id="offley4" n="4"/>
give him his freedom at the age of twenty
years. He also bought my sister for a term
of years, say until she was twenty-five years old.
He gave her her freedom at the age of sixteen
years. He bought my grand-mother, who was
too old to set free, that she might be exempted
from hard servitude in her old age.</p>
        <p>Previous to the sale of this family, my
mother was living with her master's children,
and they persuaded mother to not consent to
father's buying the children, and told father if
he attempted to buy one of them they would
shoot him dead on the auction ground; that
they would buy the children themselves, and
they should have their freedom according to
their father's will. Mother told them they
might buy them and welcome, but you had
better throw your money in the fire, for if you
buy one of my children I will cut all three of
their throats while they are asleep, and your
money will do you no good. Her young masters
<pb id="offley5" n="5"/>
were afraid that she meant what she said,
and they concluded that it would bring a
disgrace upon the family to prohibit a man from
buying his own children, though mother had no
intention of doing as she said.</p>
        <p>The auctioneer was a true friend to father,
and used great deception in making the purchaser
believe that the two children would die
unless they could have their mother's care, so
that father bought them at his own price, as
no person bid against him. They wanted to
have mother and father to work for them, and
they would bring up the two children as mother
had; neither had any care of a family, and
they was afraid the children would suffer.
Mother said if they did suffer they would not
be accountable for it,—that she had two hands,
and she could work and take care of her own
children without their help. But when she
became the mother of eight children, and
father working for twenty-five or fifty cents
<pb id="offley6" n="6"/>
per day, she often would think of her old master's
kitchen and wish for some of the good
victuals she had given to the poor whites, and
the field slaves. But little did they think they
would ever be poor. One of her young mistresses
married a miserable young man and she
went blind and died heart-broken. Her young
master's daughter married a similar kind of
wretch, and died young, as thousands of the
wicked do.</p>
        <p>I was born Dec. 18th, 1808, in the State of
Maryland, Queen Ann County, Centerville.
My mother and father were illiterate, and kept
no record of their children's births, only
referring to circumstances. But when I was seven
years old I heard mother say that her young
master's daughter Ann was two weeks older
than myself, and I got a stick, or piece of wood,
and made 1111111 notches, and at the end of
every year would add another 1 notch until
I was twenty-one years old. At that time there
<pb id="offley7" n="7"/>
was a dispute between mother and father about
my age. Mother said I was twenty-one, and
father thought I was only twenty, and I went
to Centerville and saw Miss Ann, who was
born two weeks before me. I asked her if she
was twenty-one, and she said yes she was just
twenty-one years old, and I returned from my
ten miles walk, but dare not name it to father
until he mentioned it, and I told him I had
been to see Miss Ann and she said I was twenty-one
years old; then said he you are free
from me. During my boyhood father hired
me to a slaveholder for a term of four years
to pay his house rent. From the time I was
nine years old I worked and supported myself
until I was twenty-one years old, and never
received one dollar of my wages. When I
was ten years old I sat down and taking an old
basket to pieces, learned myself to make baskets.
After that I learned to make foot mats and horse
collars, not of leather but of corn husks; also
<pb id="offley8" n="8"/>
two kinds of brooms. These articles I used to
make nights and sell to get money for myself.
When I was sixteen years old I commenced
taking contracts of wood-chopping, at fifty
cents per cord, and hired slaves to chop for me
nights, when the moon shone bright. In the
fall and winter we would make our fire and
chop until eleven or twelve at night. We
used to catch oysters and fish nights, and hire
other slaves to peddle them out on Sunday
mornings. By this way I have helped some to
get their freedom.</p>
        <p>EXODUS 20-12: Honor thy father and thy
mother, that thy days may be long upon the
land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</p>
        <p>When I was twenty-one years old I gave my
father one year's work to buy him a horse.
One year's wages for an able bodied man
$50, or $60, fifty or sixty dollars per year,
and two holidays at Easter,—two in June, two
in harvest, and six at the end of the year; one
<pb id="offley9" n="9"/>
pair shoes, one pair stockings, one pair woolen
pants, one coat, two pairs coarse tow linen
pants, two shirts, and board, is the law of the
State of Maryland allows a man, free or slave,
black or white, who hires for one year.</p>
        <p>My friends who may read this little work,
will make due allowance when they see that I
never possessed the advantage of one day's
schooling in my life, and only commenced to
learn my letters when nineteen years and
eight months old.</p>
        <p>At one time, when going to my work, I found
a piece of a chapter of an old Bible, Genesis
25, concerning Isaac, Jacob, and Esau. At
this time there was an old colored man working
for my father. He, taking the piece of Bible,
and read it to me; I do not remember ever
hearing that much of the Bible read before.
I told him I would like to learn to read; he
told me to get a book and he would learn me,
while he stayed with us. I bought a little
<pb id="offley10" n="10"/>
primer, and Sunday morning he commenced
learning me my letters. By Monday morning
I could say them all. He would give me lessons
nights and Sabbath mornings. He said
when he used to take his master's children to
school, he would carry his book in his hat
and get the children to give him a lesson in
the interval of the school. He grew up to be
a young man, experienced religion, and joined
the M. E. church, and was authorized to preach
among his colored brethren, free and slave, and
was set free some time before he worked for
my father.</p>
        <p>After he left our house I was without a
teacher, and there was an old man about
seventy-five or eighty years old, a slaveholder,
owned a small farm and one slave woman married
to a slave belonging to another slaveholder.
This woman was the mother of two small
children. Her old master had five daughters,
one son eighteen years of age, a family of ten
<pb id="offley11" n="11"/>
in number, to be supported from this little
farm,—no one to work except this son and the
slave woman, only as I would go and help them
occasionally. By this the young man and I
became very intimate, and I learned him the
art of wrestling, boxing and fighting, and he
learned me to read. After that I went to work
on a rail road; then I taught boxing school,
and learned to write. After that I went to
St. George, Del., to work at a hotel. One day
a white boy came to me and said that he was
hungry; his father gambled away his money,
and if I would give him and his little sister
something to eat occasionally, he would come
three nights in the week and set copies for me
to write, and learn me to cypher. The landlady
was very glad of the opportunity, and
gave me the privilege of giving them as much
as I pleased, and I used to take them in the kitchen
and give them what they could eat, and fill
their little basket to take home. He would
<pb id="offley12" n="12"/>
stay with me sometimes until 2 or 3 o'clock
P. M., and learn me to cypher to the single
rule of three.</p>
        <p>I arrived at Hartford on the 15th of Nov.,
1835. Since that time some of my good white
friends have assisted me by referring me to
good books, and giving good instruction, of
which I have reason to believe some of them
are in heaven, and others on earth doing good.</p>
        <p>My mother's and father's theology, or the
way we children were taught by our parents,
neither of them could read; but as mother's
master was a member of the M. E. church, and
used to read the Bible to his slaves—not learn
nor teach them to read, but read the Bible
to them.</p>
        <p>First, man is a compound being, possessing
two natures, a soul and a body; the body is
of the earth, and must die and return to the
dust from whence it came; but the soul is immortal;
that is, will never die, but will live forever
<pb id="offley13" n="13"/>
in happiness with God, or exist in hell
for ever. This theology teaches of two places
for the souls of the human family after death,
and the condition by which they must go first.
If children were obedient to their parents or
their owners, and prayed to the Lord to forgive
them of their sins and make them good
children, and keep them from telling lies, from
stealing, from taking the Lord's name in vain,
and to keep the Sabbath holy. But above all,
never to be saucy to old people, lest our case
should be like the forty-two children destroyed
by the two she bears—II KINGS, chap. 2-23:
And he went up from thence unto Bethel, and
as he was going up by the way there came
forth little children out of the city and mocked
him, and said unto him, Go up, thou
head, go up thou bald head. Verse 24: and
he turned back and looked on them and cursed
them in the name of the Lord; and there came
forth two she-bears out of the wood and tore
<pb id="offley14" n="14"/>
forty and two children of them. And I am
glad to know that even from the most oppressed
slave to the most refined white family's
children at the south, are taught to respect the
old, white or black. Their children call old
colored people aunt and uncle by way of respect.
None use the word ‘nigger’ but the low
and vulgar.</p>
        <p>Our family theology teaches that God is no
respecter of persons, but gave his son to die
for all, bond or free, black or white, rich or
poor. If we keep his commandments, we will
be happy after death. It also teaches that if
God calls and sanctifies a person to do some
great work, that person is immortal until his
work is done; that God is able and will protect
him from all danger or accident in life if he is
faithful to his calling or charge committed by
the Lord. This is a borrowed idea from circumstances
too numerous to mention. Here,
is one man we present as a proof of the
<pb id="offley15" n="15"/>
immortality of man, while in the flesh: Praying
Jacob. This man was a slave in the State of
Maryland. His master was very cruel to his
slaves. Jacob's rule was to pray three times a
day, at just such an hour of the day; no matter
what his work was or where he might be, he
would stop and go and pray. His master has
been to him and pointed his gun at him, and
told him if he did not cease praying he would
blow out his brains. Jacob would finish his
prayer and then tell his master to shoot in
welcome—your loss will be my gain—I have
two masters, one on earth and one in heaven
—master Jesus in heaven, and master Saunders
on earth. I have a soul and a body; the
body belongs to you, master Saunders, and
the soul to master Jesus. Jesus says men
ought always to pray, but you will not pray,
neither do you want to have me pray. This
man said in private conversation that several
times he went home and drank an unusual
<pb id="offley16" n="16"/>
quantity of brandy to harden his heart that he
might kill him; but he never had power to
strike nor shoot him, and he would freely give
the world, if he had it in his possession for
what he believed his Jacob to possess. He
also thought that Jacob was as sure of Heaven
as the apostle Paul or Peter. Sometimes Mr.
S. would be in the field about half drunk,
raging like a madman, whipping the other
slaves; and when Jacob's hour would come for
prayer, he would stop his horses and plough
and kneel down and pray; but he could not
strike the man of God.</p>
        <p>The first Methodist minister that ever
preached. in a certain town in Queen Ann's
county, there was a great revival of religion
among the rich and poor, black and white, free
and slaves. When many of them experienced
religion they would disobey their ungodly
masters and would go to meetings nights and
Sundays. Two rich slaveholders waylaid the
<pb id="offley17" n="17"/>
minister at night, and taking him off from his
horse and beat him until they thought he was
dead. But the Lord saved his life to preach
his Word, and many were converted in the
same town through his preaching, and many
masters, when converted, set their slaves free.</p>
        <p>My grandmother died at ninety years of
age; my mother at seventy, and my father at
eighty years of age. These three friends died
in the strongest triumph of faith in Jesus, who
when on earth said he would be with his people
to the end of the world. Amen.</p>
        <p>Perhaps some person will ask why did I
teach the art of wrestling, boxing and fighting,
when desirous to learn to read the Bible? I
answer because no one is so contemptible as a
coward. With us a coward is looked upon as
the most degraded wretch on earth, and is only
worthy to be a slave. My brother's master,
Governor R. Right, of Maryland, taught his
children never to take an insult from one of
<pb id="offley18" n="18"/>
their equals—that is, from the rich and
educated. Their domestic slaves were taught not
to take an insult from another rich man's
domestic slave under any consideration. By
this, you perceive, I was trying to be respectable
by doing like the rich. Those who read
the lives of our great statesmen, know they
were duellists. Then I thought he who could
control his antagonist by the art of his physical
power was a greater man. But I thank the
Lord, since the 21st of Feb., 1836, I have been
enabled to see things in a different light, and
believe the man is greater who can overcome
his foes by his Christlike example.</p>
        <p>A word to my colored friends. It is often
said that we are a degraded people in this
country as well as in Africa. Before we
consent to the charge, let us look at the word
degradation. Walker says it means “deprivation
of office or dignity, degeneracy, to lessen, to
diminish.” I cannot see that his explanation
<pb id="offley19" n="19"/>
has anything to do with the charge against
us in a moral sense of the term. When properly
taken into consideration, if we only
number one-sixth part of the population of
the United States. Because we have six men
against one to vote us out of office; that is
not degrading us, it is oppressing us. If six
colored men should take a white child from
its parents, and teach it that its highest obligations
belong to us, we six men, that we stand
in the place of God—this is the kind of education
many of our people have at the south.
Now I ask if this child should become a
sabbath-breaker, or a liar, a thief, or a drunkard,
or an adulterer, not having the advantage to
know better, I ask who is the degraded man?
Paul says, Romans 4; 15: For where there is
no law there is no transgression. Then the
moral guilt rests on the oppressor and not on
the oppressed. We must not feel that we are
degraded. The true meaning of the word
<pb id="offley20" n="20"/>
degrade, is to be low, mean, contemptible, willing
to do a mean act that we know is displeasing
in the sight of God and man. Therefore we
may be oppressed by man, but never morally
degraded, only as we are made willing subjects
to do sinful acts against what we know or have
the power to know is wrong in the sight of
God and man.</p>
        <p>No difference how poor we are, if we are
respectable, honest, and upright, with God,
ourselves, and our fellow man. For St. Peter
declares, Acts 10, 34-35, that God is no
respecter of persons. But in every nation, he
that feareth him, and worketh righteousness, is
accepted with him. And if any man is accepted
with his God, then oppression, nor prejudice,
or prisons, or chains, or whips, or anything
formed by man, cannot degrade us. No, we
must voluntarily subscribe to some mean act
before we can be mean or low in the sight of
our dear Lord and Master.</p>
        <pb id="offley21" n="21"/>
        <p>My dear and much beloved, allow
me to say to one and all, be sure to send your
children to the day and sabbath schools.</p>
        <closer>Yours in love,
<signed>G. W. OFFLEY.</signed></closer>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="text">
        <pb id="offley22" n="22"/>
        <head>WHAT A MERCY.</head>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>What a mercy, a mercy is this!</l>
          <l>What a mercy, a mercy is this!</l>
          <l>What a mercy is this, what heavenly bliss,</l>
          <l>Jesus died to redeem a lost race.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>What will, oh, what will become of me,</l>
          <l>What will, oh, what will become of me,</l>
          <l>What will become of me when death approaches me,</l>
          <l>If the Saviour is not found in my heart.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>It is awful, 'tis awful to relate,</l>
          <l>It is awful, 'tis awful to relate,</l>
          <l>'Tis awful to relate, if death should be my fate,</l>
          <l>If the Saviour is not found in my heart.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>But welcome, but welcome death to me,</l>
          <l>But welcome, but welcome death to me,</l>
          <l>But welcome death to me, if Christ should set me free,</l>
          <l>If my Saviour is found in my heart.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>Adieu and adieu to you all,</l>
          <l>Adieu and adieu to you all,</l>
          <l>Adieu and adieu to you all, my Saviour doth me call,</l>
          <l>He hath promised to make me anew.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>Adieu to affliction and pain,</l>
          <l>Adieu to affliction and pain.</l>
          <pb id="offley23" n="23"/>
          <l>Adieu to all pain, for dying is gain,</l>
          <l>If my Saviour is found in my heart.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>How reviving and cheering to my mind,</l>
          <l>How reviving and cheering to my mind,</l>
          <l>How cheering to my mind the friends I left behind,</l>
          <l>If my Saviour is found in my heart.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>But we hope and we hope for to meet,</l>
          <l>But we hope and we hope for to meet,</l>
          <l>But we hope and we hope for to meet, and worship at his feet,</l>
          <l>And reign with our Saviour above.</l>
        </lg>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="text">
        <head>JACOB'S LADDER.</head>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>As Jacob on travels was wearied by day,</l>
          <l>At night on a stone for a pillow he lay,</l>
          <l>A vision appeared—a ladder so high,</l>
          <l>With its foot on the earth, and the top in the sky.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>CHORUS—Hallelujah to Jesus who died on the tree,</l>
          <l>To raise up his ladder of Mercy for me.</l>
          <l>Press forward! press forward! the prize is in
view,</l>
          <l>And a crown of bright glory is waiting for you.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>The ladder is long—it's strong and well made—</l>
          <l>Stood thousands of years, and is not decayed;</l>
          <l>It's so free of access, all the world may get up,</l>
          <l>And angels will guard you from bottom to top.—CHORUS.</l>
        </lg>
        <pb id="offley24" n="24"/>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>This ladder is Jesus, the glorious God-man,</l>
          <l>Whose blood rightly streaming from Calvary ran,</l>
          <l>On his perfect atonement to heaven we rise,</l>
          <l>And sing in the mansions prepared in the skies.—CHORUS.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>Come let us ascend—behold! never fear—</l>
          <l>It stood every tempest and always will bear;</l>
          <l>Millions have tried it, and reached Zion's hill,</l>
          <l>And thousands by faith are climbing it still.—CHORUS.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>Our fathers upon it have mounted to God,</l>
          <l>Have finished their labors and reach'd their abode,</l>
          <l>And we are a climbing, and soon will be there,</l>
          <l>To join in their raptures, their happiness share.—CHORUS.</l>
        </lg>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>