<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % external-entities SYSTEM "./extEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY % internal-entities SYSTEM "./intEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY thompfp1 SYSTEM "thompfp1.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY thompfp2 SYSTEM "thompfp2.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY thompht SYSTEM "thompht.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY thomptp SYSTEM "thomptp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY thompcv SYSTEM "thompcv.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>Sketches of the History, Character, and Dying Testimony, of Beneficiaries of the Colored Home, in the City of New-York:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Thompson, Mary W.</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name>Bethany Ronnberg</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by</resp>
          <name>Bethany Ronnberg</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Carlene Hempel and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1999</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca. 160K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1999.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>©  This work is the property of the 
University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for 
research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement 
of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note anchored="yes">Call number E185.93 N56 T4 1851 
(Davis Library, UNC-CH)</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="title page">Sketches of the History, Character, 
and Dying Testimony, of Beneficiaries of the Colored Home, in the 
City of New-York.</title>
            <title type="cover">Broken Gloom.</title>
            <title type="half-title page">Broken Gloom.</title>
            <author>Thompson, Mary W.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
            <publisher>John F. Trow, Printer, 49, 51, amp; 53 Ann-St.</publisher>
            <date>1851</date>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American 
South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ 
and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using 
Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject 
Headings </title>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Older African Americans -- Institutional care -- New York (State) -- New York.</item>
            <item>Older African Americans -- Medical care -- New York (State) -- New York.</item>
            <item>Older African Americans -- New York (State) -- New York.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Medical care -- New York (State) -- New York.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- New York (State) -- New York.</item>
            <item>Colored Home (New York, N.Y.)</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2004-11-18,</date>
        <respStmt>
          <name> Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-03-26, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-03-19, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Carlene Hempel</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-03-14, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Bethany Ronnberg</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="cover">
        <p>
          <figure id="cover" entity="thompcv">
            <p>[Cover Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="half-title">
        <p>
          <figure id="half" entity="thompht">
            <p>[Half-Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="frontispiece">
        <p>
          <figure id="frontis1" entity="thompfp1">
            <p>Broken Gloom.<lb/>[1st Frontispiece Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="frontispiece">
        <p>
          <figure id="frontis2" entity="thompfp2">
            <p>FRONT VIEW OF THE COLORED HOME.<lb/>[2nd Frontispiece Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="title page">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="thomptp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">SKETCHES
<lb/>
OF THE
<lb/>
HISTORY, CHARACTER, AND DYING TESTIMONY,
<lb/>
OF
<lb/>
BENEFICIARIES
<lb/>
OF
<lb/>
THE COLORED HOME, IN THE CITY OF NEW-YORK.</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>PREPARED BY</byline>
        <docAuthor>MARY W. THOMPSON,</docAuthor>
        <docEdition>AND PUBLISHED FOR THE BENEFIT OF THE INSTITUTION.</docEdition>
        <docImprint><pubPlace>NEW YORK:</pubPlace>
<publisher>JOHN F. TROW, PRINTER, 49, 51 &amp; 53 ANN-ST.</publisher>
<docDate>1851.</docDate></docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="poem">
        <lg type="poem">
          <l rend="indent1"><hi rend="italics">Darkness</hi>, 
which might be <hi rend="italics">felt</hi>,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Hung o'er that dreary land,</l>
          <l rend="indent1">Where Afric's sable children dwelt</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Amidst its glittering sand.</l>
          <l rend="indent1">Those shadows there, might still</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Have direful influence shed,</l>
          <l rend="indent1">O'er grove, and glen, and towering hill,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Deepening in awful dread,</l>
          <l rend="indent1">Had not Almighty Power,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">With beams of light Divine,</l>
          <l rend="indent1">Broke through the gloom, in <hi rend="italics">Mercy's</hi> hour,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">In radiance there to shine.</l>
        </lg>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="contents">
        <pb id="thompson3" n="3"/>
        <head>CONTENTS.</head>
        <list type="simple">
          <item>Preface, . . . . . <ref target="thompson5" targOrder="U">5</ref></item>
          <item>Introductory 
Remarks, . . . . . <ref target="thompson9" targOrder="U">9</ref></item>
          <item>Biographical Sketches:—</item>
          <item>Hercules Schureman, . . . . . <corr><ref target="thompson17" targOrder="U">17</ref></corr></item>
          <item>Jonathan Skinner, . . . . . <ref target="thompson19" targOrder="U">19</ref></item>
          <item>Tommy Warner, . . . . . <ref target="thompson20" targOrder="U">20</ref></item>
          <item>Blind Sopha, . . . . . <ref target="thompson21" targOrder="U">21</ref></item>
          <item>Amy Jordan, . . . . . <ref target="thompson22" targOrder="U">22</ref></item>
          <item>Judy Richards, . . . . . <ref target="thompson25" targOrder="U">25</ref></item>
          <item>Abigail Dobson, . . . . . <ref target="thompson28" targOrder="U">28</ref></item>
          <item>Edward, . . . . . <ref target="thompson30" targOrder="U">30</ref></item>
          <item>Phillis Douglas, . . . . . <ref target="thompson31" targOrder="U">31</ref></item>
          <item>Betsey Johnson, . . . . . <ref target="thompson33" targOrder="U">33</ref></item>
          <item>Phebe Spalding, . . . . . <ref target="thompson35" targOrder="U">35</ref></item>
          <item>Old Sarah Henry, . . . . . <ref target="thompson36" targOrder="U">36</ref></item>
          <item>Eliza Didymus, . . . . . <ref target="thompson37" targOrder="U">37</ref></item>
          <item>Poor Johnny, . . . . . <ref target="thompson39" targOrder="U">39</ref></item>
          <item>Catherine Queen, . . . . . <ref target="thompson40" targOrder="U">40</ref></item>
          <pb id="thompson4" n="4"/>
          <item>Katy Schenck, . . . . . <ref target="thompson41" targOrder="U">41</ref></item>
          <item>Margaret Simpson, . . . . . <ref target="thompson48" targOrder="U">48</ref></item>
          <item>Diana, . . . . . <ref target="thompson48" targOrder="U">48</ref></item>
          <item>Minutes of Chaplain, . . . . . <ref target="thompson50" targOrder="U">50</ref></item>
          <item>Serena Johnson, . . . . . <ref target="thompson52" targOrder="U">62</ref></item>
          <item>Diana Rayner, . . . . . <ref target="thompson52" targOrder="U">52</ref></item>
          <item>Sarah Robinson, . . . . . <ref target="thompson53" targOrder="U">53</ref></item>
          <item>Blind Diana, . . . . . <ref target="thompson53" targOrder="U">53</ref></item>
          <item>Incidents, . . . . . <ref target="thompson54" targOrder="U">54 to 56</ref></item>
          <item>Sketches from Mrs. R.'s Report, . . . . . <ref target="thompson64" targOrder="U">64</ref></item>
          <item>Peter Bensé, . . . . . <ref target="thompson67" targOrder="U">67</ref></item>
          <item>Concluding Remarks, . . . . . <ref target="thompson73" targOrder="U">73</ref></item>
          <item>Condensed Statement of the Colored Home, . . . . . 
<ref target="thompson75" targOrder="U">75</ref></item>
          <item>Managers' Names, &amp;c., . . . . . 
<ref target="thompson77" targOrder="U">77</ref></item>
        </list>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="preface">
        <pb id="thompson5" n="5"/>
        <head>PREFACE.</head>
        <p>THE design of this little book is to make known more
extensively the character of the Institution on whose behalf
these pages speak,—to prove its usefulness in carrying out the
plan of benevolence in pursuance of which it was originally
established, and which, in its operations thus far, has fully
proved its utility and advantages, showing itself worthy the
patronage and support of a benevolent and Christian public.</p>
        <p>The Institution not only provides protection and a peaceful
home for the respectable, worn-out colored servants of both
sexes of our city, by sheltering and sustaining them during the
lingering days of declining life, but furnishes them in their last
moments the consolations of religion.</p>
        <pb id="thompson6" n="6"/>
        <p>It also relieves the Alms-House and the community of
another portion of colored persons, who, being sick or diseased,
hopeless and helpless, have no means to provide for
themselves, and who would necessarily, otherwise, become a
burden upon society. These latter, by an arrangement entered
into with the commissioners, are received into this Home for a
season, or until they are healed of their sicknesses and able to
resume employment—thus they are rescued from much
suffering and destitution, being cared for, instructed in the right
way, lifted up from degradation and wretchedness, and encouraged
to habits of industry and propriety.</p>
        <p>The Managers contemplate, so soon as their means will
justify them, erecting a chapel, or a building with chapel
accommodations, and school-room, for the instruction of the
inmates who choose to avail themselves of the privilege of
learning to read and write. They have also accommodation
rooms for workshops, where the inmates of the Home, not
incapacitated by illness or infirmities, may be taught some
handicraft which may be a source of profit to them after leaving
the Institution, enabling them to support themselves by their
industry.</p>
        <pb id="thompson7" n="7"/>
        <p>We have commenced this work in faith; trusting that
the public will contribute to our aid to enable us to carry
out our plans of operation. The enterprise certainly commends
itself to the judgment and liberality of our humane citizens, to
whom we look for encouragement, sincerely trusting we
shall not be disappointed.</p>
        <closer><signed>M. W. T.</signed>
<dateline>NEW-YORK, 1851.</dateline></closer>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="introduction">
        <pb id="thompson9" n="9"/>
        <head>INTRODUCTORY REMARKS.</head>
        <p>THE original cause of all suffering is sin. It is this that
has “<hi rend="italics">brought death into the world, 
with all our woe</hi>.”
The fact is established by the experience of every age.</p>
        <p>To the Christian, the sufferings of this life, however
painful and severe, are not worthy to be compared with
the glory that shall be revealed. Having passed through
all its sorrows, its toils, and its deprivations, he rejoices
when
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l rend="indent1">“The 
soft peace-march beats</l><l rend="indent2">Home! brothers, Home!”</l></lg></q></p>
        <p>Notwithstanding the suffering which all are called to
endure, while passing through this vale of tears—some
more, some less—it is yet pleasant to
<pb id="thompson10" n="10"/>
know, that much of this anguish and misery can be
alleviated, soothed, and made more endurable, by the
exercise of sympathy and kindness. For the true
illustration of these Christian virtues, and to confirm us in
our devotion, we have a perfect pattern for our imitation
in Christ, <hi rend="italics">who bore our sins in His own body on the tree</hi>.
Thus, having the embodied testimony of Him, whose
earthly pilgrimage was, that “<hi rend="italics">He went about doing
good</hi>,” Christians are bound to carry out the Divine
intention bequeathed by Him whose mission was <hi rend="italics">mercy</hi>,
and whose precepts and example are obligatory on all
who profess to be His followers.</p>
        <p>Jesus left no duty unfulfilled: nor may His children
leave undone the work that He hath given them to do.
They are to imitate Him in all His imitable perfections;
not that 'tis possible that their devotion can ever equal
His, nor that they can thereby make themselves
meritorious in the sight of God: nay—but because He hath
commanded us to tread in His foot-prints, and taught,
that “herein is His Father glorified, that we bear much
fruit,” is the heart that from love to Him desires His glory,
impelled to pray, and toil, and struggle, that by its
obedience Christ may be glorified, and wretched men be
blest.</p>
        <p>Christian sympathy is no dull, inoperative principle;
no bidding “Be ye warmed and clothed,” the
<pb id="thompson11" n="11"/>
while it shutteth up its bowels of compassion; it is not
satisfied with a mere knowledge of its duty; but
awakened at the cross, where it is made immeasurably a
debtor. As Jesus did, it seeks the poor, the destitute, the
suffering, that it may minister to their necessities and
sorrows, and, if possible, assuage their woes.</p>
        <p>Jesus sought the wretched and lost; His mercy was
extended to all ranks and conditions of men; none were
too humble for His eye of kingly love—none too depraved
and fallen for His compassion. His presence, though He
was the King of kings, won to His healing lip and hand
the sorrow-stricken and the poor. The worst of sinners,
despairing of every other source of relief, knew so well
from His own lips His heavenly mercy; that despite the
crimson guilt that would have driven them from His
spotless purity, they had no power to resist the gentle
kindness that drew them to His feet, but came and sought
and found forgiveness. Whoever came, believing in Him,
received the blessing, and none were ever sent unblessed
away. The sick and suffering were healed of their
maladies; the suppliant, bowed together by the spirit of
infirmity—by a word from His merciful lips became loosed,
till she stood erect before Him. The captive He set free;
He made the lame man leap as an hart, and the tongue
<pb id="thompson12" n="12"/>
of the dumb to sing. The accused, condemned by men,
was forgiven, freed from condemnation by His tender
word of pity, “<hi rend="italics">Neither do I condemn thee; go, and sin no
more</hi>.” The blind, who heard of His approach, lifted their
piercing cry at His coming; He touched with His finger
their sightless balls, and forthwith there fell from their
eyes as it had been scales; and in the breaking of the
glory of the light of heaven on their unprisoned senses,
they ran, and leaped, and followed Jesus. The sorrowing
mother, sister, friend, mourning in bitterness of grief the
departed, received again to their embrace the loved ones
who had been enshrouded for, or had lain in, the grave —
“<hi rend="italics">Maid, 
arise</hi>!<sic corr="quote not necessary">’</sic><ref id="ref1" n="1" rend="sc" target="note1" targOrder="U">*</ref> 
“<hi rend="italics">Young man, I say unto thee, 
arise</hi>!”<ref id="ref2" n="2" rend="sc" target="note2" targOrder="U"><corr>** </corr></ref>
“<hi rend="italics">Lazarus, come 
forth</hi>!”<ref id="ref3" n="3" rend="sc" target="note3" targOrder="U">***</ref> 
and the dead lived again to
manifest His praise and glory.</p>
        <p>How is this spirit of Jesus Christ to be developed
toward the wretched and impoverished children of
Africa?</p>
        <p>We do not deem it necessary to discuss the point,
that the formation of the head and brain make the man or
woman what they are; we leave this for the philosopher
and man of science. But we <hi rend="italics">do</hi> believe, that much
depends upon the arrangement
<note id="note1" n="1" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref1"><p>* 
Luke viii. 54.</p></note>
<note id="note2" n="2" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref2"><p>** 
Luke vii. 14.</p></note>
<note id="note3" n="3" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref3"><p>***  
John xi. 43.</p></note>
<pb id="thompson13" n="13"/>
and strength of the physical system; its immediate
connection with circumstances and advantages; its
occupations, means, and disposition for improvement.
This is evident amongst the white population which flock
to our shores. Many of them are miserable outcasts from
their own country, where they knew little else than
poverty and woe; and who, seeking relief from the
burdens that oppressed them, have come to the land of
<hi rend="italics">light, liberty</hi>, and <hi rend="italics">enterprise</hi>. 
Here, they are taken by the
hand, treated as human beings, placed upon the same
level with ourselves, and made fellow-citizens, and
cheered with the hope, not only of rising to notice and
consideration, but, sharing every civil blessing we enjoy,
are, in due time, even suffered to be competitors to
exalted place and honor.</p>
        <p>It is this that constitutes us a noble and
magnanimous nation, the result of the principles of that
glorious Constitution, that causes us to stand out in
bright and bold relief upon the list of the nations of the
world—a <hi rend="italics">free, generous</hi>, sympathizing, independent and
happy people. None who come to our shores are turned
away; we open our <hi rend="italics">hearts</hi> and bid them welcome; we
open our <hi rend="italics">hands</hi> and relieve the suffering and wretched
exile, and give him a <hi rend="italics">home</hi>, and bestow upon 
<hi rend="italics">him</hi>
blessings, who never knew till now what blessings were.</p>
        <pb id="thompson14" n="14"/>
        <p>The foregoing remarks are not to be considered as
irrelevant to our purpose, nor do we ask to have the same
broad principles carried out toward those for whom these
pages do especially plead, to wit, the infirm and poor of
our colored population. The providence of God, as also
the usages and order of society, seems to have placed
these in a different sphere from those who are made of
fairer dust, and who are born and placed under happier
auspices; they are of a different <hi rend="italics">caste</hi>; but we would
speak of them as human beings, possessing <hi rend="italics">immortal
spirits</hi>, sensible of their accountability to God; we
believe them to be endowed with minds capable of
intellectual culture, and of giving glory to God, by a
sincere and humble profession of faith in Christ; and by
an unpretending and Christian deportment.</p>
        <p>Of their seeming inferiority, incapabilities, and other
humiliating considerations, much might be said in
vindication and defence, from the position in which they
have ever been held, since their introduction among
civilized communities; taught from the beginning to view
themselves as constituted by nature of an inferior order,
subject to the will, and to labor for their superiors. This
being ingrafted upon their minds from the very start,
they come to believe it a truth to which they are bound to
yield with all submission; and until they are brought to
<pb id="thompson15" n="15"/>
colonize themselves in a region separate and distinct
from those who cannot, and will not consider them as
equals, nor admit them to the participation of
constitutional privileges and rights, they must for ever
remain in a state of vassalage, or marked distance from
us.</p>
        <p>Time, and judicious legislation will eventually bring a
change; when the colored of our race will be elevated to
their proper position and standard. <hi rend="italics">Liberia</hi> is a witness
of this, in the growing success of its efforts, and in the
judicious management of her rulers.</p>
        <p>But, while time and effort are working these changes,
much can be done to improve and advance the moral
culture and <sic corr="physical">physicial</sic> condition of those to whom we
allude, whom Providence has thrown upon our charities;
and who, from imperative circumstances, must remain in
our midst. We can show them that we care for them, and
for their comfort and welfare, and make them happier in
their depressed situation.</p>
        <p>The following facts will confirm this opinion.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed>M. W. T.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1>
        <pb id="thompson17" n="17"/>
        <head>SKETCHES.</head>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <head>HERCULES SCHUREMAN</head>
          <p>WAS one of the earliest inmates of the Colored Home;
he was a man of unusual size, about six feet four inches—
large muscular frame, indicating great physical strength.
He was over 100 years of age when he entered the Home,
and for some time after was confined to his bed by
sickness and infirmities. Yet he was happy and cheerful,
in finding, as he remarked, “such a resting-place as this,
for the remainder of his pilgrimage.” And still more happy
did he seem in the anticipation that when his days on
earth should be ended, he should be permitted to glorify
in heaven the Saviour whom he loved to serve.</p>
          <p>In his person, old Hercules was dignified, and his
manner and language such, as to command respect and
attention. He was once a slave, but in
<pb id="thompson18" n="18"/>
early life, by his industry and good conduct, purchased
his freedom, became a minister of the Gospel in the
Methodist connection, and for more than <hi rend="italics">fifty years</hi> he
preached Christ, and proclaimed to his dying fellow-men,
the grace of God which bringeth salvation, and “<hi rend="italics">that
liberty wherewith Christ maketh his people free</hi>.” He
was well instructed in the Scriptures; and although
unskilled in human learning, nature had endowed him
with great mental abilities, combined with a most retentive
memory, which being enriched and sanctified by the
Divine Spirit, made him truly a remarkable man.</p>
          <p>“I have never been more impressed with the fact,”
remarks Mrs. A., one of the Managers, “than when, at
the social meetings at the Home, this aged disciple of
more than a century would pour forth the desires of his
soul in a strain of fervent prayer, which for strong
figurative language I never heard equalled.” He died in
the faith in which he had lived; and, “<hi rend="italics">like a shock of
corn fully ripe</hi>,” has, we trust, been gathered into the
heavenly garner. His age was 105.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <pb id="thompson19" n="19"/>
          <head>JONATHAN SKINNER</head>
          <p>WAS another disciple of Christ to whom it has been the
privilege of this Institution to “<hi rend="italics">give 
a cup of cold water</hi>.”
He also was a Methodist minister. His age 87. He was
amongst the earliest of the beneficiaries of the Home. It is
to be regretted that something of his early history was
not obtained; but enough of his pious labors were
witnessed to rank him among the most useful servants of
God.</p>
          <p>As long as his strength would permit, he went from
one sick bed to another, praying for, and encouraging
the penitent to hope and trust in <hi rend="italics">Him</hi> who sent His
Gospel to the poor.</p>
          <p>To none could the language of the poet be more
justly applied—
<q type="poem" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“Prayer is the Christian's vital breath,</l><l>The Christian's native air;</l><l>His watchword at the gate of death,</l><l>He enters heaven with prayer.”</l></lg></q></p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <pb id="thompson20" n="20"/>
          <head>TOMMY WARNER</head>
          <p>WAS a native of Western Africa, and when he had
nearly reached the period of manhood, was taken from
his native land, and brought to the West Indies as a
slave; from thence he was transported to the South,
where he remained for many years. He <sic corr="afterwards">af-afterwards</sic> came
to the city of New-York, and previous to his entering the
Colored Home (1844) was for sixteen years an inmate of
the City Alms-House. He died in January, 1847, aged
about <hi rend="italics">one hundred years</hi>.</p>
          <p>He was a most exemplary person in his general
character, exceedingly amiable in disposition, of retiring
habits, having but little intercourse with those about him.
The only person to whom he appears to have formed any
particular attachment, was “Old Henry,” who two years
was his room-mate. Henry died about six months before
Tommy; after which Thomas said but little, nor took
much notice of passing events. When spoken to on the
subject of Henry's death, his general remark was, “I think
he gone home; I think the Lord help him up;” at the same
time making a motion with both his hands expressive of
his views. He wished to be buried near
<pb id="thompson21" n="21"/>
his friend Henry, and as a space had been left by his
side for this purpose, his desire was gratified.</p>
          <p>It was on the Sabbath that Thomas was buried. At 12
o'clock, the inmates, male and female, assembled in the
hall, filling that large space almost to overflowing, while a
deep seriousness pervaded the assembly. “<hi rend="italics">Jerusalem,
my happy home</hi>!” was selected by one of the inmates
as a hymn of which he was particularly fond: it was sung.
The funeral service was then read, followed by
appropriate remarks. Thomas needed no eulogy, for all
knew and loved him. Followed by five of the oldest
female inmates, and all the old men who could walk, he
was conveyed to his final resting-place, and laid by the
side of his friend Henry. The reflection is a pleasant one,
that all his wants on earth were supplied—all his wishes to
the utmost gratified.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <head>BLIND SOPHA.</head>
          <p>SHE was brought from Africa when about seventeen
years of age. After passing a long life of accumulated
sufferings, she was eventually sent to our alms-house,
where she lingered four years. Of the
<pb id="thompson22" n="22"/>
name of her master we are uninformed; but she often
spoke with much affection of him.</p>
          <p>A more emaciated frame was seldom seen; having
been previously accustomed to the best food, the change
of diet in advanced age was trying to her system, and
she wasted away without apparent disease. Yet she
never complained or asked for any thing. While at the
alms-house, on receiving her weekly allowance, her
broken thanks were mostly accompanied with tears.
<ref id="ref4" n="4" rend="sc" target="note4" targOrder="U">*</ref></p>
          <p>One of the committee giving her some refreshment
before her death, she placed her hand in hers. Sopha
raised it to her lips, kissed it many times, and said, “God
bless you, Missy. Sopha never eat more. Oh, God will
bless you, dear Missy.” Soon after, she calmly departed.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <head>AMY JORDAN</head>
          <p>WAS a slave by birth, born in the State of Virginia. She
twice worked for and paid the amount required for her
freedom—once to her mistress, who died before
<note id="note4" n="4" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref4"><p>*
 Previous to establishing “the Home,” the managers
procured accommodations for their pensioners at the Alms-House, 
where they were visited and attended to by them.</p></note>
<pb id="thompson23" n="23"/>
making out her free papers, and then again she
worked and paid the same amount to the children; or, as
she termed it, “once to her <hi rend="italics">old mistress</hi>, 
and once to her
<hi rend="italics">young master</hi>.” She had one child, a son, 
who in his early
life was taken from her and sold into bondage, and
carried into a distant part of the country, since which time
she had never heard of him. After overcoming a
succession of obstacles, she at length found herself in a
free city, where she lived, supporting herself by honest
industry, until her health and strength failed; she then
sought admission into the Alms-House. After the
purchase of the building occupied as the “Colored
Home,” she was one of the first inmates, where she
continued in infirm health until she entered into her final
rest.</p>
          <p>Amy was baptized by immersion at Norfolk, Va.,
twenty-two years before her death. She was an
exemplary Christian. Her views of the Gospel plan were
clear and Scriptural. Her sickness was long and
protracted; she suffered much in consequence, yet she
was never heard to complain, or manifest impatience,
though her views of the “better land” were of such a
happy cast, that she often longed to be gone, looking to
her Heavenly Home with increased delight as her end
drew near.</p>
          <p>During her lingering days, she frequently spoke
<pb id="thompson24" n="24"/>
of her son, and it awakened feelings of deep sympathy to
hear her relate the circumstances of this painful
separation, for he was her “<hi rend="italics">only child</hi>;” 
and she often
spoke of him with maternal tenderness; ever manifesting
under all her trials a spirit of forgiveness to those who
had deprived her of this joy of her life, and exhibiting a
temper and disposition that would adorn human nature in
any situation. She never spoke with bitter or revengeful
feelings; but displayed, as far as she was able, the spirit
of her Divine Master, by her gentleness, humility, and
forgiveness.</p>
          <p>As death approached, and she appeared to be fast
sinking, her kind physician, Dr. F., urged her to take
some medicine. She said, “Oh no, doctor, let me be
gone, I long to be at <hi rend="italics">Home</hi>,—I 
will do as you say, but I
want to be away, my blessed Master waits for me; oh
<hi rend="italics">precious, glorious</hi> Master!” 
And such were her longings
and talk, until death closed the scene. Her faith seemed
remarkably bright, and her confidence in her Lord's
promises unwavering, sure, and steadfast. “How
unlike,” says Dr. F., “the dying words of the skeptical,
yet intellectual and accomplished Charles Lamb, ‘I am
unwilling to leave this beautiful spot called earth, I am
unwilling to part from its green fields, its refreshing
shades, and verdant lawns, for that unknown land that
men 
<pb id="thompson25" n="25"/>
call heaven,’ ”&amp;c. What a contrast with the faith of this
humble child of Africa!—Her last words were: 
“<hi rend="italics">Christ is
near me; I want nothing more</hi>.” Her age was 76.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <head>JUDY RICHARDS</head>
          <p>WAS another of the most worthy pensioners of the
Colored Home. She was an inmate of but one year, when
she was called to take possession of her promised
inheritance. During the short period she was an inmate,
she rendered herself an object of peculiar interest to all
from the strength of her gratitude and affection toward
those from whom she received favors, as well as from the
high attainments which she had made in Christian
knowledge and experience. She was an enlightened
Christian, and her whole walk was consistent with her
high and holy calling. Her time was mostly spent in
reading the Scriptures, or in religious conversation with
the sick and dying. Humility was a prominent feature in
her Christian character; and many who sought interviews
with her, felt that it was to their own edification in
spiritual things, rather than that of “imparting any
spiritual gift;” and those of
<pb id="thompson26" n="26"/>
the managers who were in the habit of visiting her for
this purpose, will not soon forget the affectionate
cordiality with which she welcomed them, and the fervor
with which she implored the Divine blessing to rest
upon them. The writer of the Sixth Annual Report says,
“It was always refreshing to enter into religious
conversation with her; and gladly would we have sat at
her feet to hear her discourse in simple eloquence of the
preciousness of <hi rend="italics">her</hi> Jesus, as 
it always pleased her to
call Him.” Toward the latter period of her life her mind
became somewhat harassed with doubts in reference to
her personal acceptance with Christ; and she seemed for
a time to be enveloped in thick darkness. On one
occasion she said to a young friend, “Can't you say
something to comfort me? Something about Christ?”
The reply was, “Aunt Judy, I feel as if I ought to come to
you for instruction.” She said, “Oh, but my Jesus is not
nigh me! He is a great way from me, and I want you to
help me find Him.”</p>
          <p>Her soul was burdened for several weeks, during
which time she observed many seasons of fasting and
special prayer. She repeatedly gave directions to those
who prepared her food, to make no provision for her
breakfast; nor was the cause of her abstinence known
until some time afterwards. Thus evincing that her
fasting was not that of “the
<pb id="thompson27" n="27"/>
Pharisee, who appears unto men to fast.” Finding no relief
from this occasional abstinence, she at length devoted
three days to special humbling of her soul before God,
during which time she took scarcely food enough to
sustain her animal frame. At last the powers of nature
yielded under this excessive mortification, and the
physician was called in to see her. He rebuked her
imprudence, reminding her that at her advanced age she
could not endure so long abstinence. Her reply showed
the power with which the adversary had plied his
temptations, as well as her own determined resolution to
resist to the last. “This kind,” she said, “goeth not out,
but by prayer and fasting.”</p>
          <p>She at length found the peace she had been seeking;
and enjoyed to the last hour of her life a holy serenity of
soul and an unfaltering reliance on her Saviour. But her
aged frame had received a shock from which it could not
recover, and she continued gradually to decline till the
second of September, 1845, when death came as an angel
of mercy to deliver her from her infirmities. During the last
week of her life there was a constant looking forward to
her joyful reward. Often in the night her companions were
awakened from their sleep by her exclamations, such as,
“Only at the feet of Jesus I wish to lie! I feel to lay
very close
<pb id="thompson28" n="28"/>
at his feet!”—and by her singing hymns descriptive of the
happiness of the heavenly state. Her last words were,
“Praise the Lord! I am on my journey 
<hi rend="italics">home</hi>!” Aunt Judy
was 90 years of age, and had been a professing Christian
60 years.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <head>ABIGAIL DOBSON</head>
          <p>WAS a native of the West Indies. Came to this country in
her early years, and to the city of New York, about the
year 1806. She had lived in the family of Captain Conger.
Her mother, she stated, was a servant in the family. Abby
was quite aged, but cannot exactly say how old, but she
“remembered <hi rend="italics">Mr. 
Washington's wars</hi>.” In 1812 she
became afflicted with an inflammation of her eyes, which
in the following year resulted in the total loss of her
sight; and from that time until the day of her death she
was never able to distinguish between the light of day
and midnight darkness. She entered the N. Y. Alms-House in 1813, 
from whence she was transferred to the
Colored Home in 1844; where she closed her life, after
much suffering, on the 3d of February, 1847, leaving the
clearest
<pb id="thompson29" n="29"/>
evidence that the change was to her one of joy and not of
sorrow. She had been for some time a consistent member
of the Amity Street Baptist Church, and was exemplary as
a Christian, mild and amiable in her intercourse with those
around her, patient under suffering, with a constant
looking forward to the “rest which remaineth for the
people of God.” She had no particular disease; nature
seemed gradually to give way, and she sunk to sleep as a
little child. The chaplain, in one of his reports, speaking
of an interview he had with her, says: “On inquiring the
state of her mind, she expressed herself as happy in the
midst of her afflictions. Sometimes distressing doubts
obscured her prospects. ‘But,’ said I, ‘you can trust in
the Lord Jesus Christ, can you not?’ ‘Yes,’ was her
answer; ‘I do; I can say with Job, “Though He slay me,
yet will I trust in Him.” The Saviour comforts me, and the
hope of being with Christ revives me, rejoices my soul.’ In
regard to the probable result of her sickness she said, ‘I
have no will of my own—my Master's will is mine. The
Lord is my shepherd, I shall not want.’ When prayer was
proposed, she said, ‘I greatly desire you should pray for
me; pray that I may be faithful to the end; pray that I may
have clearer evidence of my interest in Christ, and that He
would strengthen me to do and to suffer to the end.’ ”</p>
          <pb id="thompson30" n="30"/>
          <p>To this the physician adds—“She was unconscious
for some hours before she breathed her last.
Her last words to me were, ‘I thank my Master, I feel no
pain.’ ”</p>
          <p>All who approached her she welcomed with a
cheerful smile. Devout and constant in prayer, she bore
in remembrance before her Father's throne all she held
dear on earth. During the sickness of any of the
Managers, it seemed to be her comfort continually to
commend them to her covenant-keeping God.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <head>EDWARD.</head>
          <p>THE Chaplain remarks of this young lad: “My attention
was drawn to one sitting in the corner of the room,
reading the Memoir of J. B. Taylor. Near him lay a Bible
and a hymn-book, which gave rise to the following
conversation: ‘Well, Edward, what do you think of the
Bible?’ ‘The Bible? It is my main guide.’ ‘And what do
you think of its author, Jesus Christ?’ ‘He is a precious
<hi rend="italics">Saviour</hi>! I feel him to be so.’ ‘But 
he afflicts you, does he
not?’ ‘Yes; but no matter for
<pb id="thompson31" n="31"/>
that; these light afflictions, which are but for a moment,
are working for me an exceeding and eternal weight of
glory.’ ‘And how, Edward, do you expect to get to
heaven? and what will you do when you get there?’ ‘I
shall get to heaven through Jesus Christ; and I shall
there give God all the glory, and continually praise Him.’ 
”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <head>PHILLIS DOUGLAS</head>
          <p>HAD been a slave in the State of New Jersey, and at the
early age of twelve years chose God as the guide of her
youth, who she said had not forsaken her in her old age.
She was very aged when she came to the Home; was a
paralytic and deprived of the use of her hands. Yet she
manifested a great desire to be useful. In the days of her
youth, and when in bondage, she used to pray that she
might be free and become a missionary. The first part of
her prayer was answered some years ago; and her
second request was answered when she became a
beneficiary of the Colored Home. Being able to read, and
fully appreciating the privilege, she determined to impart
her knowledge to the young who
<pb id="thompson32" n="32"/>
were inmates, and to others of her aged companions who
were disposed to learn. She took great pleasure in this
employment, teaching them their catechism, and learning
them to sing hymns. Wonderful was her success, and
rich her reward in this labor of love. One of the aged
women, who had passed her threescore years without
learning a letter, became her pupil, and in the course of a
month, with a stammering but exulting tongue, she read
the pages of God's Word. And there is much reason to
believe, also, that the prayers and counsels of Phillis,
accompanied by the power of Divine truth, have resulted
in salvation to this precious soul. It may truly be said of
her, “She has done what she could.”</p>
          <p>A few hours before the death of Old Phillis, she
remarked: “I cannot tell how much I have suffered from
head to foot, but it is nothing compared with the love of
God in my soul. I would willingly suffer it all over again,
to enjoy the peace of God which comforts me.” She
rejoiced in the prospect of the rest in heaven.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <pb id="thompson33" n="33"/>
          <head>BETSEY JOHNSON.</head>
          <p>THIS remarkable woman attained the patriarchal age of
one hundred and fourteen years, and although her eye
became dim and her physical force abated, yet the eye of
her soul gazed with increasing clearness upon the
realities of the eternal world, and her spiritual energies
waxed stronger and stronger, as the number of her days
diminished.</p>
          <p>Although she was unable to read, yet so retentive
was her memory, that she could repeat extensively from
the Scriptures and from Dr. Watts's Hymns. She appears
to have lived until she was about ninety-four years old,
before she was brought to a knowledge of the truth as it
is in Jesus, when she illustrated the sincerity of her
profession by a consistent walk and conversation. In the
midst of all her infirmities and sufferings, she exhibited to
all around her indubitable marks of a Christian temper;
and when the messenger of death approached (who had
long lost his terrors to her), she called for the inmates of
the Home, and with her dying breath solemnly charged
them to meet her in Heaven; then in the triumph of faith
she breathed out her soul in the arms of her Redeemer.</p>
          <pb id="thompson34" n="34"/>
          <p>Betsey was a pure native of Africa, and in her earliest
life was brought to one of the West India islands. From
thence she was taken to Virginia, about the period she
used to call the “<hi rend="italics">Old War</hi>,” 
before the Revolution.
During the War of our Independence she remained in the
Southern States, frequently changing owners. She often
spoke of one of her young mistresses, whom she
tenderly loved; and probably from her she learned the
first lessons of religious truth. She remembered well most
of the incidents of the Revolution, and the names of many
of the most prominent characters of those days were
familiar to her. During that period she married (being
probably about thirty-five), and had several children.</p>
          <p>Her piety was of a most interesting character. She
seemed to feel, that all the various trying circumstances
through which she had been called to pass, were
intended for her eternal good. Her mind, at times,
appeared to rise above this earth, and her spiritual
contemplations were of a most delightful character. She
had been for a number of years a member of the Spring-street 
Presbyterian Church, under the pastoral charge of
the Rev. Dr. Patten, and was highly esteemed for her
consistency by the members of that congregation.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <pb id="thompson35" n="35"/>
          <head>PHEBE SPALDING.</head>
          <p>SHE was an aged pilgrim. She died suddenly of cholera,
after three hours' illness. But although
suddenly came the messenger, he found her not
unprepared, nor unsupported in that period of bodily
agony. She called her companions around her bed to tell
them of her happiness, said her “Saviour was
near, and the angels around to carry her home.” After a
paroxysm of pain, she said: “Precious Saviour, stand by
me!” and thus passed quietly away.</p>
          <p>The evening before her death, she came into the
room, clapping her hands, and joyfully exclaiming,
“Glory! Glory!” “What is the matter?” inquired
the physician, surprised at so much noise in a time of
such dismay; (for they were falling around on every side,
the worst days of the cholera.) “Why,” she replied,
“Thomas L—has expressed a hope: I think he will only live
a few hours.” Thomas, however, recovered and lived;
but before morning, Phebe had entered the eternal world.</p>
          <p>She was anxious in life to be useful, and occupied her
time in teaching her old companions to read the
Scriptures; and her patience and zeal in this
<pb id="thompson36" n="36"/>
duty were most interesting. She never expressed herself
weary, but only laid aside her book when her pupils
became fatigued.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <head>OLD SARAH HENRY</head>
          <p>WAS born in New Rochelle, <sic corr="Westchester">Wescthester</sic> County; had
lived in the family of Mr. William Post; said she “<hi rend="italics">was
married on the day that the Asia fired on the city</hi>.” She
was in the Home several years, and died at the age of 90
years. She always received the visits of the managers
with a smile of welcome: “I am always so glad to see my
people” (as she termed the ladies of the Institution). On
one occasion of these visits, she said: “Here I am yet,
bless the Lord! waiting patiently for my precious Saviour
to call me home; He knows the best time, I feel no will of
my own; I feel satisfied to lay here upon my sick bed;
and try, when I am in pain, to think, Oh how glorious will
be that home, where there is no more pain—no suffering—
no <hi rend="italics">sin</hi>; I long for it; but I am willing to wait till my Saviour
sees fit to call me. Here there is no rest—no peace; all in
this world is like a cobweb, the least wind breaks
<pb id="thompson37" n="37"/>
it, and if any thing strikes against it, it goes to pieces; so
is the peace of this world broken: but where my Saviour
is, <hi rend="italics">there</hi> is rest and peace.” Thus was this aged saint
always gentle, submissive, and apparently contented
and happy. She has gone to her heavenly rest.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <head>ELIZA DIDYMUS</head>
          <p>WAS, for two years previous to her decease, an inmate of
the Female Hospital of the Institution, with consumption.
Her case was in many respects peculiar, sometimes
greatly improving, so that she was able to walk about,
and then relapsing into a delirium, from excessive debility.
She would thus remain for several days; but her
wanderings of mind were all of a pleasant character; she
was straying amidst delightful gardens, or where the
sounds of sweet music could be heard; or she was
among early friends, and pleasing associations. Ever
thankful for favors, she remembered them with the
warmest gratitude.</p>
          <p>During the few last months of her life she was much
exercised on religious subjects, and, for some
<pb id="thompson38" n="38"/>
weeks before her death, seemed happy; at times joyfully
longing to be gone. To the managers she was strongly
attached, and each week longed for the visiting day, that
she might once more see them, and thank them for all
their kindness. Of one of them, in particular, who
frequently visited her, read and conversed with her, she
was very fond. “My dear Mrs. N.,” she would say, “I
<hi rend="italics">must</hi> see her once more, she has been 
so kind to me.” One
morning she thought herself drawing near her end, but
expressed a wish to live to see the physician; at 11 o'clock
he arrived, and shortly after seeing her, finding her very
low, he told her that she was apparently about to depart.
“And is it so?” she exclaimed; “Is the time at length
arrived?” Joy beamed in her countenance; and she
reached out her hand in farewell to all.</p>
          <p>At her request Mr. B. engaged in religious exercise,
and such was the solemnity of the scene that all were
affected to tears. “Let me meet you all again,” she said;
“<hi rend="italics">Farewell, farewell, all</hi>!” 
And so departed.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <pb id="thompson39" n="39"/>
          <head>“POOR JOHNNY,”</head>
          <p>AS he was familiarly called, was a little colored boy,
who came to the Home in 1846. He was about 13
years of age, and had been from his earliest life a
victim of scrofulous disease. About this period it
had settled in his right hip-joint, which rendered it
difficult for him to walk even with the help of
crutches. He was a great favorite of the entire
household, and a pet with all his physicians; and
as long as he could walk, was in the habit of coming
to the doctor's table to receive whatever had been set
aside for his dinner. He was of a meek and gentle
spirit, and grateful for every mark of attention
shown him, so that it was a pleasure to do him
kindness. The last year of his life he was almost
entirely confined to his bed, and for months his
body was racked with pain too distressing for words
to describe; even the changing of his clothing was
torture to his emaciated limbs, which were covered
with sores; but he was a pattern of patience. That
dark skin covered one of the most amiable and
engaging spirits ever witnessed. Not a murmur escaped
him; quiet, and bearing his afflictions with a submission
that astonished the beholder; though young,
<pb id="thompson40" n="40"/>
he seemed at this early age to have deep religious
impressions, and to be sustained by grace, and to look
forward with joyful prospect to death, as a gain to the
child of God. His love and affection for all around him
was extremely affecting; sharing with them the little
dainties that were occasionally brought to him by friends.
At length, worn out by his sufferings—in the morning of
his life—one day, at early dawn, he calmly fell asleep
without a sigh or a groan. His end was peace. His death,
we think, was gain.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <head>CATHARINE QUEEN.</head>
          <p>WE are unable to give her early history. But she had
been some years at the Home. Her age was 97. For a long
time she was very infirm and helpless. She died in May,
1850. Some of the managers spent much time by the side
of her bed, reading the Scriptures and conversing with
her. This she greatly enjoyed, and always received it with
great thankfulness. Catharine was of a thoughtful and
contemplative turn, and always in so happy a state of
mind, as made it a pleasure to visit her
<pb id="thompson41" n="41"/>
room. Her remarks were of a character indicative of deep
humility and entire submission to the will of her
Heavenly Father; observing, that He knew what was for
her good; and “although at times,” said she, “I suffer
greatly from pain, yet never more than for my good.”
Occasionally she seemed impatient to be gone, yet again
would check herself, and say—“It was not right; it is my
duty to wait the will of God.”</p>
          <p>“Aunt Queen,” and “Aunt Katy Schenck,” as they
were familiarly termed, were room-mates, their beds were
contiguous, and they appeared to have a kind regard for
each other. Intimate friends in the latter days of their
pilgrimage, by death they were not long divided; their
society was pleasant, cheerful, instructive, and shed a
lustre on the holy religion they so humbly professed.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <head>KATY SCHENCK.</head>
          <p>“I WOULD like to tell you many things,” said she one
day to one of the reading committee (Mrs. T.), “but I will
do it some other time.” She was requested to relate what
she had to say, <hi rend="italics">now</hi>. “Well,
<pb id="thompson42" n="42"/>
I will give you a little of my history. I was born in
Monmouth, New Jersey, in the family of Gerrit
Vandeveer, where I lived until I was thirty years old. He
was a kind and good master, gave me plenty to eat, and
treated me well; our house was within three miles where
<hi rend="italics">the great battle was fought</hi>, and I might have seen it if I
had been a mind to. I was very wicked in my early life, but
I was industrious and worked hard.”</p>
          <p>“When I was about twelve years old, I had strong
convictions of sin, but resisted them, and strove to get rid
of them by carelessness, and endeavored to drive religion
from my thoughts; but I could not, although I gave
myself to loose and wicked company. After a while my
convictions left me, and I continued on in my wicked
ways until I was seventeen; then the Lord took hold of
me again, but I was determined to resist, and I fought
against Him with all my might; and how long do you think
I fought against the Lord;” said she, looking earnestly in
my face, “<hi rend="italics">why, till I was twenty-eight 
years old</hi>;” and
even then the devil seemed determined that I should
serve <hi rend="italics">him</hi>, and not the <hi rend="italics">Lord</hi>. 
But I worked on in my
duties, and tried to serve God with all my might. Oh how
my mind did strive, I cannot tell you, but it is fresh in my
memory.”</p>
          <pb id="thompson43" n="43"/>
          <p>“One day, when my mind was thus dreadfully
distressed, I was going a milking, but I felt so
wretched, I did not know what to do; it seemed that hell
was ready to receive me—it was evening—I fell upon my
knees—I prayed, <hi rend="italics">Lord, have mercy
upon me and help me</hi>! All at once, I looked up, and I
thought I saw heaven open, and it appeared to me the
Lord was stooping down and lifted me up; and these
words came to me: ‘<hi rend="italics">Thy people shall be willing in the
day of Thy power</hi>.’ I stood still—I felt such a change!
I hardly knew what I was doing—I could not milk,
I could do nothing but rejoice—I shouted aloud, and
ran home, telling all my folks how happy I was. They
did not know what to think; they asked me if I was crazy.
I went to bed, but I could not sleep for my happiness.
I felt now that the Lord had fast hold of me, and I was
safe. I was now willing and desirous
to serve God, and I went on my way rejoicing.”</p>
          <p>“Thus in this graphic language did this old
Christian woman describe the struggles connected
with her conversion. And I could have lingered to have
heard more of her subsequent history, but
my duties directed me onward.</p>
          <p>“Not long after the above, I again,” continues
Mrs. T., “visited this old servant; she was sick and in
bed. I found her very feeble, and remarked,
<pb id="thompson44" n="44"/>
I had come to read to her, if she was able, and would like
to hear me. She replied, she ‘would be very glad to hear
me.’</p>
          <p>“I read one of Burder's sermons to the aged, entitled,
‘<hi rend="italics">Peace in Death</hi>.’ During my reading, she frequently
interrupted me with remarks both forcible and strong.
After I had concluded reading, I said, ‘You are very sick,
and very old. We are all liable to sickness, and it is
appointed that we all must die! The <hi rend="italics">young</hi> sometimes
depart in early life; but aged persons cannot expect to live
much longer, but it matters not, so long as they die
peaceful and happy; and now I have been reading to you
about a <hi rend="italics">good old man</hi>, of whom you have doubtless
often read in the Bible, good old Simeon. You remember
his history, do you not?’ She quickly replied, ‘What? old
Simeon and Anna? Yes, indeed!’ and raising herself upon
her bed, she commenced such a strain of eloquence as
completely astonished me. I was silent, and waited to
listen to her; I had gone to be her instructor and consoler;
but she was my teacher, and I felt I could linger at her
side, for it was good to be there. She had raised herself
upon her bed—‘Simeon,’ said she, ‘was a good man, he
was waiting for the salvation of God, and when he took
the blessed Jesus in his arms, he was convinced that it
was <hi rend="italics">the Saviour</hi>
<pb id="thompson45" n="45"/>
he held there, and he said, “<hi rend="italics">Now lettest thou thy servant
depart in peace, for mine eyes have seen thy salvation</hi>.”
Now I feel just as Simeon did; I am ready to depart when
God shall see fit. I am a poor, helpless sinner, I can do
nothing—indeed there is nothing for me to do, for my
Saviour has done all; and I am just waiting for Him to call
me home. I lay here upon my bed, and I <hi rend="italics">think</hi>, 
and <hi rend="italics">think</hi>;
I don't say <hi rend="italics">nothing</hi>, but I feel as 
<hi rend="italics">Mary</hi> did—I don't tell all I
feel, but I keep it in my heart; I am an ignorant woman,
and cannot express myself very well; but I trust I have
been taught in the school of Christ, and have learned of
Him. I used to go to Sunday school; I learned much there,
and I bless God I ever went.’</p>
          <p>“I was fearful she would fatigue herself, and
reminded her of her weakness; she replied, ‘I would like
to tell you many things,’ and proceeded: ‘Well, I would
say that the Lord has taught me many things, and I have
tried to teach others; I may say (and I would speak it
without pride), <hi rend="italics">I have preached the Gospel</hi>, that is, I
have tried to speak for God, when I had a good chance. I
must tell you a little story: I was at one time travelling in a
vessel on the Ohio river; I had said something to
someone about religion; the captain of the boat and his
wife began to ridicule and abuse me; there were
<pb id="thompson46" n="46"/>
also several young men on board who were going to
some college, and they likewise joined with the captain
and his wife, and tried to make sport of me, taunting me
for my complexion, making many foolish speeches, such
as they thought would hurt my feelings. I said nothing
for a while, but waited until they had ceased; then I
turned to them and said, ‘Gentlemen, have you got
through with your speeches?’ They replied, ‘Yes.’ ‘Well,’
I said, ‘now it is my turn.’ ‘Go on,’ 
said they. ‘Well, you are
on your way to College, aint you?’ ‘Yes.’ ‘Well, you need
schooling, but you'll never complete your education till
you get it in the school of Christ; and, if you don't get it
there, and die in your sins, you will <hi rend="italics">perish for ever</hi>! You
have tried to make sport of me, and you think you are
fine gentlemen, but I tell you, you aint hurt my feelings; I
feel sorry for you, <hi rend="italics">because</hi> I think you don't know any
thing you ought to know, and are not “wise unto
salvation.” ‘I talked on,’ said she, ‘and when I was done, a
young Englishman turned to me and said, ‘Mother,
where did you get your learning, and who told you all
these things? did you get it from the priest?’ I said ‘No! I
learned it in the school of Christ, and from His blessed
word the <hi rend="italics">Bible</hi>; and I tell you, if you don't go to that
school, but die in your sins and <hi rend="italics">ignorance</hi>,
<pb id="thompson47" n="47"/>
you will never get to heaven. Whether what I said did
them any good, or made an impression on them, I don't
know, but they teased me no more, and on the rest of the
way were very civil and polite; I thought they seemed to
have felt what I said, and I prayed God they might.’ ”</p>
          <p>This old disciple was a lively Bible Christian, and
generally speaking, was of a good and cheerful temper. In
conversing of the new Home then being built, to one of
the Managers, she remarked, “it will be very nice, but it
must not make us forget the home in the heavens, the
building not made with hands, built upon a sure
foundation; for this new Home we are to have built for us
here, must finally crumble and fall to the ground; but that
in the heavens will last as long as God himself.” So rich
was her experience,—so interesting her conversation;
something so attractive about her, so cheerful, and she
had so many pleasant things to say, all savoring of
Christian piety, of God's goodness and mercy to sinners,
His condescension and kindness, especially towards
herself; that it was pleasant to linger by her side.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <pb id="thompson48" n="48"/>
          <head>MARGARET SIMPSON</head>
          <p>WAS born in North Hampton, eastern shore of
Maryland; came to New-York in her childhood, and lived
in the family of the widow Townsend many years; says
she has worked hard all her life, and has fairly worn out
in service. She came to the Home in 1844. And although
very feeble, tried to do what she could to make herself
useful, by assisting in some of the household affairs, She
was “thankful that she had so good a home in her last
days.”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <head>DIANA.</head>
          <head>FROM MRS. T.'S REPORT.</head>
          <p>IN one of the wards of the Hospital, where I had gone to
read and converse with the sick, lay Diana, (a young
woman,) very low—scarcely able to give utterance to her
words. Her mind was dark and ignorant, she “knew her
heart was unchanged” (I use her own words), “but
believed that Christ was able to save her, an hoped he
would.” I
<pb id="thompson49" n="49"/>
read to her the 51st Psalm, and a suitable tract. She
listened attentively, and I saw the tears fill her eyes. On
my leaving her, she thanked me for the interest I felt for
her. Alas! what Christian can visit such scenes—witness
the darkness of ignorance, and hear the simple, earnest
expressions of hope, coming from untaught lips, and not
feel a deep interest in the objects which excite it; and
strive faithfully to discharge a Christian's duty to the
helpless and ignorant around him?</p>
          <p>In the same room was Catharine——, also a young
woman of pleasing countenance. She greeted me with a
smile. On my addressing some words to her, she replied,
“I am very weak and feeble; I do not expect to get well—
indeed, I have no wish to stay in this world; I am still
young, but I have seen enough to know that it is a world
of sin and trial; and if it should please my Heavenly
Father to take me away from it, why I am willing to go; yet
I would be patient and wait His time. I thank Him that I
was ever brought to this place, it is a good Home, and I
have a great many mercies and comforts; I can read, and I
take great satisfaction in reading the Bible and other good
books; I bless God I ever came here.”</p>
          <p>“I have always derived,” remarks Mrs. T., in her
Report, “great satisfaction from visiting this young
<pb id="thompson50" n="50"/>
person; she is so mild, humble, pleasant and cheerful
amid her pains, and unmurmuring under her afflictions.”
She rests now from all these; and we trust, “sleeps in
Jesus.”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <head>FROM THE MINUTES OF THE CHAPLAIN.</head>
          <p>THE Chaplain remarks—“Among those of the beneficiaries
was Phebe Green; she has recently been called to her
heavenly home. Her exemplary deportment for a long time
gave satisfactory evidence that her name had been
written in the book of life.</p>
          <p>“In her last moments she was not alone, for the
Saviour on whom she relied was with her, and the arms of
everlasting love carried her safely through the trying
conflict. She died with the name of Jesus on her lips,
exclaiming, ‘<hi rend="italics">Come, Lord Jesus, 
come quickly</hi>.’ The 27th
Psalm, which was read to her, seemed to afford her sweet
and refreshing views of the Redeemer, in whom she
reposed her confidence, and through whose merits alone
she hoped for salvation.”</p>
          <p>“As I approached the couch of a dying youth,
calling me by name, he earnestly requested that prayer
might be offered in his behalf, remarking
<pb id="thompson51" n="51"/>
that his ‘time was short.’ Prayer was offered, and his
immortal spirit commended to Him who hears the feeblest
breathings of the penitent; and who can save even at the
eleventh hour those who confide in the merits of the Lord
Jesus. He died in about two hours after.”</p>
          <p>“Another individual, Carter,—who was far advanced in
life, and while in health was a constant attendant on the
public service of God; her seat was seldom vacant, and
her whole soul seemed absorbed in the truths which were
uttered. Previous to her last illness, she would
occasionally repair to the room of a pious female for the
purpose of religious conversation, and to listen to the
reading of the sacred Scriptures. When assailed by the
disease which closed her earthly pilgrimage, her mind was
peaceful, and her heart filled with universal love. On the
day preceding her <sic corr="dissolution">disolution</sic>, 
she exclaimed with
emphasis, ‘<hi rend="italics">Oh, I want to go to Heaven</hi>!’ 
On being asked
why she wished for heaven? she replied, ‘Because God is
there.’ She was habitually prayerful, and her consistent
Christian deportment has furnished ample testimony to
those who knew her best, that she was truly a ransomed
soul, and, we trust, has reached that world of purity,
where sin and suffering are unknown.”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <pb id="thompson52" n="52"/>
          <head>SERENA JOHNSON</head>
          <p>HAD long been confined to her room by infirmity and
disease. On inquiring of her what was the present state of
her mind, she replied, “<hi rend="italics">I am still at the feet of Jesus,
every day begging for mercy; I
think I shall be ready, through Jesus Christ, when death
comes; I lean on Him, I depend on Him, I can do nothing
without Him. I hope He will keep me in the hollow of His
hand, and close by His bleeding side. The prayers of
God's people lift me up—make my heart warm</hi>.” “She
loves the society and conversation of Christians, and
feels neglected, if in her solitude a few moments are not
spent with her in prayer. Such was the simple testimony
which this poor and ignorant colored woman gave of the
power of religion on her own heart.”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <head>DIANA RAYNER.</head>
          <p>“I WELL remember her as my guide in months past to
the various apartments of the sick, infirm, and
<pb id="thompson53" n="53"/>
anxious. She always evinced that sympathy and love for
others which characterized Christian benevolence. We
trust she sleeps in Jesus—and will hereafter awake in His
likeness.”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <head>SARAH ROBINSON.</head>
          <p>As she gradually declined in health, no cloud seemed
to obstruct her spiritual vision. She patiently and
submissively waited for her release from sin
and suffering, and appeared to have a foretaste of
heaven in her soul.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <head>BLIND DIANA.</head>
          <p>“ON approaching the bed of Blind Diana, she
immediately recognized my voice, greeted me cordially,
and spoke of the inward peace she experienced,
and the implicit confidence she felt in the. Saviour;
‘His will,’ said she, ‘is my will, and I am still waiting for
Him.’ This poor blind one seems to take hold on Christ by
intelligent faith and hope,
<pb id="thompson54" n="54"/>
and the consciousness that He is her friend, seems to
mitigate her sufferings, and enable her joyfully to
anticipate the change which is approaching. Such
examples of patient, Christian submission, are cheering to
the pious heart, and eminently worthy of imitation.</p>
          <p>“Few of the pensioners interest me more than Blind
Diana; never have I seen any thing like impatience or
dissatisfaction with the dispensations of Divine
Providence towards her; on the contrary, sweet
submission to the Divine will marks her whole
deportment. ‘Do not the days seem long,’ said I, ‘as you
can neither read nor work?’ ‘Oh no!’ was her prompt
reply, ‘for though blind, I can <hi rend="italics">think</hi> 
of my precious
Saviour, and converse with Him. I have in Him something
to lean upon, and no one knows how much comfort I
have in my Saviour. It is all well, whatever He is pleased
to lay upon me—<hi rend="italics">I shall be at home by and by</hi>!’
Such is the uniform state of her mind; calm, peaceful,
‘looking unto Jesus, the author and finisher of her faith.’
She now, we trust, beholds with unsealed eyes, and
unobstructed vision, the refulgent glory of heaven.”</p>
          <p>“In the Female Department I was addressed by one
who lay sick and low. She greeted me cordially. I had
scarcely commenced conversation,
<pb id="thompson55" n="55"/>
when the tears started in her eyes, and she exclaimed:
‘I feel that I am a poor sinner, but God is kind
and good to me in my afflictions, and I can trust in
Him.’</p>
          <p>“Every successive month affords encouragement
to believe that the Divine Spirit is graciously operating
on some of the objects of this Christian charity.
Our religious services are marked by seriousness
and devout attention, and by many we are cordially
greeted as messengers of good tidings to the poor
and the perishing.</p>
          <p>“I have repeatedly conversed and prayed with
those who are confined by sickness and infirmity to
their rooms, and listened with much pleasure, as they
testified from their own experience to the faithfulness and
love of their Redeemer, and witnessed their sweet
submission to the Divine will.</p>
          <p>“A beautiful and affecting illustration of the power
and influence of Evangelical faith was recently
presented, in the case of one far advanced in life,
and an invalid. It appears, that at a very early
age religious impressions were made on her mind
by a relative of her mistress, who sang the <hi rend="italics">Ten
Commandments</hi> in verse, and who told her that
‘He who gave us those Commandments would be
her <hi rend="italics">friend</hi>, if she would trust in Him.’ This simple
truth was received into a good and honest heart;
<pb id="thompson56" n="56"/>
<hi rend="italics">she believed</hi>, and it was counted to her for
righteousness. ‘I have always, since that time,’ said she,
‘trusted in Him, and I will <hi rend="italics">still</hi> trust.’ 
She requested prayer,
‘that God would do with her just as He pleased;’ she was
‘willing to suffer all He could lay upon her.’ Her simple
and unaffected manner, accompanied with tears of
gratitude for what God had done for her, was most
affecting, and well calculated to magnify the grace of
God, as exhibited in one more than fourscore years of
age, and near her Heavenly Home.</p>
          <p>“Another aged woman always greets me cordially
and with childlike simplicity; speaks feelingly of her
dependence on God, and of the preciousness of the
Saviour to her soul, and is never willing to have me leave
her without offering prayer. She thinks much of Jesus
Christ, and appears to rest her hope of salvation
confidently on His merits alone.</p>
          <p>“Passing by another of these aged and afflicted
servants of God, who for successive months has been an
invalid and confined to her bed and room, she said:
‘<hi rend="italics">Jesus is near and precious</hi>! If the whole of New-York
were offered me for Christ, I would not accept it: His will
is my will; if He afflicts, <hi rend="italics">it is all right</hi>.’</p>
          <p>“One, sick and blind, on recognizing my voice,
extended her emaciated hand to welcome me.</p>
          <pb id="thompson57" n="57"/>
          <p>“Here was presented an impressive instance of
patient submission, which might have shamed many of
the professed followers of the Saviour. She is cheerfully
anticipating the change which must ere long take place.
Death to her seems divested of his terrors, as she reclines
sweetly on the arm of Infinite Benevolence. She is indeed
‘a living epistle, known and read of all;’ and her Christian
example commands the respect and admiration of even
the impenitent around her.</p>
          <p>“Another case has interested me much. She, too, is
one of God's afflicted people, but happy in the
consciousness that her peace is made with God. She
longs to be gone, but is submissive to the will of Heaven.
‘<hi rend="italics">Glorious prospects</hi>!’ she says, 
‘are opening to my view;
and why one so poor, ignorant, useless, and unworthy,
should be continued, is incomprehensible.’ I endeavored
to explain the mystery, that perhaps it was that she might
show to those around her the efficacy of the blessedness
of that religion which gives peace and consolation amidst
the sharpest trials. This seemed a new idea, and one that
afforded pleasant reflection; and she reiterated the
sentiment, ‘<hi rend="italics">All the days of my appointed time will I wait
till my change come</hi>.’</p>
          <p>“My attention was called by a colored man, who
conducted me to the sick-bed of one in the male
<pb id="thompson58" n="58"/>
department. He was very ill, though able to converse; and
seemed deeply concerned for his soul. It appeared, from
his own voluntary confession, that he had been
notorious for his impiety. Profane, rancorous in his
opposition to religion and the friends of religion, he had
carefully sought to shun their influence, and to close his
ear against the truth. It was apparent that the Holy Spirit
was striving with him, for he hesitated not to express his
penitence for sin, and requested me to pray for him.</p>
          <p>“On a subsequent visit, I found him more composed;
and light seemed breaking into his benighted mind.
Alluding to his former antipathy to Christians, he said he
now felt very different; he loved to have them near him,
and to hear their conversation and prayers. He felt he
could give himself to the Lord Jesus Christ, and believed
that, though a great sinner, God could forgive him for
Christ's sake. When asked what I should pray for, he
said, ‘That my associates may seek their salvation and
come to Jesus Christ.’ This unexpected and ingenuous
concern for others seemed to furnish some cheering
evidence that, ‘though he was once blind, he now saw.’
A short time before his death, he said to one who had
formerly in vain attempted to converse with him in
reference to his soul, ‘The time was when I hated you
and your religious conversation,
<pb id="thompson59" n="59"/>
but now I love you as a Christian.’ His end was full of
comfort and hope, and we feel encouraged to believe he
was indeed ‘<hi rend="italics">a brand plucked out of 
the fire</hi>.’ ”</p>
          <p>“After one of our religious services, an aged invalid
approached me with tears. On asking the cause of her
solicitude, she replied, that ‘though a professor of
religion, she had been neglectful of prayer, and other
Christian duties, and consequently had lost that sweet
sense of forgiveness she once enjoyed.’ I endeavored to
impress her mind with the sinfulness and ingratitude of
neglecting her soul; and urged her to look to Him who
invites the wanderer to return and obtain forgiveness.”</p>
          <p>“On one occasion I was much interested by the
conversation of two individuals, who had been
unavoidably prevented from attending service. One of
them remarked, with an expression of countenance and
an emphasis which indicated truth and honesty—‘Though
not always with you, I <hi rend="italics">can</hi> and do pray for you.’ In
another apartment, one remarked, that before he came to
the Home, ‘<hi rend="italics">he knew not that he had an 
immortal soul</hi>,
but supposed that at death he should be like the beasts
that perish, but since he had heard the Gospel, his views
had been entirely changed.’ He now
<pb id="thompson60" n="60"/>
converses intelligently in regard to the plan of salvation.”</p>
          <p>“A poor inmate severely afflicted with cancer has
recently deceased. Her coffined remains were conveyed
to the chapel on the Lord's Day, and from thence by her
relations to the place of interment. She continued to the
last hour of her life steadfast in the faith of the Gospel,
and has left to surviving friends the cheering hope, that
her end was peace. This event furnished an opportunity
to speak to the assembled inmates of the necessity and
importance of habitual preparation for death and
judgment, which we endeavored to improve.”</p>
          <p>“On inquiring of a sick man with whom I had been
conversing, if he desired prayer should be offered in his
behalf; with tears starting in his eyes he emphatically
exclaimed, ‘Oh yes! I want faith to throw myself right on
the Lord Jesus Christ.’ ”</p>
          <p>“Another, who was a poor victim of consumption,
expressed himself as being happy in the prospect of
death, and desired that prayer should be offered, ‘<hi rend="italics">that he
might get safe home</hi>.’ ”</p>
          <p>“In the male department is a man about 30 years old.
About one month since he was led to see himself as lost
and ruined by sin, and to look to Christ as his only
refuge. He seems like one newborn into the kingdom of
grace, and to have adopted
<pb id="thompson61" n="61"/>
the resolution of Joshua— ‘As for me, I will serve the
Lord.’ ”</p>
          <p>“A female, whose attention has recently been
arrested, voluntarily came to me, to tell me what God had
done for her soul. She also appears humble, penitent, and
much impressed with the love of Christ in dying for
sinners. Speaking of her interest in the spiritual welfare of
the unconverted, she remarked, ‘she now loved them
better than ever, and prayed that God would open their
eyes to see their lost condition.’ Her simple and
unaffected manner, and her deep feeling, carried
conviction to the mind that the blessed Spirit had indeed
begun a good work which He would carry onward to
maturity.</p>
          <p>“Two aged women have also expressed deep
concern for their spiritual welfare, and appear to feel that
they have too long neglected salvation, and that it is
high time to give the subject immediate attention.”</p>
          <p>“At the close of one of our religious services, I was
informed that an aged inmate, very ill, was desirous to
see me. She was 87 years of age, and for 70 of that
number had professed religion. As I approached her
bedside, extending her withered had, she exclaimed, ‘<hi rend="italics">Oh,
I am happy! I am ready to go to my heavenly home at
any time</hi>;
<pb id="thompson62" n="62"/>
<hi rend="italics">the Saviour is precious; I would not give up the hope I
have of an interest in Him for millions of worlds</hi>! I have
always found Him faithful to His word; but when I get
yonder’ (raising her eyes towards heaven), ‘that will be
best of all.’ This old person has always been one of the
most regular attendants upon religious worship, and her
exemplary deportment has uniformly evinced the sincerity
of her profession and her ripeness for heaven.”</p>
          <p>“A few days since, I was requested to visit one in the
hospital, on whom a surgical operation was about to be
performed. Seating myself by his bedside, I had scarcely
commenced conversing with him, when I discovered that
his mind was awake to the subject of religion, and that he
was anxious for instruction: his sins appeared before him
in fearful magnitude, and all hope of pardon seemed to
have fled. He imagined he had sinned beyond the
possibility of forgiveness. He, however, listened with
evident interest, as I endeavored to preach to him the
blessed Gospel of the Son of God, and unfold the fulness
and freeness of salvation through Christ Jesus. After
conversing and praying with him, I took my leave of him,
promising to see him again shortly.</p>
          <p>“On the following Thursday I repaired to his
bedside, and found him extremely feeble, in
<pb id="thompson63" n="63"/>
consequence of the operation to which he had submitted,
and that he could converse but little. On this occasion, I soon
perceived that a great change had taken place in his
experience—the clouds had dispersed, and he now
joyfully received the good news that Jesus Christ came
to seek and to save the lost; and that whoever believeth
on Him, should not perish, but have everlasting life. He
remarked, ‘that he thought he had given himself to the
Saviour, and that he could now rely on Him for salvation.
Yesterday,’ said he, ‘was a sweet day, for it was
impressed upon my mind, that if I would believe on
Christ, He would save my soul. He makes me happy, <hi rend="italics">He
is indeed precious to my soul</hi>. I wish I was able to talk,
but I am too weak.’ His view of the plan of salvation
appears Scriptural, and I cannot but hope he has made
his peace with God.”</p>
          <p>“The triumphs of Divine grace,” concludes the
Chaplain, in one of his Reports to the Managers, “which
we are permitted to witness among these poor ignorant
subjects of your charity, seem often to consecrate the
place, and call forth involuntarily the exclamation of the
poet—
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>‘The chamber where
 the good man meets his fate,</l><l>Is privileged beyond the common walks of life,</l><l>—quite on the verge of heaven.’</l></lg></q>
<pb id="thompson64" n="64"/>
And we are constrained to feel that the self-denying
effort in which this Society is engaged, is eminently
approved of God. And may we not hope that some bright
gems, that will adorn the Saviour's crown, will be
gathered from those who have been the humble
pensioners of your bounty? ‘Cast thy bread upon the
waters; for thou shalt find it after many days.’</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <head>MRS. R.'S STATEMENT.</head>
          <p>Mrs. R., of the Reading Committee, in speaking
of the readiness with which the inmates listened to
religious instruction, states:—</p>
          <p>“It is a delightful occupation, and not unworthy the
follower of Jesus, to sit in the society of such as when He
was on earth He delighted to meet and to bless—the poor,
the sick, the lame, and the blind; and to dispense, not
indeed like Him the words which gave the body healing;
but those of spiritual comfort and hope. It is truly
gratifying to find so many among those whom the world
overlooks as poor and ignorant, ‘rich in faith,’ and wise
unto salvation. They cannot, in some instances, read—nor
can they in words of burning eloquence explain
<pb id="thompson65" n="65"/>
how the love of God has operated to work in them a
return of that love—but they have the witness within.
‘<hi rend="italics">Jesus is precious, very precious</hi>.’ 
‘<hi rend="italics">The Lord has taken
sin from the soul</hi>,’ are expressions testifying their
experimental knowledge of the justifying and sanctifying
grace of God.</p>
          <p>“One on her death-bed said to me: ‘Jesus is with me
all the time—when I awake in the night, it seems as if His
arms were around me, and all the day He continues near
me.’ These expressions prove nothing in themselves,
except, as in the case of these persons, supported by the
tenor of the daily life—but they come with a power which
no human eloquence can give.”</p>
          <p>It is certainly very encouraging to the hearts of the
Reading Committee to receive so kind a welcome from
those poor creatures, who <hi rend="italics">know</hi> that we come to minister
to their spiritual rather than their bodily wants. Many
among them seem to be sensible of the importance of
being able to read the Scriptures, and are diligent
scholars at the feet of those of their number who were
more fortunate in early life, and obtained this
accomplishment. One woman, of perhaps 70 years, began
to learn her alphabet, and in about <hi rend="italics">one</hi> month, such was
her application and zeal, that, with the aid of occasional
prompting, she learned to read several chapters in St.
John's Gospel. “One aged
<pb id="thompson66" n="66"/>
woman (continues Mrs. R.) excited my interest by her
contentment of spirit. I ventured to ask her the cause of
her cheerfulness. ‘Oh,’ said she, ‘I live in hope of a better
place when I leave this one; I take comfort in thinking of
Heaven. I know my kind Master, who has carried me so
far on my way towards it, will not desert me in my old
age. His grace <hi rend="italics">has</hi> been, and I trust ever will be, my
support on the way.’ Again: ‘A girl, to whom my attention
was directed, had been brought to the home a few weeks
since in the last stage of consumption. Although her
bodily health was hopelessly gone, she had recourse to
the Physician of souls, and found recovering grace at the
last hour—grief for sin, and anxiety for pardon, for many
days overcame and swallowed up her bodily sufferings.
A short time before her death she seemed to find spiritual
comfort, and she finally breathed her last, with her song
of triumph on her lips. These and other instances show
the incalculable benefit of this Institution to the souls of
that neglected class who come under its care.”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="sketch">
          <pb id="thompson67" n="67"/>
          <head>PETER BENSÉ</head>
          <p>OR “<hi rend="italics">Peter Polite</hi>,” as he 
was familiarly called at the
Home, on account of his suavity of manner and
respectful demeanor toward every one.</p>
          <p>To his superiors he always observed a marked
deference, while to his associates and familiars he was
courteous and pleasant. His address and manner
appeared to belong to the school of Louis XIV.</p>
          <p>We do not feel authorized to make any special record
of him as a decided Christian character; but, from his
general conduct and moral deportment while an inmate of
the Home, we have reason to hope that he was not
unmindful of his eternal interests; and trust that he
found mercy of the Lord in the day of his extremity. The
varied and singular events of his changeful life, make him
worthy a passing notice in this brief history: we therefore
give a short sketch of him, as obtained from verbal
conversation occasionally had with him by the resident
physician, Dr. J. D. Fitch, to whom he appeared pleased
to communicate some of the past scenes and
circumstances connected with his early life.</p>
          <p>His statement was, that he was born in one of
<pb id="thompson68" n="68"/>
the West India islands, and that at a very early age he
was taken by a gentleman to England, with whom he lived
in the city of London until he was probably twenty years
old. He then accompanied some public functionary (name
not recollected) as <hi rend="italics">valet</hi>, to the 
Court of St. Petersburgh.
In that city he remained until he was probably thirty-five
years old. While there, he frequently accompanied his
master to court, where, from his complexion, he was
viewed somewhat as a curiosity, and was treated by
members of the royal family with marked kindness and
favor. He spoke of the Empress Catharine with strong
expressions of respect and esteem, and even of affection,
on account of her great kindness and attention to him. On
one occasion, when his master's duties required him to be
absent for some weeks from St. Petersburgh, at the
special request of the Empress he was permitted to
remain at the Palace Royal until his return; where he
served not only as ‘<hi rend="italics">valet</hi>’—but, 
having considerable taste
as a <hi rend="italics">coiffeur</hi>, he was frequently employed in that capacity
by the Royal Household.</p>
          <p>Among other reminiscences mentioned by Peter, he
stated, that he was either in or near the palace at the time
of the assassination of the Emperor Paul in 1801. He
seemed quite familiar with the principal occurrences of
that eventful period—and while relating them manifested
deep feeling and interest.</p>
          <pb id="thompson69" n="69"/>
          <p>During his residence in St. Petersburgh, he married a
young native Russian woman, by whom he had two sons.
About this time, (probably about 1810,) his master was
recalled home. After bidding adieu to his wife and
children, he entered with his master on board of an
English vessel then awaiting them at one of the Russian
seaport towns. He remarked it was a severe trial for him to
part with his family—but he left them with the
determination of returning to them whenever
circumstances would permit him so to do.</p>
          <p>While on their way to England, and on the coast of
France, their vessel was taken by a French cruiser, and
carried into Brest; from thence he, with his master, were
conveyed prisoners to Paris. He stated that his master,
although held a prisoner, was, by the order of Napoleon,
treated with great attention, and allowed to visit and
receive visits from many distinguished individuals
residing in Paris. Among these were Marshals Ney and
Soult.</p>
          <p>On one occasion his master was invited to dine with
the latter; Peter accompanied, and waited on him at table,
this being customary. There were many prominent
characters present, who flourished during the career of
the Emperor Napoleon. He remained in Paris until after
peace, and after the
<pb id="thompson70" n="70"/>
entrance of the allied armies; leaving it just after Napoleon
had departed for Elba.</p>
          <p>During his stay in Paris, which was three or four
years, he had frequent opportunities of seeing the
Emperor both at Reviews and at the Palace Royal, as
attendant on persons connected with the families of Soult
and Ney. He was in London at the visit of the Emperor of
Russia and King of Prussia to the Prince Regent, and
appeared familiar with all the gay scenes of that period.
He saw the Prince Regent on horseback ride around Hyde
Park, accompanied by Royal personages; and he was at
London during the coronation of George IVth, assisting
as <hi rend="italics">coiffeur</hi> to his master, who attended on that august
occasion. He frequently, in his relation of the events of
his life, mentioned many of the circumstances attending
the all-exciting subjects of that day. He related many
things connected with the trial of Queen Caroline,
consort of George IV.; had frequent opportunities of
seeing her; and his sympathies were great on her behalf.</p>
          <p>Amidst all the changing vicissitudes of his
wandering life, Peter remarked that he never forgot his
wife and children, but constantly looked forward to the
time when he should again return to them. When in
London the last time, he received information in some
way, that his family had gone to the
<pb id="thompson71" n="71"/>
United States and had landed in New-York, expecting to
meet him there. On this intelligence, he obtained
permission of his master to go and join them. He
immediately left England and proceeded to America, full
of hope and anticipated happiness of again clasping to
his bosom the wife of his youth, and his children. But ah!
how sad was his disappointment! On arriving in New-York, all his 
inquiries respecting them were unsuccessful,
and he could gain no information whatever respecting
them. His continued efforts incurred expenses, and his
little fund becoming exhausted,—poor and dispirited he
sought the situation of a waiter, still determined, so soon
as he could raise the means, to go back to St.
Petersburgh, and seek his family.</p>
          <p>The accomplishment of this hope he never realized.
Anxieties, and the infirmities of age broke down his
health—his means of sustenance failed—and in this day of
his emergencies (1841), he came to the <hi rend="italics">Colored Home</hi>,
seeking there within its walls a refuge and a resting-place.
Here he remained until his decease, which
occurred in June 1848, being as was supposed about
ninety-three years old.</p>
          <p>Peter Bensé was remarkable for his fluency of
expression,—he spoke with the French accent. His memory
was remarkably retentive; in which there seemed but one
defect; there appeared to be a perfect
<pb id="thompson72" n="72"/>
vacuum in his mind as to the time which had elapsed
since he separated from his wife and children; and when
within a few days of his death his spirits revived, and he
spoke cheerfully of the hope of again meeting them;
associating always the idea that he should find them as
youthful and juvenile as when he parted from them—
although nearly half a century had passed away.</p>
          <p>Among the articles which he considered of great
value, were notes of recommendation from many
distinguished personages both in England and France;
and most particularly, a large parchment, on which was
written his passport in the Russian language. His
appearance when walking in the street was dignified;
carrying in his hand a large <hi rend="italics">brass-headed</hi> cane, the
companion of many years. His head was covered with full
bushy hair, which, being whitened by age, had much the
appearance of a wig.</p>
          <p>Alas! poor <hi rend="italics">Bensé</hi>. Heaven had decreed that you
should never meet again on earth the loved ones of your
earlier days. May the hope be realized in that land of joy
and gladness, where sorrow, disappointment, and parting
are never known.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div1 type="conclusion">
        <pb id="thompson73" n="73"/>
        <head>CONCLUDING REMARKS.</head>
        <p>IT would extend the limits of these pages too far,
and time would fail us, to tell of <hi rend="italics">all</hi> those who have
found the Home but a pleasant stage in their journey
through this weary world to their final resting-place;
and who have died in faith in a certain hope
of finding a “better country, even a heavenly;
wherefore God is not ashamed to be called <hi rend="italics">their</hi>
God, for He hath prepared for them a city.”</p>
        <p>In the foregoing instances we see that the minds of
these sable ones were as susceptible of those feelings
which dignify and elevate human nature as those of
others; and the humble, grateful expression of their sense
of God's mercy to them through Christ, as sincere and
lively as ever emanated from those who may have been
highly cultivated, or placed in more enlightened society
under greater advantages.</p>
        <p>The influence of grace upon the heart is the same in
its effects upon all classes; as far as changing the will
and temper is concerned. It humbles pride, and subdues
the will; it changes the heart of man, and brings him to
view himself in his true character; a poor, wretched
sinner, exposed to
<pb id="thompson74" n="74"/>
the just displeasure of a Holy God whom he has
offended.</p>
        <p>When he becomes sensible of this, he is willing to be
saved on God's terms. And this is the same, whether in
the son of a prince, or untutored, unlettered child of
obscurity, whatever be his complexion or circumstances.
He who “made of one blood all nations of men,” careth
alike for all. The Saviour died for sinners—that whoever
believeth on Him, should not perish, but have everlasting
life. The redemption of the soul is <hi rend="italics">precious</hi>.</p>
        <p>Can we, then, be too earnest in seeking it both in
ourselves and others?—can we do too much to cause
“the abundant grace by the thanksgiving of many, to
redound with glory to God?” Led of His Spirit and His
Providence; and blessed as we have in this effort been of
Him; is it possible that we can do too much for Jesus?—
for Jesus, who for us endured the cross, despising the
shame!</p>
        <closer>
          <signed>M. W. T.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="appendix">
        <pb id="thompson75" n="75"/>
        <head>CONDENSED STATEMENT OF THE COLORED
HOME—ITS ORIGIN, &amp;c.</head>
        <p>THE Colored Home of the city of New-York originated in
the liberality of <hi rend="italics">one</hi> Christian lady—Miss Jay, daughter of
the late distinguished and venerable John Jay, of New-York.</p>
        <p>The sum of One Thousand Dollars was paid over by
Miss Jay, to a few ladies who convened at the residence
of her sister, Mrs. Maria Bauyer, in the autumn of 1839.
The sum appropriated was especially designed for the
relief of the <hi rend="italics">sick and respectable Colored Aged</hi>.</p>
        <p>This was the origin of the Colored Home. In the year
1845, the Society was incorporated by the State
Legislature, under the title of “<hi rend="italics">The 
Society for the Support of
the Colored Home</hi>.” A petition was also presented to the
Legislature for the repeal of certain acts passed March
11th, 1839, and May 26th, 1841 (which appropriated
<pb id="thompson76" n="76"/>
$10,000 for a State Hospital in the city of New-York),
asking a transfer of the money therein named to the Colored
Home.</p>
        <p>These acts were repealed, a new act framed, and the money
aforesaid was transferred to the Managers of the Colored
Home, to be applied to the erection of a permanent building on
the real estate belonging to the said Home in the city of New-York,
 for the relief and support of disabled Colored Sailors, and
other infirm and destitute colored people.</p>
        <p>With a view to more extensive usefulness, the Society made
arrangements with the Commissioners of the Alms-House, to
receive into the Institution, at a very low rate, all colored
paupers of the city, reserving the right to reject such applicants
as the resident physician should medically pronounce unfit
patients for the Colored Home.</p>
        <p>In 1848, the Society purchased 44 lots of ground lying on
Sixty-Fifth-street, between Avenue A and First Avenue; upon
which the Managers have recently erected a suitable building. It
consists of two distinct divisions or wings, for the
accommodation of the male and female departments, each 100
by 26 feet, separated by a ground plot of 100 feet, the whole
forming an open square.</p>
        <p>At the first meeting, in 1839, after the adoption of
<pb id="thompson77" n="77"/>
the constitution, twelve individuals were proposed and
received as objects worthy of relief.</p>
        <p>During the year 1847, the statistics show that the
Institution had, during that period, under its care nearly <hi rend="italics">one
thousand</hi> persons; a large proportion of whom were from the
Alms-House.</p>
        <p>The Colored Home is conducted in a careful and judicious
manner.</p>
        <p>The following persons at present constitute its Board of
Officers and Managers:—</p>
        <list type="simple">
          <head>OFFICERS:</head>
          <item>MRS. MARY ANN WELLS, <hi rend="italics">First Directress</hi>.</item>
          <item>MRS. SAMUEL J. BEEBEE, <hi rend="italics">Second Directress</hi>.</item>
          <item>MRS. WILLIAM W. CHESTER, <hi rend="italics">Recording Secretary</hi>.</item>
          <item>MRS. N. E. RUSSELL, <hi rend="italics">Corresponding Secretary</hi>.</item>
          <item>MRS. JOHN HARPER, <hi rend="italics">Treasurer</hi>.</item>
        </list>
        <list type="simple">
          <head>MANAGERS:</head>
          <item>Mrs. P. G. Arcularius,</item>
          <item>Mrs. C. B. Noon,</item>
          <item>Mrs. Thomas D. Moore,</item>
          <item>Mrs. Harvey Peet,</item>
          <item>Mrs. Edward Stone,</item>
          <item>Mrs. Col. Thompson,</item>
          <item>Mrs. B. B. Atterbury,</item>
          <item>Mrs. E. M. De Peyster,</item>
          <item>Mrs. Washington Roosevelt,</item>
          <item>Mrs. E. B. Goddard,</item>
          <item>Mrs. J. D. Fitch,</item>
          <item>Mrs. E. D. Willis,</item>
          <item>Mrs. John A. Livingston,</item>
          <item>Mrs. F. S. Winston,</item>
          <item>Mrs. J. W. Smyth,</item>
          <item>Miss Sarah Bunce,</item>
          <item>Miss M. Beebee,</item>
          <item>Miss M. C. De Peyster,</item>
          <item>Miss Elizabeth Clarkson Jay,</item>
          <item>Miss A. Hamilton,</item>
          <item>Miss C. Murray.</item>
        </list>
        <pb id="thompson78" n="78"/>
        <list type="simple">
          <head>ADVISERS:</head>
          <item>W. W. Chester, Esq.,</item>
          <item>John Jay, Esq.,</item>
          <item>W. G. Bull, Esq.,</item>
          <item>James D. Fitch, M. D.,</item>
          <item>John Harper, Esq.,</item>
          <item>Stephen Cambrelling, Esq.,</item>
          <item>John A. Bunting, Esq. </item>
          <item><hi rend="italics">Chaplain</hi>—REV. CHARLES C. DARLING.</item>
          <item><hi rend="italics">Steward</hi>—JAMES BEATTY.</item>
          <item><hi rend="italics">Matron</hi>—ANN M. BEATTY.</item>
          <item><hi rend="italics">Teacher</hi>—SARAH BEATTY.</item>
        </list>
        <list type="simple">
          <head>MEDICAL DEPARTMENT:</head>
          <item><hi rend="italics">Resident Physician</hi>—JAMES D. FITCH, M. D.</item>
          <item><hi rend="italics">Assistant Physician</hi>—Dr. H. K. OLMSTED.</item>
        </list>
        <list type="simple">
          <head>MEDICAL COUNCIL:<lb/>
HONORARY MEMBERS.</head>
          <item>J. Cheeseman, M. D.</item>
          <item>Thomas Cock, M. D.</item>
        </list>
        <list type="simple">
          <head>PHYSICIANS:</head>
          <item>J.  W. Francis,</item>
          <item>T.  M. Markoe, M. D.</item>
          <item>George Wilkes, M. D.</item>
        </list>
        <list type="simple">
          <head>SURGEONS:</head>
          <item>Willard Parker, M. D.</item>
          <item>G.  A. Sabine, M. D.</item>
          <item>J. K. Rodgers, M. D.</item>
        </list>
      </div1>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI.2>