<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>The Life, and Dying Speech of Arthur, a Negro Man; Who Was 
Executed at Worcester, October 20, 1768. For a Rape Committed on the Body of One Deborah Metcalfe:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Arthur, 1747-1768</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text transcribed by</resp>
          <name> Elizabeth Wright </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Elizabeth S. Wright and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>2001</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca.  25K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>2001.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="caption"> The Life, and Dying Speech of Arthur, a Negro Man; 
Who Was Executed at Worcester, October 20, 1768. For a Rape Committed on the Body of One Deborah Metcalfe</title>
            <author>Arthur, A Negro Man.</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>Broadside, 1 p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
            <publisher> [s. n.]</publisher>
            <date>1768</date>
            <authority/>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="yes">This electronic edition has been transcribed from a microfiche printout.</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>This electronic edition has been transcribed from a microfiche provided by Duke University Libraries.</p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>African American criminals -- Massachusetts -- Biography.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Massachusetts -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Arthur, 1747-1768.</item>
            <item>Crime -- Massachusetts -- History -- 18th century.</item>
            <item>Fugitive slaves -- Massachusetts -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Last words.</item>
            <item>Metcalfe, Deborah.</item>
            <item>Rape -- Massachusetts -- History -- 18th century.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- Massachusetts -- History -- 18th century.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Massachusetts -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves' writings, American -- Massachusetts.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2001-09-28, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2001-05-28, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2001-04-27, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Elizabeth S. Wright</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2001-04-25, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Elizabeth S. Wright</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished transcribing and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div1 type="statement">
        <head>The LIFE, and dying SPEECH of ARTHUR, a Negro Man;<lb/>
                       Who was Executed at Worcester, October 20, 1768. 
<lb/>
                  For a Rape committed on the Body of one Deborah Metcalfe </head>
        <p>I was born at <hi rend="italics">Taunton</hi>, January 15, 1747, in the house of <hi rend="italics">Richard Godfrey</hi>, Esq., my Mother being his Slave, where I lived
fourteen Years; was learned to read and write, and was treated very kindly by my Master; but was so unhappy as often to
incur the Displeasure of my Mistress, which caused me then to run away: And this was the beginning of my many notorious
Crimes, of which I have been guilty. I went first to <hi rend="italics">Sandwich</hi>, where I lived two Months in a very dissolute Manner, frequently
being guilty of Drunkenness and Fornication; for which crimes I have been since famous, and by which I am now brought to this
untimely Death. </p>
        <p>At <hi rend="italics">Sandwich</hi>, I stole a Shirt, was detected, and settled the Affair, by paying twenty Shillings. My Character being now known, I
thought proper to leave the Place; and accordingly shipped myself on board a Whaling Sloop, with Capt. <hi rend="italics">Coffin</hi>, of <hi rend="italics">Nantucket</hi>:
We were out eight Months, and then returned to <hi rend="italics">Nantucket</hi>, from whence we sailed, where I tarried six Weeks. In which
Time I broke a Store of Mr. <hi rend="italics">Roach's</hi>, from which I stole a Quantity of Rum, a pair of Trowsers, a Jacket, and some
Callicoe—The next Day I got drunk, and by wearing the Jacket, was detected, for which Offence I was whip'd with fifteen
Stripes, and committed to <sic corr="Gaol">Goal</sic>, for the Payment of Cost, &amp;c. from whence I escaped in half an Hour, by breaking the Lock.
Being now hardened in my Wickedness, I the next Night broke another Store in the same Place, from which I took several
Articles, and then shipped my self on board a Vessel bound to <hi rend="italics">Swanzey</hi>, where I was discovered, taken on Shoar, and whip'd
sixteen Stripes; being then set at Liberty, I returned to <hi rend="italics">Taunton</hi>, after one Year's absence, where my Master received me kindly,
whom I served three Years: In which Time I followed the Seas, sailing from <hi rend="italics">Nantucket</hi>, and <hi rend="italics">Newport</hi>, to divers parts of the
<hi rend="italics">West-Indies</hi>, where I whored and drank, to great Excess. Being now weary of the Seas, on the 27th of October 1764, I came
again to live with my Master at <hi rend="italics">Taunton</hi>, where I behaved well for six Weeks; at the Expiration of which Time, going to Town
with some Negroes, I got intoxicated; on returning home went into an House where were several Women only, to whom I
offered Indecencies, but was prevented from executing my black Designs, by the coming in of <hi rend="italics">James Williams</hi>, Esq.; upon
which I left the House, but was overtaken by him, who with the Assistance of Mr. <hi rend="italics">Job Smith</hi>, committed me to <hi rend="italics">Taunton</hi> <sic corr="Gaol">Goal</sic>:
On the next Day I was tried before the same Mr. <hi rend="italics">Williams</hi>, and was whip'd thirty-nine Stripes for abusing him, uttering three
profane Oaths, and threatening to fire Mr. <hi rend="italics">Smith's</hi> House. My Master being now determined, by the Advice of his Friends, to
send me out of the Country, I was sold to Mr. <hi rend="italics">John Hill</hi>, of <hi rend="italics">Brookfield</hi>, with whom I lived only one Week; was then sold to my
last Master, Capt. <hi rend="italics">Clarke</hi> of <hi rend="italics">Rutland</hi> District, where I behaved well for two Months, and was very kindly treated by my Master
and Mistress. I then unhappily commenced an Acquaintance with a young Squaw, with whom (having stole Six Shillings from
one of my Master's Sons) I was advised by some other Negroes, to run away, to avoid being taken up. By Advice of my
Companion (who like the rest of her Sex, was of a very fruitful Invention) I had recourse to the following Expedient: I dressed
in the Habit of a Squaw, and made of my own Cloaths a Pappouse; in this manner we proceeded to <hi rend="italics">Hadley</hi> undiscover'd
where I was introduced by my Companion, to an Indian Family, where I tarried only one Night, being discover'd in the
Morning by one Mr. <hi rend="italics">Shurtleff</hi>, a Person who had been sent after me; with him I went to <hi rend="italics">Springfield</hi>, where I met my Master,
who took me down to <hi rend="italics">Middletown</hi> with a Drove of Horses, where he sold me to a Dutch Gentleman, whose Name I have
since forgot. The very Night after I stole from the Widow <hi rend="italics">Sherley</hi>, (a Person whom kept a public House in that Place) five
Pounds; and the next Night, by getting drunk and loosing some of the Money, I was detected and put under the Custody of
two Men, for Trial the next Day; From whom I escaped, and went to <hi rend="italics">Farmington</hi>, where being advertised, I was immediately
taken up by Mr. <hi rend="italics">John Petterill</hi>, who carried me to my old Master <hi rend="italics">Clarke's</hi>, in <hi rend="italics">Rutland</hi> District, with who, I spent the Summer,
frequently stealing and getting drunk. My Master being now wearied by my repeated Crimes, was determined to part with me:
And accordingly we set off for <hi rend="italics">Boston</hi>, at which Time I took two Dollars from my Master's desk. On our Way thither, tarrying
some Time at Mr. <hi rend="italics">Fisk's</hi> in <hi rend="italics">Waltham</hi>; I went with some Negroes to a Husking, at Mr. <hi rend="italics">Thomas Parkes's</hi>, in <hi rend="italics">Little Cambridge</hi>,
where they on the same Night introduced me to a white Woman of that Place: And as our Behaviour was such, as we have
both Reason to be ashamed of, I shall for her sake pass it over in Silence. On the next Day I went to <hi rend="italics">Boston</hi>, was pursued by
her Husband, who found me at the Sign of the white Horse, where I left him in Conversation with my Master, who sent me to
<hi rend="italics">Little Cambridge</hi> with his Team; he again came up with me on <hi rend="italics">Boston</hi> Neck, where we came to Blows, and I coming off
Conqueror, put on for <hi rend="italics">Cambridge</hi>. The next Night I went to another Husking at <hi rend="italics">John Denney's</hi>, of that Place; after huskings, I
went to a Tavern opposite Mr. <hi rend="italics">Denney's</hi>, and took from a Team there, a Horse, Saddle and Bridle, and rode to <hi rend="italics">Natick</hi>, where
I met with the Squaw, with whom I formerly made my Tour to <hi rend="italics">Hadley</hi>, and with her spent the Day; and returning to
<hi rend="italics">Cambridge</hi>, I met my Master, with another Man, in pursuit of me. At our Arrival there, I was sentenced by five Men (to whom
the Matter was left) to receive fifteen Stripes, or pay four Dollars; and my Master was so good natur'd, or rather silly, as to
pay the Money, and let me go with Impunity. </p>
        <p>From here we went to <hi rend="italics">Waltham</hi>, where my Master heard that the injured Husband before mentioned, was after me with a
Warrant, which determined him to ship me off; accordingly, he went to <hi rend="italics">Boston</hi> to get a Birth for me, and order'd me to come in
the Night: In Pursuance of which Order, I set off, but having a natural Aversion to walking, for my own Ease, and that I might
make the greater Dispatch, I took a Horse from the Stable of one Mr. <hi rend="italics">Cutting</hi>, rode to <hi rend="italics">Roxbury</hi>, and let him go: I walked over
the Neck, and took Lodging in a Barn belonging to one Mr. <hi rend="italics">Pierpont</hi>, where I was met by my Master, who told me to tarry 'till
the next Day, when I should be taken on board a Vessel bound for <hi rend="italics">Maryland</hi>. But they not coming at the Time appointed, and
I not having had any Victual since I left <hi rend="italics">Waltham</hi>, thought proper to leave the Barn for better Quarters; accordingly made the
best of my way to <hi rend="italics">Dorchester</hi> where I stole a Horse, Saddle and Bridle, and proceeded to <hi rend="italics">Easton</hi>, to pay a Visit to my
Parents: who suspecting my Situation, insisted on my returning to my Master, which I promised without either Thoughts or
Inclination of performing: For instead of returning to <hi rend="italics">Boston</hi>, I steered my Course for <hi rend="italics">Sandwich</hi>. On my way there, at
<hi rend="italics">Rochester</hi>, stole a Bason. When I got to <hi rend="italics">Sandwich</hi>, I went to an Indian House, where I had been formerly acquainted, and with
the Squaws there, spent my Time in a manner which may be easily guessed; but was taken up on Suspicion, by one Mr. <hi rend="italics">Fisk</hi>,
and by him carried before Col. <hi rend="italics">Otis</hi>, who on my confessing that I stole the Horse at <hi rend="italics">Dorchester</hi>, committed me to the
<hi rend="italics">Barnstable</hi> <sic corr="Gaol">Goal</sic> for Trial, from whence I escaped in two Days. I then went to <hi rend="italics">Southsea</hi>, an Indian Village in Sandwich, where I
tarried for six Weeks, spending my Time in drinking and whoreing with the Squaws. By this time I got almost naked; and on
going to <hi rend="italics">Falmouth</hi>, went into some Shoemaker's Shop, and from thence stole a pair of Shoes: And from a House in the same
Place, I stole a Shirt, and a pair of Trowsers. At Night my Companions getting drunk, I left them; and at a Tavern there, stole a
Horse, Saddle and Bridle, on which I returned to the Indian Village, and then let him loose. After tarrying one Week more, I
was again taken up and committed to <hi rend="italics">Barnstable</hi> <sic corr="Gaol">Goal</sic>, where after laying three Weeks, I was tried and sentenced to receiving
twenty Stripes; but being unwell, the Man from whom I stole the Horse at <hi rend="italics">Dorchester</hi>, took me out of <sic corr="Gaol">Goal</sic>, so that I again got
off unpunished; With him I lived about three Weeks, and behaved well. </p>
        <p>In the mean Time, my Master being sent for, once more took me home, where I had not three Weeks, before another Negro of
my Master's told me that the young Squaw, so often mentioned, was desirous of seeing me. I one Night, after having stole
some Rum from my Master, got pretty handsomely drunk, took one of his Horses, and made the best of my way to her usual
Place of Abode; but she not being at home, the Devil put it into my Head to pay a Visit to the Widow <hi rend="italics">Deborah Metcalfe</hi>,
whom I, in a most inhumane manner, ravished: The Particulars of which are so notorious, that it is needless for me here to relate
them. The next Morning the unhappy Woman came and acquainted my Master of it, who immediately tyed me, to prevent me
running away, and told her (if she was desirous of prosecuting me) to get a Warrant as soon as possible; but she being unwilling
to have me hanged, proposed making the Matter up for a Proper Consideration, provided my Master would send me out of
the Country; to which he agreed, and accordingly set off with me for <hi rend="italics">Albany</hi>: But we were overtaken at <hi rend="italics">Glasgow</hi>, by Mr.
<hi rend="italics">Nathaniel Jennison</hi>, who it seem'd had got a Warrant for me. On our return to <hi rend="italics">Rutland</hi> District, we stop'd at a Tavern in
<hi rend="italics">Hardwick</hi>, where after I had warmed my self, <hi rend="italics">Jennison</hi> was Fool enough to bid me put along, and he would overtake me;
accordingly I went out of the Door, and seeing his Horse stand handily, what should I do, but mount him, and rode off as fast
as I could, leaving <hi rend="italics">Jennison</hi> to pursue me on Foot. I got home before Bed-time, and took up my Lodging in my Master's Barn
for the Night, where I had a Bottle of Cherry-Rum (which I found in Mr. <hi rend="italics">Jennison's</hi><sic corr="bags"> Baggs</sic>) to refresh my self with. </p>
        <p>On the next Day, being the 30th of March 1767, was discovered, and committed to <hi rend="italics">Worcester</hi> <sic corr="Gaol">Goal</sic>, where I continued 'till the
20th of April following; at which Time I broke out with the late celebrated <hi rend="italics">FRASIER</hi>, and a young Lad, who was confined for
stealing. After which, at <hi rend="italics">Worcester</hi>, we broke into a Barber's Shop, from whence we stole a Quantity of Flour, a Comb, and a
Razor: We then set off for <hi rend="italics">Boston</hi>. At <hi rend="italics">Shrewsbury</hi>, we stole a Goose from Mr. <hi rend="italics">Samuel Jennison</hi>; and from the Widow
<hi rend="italics">Kingsley</hi>, in the same Place, we stole a Kettle, in which we boiled the Goose, in <hi rend="italics">Westborough</hi> Woods. At <hi rend="italics">Marlborough</hi>, we
broke into a Distill-House, from whence we stole some Cyder Brandy: In the same Town we broke into a Shoe-maker's
Shop, and took each of us a pair of Shoes. We likewise broke into Mr. <hi rend="italics">Ciperon Howe's</hi> House, in the same Place, from
whence we stole some Bread, Meat and Rum. At <hi rend="italics">Sudbury</hi>, we stole each of us a Shirt, and one pair of Stockings. At <hi rend="italics">Weston</hi>
we stole some Butter from off a Horse. At <hi rend="italics">Waltham</hi> we broke into a House belonging to one Mr. <hi rend="italics">Fisk</hi>, from whom we took a
small Sum of Money, some Chocolate and Rum. At <hi rend="italics">Watertown</hi> we stole a Brass Kettle from one Mrs. <hi rend="italics">White</hi> of that Place.
My Companions now left me; upon which I went to Mr. <hi rend="italics">Fisk's</hi> in <hi rend="italics">Waltham</hi>, who knew me: And having heard of my Escape
from <hi rend="italics">Worcester</hi> <sic corr="Gaol">Goal</sic>, immediately secured me, and with the Assistance of another Man, brought me back again, where on the
17th of September following, I was tryed and found guilty. Upon which, by the Advice of my Counsel, I prayed for the Benefit
of the Clergy; which after a Year's Consideration, the Court denied me: And accordingly I was, on the 24th of Sept. last,
sentenced to be hanged, which I must confess is but too just a Reward for many notorious Crimes. </p>
        <p>I cannot conclude this is my Narrative, without gratefully acknowledging the unwearied Pains that was taken by the Rev. Mr.
<hi rend="italics">McCarty</hi>, to awaken me to a proper Sense of my miserable and wretched Condition, whose frequent Exhortations, and most
fervent Prayers, together with those of the rest of God's people, and my own sincere Endeavours after true Repentance, will I
hope prove the Means of my eternal Well-being; which I hope is still the Prayers of every Christian, to whom my unhappy
Situation is known.—I earnestly desire that this Recital of my Crimes, and the ignominious Death to which my notorious
Wickedness has bro't me, may prove a Warning to all Persons who shall become acquainted therewith. But in a particular
Manner, I would solemnly warn those of my Colour, as they regard their own souls, to avoid Desertion from their Masters,
Drunkenness and Lewdness; which three Crimes was the Source form which have flowed the many Evils and Miseries of my
short Life. Short indeed! For I am now at the Age of 21 Years only, just going to launch into a neverending Eternity; not by a
natural Death, but to the Dissolution of Soul and Body, so dreadful in itself, are added the Ignominy and Terror of that
particular kind of Death, which I am now going to suffer.—I freely acknowledge I have been better treated by Mankind in
general, than I deserved: Yet some Injuries I have received, which I now freely forgive. I also humbly ask Forgiveness of all
whom I have injured, and desire that they would pray that I may receive the Forgiveness of God, whom I have most of all
offended; and on whose Pardon and Grace depends my eternal Happiness or Misery.—</p>
        <closer><dateline><name>Worcester <sic corr="Gaol">Goal</sic>
 </name><date>Oct. 18, 1768 </date> </dateline>                                                     <signed><name>   Arthur</name></signed></closer>
      </div1>
      <trailer>Boston: Printed and Sold in Milk-Street  1768</trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>