<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY jackcv SYSTEM "jackscv.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY jacktp SYSTEM "jackstp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>The Story of Mattie J. Jackson;</emph>
<emph> Her Parentage—Experience of Eighteen Years in 
Slavery—Incidents During the War—Her 
Escape from Slavery. A True Story:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Mattie J. Jackson</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Lee Ann Morawski</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by</resp>
          <name>Lee Ann Morawski</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Bethany Ronnberg  and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1999</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>100 K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1999.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, 
teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability 
is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note anchored="yes">E 449.J3
(University of New Hampshire Library)</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>The Story of Mattie J. Jackson;  Her Parentage—Experience 
of Eighteen Years in Slavery—Incidents During the War—Her 
Escape from Slavery. A True Story.</title>
<author>Mattie J. Jackson</author><imprint><pubPlace>Lawrence:</pubPlace><publisher>Printed at Sentinel Office,</publisher><date>1866</date></imprint></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ 
respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been 
preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor 
(SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
<edition>21st 
edition, 1998</edition></bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Jackson, Mattie J.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- Missouri -- History -- 19th century.</item>
            <item>Fugitive slaves -- Missouri -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Missouri -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Missouri -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.</item>
            <item>Slaves' writings, American -- Missouri.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>1999-10-21, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-07-13, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project 
manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-07-09, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Bethany Ronnberg</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-07-06, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Lee Ann Moraswki</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="iamge">
        <p>
          <figure id="cv" entity="jackcv"/>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="image">
        <p>
          <figure id="tp" entity="jacktp"/>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">THE STORY
<lb/>
OF
<lb/>
MATTIE J. JACKSON;</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="subtitle">HER PARENTAGE—EXPERIENCE OF EIGHTEEN 
YEARS IN SLAVERY—INCIDENTS 
DURING THE WAR—HER ESCAPE FROM SLAVERY.</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="subtitle">A TRUE STORY.</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>WRITTEN AND ARRANGED BY</byline>
        <docAuthor>DR. L. S. THOMPSON,
<lb/>
(FORMERLY MRS. SCHUYLER,)</docAuthor>
        <docAuthor>AS GIVEN BY MATTIE.</docAuthor>
        <docImprint><publisher>LAWRENCE:</publisher>
<pubPlace>PRINTED AT SENTINEL OFFICE, 123 ESSEX STREET.</pubPlace>
<docDate>1866.</docDate></docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="dedication">
        <pb id="jackson2" n="2"/>
        <head>PREFACE.</head>
        <p>The object in publishing this book is to gain sympathy from the
earnest friends of those who have been bound down by a dominant
race in circumstances over which they had no control—a butt of 
ridicule and a mark of oppression; over whom weary ages of degradation
have passed. As the links have been broken and the shackles
fallen from them through the unwearied efforts of our beloved martyr 
President Lincoln, as one I feel it a duty to improve the mind,
and have ever had a thirst for education to fill that vacuum for
which the soul has ever yearned since my earliest remembrance.</p>
        <p>Thus I ask you to buy my little book to aid me in obtaining an
education, that I may be enabled to do some good in behalf of the
elevation of my emancipated brothers and sisters. I have now
arrived at the age of twenty. As the first dawn of morning has
passed, and the meridian of life is approaching, I know of no other
way to speedily gain my object than through the aid and patronage
of the friends of humanity.</p>
        <p>NOTE. Miss Jackson sustains a high moral character—has been
much respected since she has been in Lawrence<corr sic=" ">.</corr> She is from St.
Louis, Missouri, and arrived here on the 11th of April, 1866. To
gain the wish of the heart is utterly impossible without more means
than she can obtain otherwise. Her friends have borne her expenses
to Lawrence, and have and are still willing to render her aid as far
their limited means will allow. She was in the same condition of
all the neglected and oppressed. Her personal requirements are
amply supplied. She now only craves the means to cloathe and
qualify the intellect. My humble prayer is that she may meet with
unlimited success.</p>
        <p>This young lady is highly worthy of all the aid our kind friends
feel a duty to bestow upon her. She purposes lecturing and relating
her story; and I trust she may render due satisfaction and bear
some humble part in removing doubts indulged by the prejudices
against the natural genius and talent of our race. May God give
her grace and speed her on her way.</p>
        <closer><salute>Respectfully yours,</salute>
<signed>   L. S. T.</signed></closer>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="narrative">
        <pb id="jackson3" n="3"/>
        <head>MATTIE'S STORY.</head>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <p>MY ancestors were transported from Africa to America at the
time the slave trade flourished in the Eastern States. I cannot
give dates, as my progenitors, being slaves, had no means of
keeping them. By all accounts my great grandfather was 
captured and brought from Africa<corr sic=" ">.</corr> 
His original name I never
learned. His master's name was Jackson, and he resided in the
State of New York. My grandfather was born in the same
State, and also remained a slave for some length of time, when
he was emancipated, his master presenting him with quite an
amount of property. He was true, honest and responsible, and
this present was given him as a reward<corr sic=" ">.</corr> He was much encouraged 
by the cheering prospect of better days. A better condition 
of things now presented itself. As he possessed a large
share of confidence, he came to the conclusion, as he was free,
that he was capable of selecting his own residence and manage
his own affairs with prudence and economy. But, alas, his hopes
were soon blighted. More heart rending sorrow and degradation 
awaited him. He was earnestly invited by a white decoyer
to relinquish his former design and accompany him to Missouri
and join him in speculation and become wealthy. As partners,
they embarked on board a schooner for St. Charles, Mo. On the
passage, my grandfather was seized with a fever, and for a
while was totally unconscious. When he regained his reason
he found himself, near his journey's end, divested of his free
papers and all others. On his arrival at St. Charles he was
seized by a huge, surly looking slaveholder who claimed him
as his property. The contract had previously been concluded
by his Judas-like friend, who had received the bounty. Oh<corr sic=".">,</corr>
what a sad disappointment. After serving for thirty years to
be thrust again into bondage where a deeper <sic corr="degradation">degredation</sic> and
<pb id="jackson4" n="4"/>
sorrow and hopeless toil were to be his portion for the remaining
years of his existence. In deep despair and overwhelmed with
grief, he made his escape to the woods, determined to put an
end to his sorrows by perishing with cold and hunger. His 
master immediately pursued him, and in twenty-four hours found
him with hands and feet frost-bitten, in consequence of which
he lost the use of his fingers and toes, and was thenceforth of
little use to his new master. He remained with him, however,
and married a woman in the same station in life. They lived as
happily as their circumstances would permit. As Providence
allotted, they only had one son, which was my father, Westly
Jackson. He had a deep affection for his family, which the
slave ever cherishes for his dear ones. He had no other link to
fasten him to the human family but his fervent love for those
who were bound to him by love and sympathy in their wrongs
and sufferings. My grandfather remained in the same family
until his death. My father, Westly Jackson, married, at the
age of twenty-two, a girl owned by James Harris, named Ellen
Turner. Nothing of importance occurred until three years after
their marriage, when her master, Harris failed through the
extravagance and mismanagement of his wife, who was a great
spendthrift and a dreaded terror to the poor slaves and all others
with whom she associated in common circumstances, consequently 
the entire stock was sold by the sheriff to a trader residing
in Virginia. On account of the good reputation my mother
sustained as a worthy servant and excellent cook, a tyrannical
and much dreaded slaveholder watched for an opportunity to
purchase her, but fortunately arrived a few moments too late,
and she was bid off in too poor a condition of health to remain
long a subject of banter and speculation. Her husband was 
allowed to carefully lift her down from the block and accompany
her to her new master's, Charles Canory, who treated her very
kindly while she remained in his family. Mr. Canory resided
in St. Charles County for five years after he purchased my
mother. During that time my father and mother were in the
<pb id="jackson5" n="5"/>
same neighborhood, but a short distance from each other. But
another trial awaited them. Her master removed twenty miles
away to a village called Bremen, near St. Louis, Mo. My 
father, thereafter, visited my mother once a week, walking the
distance every Saturday evening and returning on Sunday evening. 
But through all her trials and deprivations her trust and
confidence was in Him who rescued his faithful followers from
the fiery furnace and the lion's den, and led Moses through the
Red Sea. Her trust and confidence was in Jesus. She relied
on His precious promises, kind ever found Him a present help in
every time of need. Two years after this separation my father
was sold and separated from us, but previous to his delivery to
his new master he made his escape to a free State. My mother
was then left with two children. She had three during the time
they were permitted to remain together, and buried one. Their
names were Sarah Ann, Mattie Jane and Esther J. When my
father left I was about three years of age, yet I can well 
remember the little kindnesses my father used to bestow upon us,
and the deep affection and fondness he manifested for us. I
shall never forget the bitter anguish of my parents' hearts, the
sighs they uttered or the profusion of tears which coursed down
their sable checks. O, what a horrid scene, but he was not her's,
for cruel hands had separated them.</p>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>The strongest tie of earthly joy that bound the aching heart—</l>
            <l>His love was e'er a joyous light that O<corr sic=" ">'</corr>er the pathway shone—</l>
            <l>A fountain gushing ever new amid life's desert wild—</l>
            <l>His slightest word was a sweet tone of music round her heart—</l>
            <l>Their lives a streamlet blent in one. O, Father, must they part?</l>
            <l>They tore him from her circling arms, her last and fond embrace—</l>
            <l>O never again can her sad eyes gaze upon his mournful face.</l>
            <l>It is not strange these bitter sighs are constant bursting forth.</l>
            <l>Amid mirth and glee and revelry she never took a part,</l>
            <l>She was a mother left alone with sorrow in her heart.</l>
          </lg>
          <p>But my mother was conscious some time previous of the change
that was to take place with my father, and if he was sold in the
immediate vicinity he would be likely to be sold again at their
will, and she concluded to assist him to make his escape from
<pb id="jackson6" n="6"/>
bondage. Though the parting was painful, it afforded her 
solace in the contemplation of her husband becoming a free man,
and cherishing a hope that her little family, through the aid of
some angel of mercy, might be enabled to make their escape
also, and meet to part no more on earth. My father came to
spend the night with us, according to his usual custom. It was
the last time, and sadness brooded upon his brow. It was the 
only opportunity he had to make his escape without suspicion 
and detection, as he was immediately to fall into the hands of a
new master. He had never been sold from the place of his birth
before, and was determined never to be sold again if God would
verify his promise. My father was not educated, but 
was a preacher, and administered the Word of God according to 
the dictation and revelation of the spirit. His former master 
had allowed him the privilege of holding meetings in the village
within the limits of his pass on the Sundays when he visited
my mother. But on this Saturday evening he arrived and gave us 
all his farewell kiss and hurried away. My mother's people
were aware of my father's intention, but rather than spare my
mother, and for fear she might be detected, they secreted his
escape. His master called a number of times and enquired for 
him and strongly pressed my mother to give him an account of 
my father, but she never gave it. We waited patiently, hoping 
to learn if he succeeded in gaining his freedom. Many anxious 
weeks and months passed before we could get any tidings from 
him, until at length my mother heard that he was in Chicago, a 
free man and preaching the Gospel. He made every effort to 
get his family, but all in vain. The spirit of slavery so strongly 
existed that letters could not reach her; they were all destroyed<corr>.</corr>
My parents had never learned the rescuing scheme of the 
underground railroad which had borne so many thousands to the 
standard of freedom and victories. They knew no other 
resource than to depend upon their own chance in running away 
and secreting themselves. If caught they were in a worse 
condition than before.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <pb id="jackson7" n="7"/>
          <head>THEIR ATTEMPT TO MAKE THEIR ESCAPE.</head>
          <p>Two years after my father's departure, my mother, with her
two children, my sister and myself, attempted to make her 
escape. After traveling two days we reached Illinois. We slept
in the woods at night<corr>.</corr> I believe my mother had food to supply
us but fasted herself. But the advertisement had reached there
before us, and loafers were already in search of us, and as soon
as we were discovered on the brink of the river one of the spies
made enquiries respecting her suspicious appearance. She was
aware that she was arrested, consequently she gave a true 
account of herself—that she was in search of her husband. We
were then destitute of any articles of clothing excepting our
wearing apparel<corr>.</corr> Mother had become so weary that she was
compelled to leave our package of clothing on the way<corr>.</corr> We
were taken back to St. Louis and committed to prison and 
remained there one week, after which they put us in Linch's
trader's yard, where we remained about four weeks. We were
then sold to William Lewis. Mr. Lewis was a very severe 
master, and inflicted such punishment upon us as he thought proper.
However, I only remember one severe contest Mr. Lewis had
with my mother. For some slight offence Mrs. Lewis became
offended and was tartly and loudly reprimanding her, when Mr.
L. came in and rashly felled her to the floor with his fist. But
his wife was constantly pulling our ears, snapping us with her
thimble, rapping us on the head and the sides of it. It appeared
impossible to please her. When we first went to Mr. L.'s they
had a cowhide which she used to inflict on a little slave girl
she previously owned, nearly every night. This was done to
learn the little girl to wake early to wait on her children. But
my mother was a cook, as I before stated, and was in the habit
of roasting meats and toasting bread. As they stinted us for 
food my mother roasted the cowhide. It was rather poor picking, 
but it was the last cowhide my mother ever had an opportunity 
to cook while we remained in his family. Mr. L. soon
moved about six miles from the city, and entered in partnership
<pb id="jackson8" n="8"/>
with his brother-in-law. The servants were then divided and
distributed in both families. It unfortunately fell to my lot to
live with Mrs. Larry. my mistress' sister, which rendered my
condition worse than the first. My master even disapproved of
my ill treatment and took me to another place; the place my
mother resided before my father's escape. After a short time
Mr. Lewis again returned to the city. My mother still remained
as cook in his family. After six years' absence of my father
my mother married again a man by the name of George Brown,
and lived with her second husband about four years, and had
two children, when he was sold for requesting a different kind
and enough food. His master considered it a great insult, and
declared he would sell him. But previous to this insult, as he
called it, <sic corr="my">may</sic> step-father was foreman in Mr. L.'s tobacco 
factory. He was trusty and of good moral habits, and was 
calculated to bring the highest price in the human market; therefore
the excuse to sell him for the above offence was only a plot.
The morning this offence occurred, Mr. L. bid my father to 
remain in the kitchen till he had taken his breakfast. After 
pulling his ears and slapping his face bade him come to the factory;
but instead of going to the factory he went to Canada. Thus
my poor mother was again left alone with two more children
added to her misery and sorrow to toil on her weary pilgrimage.</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Racked with agony and 
pain she was left alone again,</l>
            <l>With a purpose nought could move</l>
            <l>And the zeal of woman's love,</l>
            <l>Down she knelt in agony</l>
            <l>To ask the Lord to clear the way.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>True she said O gracious Lord,</l>
            <l>True and faithful is thy word;</l>
            <l>But the humblest, poorest, may</l>
            <l>Eat the crumbs they cast away.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stana">
            <l>Though nine long years had passed</l>
            <l>Without one glimmering light of day</l>
            <l>She never did forget to pray</l>
            <l>And has not yet though whips and chains are castaway.</l>
          </lg>
          <pb id="jackson9" n="9"/>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>For thus said the blessed Lord, </l>
            <l>I will verify my word; </l>
            <l>By the faith that has not failed, </l>
            <l>Thou hast asked and shall prevail.</l>
          </lg>
          <p>We remained but a short time at the same residence when
Mr. Lewis moved again to the country. Soon after, my little
brother was taken sick in consequence of being confined in a box 
in which my mother was obliged to keep him. If permitted to
creep around the floor her mistress thought it would take too 
much time to attend to him. He was two years old and never 
walked. His limbs were perfectly paralyzed for want of
exercise. We now saw him gradually failing, but was not allowed 
to render him due attention. Even the morning he died she 
was compelled to attend to her usual work. She watched over 
him for three months by night and attended to her domestic 
affairs by day. The night previous to his death we were aware 
he could not survive through the approaching day, but it made 
no impression on my mistress until she came into the kitchen 
and saw his life fast ebbing away, then she put on a sad countenance 
for fear of being exposed, and told my mother to take the 
child to her room, where he only lived one hour. When she 
found he was dead she ordered grave clothes to be brought and 
gave my mother time to bury him. O that morning, that solemn 
morning. It appears to me that when that little spirit 
departed as though all heaven rejoiced and angels veiled their faces.
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>My mother too in concert joined  - </l><l>Her mingled praise with them combined. </l><l>Her little saint had gone to God </l><l>Who saved him with his precious blood.</l></lg></q>
Who said “Suffer little children to come unto me and forbid
them not.”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>THE SOLDIERS, AND OUR TREATMENT DURING THE WAR.</head>
          <p>Soon after the war commenced the rebel soldiers encamped
near Mr. Lewis' residence, and remained there one week. They
were then ordered by General Lyons to surrender, but they 
<pb id="jackson10" n="10"/>
refused. There were seven thousand Union and seven hundred
rebel soldiers<corr>.</corr> The Union soldiers surrounded the camp and
took them and exhibited them through the city and then 
confined them in prison. I told my mistress that the Union 
soldiers were coming to take the camp. She replied that it was
false, that it was General Kelly coming to re-enforce Gen. Frost.
In a few moments the alarm was heard. I told Mrs. L. the
Unionists had fired upon the rebels. She replied it was only
the salute of Gen. Kelley. At night her husband came home
with the news that Camp <sic corr="Jackson">Jacskon</sic> was taken and all the soldiers
prisoners. Mrs. Lewis asked how the Union soldiers could take
seven hundred men when they only numbered the same. Mr.
L. replied they had seven thousand. She was much astonished,
and cast her eye around to us for fear we might hear her. Her
suspicion was correct; there was not a word passed that escaped
our listening ears<corr>.</corr> My mother and myself could read enough
to make out the news in the papers. The Union soldiers took
much delight in tossing a paper over the fence to us. It aggravated 
my mistress very much. My mother used to sit up nights
and read to keep posted about the war. In a few days my
mistress came down to the kitchen again with another bitter 
complaint that it was a sad affair that the Unionists had taken their
delicate citizens who had enlisted and made prisoners of them—
that they were babes. My mother reminded her of taking Fort
Sumpter and Major Anderson and serving them the same and
that turn about was fair play. She then hastened to her room
with the speed of a deer, nearly unhinging every door in her
flight, replying as she went that the Niggers and Yankees were
seeking to take the country. One day, after she had visited the
kitchen to superintend some domestic affairs, as she pretended,
she became very angry without a word being passed, and said—
“I think it has come to a pretty pass, that old Lincoln, with
his long legs, an old rail splitter, wishes to put the Niggers on
an equality with the whites; that her children should never be
on an equal footing with a Nigger<corr>.</corr> She had rather see them
<pb id="jackson11" n="11"/>
dead.” As my mother made no reply to her remarks, she stopped 
talking, and commenced venting her spite on my companion 
servant. On one occasion Mr. Lewis searched my mother's
room and found a picture of President Lincoln, cut from a
newspaper, hanging in her room. He asked her what she was
doing with old Lincoln's picture. She replied it was there 
because she liked it. He then knocked her down three times, and
sent her to the trader's yard for a month as punishment. My 
mistress indulged some hopes till the victory of New Orleans, when
she heard the famous Union song sang to the tune of Yankee
Doodle:</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>The rebels swore that New Orleans never should be taken,</l>
            <l>But if the Yankees came so near they should not save their bacon.</l>
            <l>That's the way they blustered when they thought they were so handy,</l>
            <l>But Farragut steamed up one day and gave them Doodle Dandy</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Ben. Butler then was ordered down to regulate the city;</l>
            <l>He made the rebels walk a chalk, and was not that a pity?</l>
            <l>That's the way to serve them out—that's the way to treat them,</l>
            <l>They must not go and put on airs after we have beat them.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>He made the rebel banks shell out and pay the loyal people,</l>
            <l>He made them keep the city clean from pig's sty to church steeple.</l>
            <l>That's the way Columbia speaks, let all men believe her;</l>
            <l>That's the way Columbia speaks instead of yellow fever.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l>He sent the saucy women up and made them treat us well</l>
            <l>He helped the poor and snubbed the rich; they thought he was the devil.</l>
            <l>Bully for Ben. Butler, then, they thought he was so handy;</l>
            <l>Bully for Ben Butler then,—Yankee Doodle Dandy.</l>
          </lg>
          <p>The days of sadness for mistress were days of joy for us.
We shouted and laughed to the top of our voices. My mistress
was more enraged than ever—nothing pleased her. One evening, 
after I had attended to my usual duties, and I supposed
all was complete, she, in a terrible rage, declared I should be
punished that night. I did not know the cause, neither did she.
She went immediately and selected a switch. She placed it in
the corner of the room to await the return of her husband at
night for him to whip me. As I was not pleased with the idea
of a whipping I bent the switch in the shape of W, which was
<pb id="jackson12" n="12"/>
the first letter of his name, and after I had attended to the
dining room my fellow servant and myself walked away and
stopped with an aunt of mine during the night<corr>.</corr> In the morning 
we made our way to the Arsenal, but could gain no admission. 
While we were wandering about seeking protection, the
girl's father overtook us and persuaded us to return home. We
finally complied. All was quiet. Not a word was spoken 
respecting our sudden departure. All went on as usual. I was
permitted to attend to my work without interruption until three
weeks after. One morning I entered Mrs. Lewis' room, and
she was in a room adjoining, complaining of something I had
neglected. Mr. L. then enquired if I had done my work. I
told him I had. She then flew into a rage and told him I was
saucy, and to strike me, and he immediately gave me a severe
blow with a stick of wood, which inflicted a deep wound upon
my head. The blood ran over m clothing, which gave me a
frightful <sic corr="appearance">appcarance</sic>. Mr. Lewis then ordered me to change my
clothing immediately. As I did not obey be became more 
enraged, and pulled me into another room and threw me on the
floor, placed his knee on my stomach, slapped me on the face
and beat me with his fist, and would have punished me more
had not my mother interfered. He then told her to go away
or he would compel her to, but she remained until he left me.
I struggled mightily, and stood him a good test for a while, but
he was fast conquering me when my mother came. He was
aware my mother could usually defend herself against one man,
and both of us would overpower him, so after giving his wife
strict orders to take me up stairs and keep me there, he took
his carriage and drove away. But she forgot it, as usual. She
was highly gratified with my appropriate treatment, as she called
it, and retired to her room, leaving me to myself. I then went
to my mother and told her I was going away. She bid me go,
and added “May the Lord help you.” I started for the
Arsenal again and succeeded in gaining admittance and seeing
the Adjutant. He ordered me to go to another tent, where
<pb id="jackson13" n="13"/>
there was a woman in similar circumstances, cooking. When
the General found I was there he sent me to the boarding house.
I remained there three weeks, and when I went I wore the same
stained clothing as when I was so severely punished, which has
left a mark on my head which will ever remind me of my 
treatment while in slavery. Thanks be to God, though tortured by
wrong and goaded by oppression, the hearts that would madden
with misery have broken the iron yoke.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>MR. LEWIS CALLS AT THE BOARDING HOUSE.</head>
          <p>At the expiration of three weeks Mr. Lewis called at my
boarding house, accompanied by his brother-in-law, and enquired
for me, and the General informed him where I was. He then
told me my mother was very anxious for me to come home, and
I returned. The General had ordered Mr. Lewis to call at
headquarters, when he told him if he had treated me right I
would not have been compelled to seek protection of him;
that my first appearance was sufficient proof of his cruelty.
Mr. L. promised to take me home and treat me kindly. 
Instead of fulfilling his promise he carried me to the trader's
yard, where, to my great surprise, I found my mother. She
had been there during my absence, where she was kept for fear
she would find me and take my brother and sister and make her
escape. There was so much excitement at that time, (1861),
by the Union soldiers rendering the fugitives shelter and 
protection, he was aware that if she applied to them, as he did not
fulfill his promise in my case, he would stand a poor chance.
If my mother made application to them for protection they would
learn that he did not return me home and immediately detect
the intrigue. After I was safely secured in the trader's yard,
Mr. L. took my mother home. I remained in the yard three
months. Near the termination of the time of my confinement
I was passing by the office when the cook of the Arsenal saw
and recognized me and informed the General that Mr. L. had
disobeyed his orders, and had put me in the trader's yard instead
<pb id="jackson14" n="14"/>
of taking me home. The General immediately arrested Mr. L
and gave him one hundred lashes with the cow-hide, so that
they might identify him by a scarred back, as well as his slaves.
My mother had the pleasure of washing his stained clothes, 
otherwise it would not have been known. My master was 
compelled to pay three thousand dollars and let me out. He then
put me to service, where I remained seven months, after which
he came in great haste and took me into the city and put me into
the trader's yard again<corr>.</corr> After he received the punishment he
treated my mother and the children worse than ever, which
caused her to take her children and secrete themselves in the
city, and would have remained undetected had it not been for a
traitor who pledged himself to keep the secret. But King
Whiskey fired up his brain one evening, and out popped the
secret. My mother and sister were consequently taken and
committed to the trader's yard. My little brother was then
eight years of age, my sister sixteen, and myself eighteen. We
remained there two weeks, when a rough looking man, called
Capt. Tirrell, came to the yard and enquired for our family.
After he had examined us he remarked that we were a fine looking 
family, and bid us retire. In about two hours he returned,
at the edge of the evening, with a covered wagon, and took my
mother and brother and sister and left me. My mother refused
to go without me, and told him she would raise an alarm. He
advised her to remain as quiet as possible. At length she was
compelled to go. When she entered the wagon there was a man
standing behind with his hands on each side of the wagon to
prevent her from making her escape. She sprang to her feet
and gave this man a desperate blow, and leaping to the ground
she made an alarm. The watchmen came to her assistance 
immediately, and there was quite a number of Union policemen
guarding the city at that time, who rendered her due justice as
far as possible. This was before the emancipation proclamation
was issued. After she leaped from the wagon they drove on,
taking her children to the boat. The police questioned my
<pb id="jackson15" n="15"/>
mother. She told them that Capt. Tirrell had put her children
on board the boat, and was going to take them to Memphis and
sell them into hard slavery. They accompanied her to the boat,
and arrived just as they were casting off. The police ordered
them to stop and immediately deliver up the children, who had
been secreted in the Captain's private apartment. They were
brought forth and returned. Slave speculation was forbidden in
St. Louis at that time. The Union soldiers had possession of
the city, but their power was limited to the suppression of the
selling of slaves to go out of the city. Considerable smuggling
was done, however, by pretending Unionism, which was the case
with our family.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>RELEASED FROM THE TRADER'S YARD AND TAKEN TO HER<lb/>
NEW MASTER.</head>
          <p>Immediately after dinner my mother called for me to accompany 
her to our new home, the residence of the Captain, together
with my brother and sister. We fared very well while we were
there. Mrs. Tirrell was insane, and my mother had charge of
the house. We remained there four months. The Captain
came home only once a week, and he never troubled us for fear
we might desert him. His intention was to smuggle us away
before the State became free. That was the understanding
when he bought us of Mr. Lewis, as it was not much of an 
object to purchase slaves while the proclamation was pending, and
they likely to lose all their property; but they would, for a trifle
purchase a whole family of four or five persons to send out of the
State. Kentucky paid as much, or more than ever, for slaves.
As they pretended to take no part in the rebellion they 
supposed they would be allowed to keep them without interference.
Consequently the Captain's intention was to keep as quiet as
possible till the excitement concerning us was over, and he could
get us off without detection. Mr. Lewis would rather have 
disposed of us for nothing than have seen us free. He hated my
mother in consequence of her desire for freedom, and her 
<pb id="jackson16" n="16"/>
endeavors to teach her children the right way as far as her ability
would allow. He also held a charge against her for reading the
papers and understanding political affairs. When he found he
was to lose his slaves he could not bear the idea of her being
free. He thought it too hard, as she had raised so many 
tempests for him, to see her free and under her own control. He
had tantalized her in every possible way to humiliate and annoy
her; yet while he could demand her services he appreciated
and placed perfect confidence in mother and family. None but
a fiendish slaveholder could have rended an honest Christian
heart in such a manner as this.</p>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>Though it was her sad and weary lot to toil in slavery</l>
            <l>But one thing cheered her weary soul</l>
            <l>When almost in despair</l>
            <l>That she could gain a sure relief in attitude of prayer</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CAPT. TIRRELL REMOVES THE FAMILY.—ANOTHER STRATEGY</head>
          <p>One day the Captain commenced complaining of the expense
of so large a family, and proposed to my mother that we should
work out and he take part of the pay. My mother told him
she would need what she earned for my little brother's support<corr>.</corr>
Finally the Captain consented, and I was the first to be disposed
of. The Captain took me in his buggy and carried me to the
Depot, and I was put into a Union family, where I remained
five months. Previous to my leaving, however, my mother and
the Captain entered into a contract—he agreeing not to sell us,
and mother agreeing not to make her escape. While she was
carrying out her promise in good faith, he was plotting to 
separate us. We were all divided except mother and my little
brother, who remained together. My sister remained with one
of the rebels, but was tolerably treated. We all fared very
well; but it was only the calm before the rending tornado.
Captain T. was Captain of the boat to Memphis, from which
the Union soldiers had rescued us. He commenced as a deck
hand on the boat, then attained a higher position, and continued
to advance until he became her Captain. At length he came in
<pb id="jackson17" n="17"/>
possession of slaves. Then his accomplishments were complete.
He was a very severe slave master. Those mushroon slaveholders 
are much dreaded, as their severity knows no bounds<corr>.</corr></p>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>Bondage and torture, scourges and chains</l>
            <l>Placed on our backs indelible stains.</l>
          </lg>
          <p>I stated previously, in relating a sketch of my mother's history, 
that she was married twice, and both husbands were to be
sold and made their escape. They both gained their freedom.
One was living,—the other died before the war. Both made
every effort to find us, but to no purpose. It was some years
before we got a correct account of her second husband, and he
had no account of her, except once he heard that mother and
children had perished in the woods while endeavoring to make
their escape. In a few years after his arrival in the free States
he married again.</p>
          <p>When about sixteen years of age, while residing with her
original master, my mother became acquainted with a young
man, Mr. Adams, residing in a neighboring family, whom she
much respected; but he was soon sold, and she lost trace of
him entirely, as was the common occurrence with friends and
companions though united by the nearest ties. When my mother 
arrived at Captain Tirrell's, after leaving the boat, in her
excitement she scarce observed anything except her little group
so miraculously saved from perhaps a final separation in this
world. She at length observed that the servant who was waiting 
to take her to the Captain's residence in the country was the
same man with whom she formed the acquaintance when sixteen
years old, and they again renewed their acquaintance. He had
been married and buried his wife. It appeared that his wife
had been in Captain Tirrell's family many years, and he also,
for some time. They had a number of children, and Capt. 
Tirrell had sold them down South. This cruel blow, assisted by
severe flogging and other ill treatment, rendered the mother 
insane, and finally caused her death.</p>
          <lg type="verse">
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>In agony close to her bosom she pressed,</l>
              <l>The life of her heart, the child of her breast—</l>
              <pb id="jackson18" n="18"/>
              <l>Oh love from its tenderness gathering might</l>
              <l>Had <sic corr="strengthened">strengthed</sic> her soul for declining age.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>But she is free. Yes, she has gone from the land of the slave;</l>
              <l>The hand of oppression must rest in the grave.</l>
              <l>The blood hounds have missed the scent of her way,</l>
              <l>The hunter is rifled and foiled of his prey.</l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
          <p>After my mother had left the Captain to take care of herself
and child, according to agreement with the Captain, she became
engaged to Mr. Adams. He had bought himself previously for a
large price. After they became acquainted, the Captain had an
excellent opportunity of carrying out his stratagem. He 
commenced bestowing charity upon Mr. Adams. As he had 
purchased himself, and Capt. T. had agreed not to sell my mother,
they had decided to marry at an early day. They hired a house
in the city and were to commence housekeeping immediately.
The Captain made him a number of presents and seemed much
pleased with the arrangement. The day previous to the one set
for the marriage, while they were setting their house in order, a
man called and enquired for a nurse, pretending he wanted one
of us. Mother was absent; he said he would call again, but
he never came. On Wednesday evening we attended a 
protracted meeting. After we had returned home and retired, a
loud rap was heard at the door. My Aunt enquired who was
there. The reply was, “Open the door or I will break it down.”
In a moment in rushed seven men, four watchmen and three
traders, and ordered mother to take my brother and me and 
follow them, which she hastened to do as fast as possible, but we
were not allowed time to put on our usual attire. They thrust
us into a close carriage. For fear of my mother alarming the
citizens they threw her to the ground and choked her until she
was nearly strangled, then pushed her into a coach. The night
was dark and dreary; the stars refused to shine, the moon to
shed her light.</p>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>'Tis not strange the heavenly orbs</l>
            <l>In silence blushed <corr>'</corr>neath Nature's sable garb</l>
            <l>When woman's gagged and rashly torn away</l>
            <l>Without blemish and without crime.</l>
            <pb id="jackson19" n="19"/>
            <l>Unheeded by God's holy word:—</l>
            <l>Unloose the fetters, break the chain, </l>
            <l>And make my people free again,</l>
            <l>And let them breath pure freedom's air </l>
            <l>And her rich bounty freely share. </l>
            <l>Let Eutopia stretch her bleeding hands abroad; </l>
            <l>Her cry <sic corr="of">f</sic> anguish finds redress from God.</l>
          </lg>
          <p>We were hurried along the streets. The inhabitants heard
our cries and rushed to their doors, but our carriage being 
perfectly tight and the alarm so sudden, that we were at the jail
before they could give us any relief. There were strong Union
men and officers in the city, and if they could have been 
informed of the human smuggling they would have released us.
But oh, that horrid, dilapidated prison, with its dim lights and
dingy walls, again presented itself to our view<corr>.</corr> My sister was
there first, and we were thrust in and remained there until three
o'clock the following afternoon. Could we have notified the 
police we should have been released, but, no opportunity was given 
us. It appears that this kidnapping had been in contemplation
from the time we were before taken and returned; and Captain
Tirrell's kindness to mother,—his benevolence towards Mr. Adams 
in assisting him to furnish his house,—his generosity in 
letting us work for ourselves,—his approbation in regard to the
contemplated marriage was only a trap. Thus instead of a
wedding Thursday evening, we were hurled across the ferry to
Albany Court House and to Kentucky through the rain and
without our outer garments. My mother had lost her bonnet 
and shawl in the struggle while being thrust in the coach,
consequently she had no protection from the storm, and the rest of 
us were in similar circumstances. I believe we passed through 
Springfield. I think it was the first stopping place after we 
left East St. Louis, and we were put on board the cars and
secreted in the gentlemen's smoking car, in which there were only 
a few rebels. We arrived in Springfield about twelve o'clock 
at night. When we took the cars it was dark, bleak and cold. 
It was the 18th of March, and as we were without bonnets and 
clothing to shield us from the sleet and wind, we suffered
<pb id="jackson20" n="20"/>
intensely. The old trader, for fear that mother might make her
escape, carried my brother, nine years of age, from one train to
the other. We then took the cars for Albany, and arrived
at eight o'clock in the morning. We were then carried on the
ferry in a wagon. There was another family in the wagon, in
the same condition. We landed at Portland, from thence to
Louisville, and were put into John Clark's trader's yard, and
sold out separately, except my mother and little brother, who
were sold together. Mother remained in the <sic corr="trader's yard">trader'syard</sic> two
weeks, my sister six<corr>,</corr> myself four.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>THE FARE AT THEIR NEW HOMES.</head>
          <p>Mother was sold to Captain Plasio, my sister to Benj Board,
and myself to Capt Ephraim Frisbee. The man who bought my
mother was it Spaniard. After she had been there a short 
time he tried to have my mother let my brother stop at his 
saloon, a very dissipated place; to wait upon his miserable crew, 
but my mother objected. In spite of her objections he took 
him down to try him, but some Union soldiers called at the 
saloon, and noticing that he vas very small, they questioned 
him, and my brother, child like, divulged the whole matter. 
The Captain, fearful of being betrayed and losing his property, 
let him continue with my mother. The Captain paid eight 
hundred dollars for my mother and brother. We were all sold 
for extravagant prices. My sister, aged sixteen, was sold for 
eight hundred and fifty dollars; I was sold for nine hundred 
dollars. This was in 1863<corr>.</corr> My mother was cook and fared 
very well. My sister was sold to a single gentleman, whose 
intended took charge of her until they were married, after which 
they took her to her home. She was her waiter, and fared as 
well as could be expected<corr>.</corr> I fared worse than either of the 
family. I was not allowed enough to eat, exposed to the cold,
and not allowed through the cold winter to thoroughly warm
myself once a month. The house was very large, and I could
gain no access to the fire. I was kept constantly at work of
<pb id="jackson21" n="21"/>
the heaviest kind,—compelled to move heavy trunks and boxes,—
many times to wash till ten and twelve o'clock at night.
There were three deaths in the family while I remained there,
and the entire burden was put upon me. I often felt to exclaim
as the Children of Israel did: “O Lord, my burden is greater
than I can bear.” I was then seventeen years of age. My
health has been impaired from that time to the present. I have
a severe pain in my side by the slightest over exertion. In the
Winter I suffer intensely with cold, and cannot get warm unless
in a room heated to eighty degrees. I am infirm and burdened
with the influence of slavery, whose impress will ever remain on
my mind and body. For six months I tried to make my escape.
I used to rise at four o'clock in the morning to find some one to
assist me, and at last I succeeded. I was allowed two hours
once in two weeks to go and return three miles. I could 
contrive no other way than to improve one of those opportunities,
in which I was finally successful. I became acquainted with
some persons who assisted slaves to escape by the underground
railroad. They were colored people<corr>.</corr> I was to pretend going
to church, and the man who was to assist and introduce me to
the proper parties was to linger on the street opposite the house,
and I was to follow at a short distance. On Sunday evening I
begged leave to attend church, which was reluctantly granted if
I completed all my work, which was no easy task. It appeared
as if my mistress used every possible exertion to delay me from
church, and I concluded that her old cloven-footed companion
had impressed his intentions on her mind. Finally, when I was
ready to start, my mistress took a notion to go out to ride, and
desired me to dress her little boy, and then get ready for
church. Extensive hoops were then worn, and as I had attached
my whole wardrobe under mine by a cord around my waist, it
required considerable dexterity and no small amount of maneuvering 
to hide the fact from my mistress. While attending to
the child I had managed to stand in one corner of the room, for
fear she might come in contact with me, and thus discover that
<pb id="jackson22" n="22"/>
my hoops were not so elastic as they usually are. I endeavored
to conceal my excitement by backing and edging very 
genteelly out of the door. I had nine pieces of clothing thus 
concealed on my person, and as the string which fastened them was
small it caused me considerable discomfort. To my great 
satisfaction I at last passed into the street, and my master and
mistress drove down the street in great haste and were soon out
of sight<corr>.</corr> I saw my guide patiently awaiting me. I followed
him at a distance until we arrived at the church, and there met
two young ladies, one of whom handed me a pass and told me
to follow them at a square's distance. It was now twilight.
There was a company of soldiers about to take passage across
the ferry, and I followed. I showed my pass, and proceeded up
the stairs on the boat. While thus ascending the stairs, the
cord which held my bundle of clothing broke, and my feet 
became entangled in my wardrobe, but by proceeding, the first step
released one foot and the next the other. This was observed
only by a few soldiers, who were too deeply engaged in their
own affairs to interfere with mine. I seated myself in a remote
corner of the boat, and in a few moments I landed on free soil
for the first time in my life, except when hurled through Albany
and Springfield at the time of our capture. I was now under
my own control. The cars were waiting in Jefferson City for
the passengers for Indianapolis, where we arrived about nine
o'clock.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>MATTIE IN INDIANAPOLIS.—THE GLORY OF FREEDOM.—<lb/>
PRESIDENT LINCOLN'S REMAINS EXHIBITED.</head>
          <p>My first business, after my arrival at Indianapolis was to find
a boarding place<corr sic="."/> in which I at once succeeded, and in a few
hours thereafter was at a place of service of my own choice<corr>.</corr> I
had always been under the yoke of oppression, compelled to
submit to its laws, and not allowed to advance a rod from the
house, or even out of call, without a severe punishment. Now
this constant fear and restless yearning was over. It appeared
<pb id="jackson23" n="23"/>
as though I had emerged into a new world, or had never lived
in the old one before. The people I lived with were Unionists,
and became immediately interested in teaching and encouraging
<sic>ing</sic> me in my literary advancement and all other important 
improvements, which precisely met the natural desires for which
my soul had ever yearned since my earliest recollection. I
could read a little, but was not allowed to learn in slavery. I
was obliged to pay twenty-five cents for every letter written
for me. I now began to feel that as I was free I could learn to
write, as well as others; consequently Mrs. Harris, the lady
with whom I lived, volunteered to assist me. I was soon 
enabled to write quite a legible hand, which I find a great 
convenience. I would advise all, young, middle aged or old, in a
free country, to learn to read and write. If this little book
should fall into the hands of one deficient of the important
knowledge of writing I hope they will remember the old maxim:—
“Never <sic corr="too">to</sic> old to learn.” Manage your own secrets, and
divulge them by the silent language of your own pen. Had our
blessed President considered it too humiliating to learn in 
advanced years, our race would yet have remained under the 
galling yoke of oppression. After I had been with Mrs. Harris
seven months, the joyful news came of the surrender of Lee's
army and the capture of Richmond.</p>
          <lg type="verse">
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Whilst the country's hearts were throbbing,</l>
              <l>Filled with joy for victories won;</l>
              <l>Whilst the stars and stripes were waving</l>
              <l>O'er each cottage, ship and dome,</l>
              <l>Came upon like winged lightning</l>
              <l>Words that turned each joy to dread,</l>
              <l>Froze with horror as we listened:</l>
              <l>Our beloved chieftain, Lincoln's dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>War's dark clouds has long held o'er us,</l>
              <l>They have rolled their gloomy fold's away,</l>
              <l>And all the world is anxious, waiting</l>
              <l>For that promised peaceful day.</l>
              <l>But that fearful blow inflicted,</l>
              <l>Fell on his devoted head,</l>
              <l>And from every town and hamlet</l>
              <l>Came the cry our Chieftain's dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb id="jackson24" n="24"/>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Weep, weep, O bleeding nation</l>
              <l>For the patriot spirit fled,</l>
              <l>All untold our century's future—</l>
              <l>Buried with the silent dead.</l>
              <l>God of battles, God of nations to our country send relief</l>
              <l>Turn each lamentation into joy whilst we mourn our murdered chief.</l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
          <p>On the Saturday after the assassination of the President there
was a meeting held on the Common, and a vote taken to have
the President's body brought through Indianapolis, for the 
people to see his dear dead face. The vote was taken by raising
the hands, and when the question was put in favor of it a thousand 
black hands were extended in the air, seemingly higher
and more visible than all the rest. Nor were their hands alone
raised, for in their deep sorrow and gloom they raised their
hearts to God, for well they knew that He, through martyred
blood, had made them free. It was some time before the remains
reached Indianapolis, as it was near the last of the route.
The body was placed in the centre of the hall of the
State House, and we marched in by fours, and divided into
twos on each side of the casket, and passed directly through the
Hall. It was very rainy,—nothing but umbrellas were to be
seen in any direction. The multitude were passing in and out
from eight o'clock in the morning till four o'clock in the afternoon. 
His body remained until twelve o'clock in the evening,
many distinguished persons visiting it, when amid the booming
of cannon, it moved on its way to Springfield, its final resting-place. 
The death of the President was like an electric shock
to my soul. I could not feel convinced of his death until I
gazed upon his remains, and heard the last roll of the muffled
drum and the farewell boom of the cannon. I was then 
convinced that though we were left to the tender mercies of God,
we were without a leader.</p>
          <lg type="verse">
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Gone, gone is our chieftain,</l>
              <l>The tried and the true;</l>
              <l>The grief of our nation the world never knew.</l>
              <l>We mourn as a nation has never yet mourned;</l>
              <l>The foe to our freedom more deeply has scorned.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb id="jackson25" n="25"/>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>In the height of his glory in manhood's full prime,</l>
              <l>Our country's preserver through darkest of time;</l>
              <l>A merciful being, whose kindness all shared</l>
              <l>Shown mercy to others. Why was he not spared?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>The lover of Justice, the friend of the slave,</l>
              <l>He struck at oppression and made it a grave;</l>
              <l>He spoke for our bond-men, and chain's from them fell,</l>
              <l>By making them soldiers they served our land well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Because he had spoken from sea unto sea</l>
              <l>Glad tidings go heavenward, our country is free,</l>
              <l>And angels I'm thinking looked down from above,</l>
              <l>With sweet smiles approving his great works of love.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>His name with the honor forever will live,</l>
              <l>And time to his laurels new lustre will give;</l>
              <l>He lived so unselfish, so loyal and true,</l>
              <l>That his deeds will shine brighter at every view.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Then honor and cherish the name of the brave,</l>
              <l>The champion of freedom, the friend to the slave,</l>
              <l>The far-sighted statesman who saw a fair end,</l>
              <l>When north land and south land one flag shall defend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Rest, rest, fallen chieftain, thy labors are o'er,</l>
              <l>For thee mourns a nation as never before;</l>
              <l>Farewell honored chieftain whom millions adore,</l>
              <l>Farewell gentle spirit, whom heaven has won.</l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>SISTER LOST.—MOTHER'S ESCAPE.</head>
          <p>In two or three weeks after the body of the President was
carried through, my sister made her escape, but by some means
we entirely lost trace of her. We heard she was in a free State.
In three months my mother also escaped. She rose quite early
in the morning, took my little brother, and arrived at my place
of service in the afternoon. I was much surprised, and asked
my mother how she came there. She could scarcely tell me
for weeping, but I soon found out the mystery. After so many
long years and so many attempts, for this was her seventh, she
at last succeeded, and we were now all free. My mother had
been a slave for more than forty-three years, and liberty was
very sweet to her. The sound of freedom was music in our
ears; the air was pure and fragrant; the genial rays of the
<pb id="jackson26" n="26"/>
glorious sun burst forth with a new lustre upon us, and all
creation resounded in responses of praise to the author and creator 
of him who proclaimed life and freedom to the slave. I was 
overjoyed with my personal freedom, but the joy at my mother's 
escape was greater than anything I had ever known. It was 
a joy that reaches beyond the tide and anchors in the harbor of 
eternal rest. While in oppression, this eternal life-preserver
had continually wafted her toward the land of freedom, which
she was confident of gaining, whatever might betide. Our joy
that we were permitted to mingle together our earthly bliss in
glorious strains of freedom was <sic corr="indescribable">indiscribable</sic>. My mother 
responded with the children of Israel,—“The Lord is my strength
and my song. The Lord is a man of war, and the Lord is his
name.” We left Indianapolis the day after my mother arrived, 
and took the cars at eleven o'clock the following evening for St.
Louis, my native State. We were then free, and instead of 
being hurried along, bare headed and half naked, through cars 
and boats, by a brutal master with a bill of sale in his pocket, 
we were our own, comfortably clothed, and having the true
emblems of freedom.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>MOTHER'S MARRIAGE.</head>
          <p>It appeared to me that the city presented an entirely new
aspect. The reader will remember that my mother was engaged
to be married on the evening after we were kidnapped, and that
Mr. Adams, her intended, had prepared the house for the
occasion. We now went in search of him. He had moved about five 
miles into the country. He had carefully preserved his furniture 
and was patiently awaiting our return. We were gone two 
years and four months. The clothing and furniture which we
had collected were all destroyed. It was over a year after we 
left St. Louis before we heard from there. We went immediately
from the cars to my aunt's, and from there went to Mr. 
Adams' residence and took him by surprise. They were married 
in a week after our return. My mother is comfortably 
<pb id="jackson27" n="27"/>
situated on a small farm with a kind and affectionate companion,
with whom she had formed an early acquaintance, and from
whom she had been severed by the ruthless hand of Wrong; 
but by the divine hand of Justice they were now reunited forever.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>MATTIE MEETS HER OLD MASTER.—GOES TO SERVICE.—IS SENT 
<lb/>FOR BY HER STEP-FATHER IN LAWRENCE, MASS.</head>
          <p>In a short time I had selected a place of service, and was
improving my studies in a small way. The place I engaged was
in the family where I was born, where my mother lived when
my father Jackson made his escape. Although Mr. Canory's
family were always kind to us, I felt a great difference between
freedom and slavery. After I had been there a short time my
step-father sent for me and my half brother to come to 
Lawrence. He had been waiting ever since the State was free,
hoping to get some account of us. He had been informed, 
previously, that mother, in trying to make her escape, had perished
by the way, and the children also, but he was never satisfied.
He was aware that my aunt was permanently in St. Louis, as
her master had given her family their freedom twenty years
previous. She was formerly owned by Major Howe, harness
and leather dealer, yet residing in St. Louis. And long may
he live and his good works follow him and his posterity forever.
My father well knew the deception of the rebels, and was 
determined to persevere until he had obtained a satisfactory 
account of his family. A gentleman moved directly from 
Lawrence to St<corr>.</corr> Louis, who made particular enquiries for us, and
even called at my aunt's. We then heard directly from my 
father, and commenced correspondence. He had not heard 
directly from us since he made his escape, which was nine years.
He had never heard of his little son who my mother was 
compelled by Mrs. Lewis to confine in a box. He was born eight
months after he left. As soon as possible after my mother 
consented to let my little brother go to his father he sent means to
<pb id="jackson28" n="28"/>
assist us to make preparations for our journey to the North. At
first he only sent for his little son. My mother was anxious
about sending him alone. He was only eleven years old, and
perfectly unused to traveling and had never been away from
his mother. Finally my father came to the conclusion that, as
my mother had endured such extreme hardships and sufferings
during the nine years he was not permitted to participate or
render her any assistance<corr sic="."/> that it would 
afford him much pleasure 
in sending for us both, bearing our expenses and making us
as comfortable as his means would allow. Money was sent us,
and our kind friend, Mr. Howe, obtained our tickets and 
voluntarily assisted us in starting. We left for the North on 
Monday, April 9th, and arrived, safe and sound, on the 11th. We
found my step-father's residence about six o'clock in the evening. 
He was not expecting us till the next day. Our meeting
is better imagined than told<corr>.</corr> I cannot describe 
it<corr>.</corr> His little
son was only two years old when he left, and I was eleven, and
we never expected to meet him again this side of eternity. It
was Freedom that brought us together. My father was 
comfortably situated in a nice white cottage, containing some eight
rooms, all well furnished, and attached to it was a fine garden.
His wife, who is a physician, was absent, but returned on the
following day. The people were kind and friendly. They 
informed me there was no other colored family in the city, but my
step-mother was continually crowded with friends and customers
without distinction. My step-mother had buried her only son,
who returned from the war in a decline. The white friends
were all in deep sympathy with them. I felt immediately at
home among such kind and friendly people, and have never felt
homesick, except when I think of my poor mother's farewell 
embrace when she accompanied us to the cars. As soon as my
step-mother had arrived, and our excitement was over, they 
commenced calculating upon placing me in the Sabbath school at
the church where my mother belonged. On the next Sabbath I
accompanied her and joined the Sabbath school, she occupying a
<pb id="jackson29" n="29"/>
side seat about middle way up the house. I was not reminded of
my color except by an occasional loafer or the Irish, usually the
colored man's enemy. I was never permitted to attend a white
church before, or ride in any public conveyance without being
placed in a car for the especial purpose; and in the street cars
we were not permitted to ride at all, either South or West.
Here I ride where I please, without the slightest remark, except
from the ignorant. Many ask me if I am contented. They
can imagine by the above contrast<corr>.</corr> My brother and myself 
entered the public school, and found a host of interested friends and
formed many dear acquaintances whom I shall never forget.
After attending school a month the term closed. I advanced in
my studies as fast as could be expected. I never attended school
but one month before. I needed more attention than my kind
teacher could possibly bestow upon me, encumbered as she was
by so many small children. Mother then proposed my entering
some select school and placing myself entirely under its discipline 
and influence. I was much pleased with the idea, but as
they had already been to so much expense for me, I could not
wish to place them under any heavier contribution<corr>.</corr> I had 
previously told my step-mother my story, and how often my own
mother had wished she could have it published. I did not 
imagine she could find time to write and arrange it, but she 
immediately proposed writing and publishing the entire story, by the
sale of which I might obtain the aid towards completing my
studies. I am glad I came to the old Bay State, the people of
which the rebels hate with an extreme hatred. I found it just
such a place as I had imagined by the appearance of the 
soldiers and the kindness they manifested.</p>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>New England, that blessed land,</l>
            <l>All in a happy Union band;</l>
            <l>They with the needy share their bread</l>
            <l>And teach the weak the Word of God.</l>
          </lg>
          <p>We never heard from my sister Hester, who made her escape
from Kentucky, except when she was on the cars, though we
have no doubt she succeeded in gaining her freedom.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <pb id="jackson30" n="30"/>
          <head>SUMMARY.</head>
          <p>On my return to St. Louis I met my old master, Lewis,
who strove so hard to sell us away that he might avoid seeing
us free, on the street. He was so surprised that before he was
aware of it he dropped a bow. My mother met Mrs. Lewis, her
old mistress, with a large basket on her arm, trudging to market. 
It appeared she had lived to see the day when her
children had to wait upon themselves, and she likewise. The
Yankees had taken possession, and her posterity were on an
equality with the black man. Mr. Lewis despised the Irish,
and often declared he would board at the hotel before he would
employ Irish help, but he now has a dissipated Irish cook.
When I was his slave I was obliged to keep away every fly from
the table, and not allow one to light on a person. They are now
compelled to brush their own flies and dress themselves and
children. Mr. Lewis' brother Benjamin was a more severe
slave master than the one who owned me. He was a tobacconist
and very wealthy. As soon as the war commenced he turned
Unionist to save his property. He was very severe in his 
punishments. He used to extend his victim, fastened to a beam,
with hands and feet tied, and inflict from fifty to three hundred
lashes, laying their flesh entirely open, then bathe their quivering 
wounds with brine, and, through his nose, in a slow rebel
tone he would tell them “You'd better walk a fair chalk line
or else I'll give yer twice as much.” His former friends, the
guerrillas, were aware he only turned Union to save his cash,
and they gave those persons he had abused a large share of his
luxury. They then, in the presence of his wife and another
distinguished lady, tortured him in a most inhuman manner.
For pretending Unionism they placed him on a table and threatened 
to dissect him alive if he did not tell them where he kept
his gold. He immediately informed them. They then stood
him against the house and fired over his head. From that, they
changed his position by turning him upside down, and raising
him two feet from the floor, letting him dash his head against
<pb id="jackson31" n="31"/>
the floor until his skull was fractured, after which he lingered
awhile and finally died. There was a long piece published in
the paper respecting his repentance, benevolence, &amp;c. All the
slaves who ever lived in his family admit the Lord is able to
save to the uttermost. He saved the thief on the cross, and 
perhaps he saved him.</p>
          <p>When I made my escape from slavery I was in a query how
I was to raise funds to bear my expenses. I finally came to the
conclusion that as the laborer was worthy of his hire, I thought
my wages should come from my master's pocket. Accordingly
I took twenty-five dollars. After I was safe and had learned to
write, I sent him a nice letter, thanking him for the kindness
his pocket bestowed to me in time of need. I have never 
received any answer to it.</p>
          <p>When I complete my education, if my life is spared, I shall
endeavor to publish further details of our history in another
volume from my own pen.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <head>CHRISTIANITY.</head>
        <p>Christianity is a system claiming God for its author, and the
welfare of man for its object. It is a system so uniform, exalted
and pure, that the loftiest intellects have acknowledged its
influence, and acquiesced in the justness of its claims. Genius
has bent from his erratic course to gather fire from her altars,
and pathos from the agony of Gethsemane and the sufferings of
Calvary<corr>.</corr> Philosophy and science have paused amid their 
speculative researches and wonderous revelations, to gain wisdom
from her teachings and knowledge from her precepts. Poetry
has culled her fairest flowers and wreathed her softest, to bind
her Author's “bleeding brow.” Music has strung her sweetest
<pb id="jackson32" n="32"/>
lyres and breathed her noblest strains to celebrate His fame;
whilst Learning has bent from her lofty heights to bow at the
lowly cross. The constant friend of man, she has stood by him 
in his hour of greatest need<corr>.</corr> She has cheered the prisoner in 
his cell, and strengthened the martyr at the stake. She has 
nerved the frail and sinking heart of woman for high and holy
deeds. The worn and weary have rested their fainting heads
upon her bosom, and gathered strength from her words and
courage from her counsels. She has been the staff of decrepit
age, and the joy of manhood in its strength. She has bent over
the form of lovely childhood, and suffered it to have a place in
the Redeemer's arms. She has stood by the bed of the dying, 
and unveiled the glories of eternal life; gilding the darkness of
the tomb with the glory of the resurrection.</p>
        <p>Christianity has changed the moral aspect of nations. 
Idolatrous temples have crumbled at her touch, and guilt owned its
deformity in her presence. The darkest habitations of earth 
have been irradiated with heavenly light, and the death shriek
of immolated victims changed for ascriptions of praise to God
and <sic corr="the">tho</sic> Lamb. Envy and Malice have been rebuked by her
contented look, and fretful Impatience by her gentle and
resigned manner.</p>
        <p>At her approach, fetters have been broken, and men have risen
redeemed from dust, and freed from chains. Manhood has
learned its dignity and worth, its kindred with angels, and
alliance to God.</p>
        <p>To man, guilty, fallen and degraded man, she shows a fountain
drawn from the Redeemer's veins; there she bids him wash 
and be clean. She points him to “Mount Zion, the city of the 
living God, to an innumerable company of angels, to the spirits 
of just men made perfect, and to Jesus the Mediator of the new
Covenant,” and urges him to rise from the degradation of sin,
renew his nature and join with them. She shows a pattern so
spotless and holy, so elevated and pure, that he might shrink
from it discouraged, did she not bring with her a promise from
<pb id="jackson33" n="33"/>
the lips of Jehovah, that he would give power to the faint, and
might to those who have no strength. Learning may bring her
ample pages and her ponderous records, rich with the spoils of
every age, gathered from every land, and gleaned from every
source. Philosophy and science may bring their abstruse
researches and wonderous revelations—Literature her elegance,
with the toils of the pen, and the labors of the pencil—but they
are idle tales compared to the truths of Christianity. They may
cultivate the intellect, enlighten the understanding, give scope
to the imagination, and refine the sensibilities; but they open
not to our dim eyes and longing vision, the land of crystal
founts and deathless flowers. Philosophy searches earth; Religion
opens heaven. Philosophy doubts and trembles at the 
portals of eternity; Religion lifts the veil, and shows us golden
streets, lit by the Redeemer's countenance, and irradiated by
his smile. Philosophy strives to reconcile us to death; Religion 
triumphs over it. Philosophy treads amid the pathway of stars, 
and stands a delighted listener to the music of the spheres; but 
Religion gazes on the glorious palaces of God, while the harpings
of the blood-washed, and the songs of the redeemed, fall
upon her ravished ear. Philosophy has her place; Religion her
important sphere; one is of importance here, the other of
infinite and vital importance both here and hereafter.</p>
        <p>Amid ancient lore the Word of God stands unique and
preeminent. Wonderful in its construction, admirable in its
adaptation, it contains truths that a child may comprehend, and 
mysteries into which angels desire to look. It is in harmony with
that adaptation of means to ends which pervades creation, from 
the <sic corr="polypous">polypus</sic> tribes, elaborating their coral homes, to man, the
wondrous work of God. It forms the brightest link of that 
glorious chain which unites the humblest work of creation with the
throne of the infinite and eternal Jehovah. As light, with its
infinite particles and curiously blended colors, is suited to an eye
prepared for the alterations of day; as air, with its subtle and
invisible essence; is fitted for the delicate organs of respiration;
<pb id="jackson34" n="34"/>
and, in a word, as this material world is adapted to man's 
physical nature; so the word of eternal truth is adapted to his moral
nature and mental constitution<corr>.</corr> It finds him wounded, sick
and suffering, and points him to the balm of Gilead and the
Physician of souls. It finds him stained by transgressions and
defiled with guilt, and directs him to the “blood that cleanseth
from all unrighteousness and sin.” It finds him athirst and
faint, pining amid the deserts of life, and shows him the wells
of salvation and the rivers of life. It addresses itself to his
moral and spiritual nature, makes provision for his wants and
weaknesses, and meets his yearnings and aspirations. It is
adapted to his mind in its earliest stages of progression, and its
highest state of intellectuality. It provides light for his darkness,
joy for his anguish, a solace for his woes, balm for his
wounds, and heaven for his hopes. It unveils the unseen world,
and reveals him who is the light of creation, and the joy of the
universe, reconciled through the death of His Son. It promises
the faithful a blessed re-union in a land undimmed with tears,
undarkened by sorrow. It affords a truth for the living and a
refuge for the dying. Aided by the Holy Spirit, it guides us
through life, points out the shoals, the quicksands and hidden
rocks which endanger our path, and at last leaves us with the
Eternal God for our refuge, and his everlasting arms for our
protection.</p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>