<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % external-entities SYSTEM "./extEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY % internal-entities SYSTEM "./intEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY leefp1 SYSTEM "leefp1.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY leefp2 SYSTEM "leefp2.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY leetp SYSTEM "leetp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>HISTORY OF THE LIFE OF REV. WM. MACK LEE</emph>
<emph>BODY SERVANT OF GENERAL ROBERT E. LEE THROUGH THE CIVIL WAR</emph>
<emph> COOK FROM 1861 TO 1865:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Lee, William Mack, b. 1835</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Fiona Mills</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by</resp>
          <name>Fiona Mills</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Carlene Hempel  and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1999</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca. 100K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1999.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note anchored="yes">Call number   E185.97.L48  1918       
(Rare Book Collection, UNC-CH)</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>History of the Life of Rev. Wm. Mack Lee</title>
<title>Body Servant of General Robert E. Lee Through the Civil War</title>
<title>... Cook from 1861 to 1865 ...</title>
<author>Lee,  Wm. Mack</author><imprint><pubPlace>[Norfolk, Va.]</pubPlace><publisher>[The Smith Printing Company]</publisher><date>1918</date></imprint></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South, Beginnings to 1920.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Pagination added to the electronic edition.</p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Lee, William Mack, b. 1835.</item>
            <item>Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870.</item>
            <item>United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 --
Anecdotes.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Virginia -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Clergy -- Virginia -- Biography.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>1999-05-04, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Sam McRae </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-03-31, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-03-30, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Carlene Hempel</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-03-24, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Fiona Mills</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="title page image">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="leetp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="first frontispiece image">
        <p>
          <figure id="frontis1" entity="leefp1">
            <p>“TRAVELER”<lb/>[1st Frontispiece Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="second frontispiece image">
        <p>
          <figure id="frontis2" entity="leefp2">
            <p>REV. WM. MACK LEE<lb/><hi rend="italics">Still Residing in the South</hi><lb/>[2nd Frontispiece Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">HISTORY OF THE LIFE OF
<lb/>
REV. WM. MACK LEE</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="main">BODY SERVANT OF
<lb/>
GENERAL ROBERT E. LEE
<lb/>
THROUGH THE CIVIL WAR</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="main">. . . COOK FROM 1861 to 1865 . . .</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <docImprint>
          <docDate><sic corr="Copyrighted">Copyrigthed</sic> year 1918, by Rev. Wm. Mack Lee 
<lb/>
STILL LIVING UNDER THE PROTECTION<lb/>
OF THE SOUTHERN STATES</docDate>
        </docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="Frontispiece">
        <list type="simple">
          <head>GENERAL ROBERT E. LEE AND OTHER GENERALS<lb/>
for whom Rev. William Mack Lee cooked four years<lb/>
during the Civil War, when he was servant to<lb/>
General Robert E. Lee—1861-1865</head>
          <item>Gen. Stonewall Jackson</item>
          <item>Gen. Ewell</item>
          <item>Gen. Mosby</item>
          <item>Gen. Bragg</item>
          <item>Gen. Elwell</item>
          <item>Gen. Anderson</item>
          <item>Gen. Pickett</item>
          <item>Gen. Early</item>
          <item>Gen. Longstreet</item>
          <item>Gen. Jos. E. Johnston</item>
          <item>Gen. Sidney E. Johnston</item>
          <item>Gen. Morgan</item>
          <item>Gen. Forrest</item>
          <item>Gen. J. B. Hood</item>
          <item>Gen. Kirby Smith</item>
          <item>Gen. Chambers</item>
          <item>Gen. Van Dorn</item>
          <item>Gen. Buell</item>
          <item>Gen. J. E. B. Stuart</item>
          <item>Gen. A. P. Hill</item>
          <item>Gen. D. H. Hill</item>
          <item>Gen. Fitzhugh Lee</item>
          <item>Gen. J. B. Gordon</item>
          <item>Gen. Harrison</item>
          <item>Gen. Price</item>
          <item>Gen. Billy Mahone</item>
          <item>Gen. Jefferson Davis</item>
          <item>Gen. Wilcox</item>
          <item>Gen. Fremont</item>
        </list>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="narrative">
        <pb id="lee3" n="3"/>
        <head>HISTORY OF THE LIFE<lb/>
of Rev. Wm. Mack Lee</head>
        <p>I was born June 12, 1835, Westmoreland County, Va.;
82 years ago. I was raised at Arlington Heights, in the house of
General Robert E. Lee, my master. I was cook for Marse
Robert, as I called him, during the civil war and his body
servant. I was with him at the first battle of
Bull Run, second battle of Bull Run, first battle of Manassas,
second battle of Manassas and was there at the fire of the last
gun for the salute of the surrender on Sunday,
April 9, 9 o'clock, A. M., at <sic corr="Appomattox">Appomatox</sic>, 1865.</p>
        <p>The following is a list of co-generals who fought with Marse
Robert in the Confederate Army: Generals Stonewall Jackson,
Early, Longstreet, Kirby, Smith, Gordon from Augusta<corr>,</corr> Ga.
Beauregard from Charleston, S. C., Wade Hampton, from
Columbia, S. C., Hood, from Alabama, Ewell Harrison from
Atlanta, Ga., Bragg, cavalry general from
Chattanooga, Tenn., Wm. Mahone of Virginia, Pickett, Forest, of
Mississippi, Mosby, of Virginia, Willcox, of Tennessee, Lyons,
of Mississippi, Charlimus, of Mississippi, Sydney
Johnston, Fitzhugh Lee, nephew of Marse Robert, and
Curtis Lee, his son.</p>
        <p>The writer of this little book, the body servant of Gen.
Robert E. Lee, had the pleasure of feeding all these men at the
headquarters in Petersburg, the battles of Decatur, Seven Pines,
the Wilderness, on the plank road between
Fredericksburg and Orange County Court House,
Chancellorsville, The Old Yellow Tavern, in the Wilderness, Five
Forks, Cold Harbor, Sharpsburg, Boonesville, Gettysburg, New
Market, Mine Run, Cedar Mountain, Civilian, Louisa Court
House, Winchester and Shenandoah Valley.</p>
        <p>At the close of the struggle, General Lee said to General
Grant: “Grant, you didn't whip me, you just overpowered me, I
surrender this day 8,000 men; I do not surrender them to you,
I surrender on conditions; it shall not go down in history I
surrendered the <sic corr="Northern">Northen</sic> Confederate Army of Virginia to you. It
shall go down in history I surrendered on <sic corr="conditions">conditins</sic>;
you have ten men to my one; my
<pb id="lee4" n="4"/>
men, too, are barefooted and hungry. If Joseph E. Johnston
could have gotten to me three days ago I would have cut my
way through and gone back into the mountains of North
Carolina and would have given you a happy time.”
What these conditions were I do not know, but I know
these were Marse Robert's words on the morning of the
surrender: “I surrender to you on conditions.”</p>
        <p>At the close of the war I did not know A from B,
although I had been preaching two years before the war.
I was married six years before the war. My wife died in 1910.
I am the father of eight daughters and I have twenty-one
grand children and eight great-grand children. My youngest
child is 42 years old.</p>
        <p>I was raised by one of the greatest men in the world.
There was never one born of a woman greater than Gen.
Robert E. Lee, according to my judgment. All of his
servants were set free ten years before the war, but all
remained on the plantation until after the surrender.</p>
        <p>The following from the Bedford Bulletin, a paper published
in the town of Bedford, Va., which town I am now visiting,
situated in the mountains in full view of the famous Peaks
of Otter; while soliciting means here to finish my church near
Norfolk, I caught inspiration to give the readers of this little
book, my friends, and friends and admirers of Marse Robert,
a brief history of his body servant and cook, the Rev. William
Mack Lee, and will, I hope, cause you to purchase one at the
price named on back of same, as I will never be able to write
another; I am too old.</p>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head>Lee's Body Servant Here.</head>
          <p>“Rev. William Mack Lee, one of the best known colored men
in the South, is in town this week making an effort to raise funds
to complete the payment on his church near Norfolk. He is a
Baptist minister and built the church at a cost of $5,500, of which
all has been paid except about $500, and he wants to raise this
before he returns home.</p>
          <p>“He was born on the plantation of Gen. Robert E. Lee, in
Westmoreland County, 81 years ago, and at the outbreak
of the civil war went to the front as the body servant of
his distinguished master. He cooked and waited on the
Southern <sic corr="chieftain">chieftian</sic> during the entire four years of the war,
being with him at the surrender at Appomatox. The fact that
the war had set him free was of small moment to him, and
he stayed with his old master until his death. He is a negro
of the old type, distinguished looking, polite in manner,
and, despite his age, is straight, firm of step and
<pb id="lee5" n="5"/>
bids fair to serve his congregation for many more years. The
first day he was in town, he went to the old Burwell
homestead, now the home of Mr. John Ballard, because he
and his master had stopped there while on a visit to Bedford,
soon after the war, and was greatly disappointed to
find that the last member of the Burwell family was dead.</p>
          <p>“He will be in town all of this week, and if you want to
help him pay for his church you will find him on the streets
or some one will tell you where he can be found.<corr>”</corr></p>
          <p>I have been preaching the gospel of Jesus Christ the best
I knew, with my limited preparation, for 57 years. My master,
at his death, left me $360 to educate myself with. I went
to school. I studied hard at the letter, but my greatest learning
came from Jesus Christ. God sent me out to preach, and
when God sends a man out, he is qualified both
with the Holy Ghost and the Spirit. He makes his words
sharp as a two-edged sword, and his feet as a burning
pillar of brass.</p>
          <p>I was ordained in Washington, D.C., July 12, 1881,
as a Missionary Baptist preacher. The beginning of my
work as an ordained minister was with the Third Baptist
Church, Northwest, Washington, D.C., which I built with
20 members, at a cost of $3,000. This church increased
from 20 to 500 members during my pastorate. I also built
another church in the same city, a frame building, 20 x 36
feet long, at a cost of $2,000. I took this church with 8
members and left it with 200 at the close of two years.</p>
          <p>My next pastorate was at Cantorsville, about eight miles
northeast of Baltimore, Md., in Baltimore county. There
were 12 members of this church, when I took charge. I
erected for a house of worship a frame building 22 x 38
at a cost of $3,500. At the end of four years the membership
had increased from 12 members to 365. I resigned
this charge and took a church in Norfolk county, Virginia,
six miles from the city of Norfolk. In this little town
called Churchland, I erected a brick building, stone front,
for a house of worship, at a cost of $5,500, in the year 1912,
all of which has been paid, with the exception of about $500.
When I began the building of this last house for God,
I sought aid from abroad. I went into three states and
by the help of the Lord, and good friends of Virginia, North
and South Carolina, I have succeeded in raising over
$5,000 for this last project. I preached in 36 counties in
South Carolina in 1915, 28 counties in North Carolina,
and 23 counties in Virginia. The following is a <sic corr="list">lst</sic> of cities
and towns that responded to my call for help in relieving
the <sic corr="indebtedness">ndebtedness</sic>
<pb id="lee6" n="6"/>
of my church:—Virginia: Norfolk, Portsmouth, Berkley,
Brambleton, Newport News, Hampton, Cape Charles,
Eastville, Pocomoke City, Charles City, Suffolk, Lynchburg,
Danville, Crewe, Blackstone, Petersburg, Ivor, Waverley,
Zuni, Appomattox, Bedford, Roanoke and Hollins. South
Carolina: Columbia, Charleston, Summersville, Kingtree,
Lake City, Bennettsville, Florence, Mullen, Hartsville,
Darlington, Marion, Dillon, Latta, Sumpter, Spartansburg,
Orangeville, and Branchville. North Carolina: Raleigh, Wilmington,
Rocky Mount, Goldsboro, Greensville, Greensboro, Selma,
Clinton, Tarboro, Little Washington, Edenton, Elizabeth City,
Wilson, Windsor, Kinston, LaGrange Beaufort, Durham, Hamlet,
Rockingham, Gibsonville, Lovington, Ahoskie, Tunis, Reidsville,
Winchester.</p>
          <p>Having stayed on Marse Robert's plantation 18 years after the war
and with limited schooling, I am not ashamed to give my history to the
world that it might cause some of the young negroes who have school
advantages from childhood and early youth, to consider life more
seriously and if men of my type had lived in their time, how far they
would exceed them along lines of religious, educational and business
activities. I contribute my success to my teaching from God. When John
was writing on the Isle of Patmos, God appeared to him and said, “Write
no more, John, seal up what thou hast written.” John fell face foremost.
God said, “Rise upon your feet, fear not, I am he who was persecuted,
seal up what has been <sic corr="written">writen</sic> and write no more.” The
apostle Paul says the letter kills a man, but the word of God makes him
alive in our Lord Jesus Christ. A man gets nothing for starting a journey,
but gets pay for being faithful and, holding out to the end. If a man lives
according to the ten <sic corr="commandments">commandmants</sic>, he will be blessed, because the
chief word in the decalogue, obedience; and obedience to God is service
to man.</p>
          <p>In addition to my pastoral duties I found time to look
after the bodily wants of my fellowman as well as his spiritual needs.
To this end I organized the State Benevolent Association of Virginia,
for colored people, at Charlottesville in 1887. In 1888 I organized at
Washington, D. C., the Supreme Grand Lodge United States Benevolent
Association of the District of  Columbia. The district associations of Virginia,
Maryland, West Virginia, and Pennsylvania are under jurisdiction of the
Grand Lodge, whose office and building is located at 428 R Street, N. W.,
Washington. I am elected Grand Chief for life at a salary of $50 per month
and traveling expenses.</p>
          <pb id="lee7" n="7"/>
          <p>This association pays sick dues and death benefits and
aids its members while out of employment by allowing a
weekly sum of $2.00 for 4 weeks each, or until employment
is secured, and gives each unfortunate a chance to
pay back same to the Association in easy installments of
25 cents a month until the amount has been paid, so advanced by the
Association's Treasurer. The brotherhood requires its members
to help those find employment who are not employed.</p>
          <p>I have some gavels made out of the poplar where Marse
Robert bade farewell to his comrades and instructed them
to go home and make themselves good citizens and may
I urge those who read this book, especially my people, to take
the advice of the humble writer, try to make yourselves
good citizens by being industrious, save your money, educate
yourselves, buy property, etc., let your religion be
more practical and less sentimental. The best friends we
have are the Southern people who know all about our raising,
and if we colored people want to get along well with
the white people, we must show our behavior to, respect
and be obedient to them. These are my views to our race.</p>
          <closer><salute>Your respectable, obedient servant,</salute>
<signed>REV. WM. MACK LEE.
<lb/>
General Robert E. Lee's cook and body servant of the Civil War.</signed></closer>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <p>Still limping from a yankee bullet, an old darkey, with a grizzled
beard and an honest face, hobbled into the office of the World-News at
a busy hour yesterday.</p>
          <p>“Kin you white folks gimme a little money fur my church?” he
asked, doffing his tattered as he bowed.</p>
          <p>Typewriters tickled their hurried denial.</p>
          <p>The aged negro cocked his head on one side. “What,
I ain't gwine ter turn away Ole Marse Robert's nigger is
yer? You didn't know dat I was Gen. Robert Lee's cook all through de
wah, did yer?” Every reporter in the office considered that introduction
sufficient, and listened for half an hour to William Mack Lee, who
followed General Robert E. Lee as body guard and cook throughout the
Civil War. When the negro lifted his bent and broken figure from a chair
to take his leave every man in the office reached into his pocket,
for a contribution.</p>
          <pb id="lee8" n="8"/>
          <p>“The onliest time that Marse Robert ever scolded me,” said
William Mack Lee, “in de whole fo' years dat I followed him
through the wah, was, down in de Wilderness—Seven Pines—
near Richmond. I remembah dat day jes lak it was yestiday. Hit
was July the third, 1863.</p>
          <p>“Whilst we was in Petersburg, Marse Robert had done got
him a little black hen from a man and we named the little black
hen Nellie. She was a good hen, and laid mighty nar every day.
We kep' her in de ambulants, whar she had her nest.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head>Prepared Feast From Small Supply.</head>
          <p>“On dat day—July the third—we was all so hongry and I
didn't have nuffin in ter cook, dat I was jes' plumb bumfuzzled.
I didn't know what to do. Marse Robert, he had gone and invited a
crowd of ginerals to eat wid him, an' I had ter git de vittles. Dar
was Marse Stonewall Jackson, and Marse A. P. Hill, and Marse
D. H. Hill, and Marse Wade Hampton, Gineral Longstreet, and
Gineral Pickett and sum others.</p>
          <p>“I had done made some flanel cakes, a little tea, and some
lemonade, but I 'lowed as how dat would not be enuff fo' dem
gemm'n. So I had to go out to de ambulants and cotch de little
black hen, Nellie.</p>
          <p>There was a tear in William Mack Lee's voice, but in his eye I
fancied that I saw the happy light that always dances in the eyes
of his race at the thought of a fowl for cooking.</p>
          <p>“I jes' had to go out and cotch little Nellie. I picked her good,
and stuffed her with breod stuffin, mixed wid butter. Nellie
had been gwine wid us two years, and I hated fer to lose her.
We had been gettin' all our eggs from Nellie.</p>
          <p>“Well, sir, when I brung Nellie inter de commissary tent and
set her fo' Marse Robert he turned to me right fo' all dem
gimmin and he says: ‘William, now you have killed Nellie. What
are we going to do for eggs?”</p>
          <p>“‘I jes' had ter do it, Marse Robert.’ says I.</p>
          <p><corr>‘</corr>No, you didn't William; I'm going to write Miss Mary about
you. I'm going to tell her you have killed Nellie.’</p>
          <p>“Marse Robert kep' on scoldin' me mout dat hen. He never
scolded 'bout naything else. He tol' me I was a fool to kill de her
whut lay de golden egg. Hit made Marse Robert awful sad ter
think of anything bein' killed, whedder der 'twas one of his soljers,
or his little black hen.”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <pb id="lee9" n="9"/>
          <head>Lee Wept Over Jackson's Death.</head>
          <p>“I have even seed him cry. I never seed him sadder dan dat
gloomy mownin' when he tol' me 'bout how Gineral Stonewall
Jackson had been shot by his own men.</p>
          <p>“He muster hurd it befo' but he never tol' me til' nex'
mawnin'.</p>
          <p>“‘William,’ he says ter me, ‘William, I have lost my right
arm.’</p>
          <p>“‘How come yer ter say dat, Marse Robert?’ I axed him.
‘Yo ain't bin in no battle sence yestiddy, an' I doan see yo' arm
bleedin'.</p>
          <p>“‘I'm bleeding at the heart, William,’ he says, and I slipped
out'n de tent, 'cause he looked lak he wanted to be by hisself.</p>
          <p>“A little later I cum back an' he tol' me dat Gineral Jackson
had bin shot by one of his own soljers. The Gineral had tol' 'em to
shoot anybody goin' or comin' across de line. And den de Gineral
hisself puts on a federal uniform and scouted across de lines.
When he comes back, one of his own soljers raised his gun.</p>
          <p>“‘Don't shoot. I'm your general,’ Marse Jackson yelled.</p>
          <p>“‘Dey said dat de sentry was hard o' hearin'. Anyway, he
shot his Gineral an' kilt him.</p>
          <p>“‘I'm bleeding at the heart, William,’ Marse Robert kep' a
sayin'.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head>Tells of His Own Wounds.</head>
          <p>“On July de twelf, 1863, I was shot myself,” continued the
old darkey, heaving a deep sigh as he withdrew his thoughts from
the death of General Stonewall Jackson.</p>
          <p>“Yer see dat hole in my head? Dat whar a piece er de shell
hit me. Anudder piece struck me nigh de hip.</p>
          <p>“I had jes give Marse Robert his breakfas' an' went to git
old Traveler fer him to ride ter battle. Traveler was Marse
Robert's horse what followed him 'round same as a dog would,
and would never step on de dead men, but allers walked betwixt
and aroun' 'em.</p>
          <p>“I went out an' curried and saddled Traveler. I hyeard dem
jack battery guns begin to pop an' bust an' roah. I saddled
Traveler and tuck him in front o' Marse Robert's tent.</p>
          <pb id="lee10" n="10"/>
          <p>“Jes' as Marse Robert cum out'n his tent a shell hit 35 yards
away. It busted, and hit me, an' I fell over.</p>
          <p>“I must o' yelled, 'cause Marse Robert said he ain't never hyeard
no noise like de wan I hollered. He cum over and tried to cheer me up,
an' I hollered lak one o' dem jackass guns.</p>
          <p>“Marse Robert lafed so hard 'cause he said he ain't never seed a
nigger holler so loud. An' den he called for de ambulants an' dey tuck
me ter de hospital.”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head>Loyal to Famous Master.</head>
          <p>William Mack Lee has all the praise in the world for “Marse
Robert.” He tells many interesting incidents of the Southern hero's life
in the tent and field.</p>
          <p>The old negro is here now trying to raise $418 with which to
complete a fund of $5,000, most of which he has already secured, for
building a church. He has built four churches and is now working on his
fifth.</p>
          <p>Among the white churches contributing to his fund are nine
Baptist, eight Methodist, and six Episcopalians, in Norfolk, four <sic corr="Baptist">Baptst</sic>
in Danville, and churches in Lynchburg, Bedford, Crew, Blackstone and
Appomattox.</p>
          <p>William Mack Lee was born in Westmoreland County, Va., at the old
Stafford House, on the Potomac River, 1835. He is 84 years old. He was
raised by General Lee as his personal servant.</p>
          <p>“Tell de white folks heah to be good ter me an' my church,” says
William. ”Tell 'em not ter turn away Robert's ole nigger.”</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>