<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY barretp SYSTEM "barretp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>Gilbert Hunt, The City Blacksmith:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Barrett, Philip, 1838-1900
 </author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Sarah Reuning</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns"> Fiona Mills and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1999</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca. 60K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1999.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, 
teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is 
included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="title page"> Gilbert Hunt, The City Blacksmith</title>
            <author>Philip Barrett</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent> 34 p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>Richmond</pubPlace>
            <publisher>James Woodhouse &amp; Co.</publisher>
            <date>1859</date>
            <authority/>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="yes">Call number E444 H9 (Special Collections, The Library of Virginia)</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>This electronic edition has been transcribed from a photocopy provided 
by the Library of Virginia. </p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ 
and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines 
has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using 
Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st 
edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Hunt, Gilbert, 1780?-1863.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Virginia -- Biography.</item>
            <item>African American blacksmiths -- Virginia -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Virginia -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Theaters -- Accidents -- Virginia -- Richmond.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2000-04-06, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-10-28, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project 
manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-10-27, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Fiona Mills</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-10-18, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Sarah Reuning</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="title page image">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="barretp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">GILBERT HUNT,
The City Blacksmith:</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>BY</byline>
        <docAuthor>PHILIP BARRETT,<lb/>
AUTHOR OF “FLOWERS BY THE WAYSIDE,” &amp;C.</docAuthor>
        <epigraph>
          <q direct="unspecified">
            <lg type="verse">
              <l>Toiling—rejoicing, sorrowing,</l>
              <l>Onward through life he goes,</l>
              <l>Each morning sees some task begun,</l>
              <l>Each evening sees its close;</l>
              <l>Something attempted, something done,</l>
              <l>Has earned a night's repose.</l>
            </lg>
          </q>
          <bibl>
            <hi rend="italics">Longfellow's Village Blacksmith.</hi>
          </bibl>
        </epigraph>
        <epigraph>
          <q direct="unspecified">
            <p>Seest thou a man <hi rend="italics">diligent in his business?</hi> 
he shall stand before
kings; he shall not stand before mean men.</p>
          </q>
          <bibl><hi rend="italics">Proverbs, xxii:</hi> 29.</bibl>
        </epigraph>
        <docEdition>PRICE, FIFTY CENTS.</docEdition>
        <docImprint><pubPlace>RICHMOND:</pubPlace>
<publisher>JAMES WOODHOUSE &amp; CO.</publisher>
<docDate>1859.</docDate></docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="contents">
        <pb id="barrett3" n="3"/>
        <head>CONTENTS.</head>
        <list type="simple">
          <item>CHAPTER I.<lb/>
HIS EARLY LIFE.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER II.<lb/>
THE BURNING OF THE PENITENTIARY.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER III.<lb/>
HIS VISIT TO AFRICA.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER IV.<lb/>
THE VISIT OF LAFAYETTE.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER V.<lb/>
THE BURNING OF THE RICHMOND THEATRE.</item>
        </list>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="introduction">
        <pb id="barrett4" n="4"/>
        <p>GILBERT HUNT.—We stated in yesterday's issue that the
citizens of Richmond would soon have their attention directed to
this meritorious old negro, by an appeal to them for “material aid.”
He has already passed the ordinary limits of human life; “the
almond tree blossoms are now adorning his brow.” Towards him
the hearts of our citizens should be turned with the warmest, the
deepest gratitude. During three score years in humility of spirit has
he lived in our midst. No man can say ought against him.—High
integrity, true, generous-hearted, disinterestedness has always
marked his walk and conversation.</p>
        <p>During the war of 1812 he worked manfully, day and night, not
even resting on the Sabbath day when his services were required,
in preparing and mounting cannon for our defence against the
encroachments of a foreign foe. At the burning of the Richmond
Theatre he acted a part which attested alike his intrepidity and
philanthropy, by fearlessly risking his life in behalf of some of
our own citizens. Shall we neglect him in his old age, when the
arm which defended, and the hand which saved our fathers and
mothers are palsied with age? The same noble-hearted courage
was displayed by him at the memorable burning of our Penitentiary.</p>
        <p>We are glad to learn that a young gentleman, (the author of “Flowers
by the Wayside,”) known to most of our citizens, proposes
publishing a brief sketch of Gilbert's life and labors—the proceeds
of which are to be <sic corr="appropriated">approriated</sic> to the aid of this magnanimous old
negro. We feel assured that his effort will find a ready response in
the hearts of our citizens, who have never been backward in the
appreciation of whatever is true, and noble, and
generous.—<hi rend="italics">Richmond Whig, May 13th</hi>, 1859.</p>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="text">
        <pb id="barrett5" n="5"/>
        <head>GILBERT HUNT.</head>
        <div2 type="text">
          <head>CHAPTER I.
<lb/>
HIS EARLY LIFE.</head>
          <p>WITHIN the narrow limits of a small wooden tenement, on one of
the most retired and unfrequented lanes of the city of Richmond,
lives and labors our hero—blacksmith. For more than threescore
years has he been pursuing, in our city, his humble calling. And
though his head is “silver'd o'er with age,” even now the merry
ring of Gilbert's anvil may be heard at early dawn, saying to many
a tardy young man—<hi rend="italics">Be diligent in business</hi>. At his door hangs a
sign painted in rude, uncouth letters. It is made of sheet iron;
perhaps to save expense, perhaps to gratify the love of the old
blacksmith for the metal which
<pb id="barrett6" n="6"/>
has so long yielded him a support. Here is the sign—
<lb/>
GILBERT HUNT,<lb/>
BLACKSMITH.</p>
          <p>We shall make him, to a great extent, his own historian:—</p>
          <p>“I was born somewhere about the year 1780, in the county of
King William, at a place called the Piping Tree, long a celebrated
tavern on the Pamunkey river. My master at this time was
proprietor of the tavern. He was a gentleman of considerable
wealth.</p>
          <p>At the marriage of my master's youngest daughter, I was brought
to Richmond, and learned the carriage-making business under her
husband, at what is now the corner of Broad and 12th streets. I
was sold by my master to a gentleman, whose place of business
was what is at present Broad, between 9th and 10th streets. I served
him till his death—about four or five years. I was then again sold.
It was during the time I was owned by my last purchaser that the
war of 1812 occurred.</p>
          <p>I remember the occurrences of that day as well as if it were
yesterday. I worked eighteen
<pb id="barrett7" n="7"/>
months for the army, at my master's shop, which was situated on
the corner of Locust alley and Franklin street—directly opposite
the present Odd-Fellow's Hall. I ironed off carriages for the
cannon, mounting one every two days. We then had four forges
going constantly. I was also busily engaged in making pick-axes,
&amp;c., shoeing horses for the army, and such other work as was
needed. We worked day and night, not even stopping to rest on
the Sabbath day. I was also engaged in making
grappling hooks for boarding the vessels down at Norfolk. During
all this time, my master gave me complete control of the whole
shop.</p>
          <p>When the express came informing the people of the coming of
the British, fear came upon all our citizens. My master, thinking it
advisable for his family to be in the country, sent me out in
search of a convenient and pleasant situation. They were then
carried out of the enemy's reach. I then returned to my regular
work—preparing guns for our country's defence.</p>
          <p>During the absence of the family, my master's residence and all its
contents were left entirely in my charge, and had the British come
upon us, no American would have fought more
<pb id="barrett8" n="8"/>
bravely for the defence of his own home and fireside than I
would have done for the defence of my master's property; for he
never treated me like a servant, but rather like a member of his
own household. He never spoke a cross word to, nor struck me
a lick during his whole life.</p>
          <p>When my master's family returned, I gave up to them the house
and all its contents, just as they were when they were put into my
hands.</p>
          <p>I have always loved my master—I love him now.”</p>
          <p>And the noble-hearted old blacksmith stopped to wipe away a
<sic corr="tear">year</sic> which was stealing down his dusky cheek.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <pb id="barrett9" n="9"/>
          <head>CHAPTER II.<lb/>
THE BURNING OF THE PENITENTIARY.</head>
          <p>“THE night on which the Penitentiary
was burned, I was quietly sitting down at home. It was about
10 o'clock when the alarm was first sounded. As soon as I found
out where it was, I at once hurried to the place. I was then a
member of the fire company. When I got there, the flames were
rapidly doing their work. The wind was high, and we found it
impossible to get any water. The fire then was burning furiously
around the front entrance, thus shutting off all possible means of
escape. I shall never forget the awfulness of the scene. It seems
as plain before me, as if it had happened last night.</p>
          <p>The prisoners were all shut up in their cells, and we still found
it impossible to stop the flames. Oh! if you could have seen the
poor fellows countenances, lighted up by the red
light of the flames, and heard their piercing
cries, you couldn't have helped doing something
<pb id="barrett10" n="10"/>
to save them, even though they were cutthroats, and rogues.</p>
          <p>There was only <hi rend="italics">one</hi> way we could get them out, that was to cut
through the walls. But we couldn't get a ladder; so Captain — ,
one of the bravest firemen that ever lived, got on top my shoulders,
and cut a hole in the wall, through which we were able to get all
of the prisoners out without any injury. We handed them down,
one at a time, to the soldiers, who kept them from getting away.
During all this time the flames were spreading like wild-fire over
the whole building. But I was perfectly reckless; in fact, I forgot
all about the fire, though the flames were hissing, and popping, and
the flakes falling all around me.</p>
          <p>I was very much struck with the conduct of the last prisoner we
got out. Just as we were about pulling him out of the fire, he ran
back into his cell to get his Bible. Captain — 
hallooed to him, telling him he had better save himself, and let his
Bible alone. But the prisoner thought differently. May-be 'twas the
Bible his mother had given him when he was a boy.</p>
          <p>The prisoners were all marched on the capitol square, and kept
under guard.</p>
          <pb id="barrett11" n="11"/>
          <p>The next day I spent in making hand-cuffs for the poor fellows. I
didn't think, the night before, I should have this to do.”</p>
          <p>We could but think as our humble historian narrated the last
incident, how often do we find it the case, that him whom we
<hi rend="italics">save</hi> to-day, we must <hi rend="italics">hand-cuff</hi> tomorrow. Such is life.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <pb id="barrett12" n="12"/>
          <head>CHAPTER III.<lb/>
HIS VISIT TO AFRICA.</head>
          <p>“I SAILED in the ship Harriett, Captain Johnson, from Norfolk,
with one hundred and sixty souls on board. The weather was
bright and cheerful, and our passage out was very pleasant, with
the exception of a violent storm just before reaching the coast.
A storm at sea, was something I never saw before. And when I saw
the great waves rolling and pitching, and heard the wild winds
moaning through the rigging, and the timbers of the vessel
creaking and groaning like they were going to come to pieces
every minute, I was very much frightened. But presently the
winds died away, the waves became quiet and smooth again,
and the bright blue sky looked as clear as if a cloud had never
darkened it.</p>
          <p>On the 17th of March we came in sight of land—the land of
Africa—the land where my fathers died—the land whose soil
I long had desired to tread.</p>
          <p>On landing we went to the house of Jack
<pb id="barrett13" n="13"/>
Lewis, who had once lived in Richmond. He received us with
great cordiality. I <sic corr="stayed">staid</sic> with him until I could make arrangements
for my accommodation.</p>
          <p>The people looked very much like those I left at home. The
natives, at the colony, were almost in a state of nakedness. Two
or three of the boys (natives) waited on me with a great deal of
politeness. They spoke broken English quite well.</p>
          <p>The country was as beautiful as any I ever saw, and was thickly
covered with a heavy growth of trees common to that climate.</p>
          <p>The soil I also found quite rich, and produced nearly all the
grains and vegetables I had been used to at home.</p>
          <p>During my visit to Africa, I took a trip of several hundred miles
into the interior of the country. I found the people much more
intelligent than I had expected. They also treated me with the
greatest kindness, saying to me—‘If you come from Mr. Carey's
country (meaning America) you will be treated with great
kindness,’</p>
          <p>After remaining several weeks in this portion of the country, I
returned to the colony.</p>
          <p>During my trip I saw many things entirely
<pb id="barrett14" n="14"/>
new to me. There were numbers of vessels in one of the rivers
getting slaves for Cuba. It made my heart sick to witness the
cruelty with which they were treated. They were all securely
ironed to prevent their escape, and put up in stalls and fed, like
cattle, on wheat bran.</p>
          <p>I also saw a blacksmith, sitting down on the sand, his legs crossed
like a tailor's, his anvil, bellows, hammers, &amp;c., all around him.
Even in this position, he could beat me working all to pieces. I
really felt ashamed of myself. After all, these Africans are not
such barbarians as people make out.</p>
          <p>After remaining several months in and about the colony, I left for
home in the brig Liberia, Captain Sharp. Our voyage was very
pleasant, and in November I reached Philadelphia, having been
absent from America about eight months.</p>
          <p>I was the only passenger, with the exception of one native, who
was anxious to see our country. He, however, remained but a short
time before returning.</p>
          <p>I was met with great cordiality in Philadelphia, Baltimore and
Richmond. Since this time I have been quietly following my calling.</p>
          <p>I have <hi rend="italics">lived</hi> in Richmond, I have <hi rend="italics">labored</hi> in
<pb id="barrett15" n="15"/>
Richmond, I hope to <hi rend="italics">die</hi> and be <hi rend="italics">buried</hi> in Richmond.”</p>
          <p>We cannot close this chapter without adding a little anecdote,
which we very much suspect lies at the bottom of our
blacksmith's returning America.</p>
          <p>“Before leaving Richmond, Captain  — presented me with a
choice lot of sample tobacco, which I took out with me. I prized it
very highly; so much so, that I slept with it under my head during
the entire voyage. No sooner had we gotten to the coast, than a
number of the natives boarded our vessel. They kissed my hands,
and gave many other tokens of friendship. They looked so honest,
that I never once suspected anything wrong. They spoke broken
English quite well. They told me if I would give them my
sample tobacco, they would land me and all my goods. This I
readily consented to do. Just as soon, however, as they <hi rend="italics">got</hi> my
tobacco, they completely <hi rend="italics">forgot</hi> my language, and I couldn't get
one word out of them. They no speak English then. I paid them in
advance, only to find myself completely <hi rend="italics">sold</hi> by people whom I
thought were perfect barbarians.</p>
          <p>They were as wise as serpents, but not as
<pb id="barrett16" n="16"/>
harmless as doves. Our people told me afterwards they were perfect
<hi rend="italics">African Yankees</hi>.</p>
          <p>After this trick, I could not help sitting down, looking towards
America, taking a good cry, and saying to myself,</p>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>‘Carry me back to old Virginia.’ ”</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <pb id="barrett17" n="17"/>
          <head>CHAPTER IV.
<lb/>
THE VISIT OF LAFAYETTE.</head>
          <p>“THOUGH it has been some thirty-five or
forty years since Lafayette visited Richmond, yet I still remember
it very well (1824). He reached here in the winter. When he
landed at Rocketts, he was met by a large number of soldiers, and
thousands of visitors from all parts of the state.”</p>
          <p>We throw in a little extract from the pen of an eye witness.</p>
          <p>“Many a revolutionary soldier left the comforts of home to
welcome one who had partaken of the same dangers and
hardships; and mothers brought their children to see and to impress
on their youthful minds the memory of the man who was beloved
by Washington.”</p>
          <p>We resume our narrative—</p>
          <p>“He came through the streets in an open carriage, drawn by four
milk-white horses. The sight was really beautiful. His hat was
under his arm all the way, and he was all the time bowing to the
ladies who were looking out
<pb id="barrett18" n="18"/>
of the windows, and shaking their handkerchiefs towards him.
The streets were crowded with people, from whom went up a
continued shout of ‘Welcome, Lafayette.’</p>
          <p>He was a fine looking man, thick, well set. His hair was slightly
gray. I think he was one of the humblest persons I ever saw to be
so great a man. He was also very much opposed to display.</p>
          <p>He had fought for us, and every body loved him, every body
praised him. I remember myself when he passed through our
country before going to Yorktown.”</p>
          <p>There are many other incidents in the life of this noble-hearted
negro, which we should like to mention, but they are familiar to
most of our citizens.</p>
          <p>We cannot commence our last chapter without commending the
persevering industry which enabled him at an early period in his
life to purchase his freedom at a cost above <hi rend="italics">eight hundred dollars</hi>.</p>
          <p>We would also add, that for half a century has he been a consistent
member of the Baptist church.</p>
          <p>Such a man needs no praise at our hands.
<pb id="barrett19" n="19"/>
Fifty years' walk and conversation, without reproach, in the
midst of any people, is certainly the highest praise which can be
conferred on any one—be he rich or poor, bond or free.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <pb id="barrett20" n="20"/>
          <head>CHAPTER V.
<lb/>
THE BURNING OF THE RICHMOND THEATRE.</head>
          <p>THAT which clothes the name and character of GILBERT HUNT
with peculiar interest, is the noble part which he bore in the
memorable burning of the Richmond Theatre, in 1811.
His strong and brawny arm was the means of
saving many a soul from the jaws of the devouring flames, and
some of the first families in our state and city now point to him
with feelings of mingled pride and gratitude for his self-sacrificing
conduct on that awful night which shrouded so many happy hearts
with gloom, and rendered so many joyous circles lonely and
desolate.</p>
          <p>Long may he yet live in the enjoyment of one of the most
precious boons earth can afford, the remembrance of those for
whom one has endangered even life itself.—<hi rend="italics">May his last days be
his best</hi>.</p>
          <p>(Before giving the account of this memorial scene, as narrated
almost entirely in the simple but graphic language of this
magnanimous
<pb id="barrett21" n="21"/>
old negro, we deem it advisable to draw one or two extracts from
other sources, feeling assured that they will be perused with
interest by our readers.)</p>
          <p>It is not often that a domestic calamity is so
mortal in its character, and so widespread in
its influence, as to merit a place in general history;
but now one presents itself, which has
formed an era in the life of Virginia, never to
be forgotten. (1811.) During the winter of
this year, unwonted gaiety prevailed in Richmond;
brilliant assemblies followed each other
in quick succession; the theatre was open and
sustained by in uncommon histrionic talent; the
fascinations of the season had drawn together,
from every part of the state, the young, the
beautiful, the gay. On Thursday night, the
26th of December, the theatre was crowded to
excess. Six hundred persons had assembled
within it, embracing the fashion, the wealth,
and the honour of the state. A new drama was
to be presented, for the benefit of Placide, a favourite
actor; and it was to be followed by the
pantomime of “The Bleeding Nun.” The
wild legend on which this spectacle was founded,
had lost none of its power under the pen of
Monk Lewis, and, even in pantomime, it had
awakened great interests. The regular piece
had been played; the pantomime had commenced; already
the curtain had risen upon the
<pb id="barrett22" n="22"/>
second act, when sparks of fire were seen to fall
from the scenery on the back part of the stage.
A moment after, Mr. Robertson, one of the actors,
ran forward, and waving his hand toward the
ceiling, called aloud, “The house is on fire!”
His voice carried a thrill of horror through the assembly.
All rose and pressed for the doors of the building.</p>
          <p>The spectators in the pit escaped without difficulty; the passage
leading from it to the outer exit was broad, and had those in the
boxes descended by the pillars, many would have been saved.
Some who were thrown down by violence, were thus preserved.
But the crowd from the boxes pressed into the lobbies, and it was
here, among the refined and the lovely, that the scene became
most appalling. The building was soon wrapped in flames;
volumes of thick, black vapour penetrated every part, and
produced suffocation; the fire approaching, caught those nearest
to it; piercing shrieks rose above the sound of a mass of human
beings struggling for life. The weak were trampled under foot,
and strong men, frantic with fear, passed over the heads of all
before them, in their way towards the doors or windows of the
theatre.—The windows even of the upper lobby were sought;
many who sprang from them perished by the fall; many were
seen with garments on fire as they descended, and died soon
afterwards from their wounds; few who were saved by this means
escaped entirely unhurt.</p>
          <pb id="barrett23" n="23"/>
          <p>But, in the midst of terrors which roused the selfishness of human
nature to its utmost strength, there were displays of love in death,
which make the heart bleed with pity. Fathers were seen rushing
back into the flames to save their children; mothers were calling
in frenzied tones for their daughters; and were with difficulty
dragged from the building; husbands and wives refused to leave
each other, and met death together; even friends lost life in
endeavouring to save those under their care. George Smith the
Governor of Virginia, had brought with him to the theatre a young
lady under his protection. Separated from her in the crowd, he
had reached a place of safety, but, instantly turning back, himself
and his young ward both became victims of the fire. Benjamin
Butts, a lawyer of great distinction, had gained the door; but his
wife was left behind. He hastened to save her, and they perished
together.</p>
          <p>Seventy persons were the martyrs of this horrible night. Besides
those already named, there perished Abram Venable, the President
of the Bank of Virginia, and Lieutenant Gibbon, who was
destroyed in attempting to save Miss Conyers. Richmond was
shrouded in mourning; hardly a family had escaped the visit of the
destroying angel, and many had lost several loved ones. And the
stroke was not felt only at home. It fell upon hearts far removed
from the immediate scene of the disaster.</p>
          <p>On the day succeeding this night, a father in
<pb id="barrett24" n="24"/>
Richmond, who had lost a child by the fire, wrote a letter to
Matthew Clay, then a member of the House of Representatives
from Virginia, to tell him that he too was called to mourn. It would
be hard to imagine circumstances more affecting than those
disclosed by this touching letter. The writer says, “Yesterday a
beloved daughter gladdened my heart by her innocent smiles;
to-day she is in heaven. God gave her to me, and God—yes, it
has pleased Almighty God to take her from me. O! sir, feel for me,
and not for me only; arm yourself with fortitude, while I discharge
the mournful duty of telling you that you have to feel also for
yourself.—Yes, for it must be told! You also were the father of
an amiable daughter, now like my beloved child, gone to join her
mother in heaven.” “The images of both my children were before
me; but I was removed by an impassable crowd, from the dear
sufferers; the youngest (with gratitude to heaven I write it,) sprang
toward the voice of her father, reached my assisting hand, and was
extricated but; . . . my dear, dear Margaret, and your sweet Mary,
with her companions, Miss Gwathmey, and Miss Gatewood, passed
together, and at once, into a happier world.” . . . . Oh! God! Eternity
cannot banish that spectacle of horror from my recollection. Some
friendly, unknown hand, dragged me from the scene of flame and
death.”</p>
          <p>On the 30th December, intelligence of this
<pb id="barrett25" n="25"/>
calamity was communicated to the Senate of the
United States; and, on motion of Mr. Bradley,
a resolution was adopted that the senators would
wear crape on the left arm for a month. On
the same day, a similar resolution was adopted
by the House of Representatives, having been
introduced in a short and feeling address, by
Mr. Dawson of Virginia.</p>
          <p>Many years passed before the impression of this event was erased
in the state where it occurred. It will never be forgotten. Some who
escaped, yet survive to tell of the scene. The day after the fire, the
Common Council of Richmond passed an ordinance forbidding
any public show or spectacle, or any open dancing assembly for
four months. A monumental church has risen on the very spot
where the ill-fated theatre once stood, and its monument, bearing
the names of many victims of the night, will recall to the
<sic corr="visitor">visiter</sic> thoughts of death and of the life beyond. Yet it is not the
nature of man to cherish depressing memories. Time, the great
destroyer, and yet the great physician, sweeps away, first, the
friends whose loss brings sorrow, and the sorrow caused by the
loss.—Another theatre has been reared in the metropolis of
Virginia, and another “Bleeding Nun” may yet be impersonated
within its walls.</p>
          <p>
            <bibl><hi rend="italics">Howison's History of Va., Vol. II, Ch. VII, pp</hi>.  410-414.</bibl>
          </p>
          <pb id="barrett26" n="26"/>
          <p>We gather the following from another source:</p>
          <p>Temporary Theatres now again gave place to a regular
one. A large brick edifice was erected in the rear of the Old
Academy or Theatre Square. That, alas! was the scene of the most
horrid disaster that ever overwhelmed our city, where seventy-two
persons perished in the flames on the fatal 26th December, 1811,
where the Monumental Church now stands, and its portico covers
the tomb and ashes of most of the victims.</p>
          <p>The writer, with some friends, reached Richmond that evening
from a Christmas jaunt in the country, and went with them to the
theatre, but it was so crowded that we could not obtain admission.
A very few hours after, he was aroused by the cry of fire, and
hastening to the spot, the first object he encountered on an open
space, was a lady lying on the grass apparently in a swoon. He
attempted to raise her, but she was dead. He afterwards learned
that she had leaped from a window, but before she could be removed
from beneath it, was crushed by those who sought for safety by
following her. The next object that thrilled him was a gentleman
so dreadfully excoriated that death mercifully put an end to his
tortures in a few hours—but it were cruel to rehearse the many
individual instances of intense suffering by the victims, and of the
scarcely less intense agony of their relatives and friends.</p>
          <pb id="barrett27" n="27"/>
          <p>On the ensuing morning, the mangled, burnt
and undistinguishable remains of many of the
victims were taken from the ruins and interred on the spot,
where their names are recorded on the monument already
mentioned and the ground was consecrated to the erection of a
church.</p>
          <p>It is due to an humble but worthy man, to record the services
rendered by him during the progress of this dreadful calamity.
Gilbert Hunt, a negro blacksmith, possessed naturally
a powerful frame, and by wielding the sledge hammer, his
muscles had become almost as strong and as tough as the iron he
worked.—Gilbert was aroused and besought by Mrs. Geo. Mayo,
to go to the rescue of her daughter.—He was soon at the theatre.
Within its walls, then filled with smoke and flame, was Dr. Jas. D.
McCaw, a man who might have been chosen by a sculptor for a
model of Hercules. The Doctor <sic corr="had">bad</sic> reached the window and broken
out the sash, when he and Gilbert recognized each other. He
called to Gilbert to stand below and catch those he dropped out.
He then seized on the woman nearest to him, and lowering her
from the window as far as he could reach, he let her fall. She was
caught in Gilbert's arms and conveyed by others to a place of
safety.—One after another the brave and indefatigable Doctor
passed to his comrade below, and thus ten or twelve ladies were
saved. The last one providentially was the Doctor's own sister,
<pb id="barrett28" n="28"/>
whose proportions were a feminine epitome of the Doctor himself.
Gilbert caught her and broke her fall, but he says he fell with her,
both unhurt.</p>
          <p>The Doctor having rescued all within his reach, now sought to save
himself. The wall was already tottering. He attempted to leap or
drop from the window, but his strong leathern gaiter, an article of
sportsman's apparel which he always wore, caught in a hinge or
some other iron projection<sic corr="no period">.</sic> and he was thus suspended in a most
horrid and painful position; he fell at last, but to be lame for life.
The muscles and sinews were stretched and torn and lacerated,
and his back was seared by the flames, the marks of which he
carried to his grave.</p>
          <p>The Doctor directed Gilbert to drag him across the street, and place
him with his back against the wall of the Baptist Church; then to get
two palings from a fence <sic corr="opposite">oppsiote</sic>.—With these for splints and
handkerchiefs for bandages, the limb was bound. Gilbert then
went in search of a conveyance to carry the Doctor home. His
removal from beneath the wall of the theatre had scarcely been
effected, before it fell on the spot where he had fallen!</p>
          <p>After a long period of suffering, he was able to resume practice;
and his profession has been adopted by son and grandson,
perpetuating the good name of Dr. McCaw, which its founder had
worthily established.</p>
          <p>
            <bibl><hi rend="italics">Richmond in By-Gone Days, Ch. XIV</hi>,  pp. 142-146.</bibl>
          </p>
          <pb id="barrett29" n="29"/>
          <p>Our narrator begins:—</p>
          <p>“It was on the night after Christmas, 1811. I had just returned from
worship at the Baptist church and was about sitting down to my
supper, when I was startled by the cry that the theatre was on fire.
My wife's mistress called to me and begged me to hasten to the
theatre and, if possible, save her only daughter—a young lady who
had been teaching me my book every night, and one whom I loved
very much. The wind was very high, and the hissing and leaping
flames soon spread over the whole building. The house was built
of wood, and consequently the work of destruction very short.</p>
          <p>When I reached the building, I immediately went to the house of a
colored fiddler, named Gilliat, who lived close by, and begged
him to lend me a bed on which the poor frightened creatures
might fall as they leaped from the windows. This he positively
refused to do. I then got a step-ladder and placed it against the
walls of the burning building. The door was too small to let the
crowd, pushed forward by the scorching flames to get out, and
numbers of them were madly leaping from the windows only to be
crushed to death by the fall. I looked up and saw Dr. — standing
near one
<pb id="barrett30" n="30"/>
of the top windows and calling to me to catch the ladies as he
handed them down.</p>
          <p>I was then young and strong, and the ladies felt as light as feathers.
By this means we got all the ladies out of this portion of the house.
The flames, by this time, were rapidly approaching the Doctor, and
beginning to take hold of his clothing; and, O me! I thought that
good man who had saved so many souls was going to be burned
up. He jumped from one of the windows, and when he touched the
ground, I thought he was dead. He could not move an inch. No
one was near him; for the wall above, was tottering like a
drunken man, ready at any moment to fall and crush him to death.
I heard him scream out, “Will nobody save me?” and, at the risk of
my own life, I rushed to him and bore him away to a place of
safety.</p>
          <p>The scene surpassed anything I ever saw. The wild shrieks of
hopeless agony, the piercing cry, ‘Lord, save or I perish,’ the
uplifted hands, the earnest prayer for mercy, for pardon, for
salvation, I think I see it now—all—all just as it happened.”</p>
          <p>And the old negro stopped to wipe away a
<pb id="barrett31" n="31"/>
tear which was trickling down his wrinkled cheek.</p>
          <p>“The next day, I went to the scene where such awful sights had
been witnessed. And oh! how my heart shudders even now at the
things which then and there met my eye.—There lay, piled
together, one mass of half-burned bodies—the bodies of all
classes and conditions of people—the young and the old, the bond
and the free, the rich and the poor, the great and the small, were all
lying there together. Some of them were so badly burned that it was
almost impossible to recognize them. Others were almost uninjured;
yet life had left their bodies, and there they lay, cold, and stiff,
and dead.</p>
          <p>I never found my young mistress, and suppose she perished
among the many other young and beautiful females, who on that
dreadful night passed so unexpectedly from <hi rend="italics">time</hi> to <hi rend="italics">eternity</hi>.</p>
          <p>I thought, after this, <hi rend="italics">there would not be any more theatres</hi>.”</p>
          <p>The old man was silent; his tale was told, tear-drops were
standing in his eyes.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div1 type="text">
        <pb id="barrett33" n="33"/>
        <head>THE BLACKSMITH'S NIGHT.</head>
        <docAuthor>BY REV. R. HOYT.</docAuthor>
        <lg type="verse">
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>O welcome hour when peaceful eve once more</l>
            <l>Spreads her dun curtain for a world's repose;</l>
            <l>Bids him be free who was a slave before,</l>
            <l>And for his woes</l>
            <l>Her mystic balm, oblivious sleep, bestows.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>How idle he, the lord of yonder dome.</l>
            <l>Yet see the gorgeous pomp his halls display;</l>
            <l>No care, no want e'er enters that proud home,</l>
            <l>While, wo the day,</l>
            <l>My sternest toil drives not the fiends away.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>There rolls a chariot to that house of mirth;</l>
            <l>These hands of mine prepared the sumptuous car;</l>
            <l>Yet less it serves to gladden my poor hearth,</l>
            <l>Than yon lone star,</l>
            <l>Now beaming through my casement window from afar.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>O, son of toil, no more shalt thou repine:</l>
            <l>I come to show how happy, good and great</l>
            <l>Thou can'st be even in this lot of thine,</l>
            <l>This low estate,</l>
            <l>Smitten beneath the hammer of thy fate.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>My ebon mantle now shall close thee round,</l>
            <l>And thou shalt tread within that dark abyss,</l>
            <l>Where, haply, some sweet solace may be found,</l>
            <l>Some quiet bliss,</l>
            <l>Some better life than thou hast known in this!</l>
          </lg>
          <pb n="34"/>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>To thee is granted to behold how Truth</l>
            <l>Links the strong worker with the happy skies,</l>
            <l>In care's deep furrows plants immortal youth,</l>
            <l>And gives the prize</l>
            <l>Of endless glory to the bravely wise.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>For man is regal when his strength is tried;</l>
            <l>When spirit wills, all matter must obey:</l>
            <l>Sweeps the resistless mandate like a tide,</l>
            <l>Away, away,</l>
            <l>Till earth and heaven feel the potent sway.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>Now as this rayless gloom aside I fling,</l>
            <l>The realm of action spreading on the view</l>
            <l>Calls to the sooty blacksmith—be a king!</l>
            <l>Thy reign renew;</l>
            <l>Grasping thy mace again, arise, arise and do!</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>And as the massive hammer thunders down,</l>
            <l>Shaping the stubborn iron to the plan,</l>
            <l>Know that each stroke adds lustre to thy crown,</l>
            <l>And yon wide span</l>
            <l>Of gazing planets shout—behold a man!</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>A glorious man! and thy renown shall be</l>
            <l>Borne by the winds and waters through all time,</l>
            <l>While there's a keel to carve it on the sea</l>
            <l>From clime to clime,</l>
            <l>Or God ordains that—Idleness is Crime!</l>
          </lg>
        </lg>
      </div1>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI.2>