<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % external-entities SYSTEM "./extEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY % internal-entities SYSTEM "./intEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY davistp SYSTEM "davistp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY davis83 SYSTEM "davis83.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY davis84 SYSTEM "davis84.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY davis85 SYSTEM "davis85.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY davis86 SYSTEM "davis86.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY davis87 SYSTEM "davis87.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY davis88 SYSTEM "davis88.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY davis89 SYSTEM "davis89.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY davis90 SYSTEM "davis90.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY davisvs SYSTEM "davisvs.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY daviscv SYSTEM "daviscv.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY davis4 SYSTEM "davis4.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY davisfp SYSTEM "davisfp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>A Narrative of the Life of Rev. Noah Davis, A Colored Man.  
Written By Himself, at the Age of Fifty-Four:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Davis, Rev. Noah, 1803 or 04—?</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Fiona Mills</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by</resp>
          <name>Fiona Mills</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Chris Hill and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1999</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca. 150K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1999.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, 
teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is 
included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note anchored="yes">Call number BX6455 .D38 A3        
(Wilson Annex, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="title page"> A Narrative of the Life of Rev. 
Noah Davis, A Colored Man. Written By Himself, at the Age of Fifty-Four.</title>
            <title type="cover"> Narrative of a Colored Man</title>
            <author>Rev. Noah Davis</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent> 89 p., 9 ill.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
            <publisher>Published by John F. Weishampel, Jr., No. 484 West Baltimore St.</publisher>
            <date>[1859]</date>
            <authority/>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>The publisher's advertisements on pp. 86-90 have been scanned as images.</p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ 
and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using 
Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Davis, Noah, 1803 or 4-</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Virginia -- Biography.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Maryland -- Baltimore -- Biography.</item>
            <item>African American Baptists -- Clergy -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Virginia -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Freedmen -- Maryland -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- Virginia -- History -- 19th century.</item>
            <item>Slaves' writings, American.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2000-04-06, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-11-01, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-11-01, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Chris Hill</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-10-21, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Fiona Mills</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="cover image">
        <p>
          <figure id="cover" entity="daviscv">
            <p>[Cover Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="frontispiece image">
        <p>
          <figure id="frontis" entity="davisfp">
            <p>REV. NOAH DAVIS,<lb/>PASTOR OF THE<lb/>SARATOGA STREET AFRICAN BAPTIST CHURCH,<lb/>BALTIMORE.<lb/>[Frontispiece Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="notice">
        <pb id="davis3" n="3"/>
        <head>NOTICE TO THE PUBLIC.</head>
        <p>THE object of the writer, in preparing this account of himself,
is to</p>
        <p>RAISE SUFFICIENT MEANS TO FREE HIS LAST
TWO CHILDREN FROM SLAVERY.</p>
        <p>Having already, within twelve years past, purchased himself,
his wife, and five of his children, at a cost, altogether,
of over <hi rend="italics">four thousand dollars,</hi> he now earnestly desires a
humane and christian public to</p>
        <p>AID HIM IN THE SALE OF THIS BOOK,</p>
        <p>for the purpose of finishing the task in which he has so long
and anxiously labored.</p>
        <p>God has blessed him in an extraordinary manner, not
only by granting freedom to him and so large a portion of
his family, but by giving him the hope of the gospel, and
permitting him to preach that gospel among his own people
—in which calling he has been engaged for about twenty
five years.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1>
        <pb id="davis4" n="4"/>
        <p>
          <figure id="ill1" entity="davis4">
            <head>THE SARATOGA STREET</head>
            <p>AFRICAN BAPTIST CHAPEL.<lb/>The building, of which the above cut is an imperfect representation, fronts as above 100 feet on Saratoga street, and 46 feet on Calvert  street. The house is of brick, and cost over $18,000.—(See page 45.)</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="title page image">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="davistp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="title page verso image">
        <p>
          <figure id="verso" entity="davisvs">
            <p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">A<lb/>NARRATIVE
<lb/>
OF
<lb/>
THE LIFE
<lb/>
OF
<lb/>
REV. NOAH DAVIS, 
<lb/>A COLORED MAN.</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="main">WRITTEN BY HIMSELF, AT THE AGE OF FIFTY-FOUR.</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <docEdition>PRINTED SOLELY FOR THE AUTHOR'S BENEFIT.</docEdition>
        <docImprint><pubPlace>BALTIMORE:</pubPlace>
<publisher>PUBLISHED BY JOHN F. WEISHAMPEL, JR.,<lb/>
No. 484 West Baltimore St.</publisher></docImprint>
        <pb id="davisvs" n="verso"/>
        <docImprint>ENTERED according to the Act of Congress, in the year 1859,<lb/>
by NOAH DAVIS, in the Clerk's office of the District Court<lb/>
of Maryland.</docImprint>
        <docImprint>STEREOTYPED BY<lb/>
JOHN F. WEISHAMPEL, JR., BOOKSELLER AND PUBLISHER,<lb/>
BALTIMORE.</docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="contents">
        <pb id="davis7" n="7"/>
        <head>Contents.</head>
        <list type="simple">
          <item>CHAPTER I.<lb/>
Early Life in Virginia—Example of Pious Parents.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER II.<lb/>
Apprenticed to the Shoe-making—Learns housework—
Intemperance—“A negro can't be trusted”—Learning how
to write and cipher.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER III.<lb/>
Religious Experience—Conviction and Conversion.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER IV.<lb/>
Marriage—License to Preach—Purchase of Freedom—
Call to Baltimore.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER V.<lb/>
Experience in Baltimore—Education—Purchase of a Wife
and two Children—Great Distress of Mind—Generous
Assistance—Church Matters.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER VI.<lb/>
A New Movement in Baltimore—Erection of a Meeting
House for the African Baptist Church—Heavy Indebtedness
—Account of the Enterprise.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER VI.<lb/>
Account of a Visit to the northern Cities—True Friends.</item>
          <item>CHAPTER VII.<lb/>
Conclusion—Object of this Book.</item>
        </list>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="narrative">
        <pb id="davis9" n="9"/>
        <head>NARRATIVE.</head>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
          <argument>
            <p>Early Life in Virginia—Example of Pious Parents.</p>
          </argument>
          <p>I WAS born a slave, in Madison county, Virginia,
March, 1804. My father, John Davis,
and his family, belonged to Robert Patten,
Esq., a wealthy merchant, residing in
Fredericksburg—who was also owner, in
connection with Mr. John Thom, of a large merchant
mill, located on “Crooked Run,” a stream
running between Madison and Culpepper
counties. My father was the head miller
in that large establishment, in which
responsible station he was much respected.</p>
          <p>There I was born, and remained until I
was twelve years old. Mr. Patten was
always considered one of the best of masters,
allowing his servants many privileges; but
my father enjoyed more than many others.
Both he and my mother were pious members
of a Baptist church, and from their godly
example, I formed a determination, before I
<pb id="davis10" n="10"/>
had reached my twelfth year, that if I was
spared to become a man, I would try to be as
good as my parents. My father could read a
little, and make figures, but could scarcely
write at all. His custom, on those Sabbaths
when we remained at home, was to spend his
time in instructing his children, or the
neighboring servants, out of a New Testament,
sent him from Fredericksburg by one of his
older sons. I fancy I can see him now, sitting
under his bush arbor, reading that precious
book to many attentive hearers around him.</p>
          <p>Such was the esteem I had for my pious
father, that I have kept that blessed book
ever since his death, for his sake; and it was
the first New Testament I read, after I felt
the pardoning love of God in my soul.</p>
          <p>My father died, August 20, 1826, aged 60
years. My mother, Jane Davis, at the death
of my father, removed from the farm, where
my father died, and spent the remainder of
her days in Fredericksburg, with her
children. She lived to good old age, and fell
asleep in Jesus, Dec. 24, 1831.</p>
          <p>My father had been allowed to keep a cow
and horse, for his own use; and to raise and
feed his hogs and poultry from the mill.—
<pb id="davis11" n="11"/>
He had the privilege of keeping his children
with him, until they were old enough to put
out to such trades as they might choose. I
had several brothers and one sister. Two of
my brothers, one older, the other younger
than myself, lived with our parents, at this
place. My oldest brother worked in the mill,
with my father, while my youngest brother
and I did little else than play about home,
and wait upon our mother. I had several
playmates, besides my brothers, and among
them were the sons of Col. Thom, and the
servant boys who stayed at his house.
Although many years have passed away since,
it gives me pleasure, even now, to recollect
the happy seasons I enjoyed with the
playmates of my childhood.</p>
          <p>But this pleasant state of things was not
to continue long. The owners of the mill
and farm concluded to sell out the whole
concern. My father and his family then
removed to another farm, belonging to our
owner, located in <sic corr="Culpepper">Culpeper</sic> county, near
Stevensburg. Here I remained nearly two years,
working, part of the time, with a carpenter,
who was building a summer residence for my
master; and the rest of the time, assisting
<pb id="davis12" n="12"/>
my father to cultivate as much ground as he
and his family could tend. Here I learned
something of a farmer's life. The overseer,
Mr. Daniel Brown, had the reputation of
being one of the best overseers in the county.
But my father's family was not put under
him further than for his protection; for after
our owner sold the mill, he set my
parents free, and allowed them to maintain
themselves, by cultivating as much ground
on the farm as they needed.</p>
          <p>Sometimes my father would leave his little
place in charge of my brother Robert and
myself, and would hire himself to work in some
mill, or go peddling poultry, vegetables, &amp;c.,
at some of the market places around.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <pb id="davis13" n="13"/>
          <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
          <argument>
            <p>Apprenticed to the shoe-making—Learns housework—
Intemperance—“A negro can't be trusted”—Learning how
to write and cipher.</p>
          </argument>
          <p>IN December, 1818, for the first time in
my life, I left my parents, to go a distance
from home; and I was sad at the thought of
parting with those whom I loved and
reverenced more than any persons on earth. But
the expectation of seeing Fredericksburg, a
place which, from all I had then learned, I
supposed must be the greatest place in the
world, reconciled me somewhat with the
necessity of saying Good-bye to the dear ones
at home. I arrived at Fredericksburg, after
a day and a half's travel, in a wagon—a
distance of some fifty miles. Having arrived in
town, a boy green from the country, I was
astonished and delighted at what appeared
to me the splendor and beauty of the place.
I spent a merry Christmas at my old master's
stately mansion, along with my older
brother, and for a while forgot the home on the
farm.</p>
          <p>But soon, another home was selected for
<pb id="davis14" n="14"/>
me, where I might learn a trade, and as I
preferred the boot and shoe-making, I was
put to Mr. Thomas Wright, a man of
sterling integrity, who was considered the best
workman in the whole town. Here I had an
older brother living, which was some
inducement for my going to live with Mr. Wright.
I was bound, to serve until I should be
twenty-one years old. This was in January, 1819.</p>
          <p>Upon entering with Mr. Wright, I learned
that the colored boys had to serve one year
with Mrs. Wright, in the house and kitchen.
The object of this was to train them for
future usefulness, when called from the shop,
to serve as waiters or cooks. Mrs. Wright
was a good manager, and a very particular
housekeeper. I used to think she was too
particular. But I have learned better since.
I have often wished, when I have been seeking
homes for my children, that I could find
one like Mrs. Wright. She would spare no
pains to teach her servants how she wanted
her work done; and then she would spare
no pains to make them do it. I have often
looked back, with feelings of gratitude and
veneration, to that pious lady, for her
untiring perseverance in training me up in the
<pb id="davis15" n="15"/>
way I should go. But she is gone, as I trust,
to receive the reward of righteousness, in a
better world.</p>
          <p>After I had been under Mrs. Wright's
special charge the first year, she could leave me
to cook a dinner, or clean the house, or do
anything she might set me at, without her
being present. I was now considered fit to
take my seat among the hands in the shop.</p>
          <p>Here I found quite a new state of things.
The shoemakers, at that time, in Fredericksburg
were considered the most intemperate
of any class of men in the place; and as the
apprentice-boys had always to be very
obliging to the journeymen, in order to get along
pleasantly with them, it was my duty to be
runner for the shop; and I was soon trained
how  to bring liquor among the men with such
secresy as to prevent the boss, who had
forbidden it to come on the premises, from
knowing it.</p>
          <p>But, in those days, the drinking of ardent
spirits was a common practice, even among
christians. With such examples all around,
I soon learned the habit of drinking, along
with every other vile habit to which my
companions were addicted. It was true in my
<pb id="davis16" n="16"/>
case, that “evil communications corrupt good
manners;” and had it not been for the
strictness with which my boss and his amiable
lady watched over me, I should in all
probability have become a confirmed drunkard,
before my time was out. But they held the
reins over me, and kept me in, until I had
served out my apprenticeship.</p>
          <p>I can say, however, that, much as I was
inclined to other vices and sins, Mr. Wright
readily gave me a recommendation for
honesty, truthfulness, and goodness of character.
In fact, he had felt such confidence in me,
that he would often leave his shoe store in my
care, when he would have to go to the north,
for a supply of stock. And I can truly say,
that I never deceived him, when he thus
trusted me. Nothing would mortify me as
much, as to hear it said, “A negro can't be
trusted.” This saying would always nerve
me with a determination <hi rend="italics">to be trustworthy.—</hi>
If I was trusted, I would deserve to be
trusted. I wanted to show that principle was not
confined to color. But I have been led to
look at it since, and have thought that
perhaps it was more pride than principle in me,
at that time, for I was a wicked sinner.</p>
          <pb id="davis17" n="17"/>
          <p>The first idea I ever got of writing, was
from trying to imitate my employer, who
used to write the names of his customers on
the lining of the boots and shoes, as he gave
them out to be made. So I tried to make letters,
and soon succeeded in writing my name,
and then the word Fredericksburg, and so
on. My father had previously taught me the
alphabet, in the spelling book, before I had
left the mill. After I became religious, I
would carry my father's New Testament to
church, and always try to get to meeting in
time to hear the preacher read a chapter
before sermon. If he named the chapter before
reading it, I would soon find it. In this way,
I gathered much information in pronouncing
many hard words in the Scriptures.</p>
          <p>It was a long time before I learned the
meaning of the numeral letters put in the
Bible over the chapters. I had often seen
them in the spelling book running alongside
a column of figures; but no one ever told
me that they were put there for the same use
as the figures.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <pb id="davis18" n="18"/>
          <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
          <argument>
            <p>Religious Experience—Conviction—Conversion.</p>
          </argument>
          <p>Just about the close of my apprenticeship,
and as I began to feel myself a man, I
commenced to visit the girls, which induced me
go still more frequently to church.</p>
          <p>At that time, there were four churches in
Fredericksburg. The colored people had
apartments for worship with the white
people, at each of these churches. They were
Methodist, Presbyterian, Episcopalian and Baptist.</p>
          <p>I had no particular preference for any one
of these denominations, more than another;
but, went wherever my favorites went. One
night a young lady invited me to go to the
Methodist church, where a prayer-meeting
was to be held. During the meeting, a
venerable old gentleman rose to his feet, and
related an account of the sudden death of a
young lady, which he had read in a newspapers.
When he related that solemn circumstance,
it so affected me, that I felt as if
I was about to die, in a sudden manner also.</p>
          <pb id="davis19" n="19"/>
          <p>Having always, from parental training,
purposed in my mind to become religious
before I died, I thought that now was the
time to begin to pray. But I could not try
to pray in the church, for I was afraid that
the girls would laugh at me. Yet I became
so troubled, that I left the house, girls and
all, intending to seek some place where I
might pray. But to my horror and surprise,
when I got out of the church, this reflection
occurred to me, “God is in heaven, and you
are on earth:—how can He hear you?” O,
what distress of mind I now felt! I began to
wonder how God could hear my prayer;. for,
sure enough, He was in heaven, and I on the
earth. In my perplexity, I started for home.</p>
          <p>Just before I reached the shop, where I
slept, this thought struck me, if possible with
more force than the former reflection: “God
does see you!” It really appeared to me as
if I could see that God was indeed looking at
me; and not only so, but I felt that He had
been looking at me all my life. I now said
to myself, “It is of no use for me to pray.—
If God has seen all my wickedness, as I feel
that He has, then there is no mercy for me.”</p>
          <p>So I ran to my lodging-place, and tried to
<pb id="davis20" n="20"/>
hide myself in a dark room. But this was
useless; for it appeared that God could see
me in the dark, as well as in the light.</p>
          <p>I now felt constrained to beg for mercy, and
spent the time in trying to obtain pardon for
my sins. But the morning came, and the
hour drew near for the hands to go to work,
and I was still unhappy.</p>
          <p>I felt so very different to what I had always
felt, that I tried to examine my impressions
of the previous night, to learn if it was true
that God did see me or not; for I thought
my imagination might have deceived me.</p>
          <p>Up to this time, I was not fully convinced
that God knew all about me. So I began to
study about the matter. As I sat on the
shoe-bench, I picked up a bunch of bristles,
and selecting one of the smallest, I began to
wonder, if God could see an object so small
as that. No sooner had this inquiry arose
in my heart, than it appeared to me, that the
Lord could not only see the bristle, but that
He beheld me, as, plainly as I saw the little
object in my hand; and not only so, but that
God was then looking through me, just as I
would hold up a tumbler of clear water to the
sun and look through it. This was enough.
<pb id="davis21" n="21"/>
I felt that I must pray, or perish; and now I
began to pray.</p>
          <p>But it really seemed, that the more I prayed
the less hope there was for me. Still I could
not stop praying; for I felt that God was
angry with me. I had sinned against his holy
laws; and now, if He should cut me off, and
send me to hell, it was but right. These
thoughts followed me day and night, for five
weeks, before I felt relief. At length, one day,
while sitting on my shoe bench, I felt that
my time had come when I must die. What
troubled me most, was that I should have to
appear before God, in all my sins;—O, what
horror filled my soul at the thought!</p>
          <p>I began to wonder what I must do. I knew
I was not prepared for death and the
Judgment. It is true that two of my shopmates, at
that time, were members of the church; but
they did not seem to care for my soul. All
the rest of the hands were as wicked as
myself. “What shall I do?” was in my mind,
all the time I sat at work.</p>
          <p>The reflection occurred to me, “Your mother
is a christian; it may be she can save you.”
But this suggestion appeared to be offensive to
God. Then came another thought,—“As
<pb id="davis22" n="22"/>
my master was a rich man, could he not do
something to help me?” But I found no
relief in either . . . . and while I sat thus, hoping
and praying, light broke into my mind—all
my trouble left me in an instant.</p>
          <p>I felt such a love and peace flowing in my
soul, that I could not sit longer; I sprang to
my feet, and cried out, “Glory to God!” It
seemed to me, that God, whom I had beheld,
a few seconds previously, angry with me,
was now well-pleased. I could not tell why
this great change had taken place in me; and
my shopmates were surprised at my conduct,
saying, that I must be getting crazy. But,
just at this moment, the thought came into
my mind, that I was converted; still, as I felt
so very different from what I had expected to
feel, I could not see how that could be. I
concluded to run and see my mother, and ask
her how people felt, when they got converted.
So I went, right away, to my mother's house,
some five or six squares from the shop.</p>
          <p>When I reached the door of her house, it
appeared to me that everything was new and
bright. I went in, and sat down. Mother
asked me how I was. I told her, I felt <hi rend="italics">right
smart.</hi> This was a new sound from me; for
<pb id="davis23" n="23"/>
my answers to this question had long been—
<hi rend="italics">“poorly.”</hi> But now came the trial; to ask
mother how people felt, when they were
converted. I felt ashamed to ask the question;
so I went into another room; and seeing a
hymn book lying on the table, I took it up.
The first hymn that struck my sight began
with these words:</p>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>“When converts first begin to sing,</l>
            <l>Their happy souls are on the wing—</l>
            <l>Their theme is all redeeming love;</l>
            <l>Fain would they be with Christ above.</l>
            <l>With admiration they behold</l>
            <l>The love of Christ, which can't be told,” &amp;c.</l>
          </lg>
          <p>These lines expressed my feelings precisely,
and being encouraged from them, I went
to my mother, and asked her the question—
“How do people feel, when they get converted?”
She replied, “Do you think you are
converted?” Now, this was a severe trial;
for, although I felt that I was really changed,
yet I wanted to hear from her, before I could
decide whether I was actually converted, or
not. I replied, “No.” Then she said, “My
son, the devil makes people think themselves
converted, sometimes.” I arose, and
<pb id="davis24" n="24"/>
left immediately, believing that the devil had
made a fool of me. I returned to my shop,
more determined to pray than ever before.</p>
          <p>I arrived, and took my seat, and tried to
get under that same weight, that I had felt
pressing me down, but a short while before.
But it seemed to me that I could not; and,
instead of feeling sad, I felt joyful in my
heart; and while trying to pray, I thought
the Saviour appeared to me. I thought I saw
God smiling upon me, through Christ, His
Son. My soul was filled with love to God
and Jesus Christ. It appeared to me, I saw
a fullness in Jesus Christ, to save every
sinner who would come to Him. And I felt, that
if I was only converted, I would tell all
sinners how precious the Saviour was. But I
could not think myself converted yet,
because I could not see what I had done, for
God to pardon my sins. Still I felt a love
to Him for what He had done for my soul.</p>
          <p>Then I began to think upon my shopmates
—and, O what pity ran through my soul for
them. I wished to pray for them; but I felt
so unworthy, that I could not do it. At last
I promised the Lord that if He would convert
my soul, I would talk to them.</p>
          <pb id="davis25" n="25"/>
          <p>* * It was several months after that, before
I was made to realize this to be the work of
God; and when it was made plain, O what
joy it did bring to my poor soul!</p>
          <p>I shortly became a member of the Baptist
church, and was baptized, in company with
some twenty others, by Rev. Geo. F. Adams,
who was then pastor of the Baptist church in
Fredericksburg—September 19,1831. This
then contained about three hundred
colored members.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <pb id="davis26" n="26"/>
          <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
          <argument>
            <p>Marriage—License to Preach—Purchase of Freedom—A
Call to Baltimore.</p>
          </argument>
          <p>I HAD not been a member of the church a
great while, before I formed an attachment to
a young woman, who ultimately became my
wife. I have ever regarded her as the special
gift of God to me. She embraced religion
about the same time that I did. We had been
acquainted with each other for several years
previous, and although we associated
frequently in the same social circle together;
yet nothing of a special liking had manifested
itself until the day she was baptized.</p>
          <p>But we were both slaves, and of course had
to get the consent of our owners, before we
went further. My wife belonged to the late
Carter L. Stephenson, Esq., who was a brother
to Hon. Andrew Stephenson, of Va. My
wife's master was quite indulgent to the servants
about the house. He never restrained
visitors from coming on his premises to visit
his domestics. It was said he had the likeliest
set of servant girls in the town; and though
<pb id="davis27" n="27"/>
I cannot say I got the prettiest, yet I think I
got the best one among them. We have
lived happily together, as husband and wife,
for the last twenty-eight years. We have
had nine children—seven born in slavery, and
two since my wife's freedom. Five out of the
seven in slavery I have bought—two are still
in bondage.</p>
          <p>Before long, the brethren chose me to fill
the office of a deacon. But it never seemed
to me to be the place that God designed for
me; though I felt willing to do whatever lay
in my power for God's glory and the good of
His people. The impression made upon my
at my conversion, to talk to sinners, increased
on me, until I could wait no longer.</p>
          <p>I related my convictions of duty to my
brethren, and particularly to one who was
always held in high esteem for his piety and
excellent character—a colored brother,
Armistead Walker. My case was first brought
by him before the colored portion of the
church; and after a full hearing of my statement,
by the white brethren, with regard to
my call to preach, &amp;c., I was licensed to
preach the gospel, and exhort sinners to
repentance, opportunity might be afforded.
<pb id="davis28" n="28"/>
I had ample opportunities at that time, for
doing good, by preaching to my fellow men,
both in town and country.</p>
          <p>Several other colored brethren, about this
time, gave evidence of having been called of
God, to the work of preaching the gospel.
Among these was a dear brother, named
Alexander Daniel. He was a bright and shining
light, among our people, and everything
considered, I think he was the best preacher
of color I ever heard. But alas, he is no
more! He was esteemed as a christian minister,
and his friends, both white and colored,
united in erecting a monument over
his grave.</p>
          <p>In my attempts to preach the gospel to my
fellow sinners, I often felt embarrassed, not
knowing how to read a chapter in the Bible
correctly. My desires now increased for such
a knowledge of the sacred Scriptures, as would
enable me to read a chapter publicly to my
hearers. I thought that if I had all my time
at my own command, I would devote it all to
divine things. This desire I think, led me
more than anything else, to ask permission
of my master, Dr. F. Patten, to purchase my
freedom. I made this a subject of prayer,
<pb id="davis29" n="29"/>
both night and day, that God would show
me what he would have me do. I felt
encouraged to hope that I should find favor
with my owner, as he had always treated me
kindly. But how shall I get the purchase
money, provided he grants my request?—
This appeared a difficult matter, but I thought
if my master would give me a chance, that I
should be able to raise the money.</p>
          <p>I went to him and stated my wishes,
informing him why I wanted to be free—that
I had been led to believe the Lord had
converted my soul, and had called me to talk to
sinners. He granted my request, without a
single objection, fixing my price at five
hundred dollars.</p>
          <p>But now I had to tell him that I had no
Money, and that I desired him to grant me
another request; which was, to let me travel
and find friends, who would give me the
money. After learning my wishes fully, he
consented, and told me, when I got ready to
start, he would give me a pass, to go where I
pleased.</p>
          <p>I thanked him sincerely for this privilege,
and after making arrangements, in the way
of obtaining suitable letters of recommendation,
<pb id="davis30" n="30"/>
I left Fredericksburg, in June, 1845,
for Philadelphia, New York, Boston, &amp;c.</p>
          <p>After spending nearly four months in
visiting the northern cities, I returned home, with
about one hundred and fifty dollars, greatly disheartened.</p>
          <p>Previous to going north, I had raised about
a hundred and fifty dollars, which I had
already paid on my debt.</p>
          <p>The cause of my failure to raise all the
money, I believe, was that I was unaccustomed
to addressing large congregations of strangers;
and often, when I was favored with an
opportunity of presenting my case to the
people, I would feel such embarrassment that I
could scarcely say anything. And I met
another obstacle, which discouraged me very
much; which was, that some persons would
tell me they sympathized with me, in my
efforts to get free; but they said it was against
their principles to give money, to buy slaves.
I confess, this was new to me, and would
cut me down much in my spirits—still I
found generous and noble-hearted friends,
who treated me with every mark of kindness.</p>
          <p>I began to wonder to myself, whether God
was in this matter, or not; and if so, why I
<pb id="davis31" n="31"/>
had not succeeded. However, having
returned home, I went to work at my trade,
for the purpose of earning the remainder of
the money. Having paid what I was able,
toward my debt, and reserving enough to
open a shop, upon my own account, my old
boss, Mr. Wright, my true and constant friend,
became my protector, so that I might carry on
my business lawfully. In this, however, I was
not very successful; but I had not been long
engaged at it, before I received a communication
from my white Baptist friends in Baltimore,
through my pastor, Rev. Sam'l Smith,
informing me that if I would come to Baltimore,
and accept an appointment as missionary
to the colored people of that city, they
would assist me in raising the balance of the
money then due upon myself.</p>
          <p>This was indeed an unexpected, and to me
an undesired call. I began to think, how
can I leave my wife and seven small children,
to go to Baltimore to live, a distance of more
than a hundred miles from them. This, I
thought, could not be. I thought my children
would need my watchful care, more now
than at any other time. It is true, they were
all slaves, belonging to a rich widow lady.
<pb id="davis32" n="32"/>
But she had always given me the entire control
of my family. Now, if I should leave
them at their tender age, mischief might
befall them. Still, as the letter from Baltimore
was from gentlemen of the best standing, it
became me to give them an answer. This I
could not do, without first consulting my
master. I did so, and after giving the
matter a careful consideration, he thought I had
better go and see those gentlemen—he was
perfectly willing to leave the matter to me.</p>
          <p>The result was, that I accepted the offer
of the brethren in Baltimore; and by them I
was enabled to pay the debt I owed; and I
have never had cause to repent it—though I
had misgivings sometimes, when I would get
into trouble.</p>
          <p>But I have found those who were my friends
at first, are my friends still. In a few weeks
after I had arrived in Baltimore, (1847,) the
white Baptists who were favorable to the
mission in behalf of the colored people, secured
for me an appointment as missionary of the
Domestic Board of the Southern Baptist Convention,
in connection with the Maryland
Baptist Union Association. I now felt a debt
of gratitude to these dear friends, that I could
<pb id="davis33" n="33"/>
not show more acceptably to them, than by
engaging heartily in the work to which I had
been thus called. I went to work, first, by
hiring a room in a private house, where I
would collect what few children I could get
together, in a Sabbath school. I continued
in this place for nearly a year, teaching the
little children, and preaching to a few grown
persons, who would come in at times to hear
what this Baptist man had to say; and who,
after satisfying their curiosity, would
generally leave me. During my stay in this
locality I could not find half a dozen colored
Baptists, who would take hold with me in
this missionary enterprise. There were some
few attached to the white churches; but only
two of those showed any disposition to help
me in this great and good work. I found
that everybody loved to go with the multitude,
and it was truly up-hill work with me.
I found some who are called Anti-Mission, or
Old School Baptists, who, when I called upon
them, would ask of what faith I was,—
and when I would reply, that I belonged to
what I understood to be the Regular Baptists,
they would answer, “Then you are not of
our faith,” &amp;c.</p>
          <pb id="davis34" n="34"/>
          <p>Now I felt lonely indeed, separated far
from home, from family, from dear brethren
and friends; thrown among strangers in a
strange place. Those I came to benefit, stood
aloof from me, and seemed to look upon all
my movements with distrust and suspicion,
and opposed to all I was trying to do for the
moral and spiritual benefit of our degraded
race. But, thanks be to God, all I found in
Baltimore were not of this stamp. Those of
the white Baptists who had been the means
of calling me to this field, adhered to me
like brethren, indeed. Could I feel at liberty
to mention names, I would bring to notice
some dear friends who have ever stood by me,
in all my efforts to do good, and whose
acts of disinterested benevolence have been
rarely equaled. But their labors of love are
recorded on high, and I must forbear.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <pb id="davis35" n="35"/>
          <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
          <argument>
            <p>Experience in Baltimore—Education—Purchase of a Wife
and Two Children—Great Distress of Mind—Generous
Assistance—Church Matters.</p>
          </argument>
          <p>WHEN I came among the colored people of
Baltimore, I found, to my surprise, that they
were advanced in education, quite beyond
what I had conceived of. Of course, as I
never had such advantages, I was far behind
the people; and as this did not appear well
in a preacher, I felt very small, when
comparing my abilities with others of a superior
stamp. I found that the great mass
of colored professors of religion were Methodists,
whose piety and zeal seemed to carry all
before them. There were, at that time, some
ten or eleven colored Methodist churches, one
Episcopalian, one Presbyterian; and one
little Baptist church, located upon the
outskirts of the city. The most of the Methodist
churches were large and influential; and the
Presbyterian church had one of the best
Sabbath schools for colored children in the city.</p>
          <p>But the Baptist colored membership was
looked upon as the smallest; and under these
<pb id="davis36" n="36"/>
circumstances, I was surrounded with
discouragements; although the ministers and
brethren of other denominations have always
treated me with marked christian kindness.</p>
          <p>I had never had a day's schooling; and
coming to one of the first cities in the Union,
where the colored people had the advantages
of schools, and where their pulpits were
occupied, Sabbath after Sabbath, by
comparatively intelligent colored ministers—what
could I expect, but that the people would
turn away from one who was trying to preach
in the room of a private house, some fifteen
by twenty feet? Yet, there was no turning
back: God had called me to the work, and it
was His cause I was advocating.</p>
          <p>I found, that to preach, like other preachers,
I must improve my mind, by reading the
Bible and other good books, and by studying
my own language. I started afresh—I got a
small stock of books, and the white brethren
loaned and gave me other useful volumes, to
which they added a word of instruction and
encouragement, whenever an opportunity
offered; and the ministers cordially invited me
to attend their Monday ministerial conference
meeting, which was very useful to me.</p>
          <pb id="davis37" n="37"/>
          <p>* * I had now been in Baltimore more
than a year. My wife and seven children
were still in Virginia. I went to see them as
often as my circumstances permitted—three
or four times a year. About this time, my
wife's mistress agreed to sell to me my wife
and our two youngest children. The price
fixed, was eight hundred dollars cash, and
she gave me twelve months to raise the money.
The sun rose bright in my sky that day;
but before the year was out, my
prospects were again in darkness. Now I had
two great burdens upon my mind: one to
attend properly to my missionary duty, the
other to raise eight hundred dollars. During this
time we succeeded in getting a better place
for the Sabbath school, and there was a
larger attendance upon my preaching, which
demanded reading and study, and also visiting,
and increased my daily labors. On the other
hand, the year was running away, in which
I had to raise eight hundred dollars. So that
I found myself at times in a great strait.</p>
          <p>My plan to raise the money was, to secure
the amount, first, by pledges, before I
collected any. * * Finally, the year was more
than passed away, and I had upon my
<pb id="davis38" n="38"/>
subscription list about one half of the money
needed. It was now considered that the
children had increased in value one hundred
dollars, and I was told that I could have them,
by paying in cash six hundred dollars, and
giving a bond, with good security, for three
hundred more, payable in twelve months. I
had six weeks, in which to consummate this
matter. I felt deeply, that this was a time
to pray the Lord to help me, and for this my
wife's prayers were fervently offered with my
own. I had left my wife in Virginia, and
come to Baltimore, a distance of over a hundred
miles; I had been separated thus for
nearly three years; I had been trying to make
arrangements to have her with me, for over
twelve months, and as yet had failed. We
were oppressed with the most gloomy forebodings,
and could only kneel down together
and pray for God's direction and help.</p>
          <p>I was in Fredericksburg, and had but one
day longer to stay, and spend with my wife.
What could be done, must be done quickly.
I went to my old friend, Mr. Wright, and
stated my case to him. After hearing of all
I had done, and the conditions I had to
comply with, he told me that if I would raise the
<pb id="davis39" n="39"/>
six hundred dollars cash, he would endorse
my bond for the remaining three hundred.—
This promise inspired me with new life. The
next thing was, how could the six hundred
dollars be obtained in six weeks. I had
upon my subscription list and in pledges
nearly four hundred dollars. But this had to be
collected from friends living in Fredericksburg,
Washington city, Baltimore, and Philadelphia.</p>
          <p>I left Fredericksburg, and spent a few days
in Washington, to collect what I could of the
money promised to me there; and met much
encouragement, several friends doubling their
subscriptions. When I arrived in Baltimore,
and made known the peculiar strait I was in,
to my joyful surprise, some of the friends who
had pledged five dollars, gave me ten; and
one dear friend who had promised me ten
dollars, for this object, and who had previously
contributed largely in the purchase of myself,
now gave me fifty. I began to count up, and
in two weeks from the time I commenced
collecting, I had in hand four hundred dollars.
Presently, another very dear friend enquired
of me how I was getting along; and when I
told him, he said, “Bring your money to me.”
<pb id="davis40" n="40"/>
I did so. It lacked two hundred dollars to
make the purchase. This, the best friend I
ever had in the world, made up the six
hundred dollars, and said, “Go, get your wife;
and you can keep on collecting, and repay
the two hundred dollars when you get able.”</p>
          <p>I was now overcome with, gratitude and
joy, and knew not what to say; and when I
began to speak, he would not have any of my
thanks. I went to my boarding house, and
shut myself up in my room, where I might
give vent to the gratitude of my heart: and,
O, what a melting time I had! It was to me
a day of thanksgiving.</p>
          <p>Having now in band the six hundred
dollars, and the promise of Mr. Wright's security
for three hundred more, I was, by twelve
o'clock, next day in Fredericksburg.</p>
          <p>At first sight, my wife was surprised that
I had come back so soon; for it was only two
weeks since I had left her; and when I
informed her that I had come after her and the
children, she could hardly believe me. In a
few days, having duly arranged all things
relative to the purchase and removal, we left
for Baltimore, with feelings commingled with
joy and sorrow—sorrow at parting with five
<pb id="davis41" n="41"/>
of our older children, and our many friends;
and rejoicing in the prospect of remaining
together permanently in the missionary field,
where God had called me to labor. I arrived
in Baltimore, with my wife and two little
ones, November 5th, 1851, and stopped with
sister Hester Ann Hughes, a worthy member
of the M. E. Church, with whom I had been
boarding for four years.</p>
          <p>The Md. Baptist Union Association was
now in session here, and it became my duty
to prepare my church letter and missionary
report, for that body. The church had now
been organized just three years; commencing
with only four members, including the pastor.
Our church statistics for the year, as
reported, were: Baptized, 2; Received by letter,
2; Present number of members, 15 . . . . . .
Sabbath school much revived, under the
special efforts of several white brethren and
sisters. Present number of Sunday scholars, 50.</p>
          <p>This year was a joyful one to me—my
little church increasing, and the Sabbath school
flourishing, under the superintendence of the
late truly excellent brother James C. Crane,
though he was with us but for a short season.
My wife and little ones were also with
<pb id="davis42" n="42"/>
me, both in the church and Sabbath school.
I was a happy man, and felt more than ever
inclined to give thanks to God, and serve Him
to the best of my ability.</p>
          <p>My salary was only three hundred dollars
a year; but with hard exertion and close
economy, together with my wife's taking in
washing and going out at day's work, we
were enabled by the first of the year, to pay
the two hundred dollars our dear friend had
loaned us, in raising, the six hundred dollars
before spoken of. But the bond for three
hundred dollars was now due, and how must this
be met? I studied out a plan; which was to
get some gentleman who might want a little
servant girl, to take my child, and advance
me three hundred dollars for the purpose of
paying my note, which was now due in Virginia.
In this plan I succeeded; and had my
own life insured for seven years for five
hundred dollars, and made it over to this
gentleman, as security; until I ultimately paid
him the whole amount; though I was several
years in paying it.</p>
          <p>Among the number that joined our little
church, was a young brother, Jos. M. Harden,
who was baptized by Dr. Fuller, but soon
<pb id="davis43" n="43"/>
became a valuable member with us, both in
the church and Sunday school. He was born
in Baltimore, and had been early taught to
read, and though he had been at ten years
old bound out, till he was twenty-one, his
love of books had made him far superior to
colored people generally, and he was very
valuable to me. Things had gone on hopefully
with me, and my little church, though
our progress was very slow. But we had to
suffer a loss in brother Harden's leaving us
for the great missionary field in Africa,
where I trust the Lord has sent him for a
great and happy work. But God has blessed
us in the person of brother Samuel W.
Madden, whose labors as a licensed preacher for
several years have been invaluable to us.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <pb id="davis44" n="44"/>
          <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
          <argument>
            <p>A New Movement in Baltimore—Erection of a Meeting
House for the African Baptist Church—Heavy Indebtedness
—Account of the Enterprise—Personal Troubles.</p>
          </argument>
          <p>FOR several years previous to Jan., 1855,
our little church and Sunday school had
occupied a very inconvenient upper room on
Courtland street. Our particular friend, Mr.
William Crane, with some other white persons
to aid him, was the devoted superintendent
of our Sunday school, and the unfailing
friend of our own little church, as well as of
me personally. Mr. Crane had felt, with us,
the great disadvantage of our place of
worship, and had exerted himself much to obtain
a more commodious room for us. But in
July, 1853; he commenced an extraordinary
effort in our behalf, by purchasing a lot—
one hundred feet by forty-six feet—with three
fronts, on Calvert, Saratoga and Davis streets,
on which a chapel building has been erected
for us.</p>
          <p>Our chapel was opened for worship Feb. 18,
1855; and Rev. Dr. Fuller preached the
opening sermon to a crowded audience.</p>
          <p>On this occasion Mr. Wm. Crane read a
<pb id="davis45" n="45"/>
detailed report of all the facts relative to this 
building—a full copy of this report may be
interesting probably to my readers, and I
have therefore obtained it, and here present
it, in connection with a picture of the building,
which will be found opposite the title page.</p>
          <q direct="unspecified">
            <text>
              <body>
                <div1 type="insert">
                  <head>HISTORY OF THE SARATOGA STREET AFRICAN
<lb/>
BAPTIST CHAPEL.</head>
                  <p>“THE questions have often been asked in
this vicinity during the last six months,
Who is putting up that large building called
the ‘Saratoga Street African Baptist Chapel?’
‘What are they putting it up for?’—
‘Who will own it, when finished?’ ‘How
much will it cost? and who will pay for it?’</p>
                  <p>These questions have often been answered,
but it seems proper, and indeed necessary, at
this time to answer them plainly and clearly,
for the information of this large assembly.</p>
                  <p>First, then, I reply: This, entire building
has been reared under my directions, in the
name of the Saratoga street African Baptist Church.</p>
                  <p>This Church was organized with only four
<pb id="miss46" n="46"/>
members, six years ago, with brother Noah
Davis, a missionary of the Md. Baptist Union
Association, as its pastor, who has labored
post faithfully in his work. But, although
colored churches of the Baptist denomination
in all of our Southern and Western cities
count their members by thousands, this church
has now only thirty members—but our hope
and prayer is, that established here in the
centre of a population of full thirty thousand
colored people, God may bless the humble
devoted efforts of His people, and increase
their numbers a hundred fold. Four years
ago, the 1st of January, we commenced a
Sunday school in Courtland street,—where
this church has always held its regular meetings,
which notwithstanding its many discouragements—
mostly from a want of devoted
self-denying teachers—has been unremittingly
kept up morning and afternoon, till
the present time, with an attendance
varying from thirty to over one hundred
scholars; and we feel assured that the hundreds
of Bibles and Testaments, tracts, &amp;c., with
the Sunday school instructions, and the
preaching of brother Davis will have laid the
foundation for a lasting blessing to his people
<pb id="davis47" n="47"/>
This little church and Sunday school
have met to-day for the first time in this
building, and in the language of the Psalmist
David, probably on an occasion like this, we
would exclaim, “Send now, we beseech thee,
O Lord—O Lord, we beseech thee, send now
Prosperity!”—(Ps. 118: 25.)</p>
                  <p>But what are the objects for which this
house has been built? I answer, the first
object was, to furnish such a room as this, for
the use of this church, where the gospel might
be preached and its ordinances administered,
and where Sunday schools and religious 
associations might be properly accommodated.
The second was, to furnish rooms in the next
story, for a male high school at one end, and
a female high school at the other, and where
colored missionaries for Africa might be
educated for that most important field of labor;
with a large hall in the centre, for a lecture
room, or for any other religious, moral, or
useful purposes. The upper story has four
separate rooms, finished for renting to
associations of colored people, with a view to
paying whatever debt may remain on the building,
and for defraying its current expenses;
—and it is hoped that, at some future day, a
<pb id="davis48" n="48"/>
reading room and a circulating library for
colored people may also be located here—the
whole of it combining a most respectable,
central, commodious <hi rend="italics">Colored People's Home.</hi></p>
                  <p>But it is asked, who owns this building?
I admit that it is an unusually mixed up affair;
but I will try to explain it. After a
great deal of searching and enquiring after a
lot or building, where this Church and Sunday
school could have a settled home, about
two years ago, I was I informed that this lot
was for sale; and realizing instantly that my
cherished objects could here be accomplished
I bought it without hesitation, for five
thousand dollars; but the loss of two years' interest
and the amount paid to tenants to move away,
makes the cost of the lot now full six thousand
dollars. I obtained the deed of J.H.B.
Latrobe, Esq., who sold it, as trustee for the
estate of Hugh Finley, deceased, under an
order of Court. After a charter of incorporation
for the Church had been made, I got Mr.
Latrobe to draw up also this deed, [here
presenting it] which he says is a perfectly good
one—from William Crane and wife, to Geo.
F. Adams, J. W. M. Williams, and John W.
Ball, as trustees for all concerned, conveying
<pb id="davis49" n="49"/>
to this Church all my right and title forever
to all of the proposed building on this lot
above the. first story: leaving me the
basement and the cellar as my own property
forever with the proviso, that the Church in its
own name should put up the entire building.
But I agreed at the same time to subscribe
five thousand dollars on the subscription book
of the Church towards erecting it. So that
I am now sole owner of the store and cellar
under the Chapel—the Church has no ownership
there at all—but the Church is legal,
owner of this Chapel and all the rooms above
it. The Church appointed me their agent to
build the house, and as, such I have made all
the contracts, paid out all the monies, and
assumed all the liabilities. Before commencing
the building, as before stated, my own
subscription was . . . . . $5,000
<list type="simple"><item>My brother, J. C. Crane, from whom I
expected efficient personal aid, gave . .1,000</item><item>Bro. Franklin, Wilson, . . . . . 1,000</item><item>A. Fuller Crane, . . . . . 500</item><item>John W. Ball, . . . . . 250</item><item>J. B. Thomas, . . . . . 100</item><item>Among our colored friends, about . . . . . 200</item><item>Amounting to, say, . . . . . $8,050</item></list></p>
                  <pb id="davis50" n="50"/>
                  <p>Since that time, the pressure on the money
market has prevented any general effort to
obtain subscriptions, but a city pastor has
subscribed . . . . . $150
<list type="simple"><item>A sister of the First Baptist Church . . . . . 100</item><item>Bro. Jonathan Batchelor, of Lynn, Mass . . . 100</item><item>Making in all, a total of . . . . . $8,400</item></list></p>
                  <p>The entire cost of the building, notwithstanding
the most rigid economy, will be over
eighteen thousand dollars, and full half of
this amount is yet unprovided for. The bills
are not all presented, but some of the larger
ones which have been settled by notes will be
due in a short time; while the largest one,
the lumber bill, has six months to run yet,
so that I am bound to settle up and pay the
entire balance of expenditure on this house,
as agent of the Church, within the coming
six months. And whatever amount of money
I advance over and above the subscriptions
and collections must, of course, remain as a
debt due me by the Church, and be on interest
until paid.</p>
                  <p>The last question, how is the money obtained
to pay for the building? has been partly
answered; but a full explanation of it will
<pb id="davis51" n="51"/>
depend on what the friends of the object will
now contribute toward paying for it. I will
subscribe one dollar for every ten dollars that
may be subscribed and paid on account of the
Church debt within the year 1855. In other
words, I will add ten per cent to any amount
which may be contributed. I may remark,
that in engaging in this project, I had not a
dollar which I wished to put out at interest.
I want much more than my capital in my
mercantile business. I am in fact borrowing,
to lend to the Church. But it is God's cause,
and I have had to trust in Him to bear me
through it. The failing health of my dear
brother, J. C. Crane,<ref id="ref1" n="1" rend="sc" target="note1" targOrder="U">*</ref> and the want of his
invaluable cooperation with me, as well as
the lack of hearty, zealous assistance on the
part of many other brethren and friends, has
been painful to me. But I hope, now that the
house is finished, the friends of our Redeemer's
cause and of the African race generally,
may not fail in lending their efficient aid.</p>
                  <p>I have only to add, brethren, “the time is
short;” we must all of us soon appear before
the judgment seat of Christ, to render an account
<note id="note1" n="1" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref1">* Died March 31 1857 See Memoir of Southern Baptist
Publication Society</note>
<pb id="davis52" n="52"/>
of all the talents committed to our
charge. If God has given me a talent for
the acquisition of money over and above
what my duty to my family requires, I
regard myself bound as a good steward to
exert that talent entirely for Him. I am not
my own, and I feel perfectly assured that any
individual who possesses the tact and ability
for acquiring money is <sic corr="necessarily">neccessarily</sic> the best
qualified for a judicious and proper disbursement
of it; and I dare not try to leave my
earthly acquisitions in testamentary charitable
bequests—to the inexperienced and
uncertain management of those who may come
after me.</p>
                  <p>May God help us to work for Him, and at
last may we hear, ‘Well done, good and
faithful servant; enter thou into the joy of
thy Lord.’”</p>
                </div1>
              </body>
            </text>
          </q>
          <p>This paper was read to the congregation,
probably a thousand people, immediately
after Dr. Fuller had preached the opening
sermon, Feb, 18, 1855; and a collection was
taken of about one hundred dollars. Subsequent
to this, a venerable widow lady of
Baltimore contributed $500, and other quite
liberal donations were made.</p>
          <pb id="davis53" n="53"/>
          <p>On the 1st of July, 1855, Mr. Crane
rendered a full account to the Church and trustees,
of all the monies received and bills paid on the building;
showing that the entire cost
of it was, . . . . . $18,207,73<lb/>
Total am't of collections credited, . . .9,547,86<lb/>
Leaving balance over-paid by him, . . $8,659,87</p>
          <p>The trustees then gave Mr. Crane a bond
for this balance, and a lease on the building,
until this debt, with interest on it, could be
paid.</p>
          <p>Our Church now had great cause of gratitude
at finding ourselves in a fine large Chapel,
in the centre of our city—a room 100 feet
long, and 19 feet high, with a gallery at each
end, a baptistery, gas lights, and sliding
partitions, to make two closed rooms under
the galleries, when needed for the changing
of clothes on baptismal occasions, as well as
for our Church prayer and conference
meetings.</p>
          <p>We were in hopes that we could rent out
the large hall, together with the six other
spacious rooms in the two upper stories, for
schools, benevolent societies, &amp;c., so as to
pay the interest on our debt, if no more; but
<pb id="davis54" n="54"/>
so far, we have not been able to do this. My
own trials , with my family, have greatly
retarded my efforts in this matter. We have
had the largest and best week-day school for
colored children in the city—a part of the
time with three teachers and over one hundred
scholars—but for four years, no rent has
been received from the school. The prices
for tuition have been so low, that they have
hardly sustained the teachers; but we trust
that our people have derived much benefit
from them already, and hope they may
receive much more good from them in the
future. Since the dedication of our Chapel,
our Church has more than doubled its membership,
and the congregation has increased
four-fold; while on our baptizing occasions
the hall is generally full. We have always
held three meetings for worship every Sunday,
to accommodate many servants, who
have no command of their time, and also
regular Wednesday and Friday evening prayer
and conference meetings. Our Sunday school
has always had two sessions a day—an hour
and a half in the morning, and an hour in
the afternoon.</p>
          <p>I have been necessarily much hindered in
<pb id="davis55" n="55"/>
my own labors, from pecuniary embarrassments,
arising from the sale of my children,
who were left in Virginia—two daughters
and three sons. The first of these, who was
about to be sold, and taken away South, was
my oldest daughter; and it was with great
difficulty and the help of friends that I raised
eight hundred and fifty dollars, and got her
on to Baltimore. But I was soon called upon
to make a similar effort to save my eldest son
from being sold far from me. Entirely unexpected,
I received the painful news that my
boy was in one of the trader's jails in Richmond,
and for sale. The dealer knew me,
and was disposed to let me have him, if I
could get any one to purchase him. I was,
of course, deeply anxious to help my boy;
but I began to think that I had already drawn
so heavily on the liberality of all my friends,
that to appeal to them again seemed out of
the question. I immediately wrote to the
owners of my son, and received an 
answer—that his price was 
fixed at seven hundred
dollars.</p>
          <p>The fact is, God had already done so much
more for me and my family than we had
ever expected that we could not tell what further
<pb id="davis56" n="56"/>
help He might give us, until we had
asked Him for it; and we could but pray over
this trying affair. I hardly knew what else
to do, but pray. The boy was twenty years
old, and had been I accustomed to waiting in
the house, for the most respectable families.
It occurred to me, that I might perhaps get
him a home near me, where we might see him
and use our parental influence over him. I
thought it was possible, that I might find
three hundred persons among my friends in
Baltimore, who would contribute one dollar
each to save my son, and that I might then
obtain some friend in Baltimore to advance
four hundred dollars, and let my son work it
out with him: and give this friend a life
insurance policy on the boy, as a security. This
plan seemed practicable, and I wrote to his
owners, asking for ten days to raise the money;
which they granted me.</p>
          <p>I now got my case made known publicly to
the different colored congregations in the city
—and was very much surprised to find how
many friends I had, and how kindly they
engaged in helping me. The result of it was,
that I obtained the three hundred dollars,
and also a kind friend to advance the four
<pb id="davis57" n="57"/>
hundred dollars, within the ten days, and
recovered my son; who is now doing well, in
working out the money advanced on him.</p>
          <p>So far, I felt that I had great reason to say,
“Hitherto the Lord hath helped me.” I had
obtained my own freedom and also that of my
wife and four children.</p>
          <p>But three of my children were still in bondage.
In 1856, the mistress of these remaining
ones died; and in settling up her estate,
it became necessary to sell all her servants at
auction with her other property. This was
the decision of the Court; and commissioners
were appointed to carry out the sale, on the
1st of January, 1857. I felt now, that I had
gone as far as I could in getting my family
free; for I felt very certain that my daughter,
about whom I felt the greatest anxiety,
would sell at auction for more money than I
could get any of my friends in Baltimore to
give for her; and I saw no way to do any
thing for the two boys. I thought I had no
chance of raising any more money myself,
and I could only pray the Lord to grant
no His grace, to reconcile us and the children,
to whatever might come upon us. But
before the end of the year, when the sale was
<pb id="davis58" n="58"/>
to take place, the time was extended six
months by the Court. My hopes now began
to revive again; I began to think that if I
could be at the sale, my daughter, though a
grown up girl might possibly not bring over
six or seven hundred dollars. In that case,
I might perhaps get six or twelve months
time, and get some friend in Baltimore to
help me, as had been the case with my son.
The sale was postponed for six months longer,
and finally occurred, Jan. 1, 1858.</p>
          <p>The money panic, of 1857, had partially
destroyed my hopes of doing anything to
relieve my daughter;—But I had secured the
promise of a kind friend in Baltimore, to go
to Fredericksburg with me, and if he liked
the appearance of the boys, to buy one or both
of them. But in this I was disappointed;
for on the day of sale this gentleman was
confined to his house by sickness. The sale
went on. My oldest son, aged twenty-one,
sold for $560; and the younger one, just
turning his seventeenth year, brought $570.
They were bought in by their young master.
But my daughter was run up to $990, by a
slave trader, who after the sale agreed to let
my friends have her, for me, for eleven hundred
<pb id="davis59" n="59"/>
dollars. These friends were gentlemen
of the first standing in the place, who,
out of kindness to me, whom they had well
known for years, gave their bond jointly
for the amount, and in this case again I got
the girl's life insured for one thousand dollars
as a security for them. The girl was of
course left in the hands of these gentlemen,
in, whom I had the most implicit confidence.</p>
          <p>I returned to Baltimore, and prepared for
the redemption of my child. I had a circular
printed, showing the facts as they were,
and scattered it among my friends.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <pb id="davis60" n="60"/>
          <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
          <argument>
            <p>Account of a Visit to the northern 
Cities—True Friends.</p>
          </argument>
          <p>During the winter and spring, I used every
effort in my power in the way of collecting
funds, but, though I met with the most
generous sympathy and kindness from all my
friends—up to the 1st of June I had in hand
only one hundred and fifty dollars. I then
applied to the Mission Board for permission
to travel and solicit funds to help me out of
my distress. This was readily granted me.
Having obtained a certificate, relative to the
objects of my journey, signed by Rev. Franklin
Wilson, Secretary of our State Missionary
Board, as well as by the pastors and
other friends in Baltimore, I started once
more on this painful business of begging
money, to purchase my fifth child out of
slavery. I went to Philadelphia, and met with
marked attention from the ministers of the
Baptist churches generally, and especially
from Rev. Messrs. McKean, Cole, and Griffith,
with whom I had been acquainted in Baltimore;
as well as Revs. Messrs Cuthbert and
Malcom, and the editors of the Christian
<pb id="davis61" n="61"/>
Chronicle, Presbyterian, &amp;c. I obtained in
this city nearly two hundred dollars.</p>
          <p>With a view to meet a particular friend in
Boston, I was induced to visit that city next.
The many acts of kindness and sympathy I
met with there can never be effaced from my
memory. I had a special introduction to the
Messrs., Gould and Lincoln, book publishers.
To the latter, I owe a lasting obligation.—
Through him I obtained a hearing of my case
in Mr. Anderson's church, Roxbury, where I
obtained very liberal aid, while the pastor
was absent, as well as in many other cases.</p>
          <p>I called on Rev. Dr. Stow, who allowed my
case to be presented to his congregation, at
an evening meeting, where I received some
fifty dollars. He also gave me a letter of
commendation to the other Baptist ministers,
with a request that they would also sign it,
which a large number did. The article was
then published gratuitously for me in the
“Watchman, and Reflector” and “Christian
Era,” Rev. L.A. Grimes, pastor of the 12th
Baptist Church, (colored,) from the respectable
position which he occupied in the community,
did much for me, in furthering my
<pb id="davis62" n="62"/>
cause, and, introducing me to others, especially
at the daily prayer meetings.</p>
          <p>I had the great privilege and pleasure of
mingling with the people of God of every
name, in these blessed meetings. The first I
went to, was at the old South Chapel. Here
I felt at first greatly <sic corr="embarrassed">embarrased</sic> when called
on to speak or pray. I thought that those
who came to these meetings must be among
the most pious and intelligent people in
Boston. The kind manner in which they
treated me, confirmed me in my impressions
of them. But the best meetings, I think I
ever enjoyed on earth, for such a length of
time, (nearly two months,) was at what was
called the North street prayer meeting, or
Father Mason's. This was in a large upper
room. It really appeared to me, that the
most of those who met at this place each day
at twelve <sic corr="o'clock">oclock</sic> to spend an hour in prayer,
to tell what God had done for their souls,
bad been made “ready,” by the Spirit of
God before they reached that sacred spot.—</p>
          <p>I know I shall fail to present a true picture
of this heavenly place; for such it was
to me, and many others. But, it may be,
that my own peculiar circumstances may
<pb id="davis63" n="63"/>
have rendered the meetings unusually precious
to me. But they were good to me in
many respects. I was a poor colored man, in
distress, and needed christian sympathy. I
found it truly, among the many white friends
with whom I met in the North street prayer
meeting. There, in that meeting, the dear
friends would pray with me and for me. In
a word, I felt at times it was good for me to
be afflicted, for surely, if it bad not been for
my peculiar circumstances, I should never
have been inside the Old South Chapel, or
North street prayer meeting, where I enjoyed
so much of God's presence, and found so
many real friends, in the midst of strangers.
I felt that I realized what the apostle Peter
meant: “If need be, ye are in heaviness,
through manifold temptation, that the trials
of your faith, being much more precious than
gold that perisheth, though it be tried with
fire, might be found unto praise and honor
and glory, at the appearing of Jesus Christ.”
—(1 Peter 1: 6,7.) Also, “For I will show
him how great things he must suffer for my
name's sake.”—(Acts 9: 16.) The arguments
I drew from these passages of Scripture
were, to show that when God wanted to
<pb id="davis64" n="64"/>
purify our faith, and strengthen our confidence
in Him, He would send trials upon us.
And to let us see how great the things we
must suffer for His name's sake, and to let
us see too how great the grace He gives us,
to enable us to endure hardness, as good soldiers
of the cross.</p>
          <p>Suffice it to say, the friends in Boston and
its vicinity gave me about four hundred dollars
towards the purchase of my daughter. I
had the privilege of meeting the Baptist
ministers in their conference meeting. Here the
Rev. Mr. Tilson, pastor of the First Baptist
Church at Hingham, invited we to spend
a Sunday evening at his place, which I did,
very greatly to my own satisfaction and profit.
During my stay in Boston, I visited
several of the smaller towns adjacent to it,—
Lynn, Cambridge, Melrose, Malden, Chelsea,
and others, and I was kindly received at all
of them. I collected in Lynn something
like $50, the most of which was given to me
by the members of the 2nd Baptist Church.
Just before leaving Boston, to my great and
agreeable surprise, I met Dr. F. Patten, surgeon
in the U.S. Navy, (my former owner,)
in the street, in that city. I had not seen
<pb id="davis65" n="65"/>
him for seven or eight years, and had no
thought of seeing him in Boston. He
recognized me first, and spoke to me before I
knew he was near; but I instantly knew him.
We greeted each other heartily, and he invited
me to visit him at Chelsea. This I did,
the same afternoon, and was kindly treated.</p>
          <p>While I sat there with him and his children,
and he was looking over my subscription
book, I was constrained to look back for
fifteen years, over all the way the Lord had
brought me, since the day this same gentleman
had given me privilege to purchase my
freedom, and handed me a pass, saying, “I
am not afraid of you running away, Noah—
you may go where you please.” I reflected,
suppose I had stayed away, when I was in
Boston, twelve years ago, begging money to
buy myself—how would it be with me and
my family to-day? But I have tried to
acknowledge the Lord in all my ways, always
asking counsel of Him, and I now feel that
He has kindly directed and kept me.</p>
          <p>I also visited New Bedford, where I met a
large number of my old acquaintances from
Virginia, and had the privilege of presenting
my object to several of the Churches, and I
<pb id="davis66" n="66"/>
received in all about $50. I next went to
Providence, Rhode Island, where I spent a
couple of weeks greatly to my advantage. It
was indeed “providence” to me. I was
permitted to present my case to nearly all the
Baptist Churches in that city. Five of these
aided my cause; but their great kindness
deserves some particular notice. The first one
I visited was Rev. Mr. Stone's, whose congregation,
with himself, greatly encouraged me.
At the First Church I told my story before an
evening meeting, and shall never forget the
kindness of the pastor, the senior deacon, and
others. I obtained here nearly $100. I was
kindly assisted by Rev. Mr. Keyser's Church,
also the Fourth Baptist Church. But at
the Central Baptist Church, Rev. Mt. Fields',
I found unbounded kindness and liberality.
After seeing my letters of recommendation,
the pastor invited me to his prayer meeting,
where I was favored with the privilege of
telling my story, freely. I had been from
home several months, and had collected in all
about seven hundred dollars, but still lacked
about four hundred to accomplish my object.
I was receiving letters every week from my
Church and family, saying that my presence
<pb id="davis67" n="67"/>
at home was greatly needed; but the idea of
going home without accomplishing my great
object, filled me with distress. While speaking
to the meeting, and telling how God had
delivered me from time to time out of trials,
I felt such a sense of my condition, that for
the moment I could not restrain my feelings
—my heart became so full, that it stopped all
utterance. At the close of the meeting, the
people showed their sympathy for me by giving
me a collection of sixty one 
dollars.—One dear brother, 
(may the Lord bless him!)
came forward, and presenting me with a ten
dollar bill, said, “Brother Davis, give yourself
no more trouble about that daughter.—
You say you have to stop in New York. Let
me say, that when you get home, whatever
you lack of the four hundred dollars, write
to me, and I will send you a check for the
balance.” This was spoken in the presence
of the whole meeting. I felt completely at
a loss for words of gratitude and thanksgiving
and merely said, the day is broke, and
the Lord has appeared for me indeed!</p>
          <p>I now left Providence, feeling  in my heart
that the place is rightly called by that name,
as far as I am concerned.</p>
          <pb id="davis68" n="68"/>
          <p>I then went to New York. In that great
city, I met with considerable assistance.
I never started out, but it seemed that the
Lord directed my steps. I was allowed to
address a prayer meeting of the First Baptist
Church, whose pastor was the late excellent
Rev. A.K. Nott, and was aided to the amount
of over seventy dollars.</p>
          <p>Rev. Dr. Lathrop, with much christian
kindness, invited me to his night meeting;
but a severe rain prevented any attendance.
He invited me again, and then he was absent
because of illness. I was depressed with
disappointment; but he had sent a request that
I might be heard, (as I afterward learned,)
and I was called on to state my case to the
audience. I was taken by surprise, for the
pastor's illness had taken all hope from me
of accomplishing anything there. Still I begun,
by telling my experience. I said that
when it had pleased God to convert my soul,
I thought that all my trouble was gone, and
gone forever; but I had since learned that I
was much mistaken—I had learned that “in
the world we shall have tribulation.” I then
went on to state my present trouble and
distress—and before I left the meeting, I
<pb id="davis69" n="69"/>
received with heart-felt gratitude, one hundred
and thirty four dollars, This reminded me
of Providence.</p>
          <p>Rev. Drs. Gillette and Armitage treated
me with much generous sympathy, as also
did many others.</p>
          <p>I visited Greenport on Long Island, where
Rev. Henry Knapp kindly aided me. Elders
Swan and Read, and the brethren generally
at New London, aided me to the amount of
about fifty dollars.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <pb id="davis70" n="70"/>
          <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
          <argument>
            <p>Conclusion—Object of this Book.</p>
          </argument>
          <p>I NOW left the north, for home, and arrived
there safely. My friends greeted me
cordially on my success in collecting money.</p>
          <p>I still lacked, however, one hundred and
forty-two dollars of the needed eleven hundred.
I had used every effort in my power
to prevent the necessity of having to call on
my generous friend in Providence. But
in spite of all my endeavors, I had to make
known to him this deficiency, which he
immediately and generously supplied, by
remitting me a check for the full amount.</p>
          <p>I was now prepared to go after my daughter,
which I did, December 1st, 1858; thus
releasing her within one year from the time
she was sold. She is now with me, and
doing well.</p>
          <p>I received a promise from the young master
of my two sons, at the time he purchased
them, that if I should succeed in paying for
my daughter during that year, he would let
me know what I might have my two boys
for. At the time, my boys were about
<pb id="davis71" n="71"/>
returning to Richmond, where they had been
hired out for several years. I charged them
to let me hear a good report of their conduct;
and if I could do anything for them, after I
had got through with the purchase of their
sister, I would do it. This. pledge I made
to the boys, in the presence of their master's
agent.</p>
          <p>Having, through the aid of a kind Providence,
been enabled to pay for my daughter,
I have felt it my duty to turn my attention
toward redeeming my word to my last children
now in bondage.</p>
          <p>But this, of course, has called up anxious
thought and prayerful meditation. I have
also considered the peculiar condition of my
church—the large outlay of money in the
erection of the building, and the heavy debt
hanging upon it, which is increased every
year by the interest. I have also considered
how long I have been supported in this field
of labor by the Missionary Board of the Southern
Baptist Convention and the Maryland
Baptist Union Association.</p>
          <p>The question then occurred to me, Could
I not, by <hi rend="italics">making a book,</hi> do something to
relieve myself and my children, and ultimately,
<pb id="davis72" n="72"/>
by the same means, help my church,
under its heavy debt, and also relieve the
Missionary Board from helping me. This
idea struck me with so, much force, that I
have yielded to it—that is, to write a short
Narrative of my own life, setting forth the
trials and difficulties the Lord has brought
me through to this day, and offer it for sale
to my friends generally, as well as to the
public at large; and, I hope it may not only
aid me, but may serve to encourage others,
who meet with similar difficulties, to put
their trust in God.</p>
        </div2>
        <trailer>END OF THE NARRATIVE.</trailer>
      </div1>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div1 type="sermon">
        <pb id="davis73" n="73"/>
        <head>SERMON.</head>
        <byline>BY REV. NOAH DAVIS</byline>
        <epigraph>
          <p>TEXT.—“But if any provide not for his own, and
especially for those of his own house, he hath denied
the faith, and is worse than an infidel.”—1 Tim. 5: 8.</p>
        </epigraph>
        <p>IN this chapter, we have several christian
duties set forth by the apostle Paul, to
Timothy, a young preacher of the gospel, who was
to teach other christians to observe them, as
evidences of the genuineness of their faith
in Christ.</p>
        <p>That faith which does not produce obedience
to the commands of Jesus must be regarded
as defective. Religion requires us to
love God, and all men, and we must show
our faith, by a life consistent with our
profession.</p>
        <p>If human nature, fallen as it is, prompts
men of the world to labor zealously to supply
their own temporal necessities and the wants
of those whom Providence has made to
depend upon them, how much more will it be
expected of those who profess to have drank
<pb id="davis74" n="74"/>
of that pure Fountain of love, the Spirit of
our blessed Lord and Saviour, Jesus Christ.
God has indeed doomed man to eat his bread
in the sweat of his face; but as if to reward
him, he has connected with it a pleasure in
the labor, and especially, in our efforts to do
good to others.</p>
        <p>In speaking from these words, let us first
consider what is here meant by “providing”
for “his own;” secondly, “and especially
for those of his own house;” thirdly, what
it is to “deny the faith;” and lastly, draw a
comparison between the one who “hath
denied the faith” and the “infidel.”</p>
        <p>1. In the first place, we are to consider
the duty enjoined in the text, to provide for
our own: which we understand to mean our
own temporal wants, such as food and raiment
and every temporal benefit. Every man is
bound by the laws of nature to provide for
himself the necessaries of life, honestly in the
sight of God and men, as far as in him lieth.
This both reason and common sense dictate.
This religion inspires. “He that will not
work, shall not eat,” is the teaching of the
Word of God. “Provide things honest in the
sight of all men,” is the instruction of the
<pb id="davis75" n="75"/>
great apostle to the Gentiles; at the same
time giving them an example, by working
with his own hands, to supply his necessities,
and the wants of those who were with him.
I have heard it said that a lazy person cannot
be a christian, and the same idea seems to be
supported in my text.</p>
        <p>“But if any provide not for his own.” Religion
benefits those who possess it, by regulating
their appetite for temporal things, as
well as giving them a relish for spiritual
ones. While we are in love with sin, we
labor hard to enjoy its pleasures. How
industriously do wicked men labor for what they
can eat, drink and wear. And shall a christian
be less active to secure for himself the
necessaries of life?—he would prove himself
indeed to be worse than the infidel. But we
have other wants to be supplied, beside those
of the body. God has given to all men an
intellectual nature—a mind, which
distinguishes them from the brutes. These minds
are capable of improvement; and every man
is under obligation to make use of the means
and opportunities which God has given him
for cultivating his mind, by educating
himself, that he may be useful to himself and
<pb id="davis76" n="76"/>
those around him. But man is a social
being as well as an intellectual one. “God
hath made of one blood, all nations of men,
for to dwell on all the face of the earth.—
(Acts 17: 26.) Much of our happiness, and
usefulness in this world arises from this
quality which man possesses over the animal
creation. And just in proportion, as we shall
cultivate, and refine our social and intellectual
natures, just in that proportion, shall
we rise above the level of the savage and
the heathen.</p>
        <p>But man has a soul, which must be fitted
for the enjoyment of God, here and hereafter.
Now to provide for the wants of the soul, is
our highest duty on earth.—Sin has unclothed
us of that innocence in which our
Creator first made us, and the responsibility
now rests upon every soul, to provide a clothing
which will stand the inspection of God
himself. This clothing, Christ has prepared
through His sufferings, and death, and it is
given to all them that believe in Him. And
surely, if it be our duty to provide temporal
things for ourselves, and for those of our own
house, how much more are we bound to seek
and secure the one thing needful.</p>
        <pb id="davis77" n="77"/>
        <p>2. But we will consider in the second place,
what is meant by providing for our own
house?—“and especially for those of his own
house?” House here means family. First,
we will consider the duty devolving upon a
christian parent, in making suitable provision
for his own house, or family. This
embraces all we have urged as his duty to
himself. It is the duty of all parents, to
provide for their families every temporal good
which adds to their own comfort or usefulness
in life. And it is no less the duty of parents
to provide for the spiritual necessities of their
own families. And first—we shall consider
the duty of parents, to provide suitable training
for their children. This is a duty which
God has enjoined and approves. He said of
Abraham, “For I know him, that he will
command his children and his household after
him, and they shall keep the way of the
Lord, to do justice and judgment, that the
Lord may bring upon Abraham, that which
He hath spoken of him.” The duty of parents
to train their children religiously, is
clearly taught under the gospel dispensation.</p>
        <p>“And ye fathers, provoke not your children
to wrath, but bring them up in the nurture
<pb id="davis78" n="78"/>
and admonition of the Lord.” Here,
we have divine authority, for teaching our
children, the things, which make for their
good, both in this life and that which is to
come. But it may be asked, to what extent
are parents bound to comply with these high
and solemn obligations? We answer, to the
utmost of their ability. To whom much is
given, of him much is required, and to whom
little is given, of him little is required.—
But all are bound to train up their children
“in the way they should go, that when they
are old, they may not depart from it.” This
duty is seen in the judgments which God has
visited upon those parents and children who
have neglected to obey the Lord in this
particular.—(1 Samuel 2: 34.)</p>
        <p>3. We are, in the third place, to enquire
what it is to “deny the faith.” Much is said
in the Scriptures about faith. Much depends
upon it. We are said to be “justified by
faith,” and “saved by faith;” we “live by
faith.” And inasmuch, as such as are spoken
of in the text are said to be worse than an
infidel, because they provide not for themselves
and families, thereby showing that they
have denied the faith, therefore let us try to
<pb id="davis79" n="79"/>
consider what genuine faith is, and what it
is to deny it. This  is the most important
point in the subject now before us. “Without
faith it is impossible to please God.”</p>
        <p>We will consider some of the effects of this
distinguishing grace. There are several
kinds of faith spoken of in the Bible. In one
case, men are said to “believe for a while.”
This faith is shown us in the parable taught
by our blessed Saviour, in the characters
represented by the seed sown upon the rock,
“which for a while believe, and in time of
temptation fall away.”—(Luke 8: 33.)</p>
        <p>There is a faith which is called dead.—
“Even so faith, if it hath not works, is dead,
being alone.”—(James 2: 17.) But the faith
which enables the christian to obey the Saviour
in all things, is said to “work by love.”
—(Gal. 5: 6.) Now we say that those who
have this faith, will never deny it. The
counterfeit may deceive,  but the genuine
cannot. We say this faith cannot deny
itself. All who are spoken of in the Old
Testament as having this faith never denied it.
By it Abel made a more excellent sacrifice to
God than Cain. By it, Enoch walked with
God, when the other portion of mankind
<pb id="davis80" n="80"/>
walked in the vain wicked imaginations of
their own hearts. “By faith Noah, being
warned of God of things not seen as yet,
moved with fear, prepared an ark for the saving
of his house.” “Abraham believed God,
and it was counted unto him for righteousness.”</p>
        <p>This is the grace which enables believers
to renounce the pleasures of sin, which are
but for a season. It gives them a complete
victory over the world. It abideth with hope
and charity. Now, whosoever professes this
faith, and then by his unholy life denies it,
by neglecting to provide for his own, and
especially for those of his own house, makes it
manifest that he never had it. It is as
unchangeable as its Author, for it is the gift of
God. It prompted Noah to labor over a
hundred years, to build an ark, to save his house.
And what it has done, it will continue to
do, for those who have it. This is the principle
in religion which purifies the heart,
overcomes the world, and causes christians
to love one another, whatever may be their
circumstances, or color or rank in life.</p>
        <p>4. We are now in the fourth and last place
to draw a comparison between those who
<pb id="davis81" n="81"/>
deny the faith, and an infidel. Now an infidel,
is an unbeliever in the religion of Christ.—
Yet he provides for his own, and especially
for those of his own house. In this he is
consistent with himself. Here he acts from
reason, and principles of nature. But the
individual who denies the faith, is one, who
has taken upon himself the solemn vow before
God and men, that he will act out what
his profession supposes him to be in
possession of, which is superior in its influence,
to the infidel's principles, yet he fails to do
as much.</p>
        <p>But again, an infidel is a bad man, and
makes no pretensions to hide it. But he
who contradicts his profession, by denying
it in the manner here set forth, is worse
for attempting to cover up a character, which
in itself is no better. But consider the
effect produced by a false faith, (and we have
shown, that such a faith, as does not come
up with the infidel's, is false,) it does the
greatest harm. Many persons, when they
make a profession of faith, suppose it is the
true faith, but after a while, they find that
their faith does not work by love, it does not
purify their hearts. They love sin secretly,
<pb id="davis82" n="82"/>
as much as before. They love worldly company
as well as ever. And they find the
employments, which their profession enjoins
upon them, irksome and dry. Such persons
are greatly deceived, yet they are ashamed to
confess it, and throw off the mask of
profession. And such persons are often the greatest
fault-finders with those, whose true faith
inspires them to endure hardness, afflictions
and deny themselves and take up their cross,
so that they may glorify their Saviour in
their bodies and spirits which are the Lord's.</p>
        <p>In conclusion, dear brethren, let us, who
have made a profession of faith, examine
ourselves, whether we be in the faith of the
gospel, or not. “Know ye not your own selves
how that Jesus Christ is in you, except ye be
reprobates.” AMEN.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="figure">
        <pb id="davis83" n="83"/>
        <head>STATISTICAL REPORT<lb/>
OF ALL THE
<lb/>
COLORED PROTESTANT CHURCHES
<lb/>
AND SABBATH SCHOOLS
<lb/>
IN BALTIMORE.</head>
        <p>
          <figure id="ill2" entity="davis83">
            <p>STATISTICAL REPORT</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="figure">
        <pb id="davis84" n="84"/>
        <head>SABBATH SCHOOL REPORT.</head>
        <p>
          <figure id="ill3" entity="davis84">
            <p>SABBATH SCHOOL REPORT</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="figure">
        <pb id="davis85" n="84"/>
        <p>
          <figure id="ill4" entity="davis85">
            <p>[Advertisement Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="figure">
        <pb id="davis86" n="84"/>
        <p>
          <figure id="ill5" entity="davis86">
            <p>[Advertisement Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="figure">
        <pb id="davis87" n="84"/>
        <p>
          <figure id="ill6" entity="davis87">
            <p>[Advertisement Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="figure">
        <pb id="davis88" n="84"/>
        <p>
          <figure id="ill7" entity="davis88">
            <p>[Advertisement Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="figure">
        <pb id="davis89" n="84"/>
        <p>
          <figure id="ill8" entity="davis89">
            <p>[Advertisement Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="figure">
        <pb id="davis90" n="84"/>
        <p>
          <figure id="ill9" entity="davis90">
            <p>[Advertisement Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI.2>