<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY capecv SYSTEM "capecv.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY capefp SYSTEM "capefp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY capetp SYSTEM "capetp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>Reminiscences of Isaac and Sukey, Slaves of B. F. Moore, of Raleigh, N. C.:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Capehart, L. C.</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Lee Ann Morawski</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by</resp>
          <name>Lee Ann Morawski</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Chris Hill  and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>2000</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca.   20K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>2000.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="title page"> Reminiscences of Isaac and Sukey, Slaves of B. F. Moore, of Raleigh, N. C.</title>
            <author>L. C. Capehart</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition/>
          </editionStmt>
          <extent>11  p., 1 ill.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>Raleigh</pubPlace>
            <publisher>Presses of Edwards and Broughton Printing Co.</publisher>
            <date>1907</date>
            <authority/>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="yes">Call number  Cp813 C23 c.2  (North Carolina Collection, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>This electronic edition has been created by Optical
Character Recognition (OCR). OCR-ed text has been compared against the
original document and corrected.  The text has been encoded using the
recommendations for Level 4 of the TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</p>
        <p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>African Americans -- North Carolina -- Raleigh --
Fiction.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- North Carolina -- Raleigh -- Fiction.</item>
            <item>North Carolina -- Fiction.</item>
            <item>Dialect literature, American -- North Carolina --
Raleigh.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2000-09-15, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2000-07-18, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2000-07-17, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Chris Hill</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2000-07-10, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Lee Ann Morawski</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="cover image">
        <p>
          <figure id="cover" entity="capecv">
            <p>[Cover Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="frontispiece image">
        <p>
          <figure id="frontis" entity="capefp">
            <p>ISAAC B. F. MOORE.<lb/>[Frontispiece Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="title page image">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="capetp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="half title">
        <head>REMINISCENCES
<lb/>
OF
<lb/>
ISAAC AND SUKEY
<lb/>
SLAVES OF B. F. MOORE,
<lb/>
OF
<lb/>
RALEIGH N. C.</head>
        <p/>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">REMINISCENCES
<lb/>
OF
<lb/>
ISAAC AND SUKEY,
<lb/>SLAVES OF B. F. MOORE,
<lb/>
Of
<lb/>
RALEIGH. N. C.</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>BY HIS DAUGHTER</byline>
        <docAuthor>L. C. CAPEHART.</docAuthor>
        <docImprint><pubPlace>RALEIGH:</pubPlace>
<publisher>PRESSES OF EDWARDS AND BROUGHTON PRINTING CO.</publisher>
<docDate>1907.</docDate></docImprint>
      </titlePage>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="cape3" n="3"/>
        <head>Isaac and the Yankee Officer.</head>
        <note anchored="yes">
          <p>Interview between Isaac B. F. Moore, as he called himself, 
(taking the name of his former master, a prominent lawyer 
of Raleigh, N.C.) and one of Kilpatrick's cavalry stationed 
in Raleigh in April, 1865.]</p>
        </note>
        <p>Isaac lived on the plantation of Mr. B. F. Moore, near the 
city of Raleigh, now owned by Mr. Bart Gatling. On this 
farm there was a fine apple orchard. The Yankees were 
camped in the grove near the “Great House,’ as, the negroes 
called the house in which the white family lived. I give 
the interview in Isaac's own words:</p>
        <p>“One day a Yankee officer tied his ridin' horse to one of de 
best apple trees in de orchard; de horse he begun to bite 
de bark on de tree, so I said, ‘Mister, dat's a mighty good 
horse-apple tree your horse is bitin', he will kill it. De 
Yankee giv me a most <hi rend="italics">sarching</hi> look and said, ‘You think 
more of a d—m apple tree dan I do of a man's life.’ He 
stood close to me wid his sharp shooter, his neck as red as 
any rose, all ready to put my candle out at any minute. You 
better believe I <hi rend="italics">cased</hi> myself away from dar. Arter dat I 
sed no more 'bout tyin' horses to apple trees.”</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="cape4" n="4"/>
        <head>Isaac Before the Mayor for Killing his<lb/>
Neighbor's Hogs.</head>
        <p>One day arter de surrender a gentleman livin' near me got 
me to watch his field to keep de hogs from rootin' up his 
'taters, so when de hogs begun to root I sot my little dog 
on em, and he fairly tore em to pieces, so de odder man he 
got mad an' ordered me 'fore de Mare. I went to see my ole 
marster to git him to pear for me. He wuz a big lawyer, he 
wus, an' all de folks was 'fraid er him; when he got mad he 
war er terror, an' er Union man, too, an' cum right out wid 
what he had to say, an' nobody would kill him, but tother 
folks was 'fraid. Sum of 'em <hi rend="italics">talked</hi> mighty big, but nebber 
went whar de fight was. But I was gwine ter tell you 'bout 
dat trial. De time was sot fur ten o'clock, an' when my 
marster got dar, I was dar too, me an' my little dog. I 
bring my little dog kase marster want de coat to see him, 
kase he said no sich dog as dat cud tare all dem hogs ter 
pieces, as de man said. Well, me and my marster waited an' 
waited (he had a case in ernudder coat); he was a mity busy 
man, anyhow, you nebber see him sittin' down doing nuthin'. 
Marster he kept talkin' 'bout losin' his time, an' arter 
erwhile de mare he cum in, an' marster he kep' on talkin' 
'bout his bein'
<pb id="cape5" n="5"/>
so late, takin' up his valable time, an' he kept on talking
—he fairly charged, didn't, giv nobody else a chance; 
so, arter erwhile, de mare got up <hi rend="italics">easy</hi> an' went out an' soon 
arter all de odder folks what cum to hear de trial dey went 
out too. When marster got thrugh talkin' he looked 'round an 
sed to me, “Well, Isaac, as everybody else is gone, we 
might as well go too”; and dat wus de las' I hear of dat 
trial.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <head>Isaac Indicted for Shooting his Neighbor's<lb/>
Hog.</head>
        <p>Er nudder time a man dited me fur shootin' his hog. I went 
up to de coat house an waited dar a long time. Nobody called 
my name an' I didn't see marster no whar, so I jes' leaves 
dar an' goes to look fur my marster. I met him on de street 
an' I says, marster, I bleeve dey is gwine ter beat us, I 
think we better peal to Spreme coat. “Nebber mind,” says 
marster, you come back wid me to de coat house. Soon as we 
got dar a man called out “Isaac B. F. Moore, cum to de 
stand.” I went up an' giv in my evidence, an' I nebber heard 
no more 'bout dat hog case frum dat day to dis.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="cape6" n="6"/>
        <head>Isaac and Mars' Ben.</head>
        <p>One very hot, sultry day in August, Isaac and his young 
master Ben went on a fishing trip about twenty miles from 
Raleigh. After they had traveled several miles conversing 
pleasantly, as the manner was in those days between master 
and servant, silence reigned for a few minutes, during 
which time Isaac was closely observing his surroundings; he 
soon spied a woodpecker tapping on the bark of a seasoned 
oak tree. Umph! says Isaac, “dat woodpecker must have a 
strong constitution to peck a hole in dat tree.” He shot at 
a bird one day and missed him, the bird alighted in a tree 
nearby, and began to pick himself. “Look at dat rascal,” 
said Isaac, “pickin' my shots out of his back.”</p>
        <p>One night he was aroused front his slumbers by dreams of 
burglars. He took his old army musket (True Blue he called 
it), went out in the yard and shot at what he thought was 
a man; when he re-entered the house his son said, “Father, 
did you kill him?” No, siree, but God knows I filled dat 
ole <hi rend="italics">beegum</hi> full of shot.”</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="cape7" n="7"/>
        <head>Isaac Rabbit Hunting.</head>
        <p>One day Isaac went rabbit hunting. He shot
at a rabbit, and was asked if he killed him. “No,
said he, “de powder got between de rabbit an' de
shots; de shots passed by him, but he <hi rend="italics">smelt</hi> de
powder an' de smoke, an' you ought to heerd him
snort!”</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <head>Isaac Voting the Democratic Ticket.</head>
        <p>One day I met one of dese highfalutin' nigger women who 
puts on so many airs; she says to me, “I'm a great mind to 
shoot you, you ole rascal, fur votin' dat ticket.” “Well, 
madam, if your fingers ken play on de trigger enny faster 
dan mine, crack a' loose.”</p>
        <note anchored="yes">NOTE.—He was always a good Democrat.</note>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <head>Isaac Watching his Corn at Night Hears it<lb/>
Growing.</head>
        <p>Dese niggers what don't work kep stealin' my
corn out de field, so I says to myself I'll ketch de
stinkin' rascal an' have him struck nine
thirty on his naked hide; So I takes my <hi rend="italics">True Blue</hi> musket, 
my pistol, my sword, an' my dirk to de field an' hides 
myself. I watched all de live long night, an' nobody cum, 
but God knows I neber heerd corn grow so fast in my life. 
'Twas nately <hi rend="italics">poppin'</hi> an' <hi rend="italics">crackin'</hi> all night long!</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="cape8" n="8"/>
        <head>Isaac's Steer in the Mire.</head>
        <p>One day “Mars Ben”, walking down the street,
met Isaac looking very anxious. “What's the 
matter, old man?” “Dat steer you bought fur me is
mired in Mr. Gatling's mill pond an' I can't git
him out.” “Who have you to help you?” “Well, 
little John Gatling is dar an' Mr. Taylor. Mr.
Taylor ain't <hi rend="italics">workin'</hi> any, he jes' doin' de 
<hi rend="italics">plannin'</hi>. We bin tryin' to <hi rend="italics">undermine</hi> him, but t'aint
no use, for he jis gits deeper and deeper.”</p>
        <p>Later on the steer was extricated. Marse Ben,
meeting Isaac, said, “Well, old man, I hear you
got your steer out of the pond; what did he do
when he got out, was he much exhausted?” “No,
<hi rend="italics">siree;</hi> de doggoned old rascal jest went to eatin'
grass like dere was nothin' de matter wid him.
Marse Ben, don't yon ever buy me ernuther pop-eyed 
steer, a pop-eyed steer is ungodly. Don't 
put a bit in all ox's mouth. De Bible speaks 
bitterly agin it.”</p>
        <note anchored="yes">NOTE—Mr. James Fontleroy Taylor, the Bard of Rhamkatte.</note>
        <p>“Marse Ben, I heerd Miss Lucy was gwine to git married 
agin'; is dat so?” “Yes, Isaac, she is to marry Mr. Baldy 
Capehart, and I hope she will be happy, for she is very 
lonely now.” “Bless my soul! I clare to gracious it's a 
mortification to seriousness!”</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="cape9" n="9"/>
        <head>Sukey's Opinion of her Master's Monument.</head>
        <p>Sukey, after the Civil War was over, lived near Oakwood 
Cemetery. Soon after the erection of a monument to my 
father, which was surmounted by a bust under a canopy, I 
came to Raleigh on a visit. As usual, she came to see me, 
and as she lived near and I had not yet seen the
bust, I asked her if she thought it resembled my
father. She replied, “It's mity like marster, all
but one thing; it ain't got no <hi rend="italics">arms</hi>. Marster
was such a busy man, always at work, it ought
to have <hi rend="italics">arms</hi> put to it.” “I hope you are getting
on well, Aunt Sukey.” “Yes, ma'am, I git so full
of de Spirit some times you could hear me holler
over here (about one mile) if de win' was blowin'
de right way. I spect if I eber gits to Heben, de
Lord will say, “take Sukey out of dar, for she
hollers too loud.”</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="cape10" n="10"/>
        <head>Sukey's Husband, Uncle “Toney,” and the<lb/>
Outsiders.</head>
        <p>It was customary in ye olden times for gentlemen 
on horseback, when returning from church,
to ride by the side of the carriage and converse
with the ladies within. It was quite difficult to
keep pace with horses trotting briskly. On one
occasion a young lady called out, “Uncle Tony,
don't drive so fast, the young men can not keep
up.” Uncle Tony, whose horses had been ploughing
during this week, replied, “<hi rend="italics">Dee</hi> horses bin
<hi rend="italics">workin</hi> all de week, dum horses bin <hi rend="italics">restin</hi> all de
week; if <hi rend="italics">dum</hi> horses can't keep up wid <hi rend="italics">dee</hi> horses,
dum horses mus' stay behind.”</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="cape11" n="11"/>
        <head>Sukey Bat Moore on the Art of Flying.</head>
        <p>One summer night about twelve o'clock my
mother was awakened by Sukey (who had just 
returned from a <hi rend="italics">revival</hi>) kneeling at her bedside,
saying, “Mistis, Mistis, pray for me,—Judy Freeman
has got religion and I can't git it.” My
mother tried to soothe, and promised to pray for 
her. Later on she gave evidence of having “come
through.” Not long afterward while in church
she felt happy, and began to shout, saying, “Oh!
I feel I can fly to heaven!” Some of the sisters
said to her, “Aunt Sukey, do try,” and under the
influence of excitement she really did jump out
of the window, and of course fell to the ground;
fortunately it was very low and she sustained no
injury. One of her friends asked her why she
failed to fly. She replied, “I dunno, honey, 'cept
as how I didn't git de <hi rend="italics">right flop</hi>”!</p>
        <note anchored="yes">NOTE—Alluding to the habit of fowls raising and 
lowering their wings in order to inflate their lungs before 
flying, which is usually termed flopping.</note>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>