<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % external-entities SYSTEM "./extEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY % internal-entities SYSTEM "./intEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY barbefp SYSTEM "barbefp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY barbe10b SYSTEM "barbe10b.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY barbe10a SYSTEM "barbe10a.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY barbe20 SYSTEM "barbe20.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY barbe11a SYSTEM "barbe11a.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY barbe11b SYSTEM "barbe11b.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY barbe24 SYSTEM "barbe24.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY barbe12a SYSTEM "barbe12a.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY barbe12b SYSTEM "barbe12b.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY barbe13a SYSTEM "barbe13a.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY barbe13b SYSTEM "barbe13b.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY barbe14a SYSTEM "barbe14a.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY barbe14b SYSTEM "barbe14b.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY barbe15a SYSTEM "barbe15a.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY barbe15b SYSTEM "barbe15b.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY barbe15c SYSTEM "barbe15c.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY barbetp SYSTEM "barbetp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY barbevs SYSTEM "barbevs.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY barbe9b SYSTEM "barbe9b.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY barbe9a SYSTEM "barbe9a.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>A History of the Amistad Captives: </emph><emph>Being a Circumstantial
 Account of the Capture of the Spanish Schooner Amistad, by the Africans on Board; 
Their Voyage, and Capture Near Long Island, New York; with Biographical Sketches of 
Each of the Surviving Africans; also, an Account of the Trials had on Their case, 
Before the District and Circuit Courts of the United States, for the District of 
Connecticut:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <editor role="editor">Barber, John Warner, 1798-1885</editor>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by </resp>
          <name id="cg">Fiona Mills</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by</resp>
          <name>Fiona Mills</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Bethany Ronnberg  and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1999</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>200KB</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1999.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, 
teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability 
is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="title page"> A History of the Amistad Captives: Being A Circumstatial 
Account of the Capture of the Spanish Schooner Amistad, by the Africans 
on Board; Their Voyage, and Capture near Long Island, New York; with 
Biographical Sketches of Each of the Surviving Africans Also, an 
Account of the Trials had on their Case, Before the District and 
Circuit Courts of the United States, for the District of Connecticut.</title>
            <author>John W. Barber</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>32p., ill.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>New Haven, CT.</pubPlace>
            <publisher>Published by E. L. &amp; J. W. Barber</publisher>
            <publisher>Hitchcock
 &amp; Stafford, Printers</publisher>
            <date>1840</date>
            <authority/>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="yes">Call number   C-Pam B234H  (Rare Book, Manuscript, and
 Special Collections Library, Duke University Libraries)</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>All footnotes are inserted at the point of reference within paragraphs.
 </p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) 
and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="spa">Spanish</language>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
        <language id="lat">Latin</language>
        <language id="fre">French</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Amistad (Schooner)</item>
            <item>Cinque.</item>
            <item>Slave insurrections -- United States.</item>
            <item>Antislavery movements -- United States.</item>
            <item>Trials (Mutiny) -- United States.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- United States -- History.</item>
            <item>Slave trade -- History -- 19th century.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2000-04-07, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-12-01, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Bethany Ronnberg</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-11-21, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Fiona Mills</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="frontispiece">
        <p>
          <figure id="frontis" entity="barbefp">
            <p>Death of Capt. Ferrer, the Captain of the Amistad, July, 1839<lb/>Don Jose Ruiz and Don Pedro Montez, of the Island of Cuba, having purchased fifty-three slaves at Havana, recently imported from Africa, put them on board the Amistad, Capt. Ferrer, in order to transport them to Principe, another port on the Island of Cuba.  After being out from Havana about four days, the  African captives on board, in order to obtain their freedom, and return to Africa, armed themselves with cane knives, and rose upon the Captain and crew of the vessel.  Capt. Ferrer and the cook of the vessel were killed; two of the crew escaped; Ruiz and Montez were made prisoners.<lb/>[Frontispiece Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="titlepage">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="barbetp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="verso">
        <p>
          <figure id="verso" entity="barbevs">
            <p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage type="titlepage">
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">A
<lb/>
HISTORY
<lb/>
OF THE
<lb/>
AMISTAD CAPTIVES:</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="subtitle">BEING A
<lb/>
CIRCUMSTANTIAL ACCOUNT
<lb/>
OF THE
<lb/>
CAPTURE OF THE SPANISH SCHOONER AMISTAD,
<lb/>
BY THE AFRICANS ON BOARD; <lb/>THEIR VOYAGE, AND CAPTURE
<lb/>
NEAR LONG ISLAND, NEW YORK;  WITH
<lb/>
BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCHES
<lb/>
OF EACH OF THE SURVIVING AFRICANS <lb/>ALSO, AN ACCOUNT OF
<lb/>
THE TRIALS
<lb/>
HAD ON THEIR CASE, BEFORE THE DISTRICT AND CIRCUIT COURTS OF THE
<lb/>
UNITED STATES, FOR THE DISTRICT OF CONNECTICUT.</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>COMPILED FROM AUTHENTIC SOURCES,
BY </byline>
        <docAuthor>JOHN W.BARBER,<lb/>MEM. OF THE CONNECTICUT HIST. SOC.</docAuthor>
        <docImprint>NEW HAVEN, CT.:
<publisher>PUBLISHED BY  E. L. &amp; J. W. BARBER.</publisher>
<publisher>HITCHCOCK &amp; STAFFORD, PRINTERS.</publisher></docImprint>
        <docDate>1840.</docDate>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="preface">
        <pb id="barber2" n="verso"/>
        <head>PREFACE.</head>
        <p>THE capture of the Amistad with her cargo of native
Africans, and the peculiar circumstances of the case, have
excited an unusual degree of interest in this country, and
in Europe. A correct statement of the facts of this extraordinary
case, is deemed desirable, and the compiler has
availed himself of the facilities at his command, for the
attainment of this object. Free use has been made of what
Professor GIBBS, of Yale College, and others, have published,
respecting the Africans. The compiler has also had
the opportunity of personal conversation with them, by
means of James Covey, the Interpreter, and has confined
himself to a bare relation of facts.</p>
        <closer><signed>J.  W.  B.</signed>
<dateline>NEW HAVEN, CT., May, 1840.</dateline></closer>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="preface">
        <p>Entered, according to Act of Congress, in the year 1840, 
by JOHN W. BARBER and EDMUND L. BARBER, in the Clerk's Office of the District 
Court of Connecticut.</p>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="barber3" n="3"/>
        <head>HISTORY
<lb/>
OF THE
<lb/>
AMISTAD CAPTIVES, &amp;c.</head>
        <p>DURING the month of August, 1839, the public attention was somewhat
excited by several reports, stating that a vessel of suspicious and piratical
character had been seen near the coast of the United States, in the vicinity of
New York. This vessel was represented as a “long, low, black schooner,”
and manned by blacks. The United States steamer Fulton, and several
Revenue Cutters, were dispatched after her, and notice was given to the
Collectors at various sea ports.</p>
        <p>The following, giving an account of the capture of this vessel, and other
particulars, is taken from the “New London Gazette.”</p>
        <q type="article" direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1 type="article">
                <p>“<hi rend="italics">The 
suspicious looking schooner” captured and brought in this port.</hi>
Much excitement has been created in New York for the past week, from the report
of several Pilot Boats having seen a clipper-built schooner off the Hook, full
of negroes, and in such condition as to lead to the suspicion that she was a
pirate. Several Cutters and naval vessels are said to have been dispatched in
pursuit of her, but she has been most providentially captured in the Sound, by
Capt. Gedney, of the surveying Brig Washington. We will no longer detain the
reader, but subjoin the official account of the capture, very politely furnished
to us by one of the officers.</p>
                <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
                  <text>
                    <body>
                      <div1 type="letter">
                        <opener><hi rend="italics">“U. S. 
Brig Washington,</hi>
<dateline>NEW LONDON, Aug. 26th 1839.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>“While this vessel was sounding this day between Gardner's and Montauk Points,
a schooner was seen lying in shore off Culloden Point, under circumstances so
suspicious as to authorize Lieut. Com. Gedney to stand in to see what was her
character—seeing a number of people on the beach with carts and horses, and
a boat passing to and fro, a boat was armed and dispatched with an officer to
board her. On coming along side, a number of negroes were discovered on her
deck, and twenty or thirty more were on the beach—two white men came forward
and claimed the protection of the officer. The schooner proved to be the
‘Amistad,’ Capt. Ramonflues, from the Havanah, bound to Guanajah, Port Principe,
with 54 blacks and two passengers on board; the former, four nights after they
were out, rose and murdered the captain and three of the crew—they then took
possession of the vessel, with the intention of returning to the coast of
Africa. Pedro Montez, passenger, and Jose Ruiz, owner of the slaves and a part
of the cargo, were only saved to navigate the vessel. After boxing about four
days in the Bahama Channel, the vessel was steered for the Island of St.
Andrews, near New Providence—from thence she went to Green Key, where the
blacks laid in a supply of water. After leaving this place the vessel was
steered by Pedro Montez, for New Providence, the negroes being
under the impression that she was steering for the coast of Africa—they
would not however permit her to enter the port, but anchored every night off the
coast. The situation of the two whites was all this time truly deplorable, being
treated with the greatest severity, and Pedro Montez, who had charge of the
navigation, was suffering two severe wounds, one on the head and one on the arm,
their lives being threatened every instant. He was ordered to change the course
again for the coast of Africa, the negroes themselves steering by the sun in the
day time, while at night he would alter their course so as to bring them back to
their original place of destination. They remained three days off Long Island,
to the eastward of Providence, after which time they were two months on the
ocean, sometimes steering to the eastward, and whenever an occasion would
permit, the whites would alter the course to the northward and westward, always
in hopes of falling in with some vessel of war, or being enabled to run into
some port, when they would be relieved from their horrid situation. Several
times they were boarded by vessels; once by an American schooner from Kingston;
on these occasions the whites were ordered below, while the negroes communicated
and traded with the vessels; the schooner from Kingston
<pb id="barber4" n="4"/>
supplied them with a demijon of water for the moderate sum of one doubloon—this schooner,
 whose name was not ascertained, finding that the negroes had
plenty of money, remained lashed alongside the ‘Amistad’ for twenty-four hours,
though they must have been aware that all was not right on board, and probably
suspected the character of the vessel—this was on the 18th of the present
month; the vessel was steered to the northward and westward, and on the 20th
instant, distant from New York 25 miles, the Pilot Boat No. 3 came alongside and
gave the negroes some apples. She was also hailed by No. 4: when the latter boat
came near, the negroes armed themselves and would not permit her to board them; they were so 
exasperated with the two whites for bringing them so much out of their way, that they expected
 every moment to be murdered. On the 24th they made Montauk Light and steered for it in the hope 
of running the vessel ashore, but the tide drifted them up the bay and they anchored where they 
were found by the Brig Washington, off Culloden Point. The negroes were found in communication 
with the shore, where they laid in a fresh supply of water, and were on the point of sailing 
again for the coast of Africa. They had a good supply of money, some of which it is likely 
was taken by the people on the beach. After disarming and sending them on board from the 
beach, the leader jumped overboard with three hundred doubloons about him, the property 
of the Captain, all of which he succeeded in loosing from his person, and then submitted 
himself to be captured. The schooner was taken in tow by the brig and carried into New 
London.”</p>
                      </div1>
                    </body>
                  </text>
                </q>
                <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
                  <text>
                    <body>
                      <div1 type="letter">
                        <opener>
                          <dateline>“<date><hi rend="italics">Tuesday,</hi> 12 <hi rend="italics">o'clock, M.</hi></date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>We have just returned from a visit to the Washington and her prize, which are
riding at anchor in the bay, near the fort. On board the former we saw and
conversed with the two Spanish gentlemen, who were passengers on board the
schooner, as well as owners of the negroes and most of the cargo. One of them,
Jose Ruiz, is a very gentlemanly and intelligent young man, and speaks English
fluently. He was the owner of most of the slaves and cargo, which he was
conveying to his estate on the Island of Cuba. The other, Pedro Montez, is about
fifty years of age, and is the owner of four of the slaves. He was formerly a
ship master and has navigated the vessel since her seizure by the blacks. Both
of them, as may be naturally supposed, are most unfeignedly thankful for their
deliverance. Jose Pedro is the most striking instance of complacency and
unalloyed delight we have ever witnessed, and it is not strange, since only
yesterday his sentence was pronounced by the chief of the <sic corr="buccaneer">bucaniers</sic>, and his
death song chanted by the grim crew, who gathered with uplifted sabres around
his devoted head, which, as well as his arms, bear the scars of several wounds
inflicted at the time of the murder of the ill-fated captain and crew. He sat
smoking his Havana on the deck, and to judge from the martyr-like serenity of
his countenance, his emotions are such as rarely stir the heart of man. When Mr.
Porter, the prize master, assured him of his safety, he threw his arms around
his neck, while gushing tears coursing down his furrowed cheek, bespoke the
overflowing transport of his soul. Every now and then he clasped his hands, and
with uplifted eyes, gave thanks to “the Holy Virgin” who had led him out of his
troubles. Senor Ruiz has given us two letters for his agents, Messrs. Shelton,
Brothers &amp; Co. of Boston, and Peter A. Harmony &amp; Co. of New York. It appears
that the slaves, the greater portion of whom were his, were very much attached
to him, and had determined after reaching the coast of Africa, to allow him to
seek his home what way he could, while his poor companion was to be sacrificed.</p>
                        <p>On board the brig we also saw Cingue, the master spirit of this bloody tragedy,
in irons. He-is about five feet eight inches in height, 25 or 26 years of age,
of erect figure, well built and very active. He is said to be a match for any
two men on board the schooner. His countenance, for a native African, is
unusually intelligent, evincing uncommon decision and coolness, with a composure
characteristic of true courage, and nothing to mark him as a malicious man.</p>
                        <p>By physiognomy and phrenology, he has considerable claim to benevolence.
According to Gall and Spurzhelm, his moral sentiments and intellectual faculties
predominate considerably over his animal propensities. He is said, however, to
have killed the Captain and crew with his own hand, by cutting their throats. He
also has several times attempted the life of Senor Montez, and the backs of
several poor negroes are scored with scars of blows inflicted by his lash to
keep them in subjection. He expects to be executed, but nevertheless manifests a
<foreign lang="fre"><hi rend="italics">sang froid</hi></foreign> worthy of a stoic 
under similar circumstances.</p>
                        <p>With Captain Gedney, the surgeon of the port, and others, we visited the
schooner, which is anchored within musket shot of the Washington, and there we
saw such a sight as we never saw before and never wish to see again. The bottom
and sides of this vessel are covered with barnacles and sea-grass, while her
rigging and sails presented an appearance worthy of the Flying Dutchman, after
her fabled cruise. She is a Baltimore built vessel, of matchless model for
speed, about 120 tons burthen, and about six years old. On her deck were grouped
amid various goods and arms, the remnant of her Ethiop crew, some decked in the
most fantastic manner, in silks and finery, pilfered from the cargo, while
others, in a state of nudity, emaciated to mere skeletons, lay coiled upon the
decks. Here could be seen a negro with white pantaloons, and the sable shirt
which nature gave him, and a planter's broad brimmed hat upon his head, with a
string of gewgaws about his neck; and another with a linen cambric shirt, whose
bosom was worked by the hand of some dark-eyed daughter of Spain, while his
nether proportions were enveloped in a shawl of gauze or Canton crape. Around
the windlass were gathered the three little girls, from eight to thirteen years
of age, the very images of health and gladness.</p>
                        <p>Over the deck were scattered in the most wanton and disorderly profusion,
raisins, vermicelli, bread, rice, silk, and cotton goods. In the cabin and hold
were the marks of the same wasteful destruction. Her cargo appears to consist of
silks, crapes, calicoes, cotton, and fancy goods of various descriptions, glass
and hardware, bridles, saddles, holsters, pictures, looking-glasses, books,
fruit, olives and olive oil, and “other things too numerous to mention”—which 
are now all mixed up in a strange and fantastic medley. On the forward
hatch we unconsciously rested our hand on a cold object, which we soon
discovered to be a naked corpse, enveloped in a pall of black bombazine. On
removing its folds, we beheld the rigid countenance and glazed eye of a poor
negro who died last night. His mouth was unclosed and still wore the ghastly
expression of his last struggle. Near him, like some watching fiend,
<pb id="barber5" n="5"/>
sat the most horrible creature we ever saw in human shape, an object of terror
to the very blacks, who said that he was a cannibal. His teeth projected at
almost right angles from his mouth, while his eyes had a most savage and
demoniac expression.</p>
                        <p>We were glad to leave this vessel, as the exhalations from her hold and deck,
were like any thing but “gales wafted over the gardens of Gul.” Captain Gedney
has dispatched an express to the United States Marshal, at New Haven, while he
his made the most humane arrangements for the health and comfort of the
prisoners and the purification of the prize. There are now alive 44 negroes, 3
of whom are girls; about 10 have died. They have been at sea 63 days. The vessel
and cargo were worth forty thousand dollars when they left Havana, exclusive of
the negroes, who cost from 20 to 30 thousand dollars. Vessel and cargo insured
in Havana.</p>
                        <p>There is a question for the laws of Admiralty to decide, whether captain Gedney
and his fellow officers are entitled to prize or salvage money. To one or the
other they are most surely entitled, and we hope they will get their just dues.
Captain Gedney, when he first espied the Amistad, was running a
line of sounding towards Montauk Point. He had heard nothing of this vessel
being on the coast till after his arrival in this port.”</p>
                      </div1>
                    </body>
                  </text>
                </q>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <p>The Amistad, as has been stated, anchored off Culloden Point, on the—of
August, and the Africans went on shore to get a supply of water for
their voyage. It appears that three of their number went up to some of the
houses in the vicinity of their landing place, and bought of the inhabitants
one or more dogs, for which they paid at the rate of three doubloons each.
Capt. Green and some others who were on this part of the island, having
heard of these circumstances, and having seen the account of the “suspicious
looking schooner” in the newspapers, concluded that these black men were
part of the crew of this vessel. Capt. Green, with four or five others, then
proceeded to the shore, where they found eight or ten blacks on the beach.
Cingue, the leader of the Africans, being one of the number on shore, gave
a whistle, upon which all the blacks sprung around him: the whites then
ran to their wagons for their guns. The blacks seeing this, sat down, and
soon came to a parley with Capt. Green, giving up to him two guns, a knife,
and a hat, and remained with him about four hours.</p>
        <p>It appears from the testimony given on the trial of the case, that the
blacks having been made to understand that there was a vessel of war in
pursuit of them, and that there were no slaves or Spaniards in this part of
the country, agreed to give up the schooner to Capt. Green, to be taken
around to another part of the island, from whence they wished Capt. Green
to carry them to Sierra Leone. At this time, or soon after, Lieut. Gedney
having discovered the Amistad, dispatched a boat with an armed force and
took possession, as has been related.</p>
        <p>Cingue having been put on board of the Washington, displayed much
uneasiness, and seemed so very anxious to get on board the schooner, that
his keepers allowed him to return. Once more on the deck of the Amistad,
the blacks clustered around him, laughing, screaming, and making other
extravagant demonstrations of joy. When the noise had subsided, he made
an address, which raised their excitement to such a pitch, that the officer
in command, had Cingue led away by force. He was returned to the Washington,
and was manacled to prevent his leaping overboard. On Wednesday
he signified by motions, that if they would take him on board the
schooner again, he would show them a handkerchief full of doubloons.
He was accordingly sent on board. His fetters were taken off, and he
once more went below, where he was received by the Africans in a still
more wild and enthusiastic manner than he was the day previous. Instead
of finding the doubloons, he again made an address to the blacks, by which
they were very much excited. Dangerous consequences were apprehended;
Cingue was seized, taken from the hold, and again fettered. While
making his speech, his eye was often turned to the sailors in charge; the
blacks yelled, leapt about, and seemed to be animated with the same spirit
and determination of their leader. Cingue, when taken back to the Washington,
<pb id="barber6" n="6"/>
evinced little or no emotion, but kept his eye steadily fixed on the
schooner.—The following relative to the judicial investigation, &amp;c. is taken
from a newspaper published in New York:</p>
        <q type="article" direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1 type="article">
                <p>“On Wednesday night, Captain Gedney dispatched an express to the U.S. Marshal
at New Haven, who gave information to his Honor A. T. Judson, U.S. District
Judge. On Thursday morning, both these gentlemen arrived, and after careful
deliberation, concluded to hold their Court on board the Washington, then lying
off the Fort, within musket shot of the schooner. Lieut. Wolcott kindly offered
the services to the U. S. cutter Experiment to take all interested on board the
Washington. The U. S. Marshal politely took us under his protection.</p>
                <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
                  <text>
                    <body>
                      <div1 type="letter">
                        <head>JUDICIAL 
INVESTIGATION.</head>
                        <opener>
                          <dateline>At anchor, on board the U. S. cutter Washington, commanded
 by Lieut Gedney.<lb/>
NEW LONDON, AUG. 29, 1839.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>His Honor Andrew T. Judson, U. S. District Judge, on the bench, C. A. Ingersol,
Esq. appearing for the U. S. District Attorney. The Court was opened by the
U. S. Marshal. The clerk then swore Don Pedro Montez, owner of part of the
cargo, and three of the slaves, and Don Jose Ruiz, also owner of part of the
cargo, and forty-nine of the slaves. These gentlemen then lodged a complaint
against Joseph Cingue, (the leader in the <sic corr="alleged">alledged</sic> offense,) Antonio, Simon,
Lacis, Peter, Martin, Manuel, Andrew, Edward, Caledonis, Bartholomew, Raymond,
Augustine, Evaristo, Casimiro, Mercho, Gabriel, Santaria, Escalastio, Paschal,
Estanilaus, Desiderio, Nicholas, Stephen, Thomas, Corsino, Lewis, Bartolo,
Julian, Frederick, Saturnio, Lardusolado, Celistino, Epifanio, Tevacio,
Genancio, Philip, Francis, Hipiloto, Venito, Tidoro, Vicinto, Dionecio,
Apolonio, Ezidiquiel, Leon, Julius, Hippoloto, 2d, and Zinon, or such of the
above as might be alive at that time. It was ascertained that Joseph Cingue, and
38 others, were alive, and on the complaint an indictment was framed charging
them with murder and piracy on board the Spanish schooner Amistad.</p>
                        <p>Joseph Cingue, the leader, was brought into the cabin manacled. He had a cord
round his neck, to which a snuffbox was suspended. He wore a red flannel shirt
and duck pantaloons.</p>
                        <p>Lieut. R. W. Meade, who speaks the Spanish language both elegantly and fluently,
acted as an interpreter between the Spaniards and the court.</p>
                        <p>Several bundles of letters were produced, saved from the Amistad, and such as
were unsealed, read. The contents being simply commercial can be of no interest
to the reader. Among the papers were two licenses from the Governor Of Havana,
Gen. Ezpeleta, one for three slaves, owned by Pedro Montez, one of the men
saved, and 49 owned by Senor Don Jose Ruiz, the other that has escaped, allowing
the said slaves to be transported to Principe, and commanding said owners to
report their arrival to the territorial Judge of the district, in which Principe
is situated. A license was found permitting Pedro Montez, a merchant of
Principe, to proceed to Matanzas, and transact business, which was endorsed by
the Governor of Havana, and the officer of the port. Regular passports were
produced, allowing the passengers to proceed to their destination. A license was
found permitting Selestino Ferrers, a mulatto, owned by Captain Ramon Ferrers,
and employed as a cook, to proceed on the voyage. Other licenses for each sailor
were produced and read, all of which were regularly signed, and endorsed by the
proper authorities.</p>
                        <p>The Custom House clearance, dated the 18th of May, 1839, was produced. Also
another dated the 27th of June, 1839, all regular. Several licenses permitting
goods to be shipped on board the Amistad, were read, and decided to be regular.</p>
                        <p>Lieut. R. W. Meade testified that he was in the boat which boarded the Amistad,
and demanded the papers, which were unhesitatingly delivered. Previous to this
demand Senor Don Jose Ruiz had claimed protection for himself and Don Pedro
Montez, the only two white men on board. The protection was immediately granted
and the vessel brought to New London.</p>
                        <p>Many of the events which are detailed in the narrative, were omitted in the
evidence as having no bearing on the guilt or innocence of the accused, in the
present state of the proceedings.</p>
                        <p>Senor Don Jose Ruiz was next sworn, and testified as follows. I bought 49 slaves
in Havana, and shipped them on board the schooner Amistad. We sailed for
Guanaja, the intermediate port for Principe. For the four first days every thing
went on well. In the night heard a noise in the forecastle. All of us were
asleep except the man at the helm. Do not know how things began; was awoke by
the noise. This man Joseph, I saw. Cannot tell how many were engaged. There was no moon.
<pb id="barber7" n="7"/>
It was very dark. I took up an oar and tried to quell the mutiny; I cried no!
no! I then heard one of the crew cry murder. I then heard the captain order the
cabin boy to go below and get some bread to throw to them, in hopes to pacify
the negroes. I went below and called on Montez to follow me, and told them not
to kill me: I did not see the captain killed. They called me on deck, and told
me I should not be hurt. I asked them as a favor to spare the old man. They did
so. After this they went below and ransacked the trunks of the passengers.
Before doing this, they tied our hands. We went on our course—don't know who
was at the helm. Next day I missed Captain Ramon Ferrer, two sailors, Manuel
Pagilla, and Yacinto—, and Selestina, the cook. We all slept on deck. The
slaves told us next day that they had killed all; but the cabin boy said they
had killed only the captain and cook. The other two he said had escaped in the
canoe—a small boat. The cabin boy is an African by birth, but has lived
along time in Cuba. His name is Antonio, and belonged to the Captain. From this
time we were compelled to steer east in the day: but sometimes the wind would
not allow us to steer east, then they would threaten us with death. In the night
we steered west, and kept to the northward as much as possible. We were six or
seven leagues from land when the outbreak took place. Antonio is yet alive. They
would have killed him, but he acted as interpreter between us, as he understood
both languages. He is now on board the schooner. Principe is about two days sail
from Havana, or 100 leagues, reckoning 3 miles to a league. Sometimes when the
winds are adverse, the passage occupies 15 days.</p>
                        <p>Senor Don Pedro Montez was next sworn. This witness testified altogether in
Spanish, Lieut. R. W. Meade, interpreter.</p>
                        <p>We left Havana on the 28th of June. I owned 4 slaves, 3 females and 1 male.
For three days the wind was ahead and all went well. Between 11 and 12 at night,
just as the moon was rising, sky dark and cloudy, weather very rainy, on the
fourth night I laid down on a <sic corr="mattress">matress</sic>. Between three and four
 was awakened by a
noise which was caused by blows given to the mulatto cook. I went on deck, and
they attacked me. I seized a stick and a knife with a view to defend myself. I
did not wish to kill or hurt them. At this time the prisoner wounded me on the
head severely with one of the sugar knives, also on the arm. I then ran below
and stowed myself between two barrels, wrapped up in a sail. The prisoner rushed
after me and attempted to kill me, but was prevented by the interference of
another man. I recollect who struck me, but was not sufficiently sensible to
distinguish the man who saved me. I was faint from loss of blood. I then was
taken on deck and tied to the hand of Ruiz. After this they commanded me to
steer for their country. I told them I did not know the way. I was much afraid,
and had lost my senses, so I cannot recollect who tied me. On the second day
after the mutiny, a heavy gale came on. I still steered, having once been master
of a vessel. When recovered, I steered for Havana, in the night by the stars,
but by the sun in the day, taking care to make no more way than possible. After
sailing fifty leagues, we saw an American merchant ship, but did not speak her.
We were also passed by a schooner but were unnoticed. Every moment my life was
threatened. I know nothing of the murder of the Captain. All I know of the
murder of the mulatto is that I heard the blows. He was asleep when attacked.
Next morning the negroes had washed the decks. During the rain the Captain was
at the helm. They were all glad, next day, at what had happened. The prisoners
treated me harshly, and but for the interference of others, would have killed me
several times every day. We kept no reckoning. I did not know how many days we
had been out, nor what day of the week it was when the officers came on board.
We anchored at least thirty times, and lost an anchor at New Providence. When at
anchor we were treated well, but at sea they acted very cruelly towards me. They
once wanted me to drop anchor in the high seas. I had no wish to kill any of
them, but prevented them from killing each other.</p>
                        <p>The prisoner was now sent to his quarters, and the Court adjourned to the
schooner, that she might be inspected and that Antonio when making his
deposition might recognize those who murdered the Captain and his mulatto cook.</p>
                      </div1>
                    </body>
                  </text>
                </q>
                <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
                  <text>
                    <body>
                      <div1 type="letter">
                        <head>
                          <hi rend="italics">Adjourned investigation on board the Amistad.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>Antonio, the slave of the murdered Captain, was called before the court, and was
addressed in Spanish, by Lieut. Meade, on the nature of an oath. He said he was
a Christian, and being sworn, he thus testified:</p>
                        <p>“We had been out four days when the mutiny broke out. That night it had been raining 
very hard, and all hands been on deck. The rain ceased, but still it was very dark. Clouds 
covered the moon. After the rain, the Captain and mulatto lay down on some 
<sic corr="mattresses">matresses</sic> that they had brought on deck. Four of 
the slaves came aft, armed with those knives which are used to cut sugar cane; 
they struck the Captain across
<pb id="barber8" n="8"/>
the face twice or three times; they struck the mulatto oftener. Neither of them
groaned. By this time the rest of the slaves had come on deck, all armed in the
same way. The man at the wheel and another let down the small boat and escaped. I was awake and saw it all. The men escaped before Senor Ruiz and Senor Montez awoke. Joseph, the man in irons, was the leader; he attacked Senor Montez. Senor Montez fought with them and wanted them to be still. The Captain ordered me to throw some bread among them. I did so, but they would not touch it. After killing the Captain and the cook, and wounding Senor Montez, they tied Montez and Ruiz by the hands till they had ransacked the cabin. After doing so, they loosed them, and they went below. Senor Montez could scarcely walk. The bodies of the Captain and mulatto were thrown overboard and the decks washed. One of the slaves who attacked the Captain has since died. Joseph was one, two of them are now below. (The boy then went on deck and picked out the two negroes who had 
conspired to kill the Captain and mulatto.)</p>
                        <p>The examination of the boy being finished, the court returned by the conveyance
which put it on board the Washington, and after being in consultation some time,
came to the following decision:</p>
                        <p>Joseph Cingue, the leader, and 38 others, as named in the indictment, stand
committed for trial before the next Circuit Court at Hartford, to be holden on
the 17th day of September next.</p>
                        <p>The three girls and Antonio, the cabin boy, are ordered to give bonds in the sum
of $100 each to appear before the said court and give evidence in the aforesaid case, and for want of such bonds to be committed to the county jail in the city of New Haven. These persons were not indicted. Lieut. R.W. Meade, Don Jose Ruiz, and Don Pedro Montez, are ordered to recognize in the sum of $100 each to appear and give evidence in said case, before the aforesaid court. The court now finally adjourned, having given an order to the U.S. Marshal, to transport them to New Haven. As we were about to leave, the following was put into our hands by Senor Ruiz, with a request that it might be published in all the city papers:</p>
                      </div1>
                    </body>
                  </text>
                </q>
                <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
                  <text>
                    <body>
                      <div1 type="letter">
                        <head>A CARD.
</head>
                        <opener>
                          <dateline>NEW LONDON AUGUST 29, 1839.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The subscribers, Don Jose Ruiz, and Don Pedro Montez, in gratitude for their
most unhoped for and providential rescue from the hands of a ruthless gang of
African <sic corr="buccaneers">bucaniers</sic> and an awful death, would take this means of expressing, in
some slight degree, their thankfulness and obligation to Lieut. Com. T.R.
Gedney, and the officers and crew of the U.S. surveying brig Washington, for
their decision in seizing the Amistad, and their unremitting kindness and
hospitality in providing for their comfort on board their vessel, as well as the
means they have taken for the protection of their property.</p>
                        <p>We also must express our indebtedness to that nation whose flag they so worthily
bear, with an assurance that this act will be duly appreciated by our most
gracious sovereign, her Majesty the Queen of Spain.</p>
                        <closer><signed>DON JOSE RUIZ,</signed>
<signed>DON PEDRO MONTEZ.”</signed></closer>
                      </div1>
                    </body>
                  </text>
                </q>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <p>The Africans were put on board of a sloop, under the charge of Lieut. Holcomb,
of the Washington, and Col. Pendleton, keeper of the New Haven prison. They
arrived in New Haven on Sunday morning, Sept. 1st. Cingue, the leader, was
separated from the rest, and was brought in by the revenue cutter Wolcott, Capt.
Mather, in irons. The whole, 44 in number, were put into the county Jail, of
which, they occupied four apartments.</p>
        <p>The following account of the Amistad captives, given individually, is partly
drawn from personal interpreter from that given by Professor Gibbs, and partly
from personal conversation had with them by the compiler, by means of an
interpreter. The accompanying profiles were mostly taken by a pentagraph from
the wax figures now exhibiting through the country by Pendleton &amp; Curtiss, which are striking and accurate likenesses of the Africans, taken from life by Mr.
Moulthrop, and are mathematically correct. [The numbers correspond with those on the wax figures.] The French sound of the vowels is the one adopted in the
orthography of names.</p>
        <p>[The map (page 9) is given to assist the reader in understanding some parts of
the outline history of the individual Africans, which is here attempted. It
gives the situation of the Mendi country, with regard to other portions of
Africa. The distance from Freetown, Sierra Leone, to Monrovia, Liberia, is in a
direct line, about two hundred miles. It will be seen on the map, that Gallinas
river discharges its waters into the ocean between these two places. Lomboko,
the place from where the Africans were embarked for Havana, is an island at the
mouth of the Gallinas.]</p>
        <pb id="barber9" n="9"/>
        <p>
          <figure id="ill1" entity="barbe9a">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Map of part of Western 
Africa.</hi>
            </head>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p>
          <figure id="ill2" entity="barbe9b">
            <p>No. 1. No. 2.</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1 type="letter">
                <p>(1.) SING-GBE,[<emph rend="bold">Cin-gue</emph>,]
(generally spelt <hi rend="italics">Cinguez</hi>) was born in Ma-ni, in Dzho-poa,
<hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> in the open land, in the Men-di country. The distance from Mani to Lomboko,
he says, is ten suns, or days. His mother is dead, and he lived with his father.
He has a wife and three children, one son and two daughters. His son's name is
<hi rend="italics">Ge-waw</hi>,(God.) His king Ka-lum-bo, lived at Mendi country. He is a planter of
rice, and never owned or sold slaves. He was seized by four men, when traveling
in the road, and his right hand tied to his neck. Ma-ya-gi-la-lo sold him
to Ba-ma-dzha, son of Shaka, king of Gen-du-ma, in the Vai country. Bamadzha
carried him to Lomboko and sold him to a Spaniard. He was with Mayagilalo
three nights; with Bamadzha one month, and at Lomboko two months. He had heard of Pedro Blanco, who lived 
at Te-i-lu, near Lomboko.<ref targOrder="U" id="ref1" n="1" rend="sc" target="note1">∗</ref></p>
                <note id="note1" n="1" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref1">
                  <p>∗The following is a phrenological 
description of the head of Cingue as given by
Mr. Fletcher: “Cingue appears to be about 26 years of age, of powerful frame, bilious and sanguine 
temperament, bilious predominating. His head by measurement is 22 3-8 inches in circumference, 15 inches 
from the root of the nose to the occipital protuberance over the top of the head, 15 inches from the 
<foreign lang="lat">Meatus Anditorious</foreign> to do. over the head, and 5 3-4 inches through the 
head at
destructiveness.</p>
                  <p>The development of the faculties is as follows: Firmness;
self-esteem; hope—very large. Benevolence; veneration; conscientiousness; approbativeness; wonder; 
concentrativeness;
inhabitiveness; comparison; form—large. Amativeness; philoprogenitiveness; adhesiveness; combativeness; destructuctiveness; secretiveness; constructiveness; caution; language; individuality; eventuality; causality; order—average. Alimentiveness; acquisitiveness; ideality; mirthfulness; imitation; size; weight; color; locality; number; time; tune—moderte and small. The head is well formed
and such as a phrenologist admires. The coronal region being the largest, the frontal and occipital nearly 
balanced, and the baislar moderte. In fact, such an African head is seldom to be seen, and doubtless in other circumstances would have been an honor to his race.”</p>
                </note>
                <p>(2.) GI-LA-BA-RU, [<emph rend="bold">Grab-eau,</emph>] (<hi rend="italics">have mercy on me</hi>,) was
born in Fu-lu, in the Mendi country, two moons' journey into the interior. His name in the public prints 
is generally spelt GRABEAU<corr sic=",">.</corr> He was the next after Cinque in command of the Armistad. 
His parents are dead, one brother and one sister living. He is married, but no children; he is a planter of rice. His king Baw-baw, live in Fu-lu. He saw Cinque at Fulu and Fadzhinna, in Bombali. He was caught on the road when going to Taurang, in the Bandi country, to buy clothes. His uncle had bought two slaves in Bandi, and gave them in payment 
for a debt; one of them ran away, and he (Grabeau) was taken for him. He was sold to a Vai-man, who sold him to Laigo, a Spaniard, at Lomboko. Slaves in this place were put into a prison, two
<pb id="barber10" n="10"/>
are chained together by the legs, and the Spaniards give them rice and fish to eat. In his country has seen people write—they wrote from right to left. They have cows, sheep, and goats, and wear cotton cloth. Smoking tobacco is a common practice. None but the rich eat salt, it costs so much. Has seen leopards and elephants, the latter of which, are hunted for ivory. Grabeau is four feet eleven inches in height; very active, especially in turning somersets. Besides Mendi, he speaks Vai, Kon-no and Gissi. He aded John Ferry by his knowledge of Gissi, in the examination at Hartford.</p>
                <p>
                  <figure id="ill3" entity="barbe10a">
                    <p>No.3. No. 4. No. 5.</p>
                  </figure>
                </p>
                <p>(3.) <emph rend="bold">Kimbo</emph> (<hi rend="italics">cricket</hi>) is 5 ft. 6 in. in height, with mustaches and long beard; in
middle life, and is intelligent. He was born at Maw-ko-ba, a town in the Mendi
country; his father was a gentleman, and after his death, his king took him for
his slave, and gave him to his son Ban-ga, residing in Bullom country. He was
sold to a Bullom man, who sold him to a Spaniard at Lomboko. He counts thus:
<foreign>1, etá; 2, filî; 3, kiau-wá; 4, náeni; 5, lóelu; 6 wêta; 7 wafurá; 8, wayapá;
9, tá-u; 10, pu.</foreign>—Never saw any books in his country. When people die in his country, they suppose the spirit lives, but where they cannot tell.</p>
                <p>(4) NAZHA-U-LU, (<hi rend="italics">a water stick,</hi>) also called from his country, <emph rend="bold">Kon-no-ma</emph>, is
5ft. 4 in. in height, has large lips, and projecting mouth, his incisor teeth
pressed outward and filed, giving him rather a savage appearance; he is the one
who was supposed to be a cannibal, (see page 5,) tattooed in the forehead with a
diamond shaped figure. He was born in the Konno country: his language is not
readily understood by Covey, the interpreter. Kon-no-ma recognizes many words in Mungo Park's Mandingo vocabulary.</p>
                <p>(5.) <emph rend="bold">Bur-na</emph>, the younger, height 5 ft. 2 in. lived in a small town in the Mendi
country. He counts in Tim-ma-ni and Bullom. He was a blacksmith in his native
village, and made hoes, axes, and knives; he also planted rice. He was sold for
crim. con. to a Spaniard at Lomboko. He was taken in the road, and was four days
in traveling to Lomboko. Has a wife and one child, a father, three sisters and
brothers living.</p>
                <p>
                  <figure id="ill4" entity="barbe10b">
                    <p>No. 6. No. 7. No. 8.</p>
                  </figure>
                </p>
                <p>(6.) GBA-TU, [<emph rend="bold">Bar-tu,</emph>] (<hi rend="italics">a club or sword</hi>,) height 5 ft. 6 in. with a tattooed
breast; was born in the country of Tu-ma, near a large body of fresh water,
called Ma-wu-a. His father is a gentleman and does no work. His king, named
<hi rend="italics">Da-be</hi>, resided in the
<pb id="barber11" n="11"/>
town of Tu-ma. He was sent by his father to a village to buy clothes; on his
return, he was seized by six men, and his hands tied behind; was ten days in
going to Lomboko. There are high mountains in his country, rice is cultivated,
people have guns; has seen elephants. <hi rend="italics">Remark.</hi>—There is a village called
Tu-ma in the Timmani country, 60 miles from Sierra Leone, visited by Major
Laing.</p>
                <p>(7.) <emph rend="bold">Gna-kwoi</emph> (in <hi rend="italics">Ba-lu</hi> dialect, <hi rend="italics">second born</hi>) was born at Kong-go-la-hung, the
largest town in the Balu country. This town is situated on a large river called
in Balu, <hi rend="italics">Za-li-bu</hi>; and in Mendi, <hi rend="italics">Kal-wa-ra</hi>: fish are caught in this river as
large as a man's body—they are caught in nets and sometimes shot with guns. When going to the gold country to buy clothes, he was taken and sold to a
Vai-man who sold him to a Spaniard named <hi rend="italics">Peli</hi>. Gna-kwoi has a wife and one
child; he calls himself a Balu-man; has learned the Mendi language since he was
a slave; 5 ft. 6 in. in height.</p>
                <p>(8.) <emph rend="bold">Kwong</emph> was born at Mam-bui, a town in the Mendi country. When a boy he was
called Ka-gnwaw-ni. Kwong is a Bullom name. He was sold by a Timmani gentleman in the Du-bu country, for crim. con. with his wife, to Luisi, a Spaniard, at
Lomboko. He is in middle life, 5 ft. 6 in. high.</p>
                <p>
                  <figure id="ill5" entity="barbe11a">
                    <p>No. 9. No. 10. No. 11.</p>
                  </figure>
                </p>
                <p>(9.) <emph rend="bold">Fu-li-wa</emph>, Fuli, (<hi rend="italics">sun</hi>,) called by his fellow prisoners Fuliwa, (<hi rend="italics">great
Fuli</hi>,) to distinguish him from Fu-li-wu-lu, (<hi rend="italics">little Fuli</hi>,) was born at Ma-no, a
town in the Mendi country, where his king, <hi rend="italics">Ti-kba</hi>, resided. He lived with his
parents, and has five brothers. His town was surrounded by soldiers, some were
killed, and he with the rest were taken prisoners. He passed through the Vai
country, when taken to Lomboko, and was one month on the journey. He is in
middle life, 5ft. 3 in. high, face broad in the middle, with a slight beard. It
was this Fuli who instituted the suit against Ruiz and Montez.</p>
                <p>(10.) <emph rend="bold">P-ie</emph>, <hi rend="italics">Pi-e</hi>, or <hi rend="italics">Bi-a</hi>, (5 ft. 41/2 in. high,) calls himself a Timmani, and
the father of Fu-li-wu-lu. He appears to have been distinguished for hunting in
his country: says he has killed 5 leopards, 3 on the land, and 2 in the water;
has killed three elephants. He has a very pleasant countenance; his hands are
whitened by wounds received from the bursting of a gun barrel, which he had
overloaded when showing his dexterity. He had a leopard's skin hung up on his
hut, to show that he was a hunter. He has a wife and four children. He
recognizes with great readiness the Timmani words and phrases contained in
Winterbottom's account of Sierra Leone. He and his son seemed overjoyed to find
an American who could articulate the sound of their native tongue.</p>
                <p>
                  <figure id="ill6" entity="barbe11b">
                    <p>No. 12. No. 13. No. 14.</p>
                  </figure>
                </p>
                <p>(11.) <emph rend="bold">Pung-wu-ni</emph>, [Pung-wu-ni,] (<hi rend="italics">a duck</hi>,) 5 ft. 1 in. high, body tattooed,
teeth filed, was born at Fe-baw, in Sando, between Mendi and Konno. His mother's brother
<pb id="barber12" n="12"/>
sold him for a coat. He was taken in the night, and was taken a six days'
journey, and sold to Garlobá, who had four wives. He <sic corr="stayed">staid</sic> with this man two years, and was employed in cultivating rice. His master's wives and children were employed in the same manner, and no distinction made in regard to labor.</p>
                <p>(12.) <emph rend="bold">Ses-si</emph>, 5 ft. 71/2 in. with a sly and mirthful countenance, was born in
Massa-kum, in the Bandi country, where his king, <hi rend="italics">Pa-ma-sa</hi>, resided. He has three
brothers, two sisters, a wife, and three children. He is a blacksmith, having
learnt that trade of his brother; he made axes, hoes, and knives from iron
obtained in the Mendi country. He was taken captive by soldiers and wounded in
the leg. He was sold twice before he arrived at Lomboko, where he was kept about a month. Although a Bandi; he appears to have been able to talk in Mendi.</p>
                <p>(13.) <emph rend="bold">Mo-ru</emph>, middle age, 5 ft. 81/2 in. with full negro features, was born at
Sanka, in the Bandi country. His parents died when he was a child. His master,
Margoná, who sold him, had ten wives and many houses; he was twenty days on his journey to Lomboko. He was sold to Be-le-wa, (<hi rend="italics">great whiskers</hi>,) i.e. to a Spaniard.</p>
                <p>(14.) <emph rend="bold">Ndam-ma</emph>, (<hi rend="italics">put on, or up</hi>,) 5 ft. 3 in. a stout built youth, born in the
Mendi country, on the river Ma-le. His father is dead, and he lived with his
mother; has a brother and sister. He was taken in the road by twenty men, and
was many days in traveling to Lomboko.</p>
                <p>
                  <figure id="ill7" entity="barbe12a">
                    <p>No. 15. No. 16. No. 17.</p>
                  </figure>
                </p>
                <p>(15.) <emph rend="bold">Fu-li-wu-lu</emph>, (<hi rend="italics">Fuli</hi>,) or, as the name has been written, Furie, (<hi rend="italics">sun</hi>,)
called Fuliwulu, to distinguish him from Fuliwa, (<hi rend="italics">great Fuli</hi>,) lived with his
parents in the Timmani, near the Mendi country. He is the son of Pie, (No. 10.)
He was taken with his father, by an African, who sold him to a Bullom man, who
sold him to Luis, a Spaniard at Lomboko. He has depression in the skull from a
wound in the for forehead. 5 ft. 2 1/2 in. in height.</p>
                <p>(16.) <emph rend="bold">Ba-u</emph>, (<hi rend="italics">broke</hi>,) 5 ft. 5 in. high, sober, intelligent looking, and rather
slightly built. Has a wife and three children. He was caught in the bush by 4
men as he was going to plant rice; his left hand was tied to his neck; was ten
days in going to Lomboko. He lived near a large river named Wo-wa. In his
country all have to pay for their wives; for his, he had to pay 10 clothes, 1
goat, 1 gun, and plenty of mats; his mother made the cloth for him.</p>
                <p>
                  <figure id="ill8" entity="barbe12b">
                    <p>No. 18. No. 19. No. 20.</p>
                  </figure>
                </p>
                <p>(17.) <emph rend="bold">Ba</emph>, (<hi rend="italics">have none</hi>,) 5 ft, 4 1/2 in. with a narrow and high head; in middle
life. Parents living, 4 brothers and 4 sisters; has got a wife and child. He is
a planter of rice. He was seized by two men in the road, and was sold to a
Gallina Vai-man, who sold him to a Spaniard. High mountains in his country, but
small streams; cotton cloth is manufactured, and hens, sheep, goats, cows, and
wild hogs are common.</p>
                <pb id="barber13" n="13"/>
                <p>(18.) <emph rend="bold">Shu-le</emph>, (<hi rend="italics">water fall</hi>,) 5 ft. 4 in, the oldest of the Amistad captives, and
the fourth in command, when on board the schooner. He was born at Konabu, in the
open land in the Mendi country. He was taken for a slave by Ma-ya, for crim.
con. with his wife. Momawru caught both him and his master Ma-ya, and made
them slaves, and sold them to a man who sold him to the Spaniards at Lomboko.
There is a large river in his country named <hi rend="italics">Wu-wa</hi>, which runs from Gissi, passes
through Mendi, and runs south into the Konno country.</p>
                <p>(19.) <emph rend="bold">Ka-le</emph>, (<hi rend="italics">bone</hi>,) 5 ft. 4 in. small head and large under lip, young and
pleasant. His parents living; has two sisters. He was taken while going to a
town to buy rice. He was two months in traveling to Lomboko.</p>
                <p>(20). <emph rend="bold">Ba-gna</emph>, (<hi rend="italics">sand</hi> or <hi rend="italics">gravel</hi>,) 5 ft. 3 in. was born at Du-gau-na, in the Konno
country, where his king, <hi rend="italics">Da-ga</hi>, lived. His parents are dead, and he lived with
his brother, a planter of rice.</p>
                <p>
                  <figure id="ill9" entity="barbe13a">
                    <p>No. 21. No. 22. No. 23.</p>
                  </figure>
                </p>
                <p>(21.) <emph rend="bold">Sa</emph>, 5 ft. 2 in. a youth with a long narrow head. He was the only child of
his parents, and was stolen when walking in the road, by two men. He was two
months in traveling to Lomboko.</p>
                <p>(22.) <emph rend="bold">Kin-na</emph>, (<hi rend="italics">man</hi> or <hi rend="italics">big man</hi>,) 5 ft. 5 1/2 in. has a bright countenance, is
young, and, since he has been in New Haven, has been a good scholar. His parents and grandparents were living; has four brothers and one sister. He was born at Si-ma-bu, in the Mendi country; his king, Sa-mang, resided in the same place. He was seized when going to Kon-go-li, by a Bullom man, who sold him to Luiz, at Lomboko.</p>
                <p>(23.) NDZHA-GNWAW-NI, [<emph rend="bold">Nga-ho-ni,</emph>] (<hi rend="italics">water bird,</hi>) 5 ft. 9 in. with a large head,
high cheekbones, in middle life. He has a wife and one child; he gave twenty
clothes and one shawl for his wife. He lived in a mountainous country; his town
was formerly fenced around, but now broken down. He was seized by four men when in a rice field, and was two weeks in traveling to Lomboko.</p>
                <p>
                  <figure id="ill10" entity="barbe13b">
                    <p>No. 24. No. 25. No. 26.</p>
                  </figure>
                </p>
                <p>(24) FANG, [<emph rend="bold">Fa-kin-na,</emph>] 5 ft. 4 in. head elevated in the middle, stout built,
and middle aged. He was born at Dzho-po-a-hu, in the Mendi country, at which
place his father, <hi rend="italics">Baw-nge</hi>, is chief or king. He has a wife and two children; was
caught in the bushes by a Mendi man, belonging to a party with guns, and says he
was ten days in traveling to Lomboko after being a slave to the man that took
him, less than a month.</p>
                <p>(25.) FAHI-DZHIN-NA, [<emph rend="bold">Fa-gin-na,</emph>] (<hi rend="itlaics">twin</hi>,) 5 ft. 4 in. marked on the face with
the small pox; was born at Tom-bo-lu, a town in Bombali, in the Mendi country.
He was made a slave by Tamu for crim. con. with his wife. Tamu sold him to a
<pb id="barber14" n="14"/>
Mendi man, who sold him to Laigo, a Spaniard, the same who purchased Grabeau. He says many people in his country have the small pox, to cure which, they oil their bodies.</p>
                <p>(26.) <emph rend="bold">Va-boi</emph>, 5 ft. 7 in. large head, stout built, and in middle life; was born
at Kon-do-wa-lu, where his king, Ka-kbe-ni (<hi rend="italics">lazy</hi>,) resided. His village was surrounded by soldiers, and he was taken by Gillewa, a Mendi man, to whom he was a slave ten years. Had a wife and one child. Gillewa sold him to Luiz, the Spaniard.</p>
                <p>
                  <figure id="ill11" entity="barbe14a">
                    <p>No. 27. No. 28. No. 29.</p>
                  </figure>
                </p>
                <p>(27.) <emph rend="bold">Fa-ban-na</emph>, (<hi rend="italics">remember,</hi>) 5 ft. 5 in. large round head, tattooed on the
breast; in middle life; he and Grabeau were from the same country, both having
the same king. He has two wives and one child; all lived in one house. His
village was surrounded by soldiers: he was taken prisoner, sold twice, the last
time to a Spaniard at Lomboko.</p>
                <p>(28.) <emph rend="bold">Tsu-ka-ma</emph>, (<hi rend="italics">a learner</hi>,) 5 ft. 5 1/2 in. young, with a pleasant
countenance; was born at Sun-ga-ru, in the Mendi country, where his king,
Gnam-be, resided: has parents living, 3 sisters, and 4 brothers. He was taken
and sold into the Bullom country, where he lived for a time with his master, who
sold him to Luiz, at Lomboko.</p>
                <p>(29.) BE-RI, [<emph rend="bold">Ber-ri,</emph>] (<hi rend="italics">stick</hi>,) 5 ft. 3 in. with mustaches and beard, broad
nose; in middle life. He was born at <hi rend="italics">Fang-te</hi>, in Gula, a large fenced town where
his king, Ge-le-wa, resided. He was taken by soldiers, and was sold to Shaka,
king of Genduma, in the Vai or Gallina country, who sold him to a Spaniard.
Genduma is on a fresh water river, called <hi rend="italics">Boba</hi>. It is three or four miles from
the river, and nine from the sea.</p>
                <p>
                  <figure id="ill12" entity="barbe14b">
                    <p>No. 30. No. 31. No. 32.</p>
                  </figure>
                </p>
                <p>(30.) FAW-NI, [<emph rend="bold">Fo-ni,</emph>] 5 ft. 2 in. stout built; in middle life. He was born at
Bum-be, a large town in the Mendi country: the name of his king was Ka-ban-du.
He is married, and has parents, brothers, and sisters living. He was seized by
two men as he was going to plant rice. He was carried to Bem-be-law, in the Vai
country, and sold to Luiz, who kept him there two months, before he took him to
Lomboko. From Bem-be-law to Lomboko is one day's walk.</p>
                <p>(31.) <emph rend="bold">Bur-na</emph>, (<hi rend="italics">twin</hi>,) the elder, has a cast in the eye; was taken when going to
the next town, by three men. His father is dead, and he lived with his mother;
has four sisters and two brothers. When his father died his brother married; all
lived in the same house. In his country are high mountains, but no rivers; has
seen elephants and leopards. He was six weeks in traveling to Lomboko, where he was kept three and a half moons.</p>
                <p>(32.) <emph rend="bold">Shuma</emph>, (<hi rend="italics">falling water</hi>,) 5 ft. 6 in. with mustaches and beard; in middle
life. He can count in the Mendi, Timmani, and Bullom. His parents have
<pb id="barber15" n="15"/>
been dead a long time; has a wife and one child, was taken prisoner in war, and
it was four moons after he was taken, before he arrived at Lomboko. Shuma spoke
over the corpse of Tua, after the Rev. Mr. Bacon's prayer. The substance of what
he said, as translated by Covey, was, “Now Tua dead, God takes Tua,—we are
left behind—No one can die but once,”&amp;c.</p>
                <p>
                  <figure id="ill13" entity="barbe15a">
                    <p>No. 33. No. 34. No. 35.</p>
                  </figure>
                </p>
                <p>(33.) <emph rend="bold">Ka-li</emph>, (<hi rend="italics">bone</hi>,) 4 ft. 3 in. a small boy, with a large head, flat and broad
nose, stout built. He says his parents are living; has a sister and brother; was
stolen when in the street, and was about a month in traveling to Lomboko.</p>
                <p>(34.) <emph rend="bold">Te-me</emph>, (<hi rend="italics">frog</hi>,) 4 ft. 3 in. a young girl, says she lived with her mother,
with an elder brother, and sister; her father was dead. A party of men in the
night broke into her mother's house, and made them prisoners; she never saw her
mother or brother afterwards, and was a long time in traveling to Lomboko.</p>
                <p>(35.) <emph rend="bold">Ka-gne</emph>, (<hi rend="italics">country</hi>,) 4 ft. 3 in. a young girl. She counts in Mendi like
Kwong, she also counts in Fai or Gallina, imperfectly. She says her parents are
living, and has four brothers and four sisters; she was put in pawn for a debt
by her father which not being paid, she was sold into slavery, and was many days
in going to Lomboko.</p>
                <p>
                  <figure id="ill14" entity="barbe15b">
                    <p>No. 36. <hi rend="italics">Antonio.</hi></p>
                  </figure>
                </p>
                <p>(36.) <emph rend="bold">Mar-gru</emph>, (<hi rend="italics">black snake</hi>,)4 ft. 3 in. a young girl, with a large, high
forehead; her parents were living; she had four sisters and two brothers; she
was pawned by her father for a debt, which being unpaid, she was sold into
slavery.</p>
                <p>The foregoing list comprises all The Africans captured with the Amistad, now
[May, 1840] living. Six have died while they have been in New Haven; viz. 1, <hi rend="italics">Fa</hi>, Sept. 3d, 1839; 2, <hi rend="italics">Tua</hi> (a Bullom name) died Sept. 11th; 3, <hi rend="italics">We-lu wa</hi> (a Bandi
name) died Sept. 14th; 4, <hi rend="italics">Ka-ba</hi>, a Mendi man, died Dec. 31st; 5, <hi rend="italics">Ka pe-lt</hi>, a
Mendi youth, died Oct. 30; 6, <hi rend="italics">Yam-mo-ni</hi>, in middle life, died Nov. 4th.</p>
                <p>
                  <figure id="ill15" entity="barbe15c">
                    <p>
                      <hi rend="italics">James Covey</hi>
                    </p>
                  </figure>
                </p>
                <p>JAMES COVEY, the interpreter for the Africans, is apparently about 20 years of
age; was born at Benderi, in the Mendi country. His father was of Kon-no
descent, and his mother Gissi. Covey was taken by three men, in the evening,
from his parents' house, at Go-la-hung, whither they had removed when he was
quite young. He was carried to the Bullom country, and sold as a slave
to Ba-yi-mi, the king of the Bul-loms, who resided at Mani. He lived there for
three years, and was employed to plant rice for the wife of Ba-yi-mi, who
treated him with great kindness. He was sold to a Portuguese, living near Mani,
who carried him, with 200 or 300 others to Lomboko, for the purpose of being
transported to America. After staying in this place about one month, Covey was
put on board a Portuguese slave-ship, which, after being out about four days
from Lomboko, was captured by a British armed vessel, and carried into Sierra
Leone. Covey thus obtained his freedom, and remained in this place five or six
years, and was taught to read and write the English language, in the schools of
the Church Missionary Society. Covey's original name was <hi rend="italics">Kaw-we-li</hi>, which
signifies, in Mendi, <hi rend="italics">war road</hi>, i.e., a road dangerous to pass, for fear of being
taken captive. His Christian name, James, was given him by Rev. J. W. Weeks, a
Church missionary, at Sierra Leone. In Nov., 1838, he enlisted as a sailor on
board the British brig of war Buzzard, commanded by Captain Fitzgerald. It was
on board this vessel, when at New York, in Oct., 1839, that James was found,
amid some twenty native Africans, and by the kindness of captain Fitzgerald, his
services as an interpreter were procured.</p>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <pb id="barber16" n="16"/>
        <p>On the 14th of September, 1839, all the captured Africans, with the exception of
Burna, who was left sick at New Haven, were removed to Hartford to await their
trial. On Wednesday, the 18th, Judge Thompson took his seat. In the afternoon
the council for the blacks, Messrs. S. P. Staples and T. Sedgwick, Jr. of New
York, and R. S. Baldwin of New Haven, moved for a <foreign lang="lat">habeas corpus</foreign> to the Marshal,
directing him to bring up the three African girls, they not being implicated in
the criminal charge. The writ was granted and made returnable the next morning.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, the matter of the <foreign lang="lat">habeas corpus</foreign> was postponed till the afternoon,
and the District Court was opened by Judge Judson, he quitting the bench of the
Circuit Court. The libels and claims in relation to the Amistad were then read
and filed as follows; 1st. Lieut. Gedney and Meade, filed their libel praying
for salvage. 2d. Captain Green, of Long Island, by Governor Ellsworth, his
Attorney, put in his libel for salvage also. 3d. Pedro Montez filed his libel
against part of the cargo, and four of the slaves, three girls and one boy, as
his property. 4th. Jose Ruiz filed his libel against the remainder of the slaves
and the balance of the property; and lastly, the District Attorney, Mr.
Hollabird, filed a claim under Lieut. Gedney's libel, on two distinct grounds:
one that these Africans had been claimed by the Government of Spain, and ought
to be retained till the pleasure of the Executive might be known as to that
demand, and the other, that they should be held subject to the disposition of
the President, to be re-transported to Africa, under the act of 1819.</p>
        <p>The Spanish Consul also asked leave to file a libel in behalf of the owners
abroad. The counsel who appeared for the Spanish owners, were Messrs. R. I.
Ingersoll, W. Hungerford, and Mr. Purroy of New York.</p>
        <p>The only matter of consequence which occurred at this time, was that the
District Judge said he had come to the decision that there could be no claim for
salvage as to the Africans.</p>
        <p>Thursday, P. M.—The three African girls were brought into Court weeping, and evidently much terrified at the separation from their companions:—the eldest being about eleven years of age. The Marshal then made his return, and justified the detention of these negroes under the libel of Lieut. Gedney—the claim of the United States, the libel of Pedro Montez, and also under an order of the District Judge, committing them as witnesses to appear at this Court. The
counsel for the Africans asked leave to consider this return, and it was granted
till the next morning.</p>
        <p>On Friday, the matter of the <foreign lang="lat">habeas corpus</foreign> was called up, and Mr. Sedgewick read
the answer to the Return, setting out at length the Spanish decrees suppressing
the slave trade, and alleging these Africans to have been born and still of
right to be free. Mr. Baldwin followed in a very elaborate argument, denying the
jurisdiction of the Court, as the property was found at Long Island, and in the
District of New York—the right of Gedney as salvor—the claim of Montez as a purchaser of slaves illegally imported into Cuba, and the authority of the District Attorney to make any claim in behalf of the Spanish Government, or that of the United States. In regard to their being recognized as witnesses, an offer
was made to give security for them, and in relation to the claim of Lieut.
Gedney, the Court remarked that, under the decision of the District Judge, they
could not be held by any process under that libel.—Thus two of the obstacles
to their discharge were removed: there remained the libel of the alleged owner,
and the claim of the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. R. I. Ingersoll replied to Mr. Baldwin, insisting that the rights of the
owners were the proper subjects of the cognizance of the District Court, and
that this Court should not interfere by this summary process to deprive them of
the opportunity of establishing those rights. He further insisted that by the
treaty of 1795 with Spain, the rights of these owners were guaranteed, and that
the President was bound to surrender them.</p>
        <p>The argument was now interrupted by the Grand Jury coming in, and requesting the Court to give them instructions respecting the murder <sic corr="alleged">alledged</sic> to have been
committed on board the Amistad. Upon an intimation of the judge, they presented
a statement of the facts of the case, and this the Court took time to consider.</p>
        <p>On the re-opening of the Court at 2 P. M., the Court delivered its charge to the
Grand Jury, instructing them that the offense of Cingue and his associates, (if
offense it was,) being committed on board a Spanish vessel, was not cognizable
in our courts. This gave a final disposition of the question whether these
Africans could be capitally punished in this country, and the Grand Jury having
no other business before them were discharged.</p>
        <pb id="barber17" n="17"/>
        <p>On the opening of the Circuit Court on Saturday morning, Judge Thompson said the Court were not prepared as yet, to dispose of the case under consideration,
<hi rend="italics">finally</hi>; and that any intimations he might then throw out, ought not to be taken
as the ultimate views of the Court. On the conclusion of his remarks, he
proposed that the case should be kept open until afternoon, and then have it
argued. A writ of <foreign lang="lat"><hi rend="italics">habeas corpus</hi></foreign> was taken out in the course of the forenoon on
the petition of Erastus Smith, Esq. of Hartford, for all the other African
prisoners returnable before this Court. The Court then took a recess until 2
o'clock. The arguments on the question were closed on Saturday evening. Messrs.
Baldwin and Staples addressed the Court in an able manner, about one hour each,
on the question of jurisdiction, and were opposed by Messrs. Hungerford and
Ingersoll. Mr. Staples, in his plea, argued that if there was jurisdiction any
where, it was in the Southern District of New York.</p>
        <p>On the opening of the Circuit Court, on Monday the 23d, Judge Thompson delivered
the opinion of the Court. He stated that the question now to be decided, was not
as to the ultimate rights of either party, but simply as to the right of the
District Court to take cognizance of the case. Had the seizure been made within
the limits of the District of New York, the District Court of Connecticut could
not have jurisdiction; if the seizure was made on the high seas, as it appeared
to be in this case, the District Court of any District to which the property was
brought, has jurisdiction. Judge Thompson, in denying the discharge of the
Africans, under the writ of the <hi rend="italics"><foreign lang="lat">habeas corpus</foreign></hi>, wished to be distinctly
understood, that, in denying their discharge, he did not decide that they were
not entitled to their freedom, but only left the case in a regular way for
decision in another tribunal, from whose decision an appeal might be taken to
that Court, and if desired, to the Supreme Court of the United States.</p>
        <p>After the adjournment of the Circuit Court, the District Court was opened. Judge
Judson said that he should direct an examination of the place where the Amistad
was taken, should be made, to determine where the seizure was actually made. The Court was then adjourned to meet in Hartford, on the third Tuesday in November, after the Judge had directed the U. S. Marshal, to see that the prisoners should be comfortably provided for, with regard to food, clothing, &amp;c. In pursuance of this direction, the Africans were remanded back to the prison in New Haven.</p>
        <p>On the l7th of October, Messrs. Ruiz and Montez were arrested in New York, on
two processes, at the suites of Cingue and Fuli, for assault and battery, and
false imprisonment. Being unable, or unwilling to give bail for $1000, which was
required, the Spaniards were lodged in prison. On a hearing of the case before
Judge Inglis, he decided that Montez should be discharged on finding common or
nominal bail, and that the amount of bail for Ruiz, should be reduced to two
hundred and fifty dollars.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, the 19th of October, the District Court at Hartford, met agreeable
to the adjournment, and the examination of witnesses occupied the whole day. On
Wednesday, seven of the Africans were brought in Court, and after some further
examination respecting the place of seizure, the Court was adjourned to sit in
New Haven, on January 7th, 1840.</p>
        <p>On the day of the adjournment, Judge Judson held a session at his chamber in the
City Hotel, for the purpose of receiving the testimony of Dr. R. R. Madden, who
had recently arrived in this country from Havana, on his return to England. He
stated that he was a British subject, and had
<pb id="barber18" n="18"/>
been a resident at Havana for more than three years, and had held official
stations there for three years; that the office he now held was that of
Commissioner of liberated Africans, and for one year held that of British
Commissioner in the Mixed Court of Justice: that the duties of his office
made him well acquainted with the details of slavery and slave trade in
Cuba. He stated that for the last three years, from <hi rend="italics">twenty</hi>, to <hi rend="italics">twenty-five
thousand</hi> slaves from Africa, were yearly introduced into the island of Cuba,
although it has been in violation of the Spanish law ever since 1820. The
Spanish authorities never interfere to stop this illegal trade, but connive at
it, receiving ten dollars a head for every negro thus introduced, which is
called a voluntary contribution, but is in reality a tax, which has no legal
sanction for its imposition. Dr. M. also stated that he had seen the Africans,
who were captured in the Amistad, and that they were of that class called in
Cuba, <hi rend="italics"><foreign lang="spa">Bozal</foreign></hi>, a term given to negroes recently from Africa: that the document
then produced before him, dated June 26th, 1839, and signed by Espelata,
the Captain General of Cuba, was a permit for the transportation of 49
slaves on board of the Amistad from Havana: that they are called in the
permit, <hi rend="italics"><foreign lang="spa">Ladinos</foreign></hi>, a term given to negroes long settled and acclimated in Cuba.</p>
        <p>That the custom, on landing the negroes illegally introduced by the slave
traders of the Havana, is to take them immediately to the <foreign lang="spa">Barracoons</foreign>, or slave
marts, which are fitted up exclusively for the reception and sale of <foreign lang="spa">Bozal</foreign>
negroes lately introduced, where they are kept by the slave traders till sold,
generally for a period of two or three weeks; that among the slave traders of
the Havana, one of the houses, the most openly engaged and notoriously
implicated in slave trade transactions, is that of Martinez &amp; Co., and that the
custom of this house is, like all other slave traders of the Havana, to send the
negroes they import into the island, immediately after landing, to the
<foreign lang="spa">Barracoons</foreign>.</p>
        <p>Dr. Madden also stated in his testimony, the trespasses or permits, for all such
negroes are commonly and usually obtained at the Havana, simply on application
to the authorities. The “<foreign lang="spa">Bozal</foreign>” negroes are called “<foreign lang="spa">Ladinos</foreign>,” and no examination
is made by the Governor or any officer of his, into the truth of the statement,
but the permit is granted for the removal of the negroes falsely called <foreign lang="spa">Ladinos</foreign>,
on the simple application of the buyers, on the payment of the fees, and no oath
required of them.</p>
        <p>That to apply for these permits, and obtain them, representing <foreign lang="spa">Bozal</foreign> negroes as
<foreign lang="spa">Ladinos</foreign>, as in the present case, is a fraud on the part of the purchaser, which
cannot take place without connivance at the trade, and collusion with the slave
traders on the part of the authorities. That the vast numbers <foreign lang="spa">Bozals</foreign> thus
illegally introduced are by these means carried into the interior, and fall into
hopeless slavery.</p>
        <p>The efforts of the committee on behalf of the Africans, were, after the
adjournment of the September court, crowned with success. Two native Africans
belonging to the crew of the British brig of war Buzzard, which came into New
York in July, from a cruise on the coast on the of Africa, were found to speak
the same language of the prisoners. With the consent of Capt. Fitzgerald, they
were allowed to come on to New Haven. When taken to the prison, the African
captives were at breakfast, and the Marshal objected to their entrance till they
had finished. One of the captives, however, coming to the door and finding one
who could talk in his own language, took hold of him and literally dragged him
in. Breakfast was forgotten, all seemed overwhelmed with joy, all talking as
fast possible.</p>
        <p>The following communication from Mr. Day, of New Haven, gives a summary account
of the African captives, as stated by themselves, from the time they left
Africa, till the time they obtained possession of the Amistad:</p>
        <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1 type="letter">
                <opener><dateline>NEW HAVEN, Oct. 8, 1839.</dateline>
<salute>[To the Editors of the Journal of Commerce.]</salute></opener>
                <p>Gentlemen—The following short and plain narrative of one or two of the
African captives, in whose history and prospects such anxious interest is felt,
has been taken
<pb id="barber19" n="19"/>
at the earliest opportunity possible, consistently with more important
examinations. It may be stated in general terms, as the result of the
investigations thus far made, that the Africans all testify that they left
Africa about six months since; were landed under cover of the night at a small
village or hamlet near Havana, and after 10 or 12 days were taken through Havana
by night by the man who had bought them, named <hi rend="italics">Pipi</hi>, who has since been
satisfactorily proved to be Ruiz; were cruelly treated on the passage, being
beaten and flogged, and in some instances having vinegar and gunpowder rubbed
into their wounds; and that they suffered intensely from hunger and thirst. The
perfect coincidence in the testimony of the prisoners, examined as they have
been separately, is felt by all who are acquainted with the minutes of the
examination, to carry with it overwhelming evidence of the truth of their story.</p>
                <closer><salute>Yours respectfully,</salute>
<signed>GEORGE E. DAY.</signed></closer>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1 type="letter">
                <opener>
                  <dateline>MONDAY, Oct. 7.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>This afternoon, almost the first time in which the two interpreters Covey and
Pratt have not been engaged with special reference to the trial to take place in
November, one of the captives named Grabeau, was requested to give a narrative
of himself since leaving Africa, for publication in the papers. The
interpreters, who are considerably exhausted by the examinations which have
already taken place, only gave the substance of what he said, without going into
details, and it was not thought advisable to press the matter. Grabeau first
gave an account of the passage from Africa to Havana. On board the vessel there
was a large number of men, but the women and children were far the most
numerous. They were fastened together in couples by the wrists and legs, and
kept in that situation day and night. Here Grabeau and another of the Africans
named Kimbo, lay down upon the floor, to show the painful position in which they
were obliged to sleep. By day it was no better. The space between decks was so
small,—according to their account not exceeding four feet,—that they
were obliged, if they attempted to stand, to keep a crouching posture. The
decks, fore and aft, were crowded to overflowing. They suffered (Grabeau said)
terribly. They had rice enough to eat, but had very little to drink. If they
left any of the rice that was given to them uneaten, either from sickness or any
other cause, they were whipped. It was a common thing for them to be forced to
eat so much as to vomit. Many of the men, women, and children died on the
passage.</p>
                <p>They were landed by night at a small village near Havana. Soon several white men
came to buy them, and among them was the one claiming to be their master, whom
they call <hi>Pipi</hi>, said to be a Spanish nick-name for <hi rend="italics">Jose</hi>. Pipi, or Ruiz, selected
such as he liked, and made them stand in a row. He then felt of each of them in
every part of the body; made them open their mouths to see if their teeth were
sound, and carried the examination to a degree of minuteness of which only a
slave dealer would be guilty.</p>
                <p>When they were separated from their companions who had come with them from
Africa, there was weeping among the women and children, but Grabeau did not
weep, “because he is a man.” Kimbo, who sat by, said that he also shed no
tears—but he thought of his home in Africa, and of friends left there whom
he should never see again.</p>
                <p>The men bought by Ruiz were taken on foot through Havana in the night, and put
on board a vessel. During the night they were kept in irons, placed about the
hands, feet and neck. They were treated during the day in a somewhat milder
manner, though all the irons were never taken off at once. Their allowance of
food was very scant, and of water still more so. They were very hungry, and
suffered much in the hot days and nights from thirst. In addition to this there
was much whipping, and the cook told them that when they reached land they would
all be eaten. This “made their hearts burn.” To avoid being eaten, and to escape
the bad treatment the experienced, they rose upon the crew with the design of
returning to Africa.</p>
                <p>Such is the substance of Grabeau's story, confirmed by Kimbo, who was present
most of the time. He says he likes the people of this country, because, to use
his own expression, “they are good people—they believe in God, and there is no slavery here.”</p>
                <p>The story of Grabeau was then read and interpreted to Cingue, while a number of
the other Africans were standing about, and confirmed by all of them in every
particular. When the part relating to the crowded state of the vessel from
Africa to Havana was read, Cingue added that there was scarcely room enough to
sit or lie down. Another showed the marks of the irons on his wrists, which must
at the time have been terribly lacerated. On their separation at Havana, Cingue
remarked that almost all of them were in tears, and himself among the rest,
“because they had come
<pb id="barber20" n="20"/>
from the same country, and were now to parted forever.” To the question, how it was possible for the Africans, when chained in the manner he described, to rise upon the crew, he replied that the chain which connected the iron collars about
their necks was fastened at the end by a padlock, and that this was first
broken, and <sic corr="afterwards">aftewards</sic> the other irons. Their object, he said, in the affray, was
to make themselves free. He then requested it to be added to the above, that “if
he tells a lie, God sees him by day and by night.”</p>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <p>
          <figure id="ill16" entity="barbe20">
            <p>[Illustration]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p>[The above engraving shows the position as described by Cingue and his
companions, in which they were confined on board the slaver, during their
passage from Africa. The space between the decks represented in the engraving is
three feet three inches, being an actual measurement from a slave vessel. The
space in the vessel that brought the Amistad captives to Havana was, according
to their statement, somewhat larger, being about four feet between the decks.]</p>
        <p>On the 7th of January, 1840, the U. S. District Court <sic corr="commenced">commened</sic> its session
in New Haven, Judge Judson presiding. The lawyers in the suit were Messrs.
Baldwin, Staples and Sedgewick, for the Africans. Messrs. Isham and Brainard of
New London, for Lieut. Gedney. Gov. Ellsworth of Connecticut, in behalf of Capt.
Green, and Mr. Cleveland of New London, in behalf of the Spanish owners of part
of the property on board of the Amistad, and lastly, Mr. Hollabird, District
Attorney, in behalf of the United States. The counsel for the prisoners withdrew
the plea which denied the jurisdiction of the court, and acknowledged that if
any court in the country could have jurisdiction of the case, this court could.
The morning was occupied in discussing technical questions, and the first
testimony introduced was on behalf of the prisoners. The deposition of Dr.
Madden was read. Messrs. Haley and Janes, of New London, James Covey, the
interpreter, and Professor Gibbs, of Yale College, then gave in their testimony,
all tending to show that the Amistad captives were recently from Africa. The
evidence on this point was so clear, that on the second day of the trial,
(Wednesday,) Judge Judson remarked that he was fully convinced that the men were
recently from Africa, and that it was unnecessary to take up time in
establishing that fact.</p>
        <p>Cingue, the leader of the Africans, being called as a witness, Covey, the
interpreter, was sworn to interpret the oath to him. The clerk read the oath and
Covey repeated it to Cingue in their native tongue. His examination was quite
minute, and was listened to by a crowded auditory, with the deepest interest. He
testified that at the time of their capture by Lieut. Gedney, a large number of
them were on shore, on Long Island. He also gave an account of the voyage to and
from Havana, till their capture; and his statements so nearly correspond with
the account already given, as to render a repetition unnecessary. While Cingue
was on his examination, he described by actions, (which spoke louder than
words,) the manner in which Pipi [Ruiz] examined the Africans to ascertain if
they were healthy
<pb id="barber21" n="21"/>
and sound. He also put himself in the position in which they were forced to
remain, when packed away on board the slaver. Grabeau and Fuliwa were then sworn and examined, who also testified to the same facts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilcox, the U.S. Marshal, was examined relative to a conversation he had
with Cingue, soon after the arrival of Covey, (the interpreter.) Mr. Wilcox
stated that he understood from Covey, (which he now denies,) that
Cingue had said that he had sold slaves, and that he himself was seized and sold
to pay a debt which he had contracted, and could not pay. Professor
Gibbs and Mr. Day who were present at the time, stated that there was much
confusion in the room, arising from many asking questions, &amp;c., and
think that Mr. Wilcox must have misapprehended what Cingue said.</p>
        <p>On Thursday afternoon, after the examination of Antonio, the slave of the
Spanish Captain, the District Attorney introduced the deposition of James Ray,
and G. W. Pierce, mariners on board of the cutter, giving a detailed account of
the capture of the Africans on Long Island. He then introduced the papers of the
Amistad, and the permits given to Montez and Ruiz, for the transportation of
<hi rend="italics"><foreign lang="spa">Ladinos</foreign></hi> to Principe. The license of Capt. Ferrer to carry slaves was from
Gaston, who signed himself a Knight of the Cross, a commander of a 74—bearing various insignia of honor, merit, and reward.</p>
        <p>The counsel for the Africans introduced Mr. D. FRANCIS BACON, of New Haven, as a
witness. Mr. Bacon stated that he left the coast of Africa on the 13th of July,
1839. He knew a place called Dumbokoro [Lomboko] by the Spaniards: it was an
island in the river or lagoon of Gallinas. <ref targOrder="U" id="ref2" n="2" rend="sc" target="note2">∗</ref>
<note id="note2" n="2" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref2"><p>∗ The following notice from Mr. Bacon, appeared in the New Haven papers,
addressed to the editors:</p></note></p>
        <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1 type="letter">
                <p>GENTLEMEN,—In connection with the report of the evidence yesterday given in
the case of the Amistad, allow me to state a few circumstances explanatory of
the manner in which I became possessed of the facts to which I testified.</p>
                <p>I was three times in Gallinas during my long wanderings on the coast of Western
Africa;—first, in January, 1838, afterwards, in May of the same year, and
last in February, 1839. On each of these visits I was the guest of Don Pedro
Blanco, long famous for his large share in the slave trade. From him and all of
his agents, and also from those of other establishments, Spanish and Portuguese,
in the same business, I received the most unbounded hospitalities. While thus an
inmate of their houses, I became familiar with all the details of their
business, which was carried on before me in the confidence that I would not
abuse their hospitality as a spy; though they had been cautioned that from my
connections I might be dangerous in this way.</p>
                <p>In the evidence given, I have therefore been careful to make use of no
circumstances relating to the traffic of which I was <hi rend="italics">thus</hi> informed, and which are not facts of common notoriety on the coast among those who have never been at Gallinas. To those Spaniards at Canines and New Sesters, I can never forget my numerous and weighty obligations. When the sea threw me, time and again, a houseless and friendless wanderer on their shore, they received and cherished me, and bade me always seek among them a welcome home in distress. They were anxious to supply every want, and their attentive kindness followed me to the last moment of my residence abroad. At the first tidings of my shipwreck they sent a vessel to search for me and my companions, then surrounded by perils on the sea and land, and from savages, while British men-of-war, scouring the coast for “<hi rend="italics">blood-money,</hi>” “passed by on the other side,” and carried the news to
those who had more charity for mariners in distress.</p>
                <p>I make this communication, because I consider it unjust both to them and me that
my evidence should go forth on any subject connected with them, without
accompanying acknowledgment of my <hi rend="italics">great</hi> indebtedness to those who could
liberally tolerate me as a great and an inmate friend, when they knew my
expressed opinions against their occupation.</p>
                <closer><salute>Yours,</salute>
<signed>D. FRANCIS BACON.</signed></closer>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <p>There is a large slave factory or
depot at this place, which is said to belong to the house of Martinez in Havana;
there are also different establishments on different islands. Mr. Bacon stated
that he had seen American, Russian, Spanish, and Portuguese vessels at Gallinas. The American flag, was a complete shelter; no man-of-war daring to capture an American vessel. The slave trade on that part of the coast is the universal business of the country, and by far the most profitable, and all engaged in it who could raise the means. Extensive wars take place in Africa, for obtaining
slaves from the vanquished. Different towns and villages make war upon each
other for this purpose. Some are sold on account of their crimes, others for
debts. The slaves are all brought on to the coast by other blacks,
<pb id="barber22" n="22"/>
and sold at the slave factories, as no white man dare penetrate into the
interior. Some of the blacks who have been educated at Sierra Leone, have been
principal dealers in the slave trade.</p>
        <p>On Friday morning, the District Attorney, according to an arrangement made with
the opposing counsel, read the substance of what Antonio G. Viga, the Spanish
Consul, at Boston, said he should testify in this case, viz: that he (Viga) had
resided in Cuba many years; knew the laws of Cuba; knew of no law in <hi rend="italics">force</hi>, against the introduction of slaves into the island; that on some plantations,
the native language of the Africans was continued for years; that the papers of
the Amistad were genuine. Mr. Janes was then called, who testified that he
called on Viga at New London, and asked him when the slave trade was prohibited,
or made piracy. He replied he thought it was in 1814, but did not know the
penalty.—Here the testimony closed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brainard opened the argument on behalf of the libelants, Lieuts. Gedney and
Meade. He contended that whether the Africans were or were not, the lawful
property of Ruiz and Montez, the Court could not set them free; crime had been
committed on board this Spanish vessel, and this government were bound to
deliver up these persons to Spain, that she may execute her own laws. Whether
they were delivered up to the Spanish authorities, or to the United States
government, his clients had performed meritorious services, for which they were
justly entitled to salvage.—Governor Ellsworth, the counsel in behalf of
Capt. Green, stated that he could not in accordance with the sentiments he
entertained, nor in justice to his client, use the <sic corr="slightest">slighest</sic> efforts either to
have these Africans delivered up to the government of Spain, or to the United
States. But if they were to be delivered up, he must claim part of the
valuation, for salvage for Capt. Green. He contended that his client had
rendered a more valuable and hazardous service than any which Lieut. Gedney and others had rendered, and therefore his right to salvage was paramount to all
others.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cleaveland followed Gov. Ellsworth, in behalf of certain houses in Cuba, who
had been shippers in the Amistad. His arguments were confined to the denial of
any right of salvage to Lieut. Gedney and others. Being in the service and pay
of the United States, they were bound to render assistance without compensation.
Capt. Green, having not in fact saved the vessel and cargo, was not entitled to
salvage, as that should be given for saving, not for the <hi rend="italics">attempt</hi> to save.</p>
        <p>On Friday P. M., Mr. Sedgewick opened the cause in behalf of the Africans, and
was followed on that side by Messrs. Staples and Baldwin. Mr. B. contended that
the Africans being born free, were entitled to their freedom, and that every
person is presumed to be a freeman until the contrary is proved. The libelants
and the United States claim they were slaves, because licenses have been
produced authorizing the transportation of <hi rend="italics"><foreign lang="spa">Ladinos</foreign></hi> from one port in Cuba to
another, a term totally inapplicable to the Amistad captives. It was perfectly
evident from the licenses or permits, that a fraud had been committed upon, or
by, the Spanish authorities. The decree of Spain of 1817, prohibits the slave
trade after 1820, with heavy penalties, and declares all slaves imported from
Africa, after that period, free. These Africans owed no obedience to the Spanish
laws. When taken at Long Island, they were in possession of their just rights,
having the Spaniards Montez and Ruiz in subjection. If not slaves when they set
foot on the soil of New York, they cannot be pronounced slaves now. Mr. B.
contended, that the Africans were not held here for any lawful purpose, that no
human being could be demanded as property, unless specifically named as such by treaty, and no such treaty had been made with Spain. There was no authority in
any officer of any foreign government to enter our limits, and take a person
thence. The government refers all applications for the delivery of criminals to
the authorities of the several States. The interference of the Spanish minister
in this case before the Court, was an insult to the government, and the courts
of justice of this country.</p>
        <p>On Saturday P. M., Gen. Isham, on behalf of Lieuts. Gedney and Meade,
<pb id="barber23" n="23"/>
made the closing argument in the case. In the course of his remarks, he took
occasion to say, that his clients authorized him to say that they would never
receive salvage on <hi rend="italics">human</hi> flesh: all they asked for, was, that if the Court
decided that the vessel, cargo, and slaves, should be restored to the Spaniards,
it should be upon terms that the owners should first pay them a reasonable
compensation for services rendered in preserving their property.</p>
        <p>On Monday A. M., Jan. 13th, Judge Judson gave a review and decision of this
case, which occupied more than an hour in the delivery. The first point his
Honor decided upon, was that respecting jurisdiction. It was necessary in order
that the Court have jurisdiction of this case, that the seizure must have taken
place within the limits of the District of Connecticut, or upon the high seas.
The determination of this point, then rested upon the legal signification of the
words <hi rend="italics">high seas</hi>. It appeared in evidence that the Amistad lay in 3 1/2 fathoms
of water off Culloden Point, 5 or 6 miles from Montauk Point, not less than half
a mile from the shore, and not in any known harbor, bay, river, or port.
Excluding these, the high seas extend to low water mark; consequently, the
Amistad must have been on the high seas. The well known position of Montauk,
adds conclusiveness to the argument, as we all understand that Montauk is a
point of land projecting into the <hi rend="italics">sea</hi>.</p>
        <p>The next points decided by his Honor, were those respecting salvage.
He stated that the services rendered by Lieut. Gedney, were such as justly
entitled him to salvage on the <hi rend="italics">vessel</hi> and <hi rend="italics">goods</hi>. The decree would be, that
the schooner and her effects be delivered up to the Spanish Government,
upon the payment, at a <hi rend="italics">reasonable rate</hi> for saving the property. An appraisement
will be ordered, and one third of that amount will be deemed just and
reasonable. The next question was, can salvage be allowed upon the slaves?
His Honor here stated that he had in the very outset of the case, decided
that the <sic corr="alleged">alledged</sic> slaves could not be sold. There was no law of the United
States nor of the State of Connecticut by which a title can be given under
any decree of this Court. Their value in the District of Connecticut was
not one cent.</p>
        <p>The libel of Messrs. Green and Fordham rested on the claim that they had in
effect taken possession of the vessel. His Honor remarked that the facts proved
would not sustain this claim, and that therefore their libels must be dismissed.
The two great questions still remained to be settled: “Shall these Africans, by
a decree of this Court, be delivered over to the Government of Spain, upon the
demand of her Minister as the property of Don Pedro Montez and Don Jose Ruiz?
But if not, what ultimate disposition shall the Government of the United States
make of them?”</p>
        <p>In Cuba, there are three classes of negroes, <hi rend="italics">Creoles</hi>, those born within the
Spanish dominions: <hi rend="italics"><foreign lang="spa">Ladinos</foreign></hi>, those long domiciliated on the island owing
allegiance to Spain, and <hi rend="italics"><foreign lang="spa">Bozals</foreign></hi>, the name given to those recently from Africa.
The negroes in question are recently from Africa, imported into Cuba in
violation of Spanish laws, and bought as slaves by Montez and Ruiz. The demand
of the Spanish Minister is, that these <foreign lang="spa">Bozals</foreign> shall be given up, that Montez and
Ruiz may have them as their property. In order to justify this demand, and
require our Government to give them up, according to our treaty with Spain, it
is necessary that <hi rend="italics">property</hi> and title should be proved. The whole evidence
offered in support of this claim is a permit or license to transport 54 <hi rend="italics"><foreign lang="spa">Ladinos</foreign></hi>,
to Guanaja. But these negroes are <hi rend="italics"><foreign lang="spa">Bozals</foreign></hi>, not <foreign lang="spa">Ladinos</foreign>. Here then, is the point
upon which this great controversy <hi rend="italics">must</hi> turn. His honor then stated, that he
found as a matter of fact, that in the month of June 1839, the law of Spain,
prohibited under severe penalties the importation into Cuba of negroes from
Africa. <hi rend="italics">These</hi> negroes were imported in violation of that law, and by the same
law of Spain, such negroes are declared free, and of course are not the property
of Spanish
<pb id="barber24" n="24"/>
subjects. With regard to the boy Antonio he being a Creole, born as he believes
in Spain, recognized by the laws of that country as being the property of Ramon
Farrer, a Spanish subject, he should decree a restoration of this slave, under
the treaty of 1795.</p>
        <p>“The question remains, What disposition shall be made of these negroes by the
Government of the United States? There is a law of Congress passed the 3d of
March, 1819, which renders it essential that all such Africans as these shall be
transported under the direction of the President of the United States to
Africa.—I shall put in form a decree of this Court, that these Africans,
excepting Antonio, be delivered to the President of the United States to be
transported to Africa, there to be delivered to the Agent appointed to receive
and conduct them home.”</p>
        <p>The case of the Africans having been appealed by the District Attorney in behalf
of the United States, it came before the Circuit Court held at New Haven, April
29th, 1840, Judge Thompson presiding. The counsel for the Africans objected to
the appeal, as coming from the Executive of the U. S. who had no interest in the
case, and of whom nothing more could be expected than to assist in bringing the
case before the proper tribunal. The arguments of both sides on this point
occupied the whole of the afternoon. On Thursday morning the Judge gave it as
his opinion that the Government have an interest in the case; these Africans are
claimed as the property of Spanish subjects, and Spain demands of this
Government that they shall be delivered over to her in compliance with our
treaty. The Government therefore have a right to conduct the inquiry, and
ascertain the facts. He should not therefore refuse the appeal. The point was a
perplexing one, and if he should decide against it, an appeal could be carried
up to the Supreme Court on this very point, and in case his decision were
reversed, the case would come back for a hearing on the main question, and then
would again be appealed, and thus the final disposal of the case be needlessly
delayed. He therefore chose, as the case would at all events be appealed, to
affirm the decision of Judge Judson <hi rend="italics"><foreign lang="lat">pro forma</foreign></hi>, and leave the whole case to be
decided by the Supreme Court, leaving the case open to the September term of the
Court for the parties to agree on the facts as far as they could, and make out a
case to be referred to <sic corr="the">he</sic> Supreme Court which site at Washington in January,
1841.</p>
        <p>
          <figure id="ill17" entity="barbe24">
            <p>
              <hi rend="italics">Village in Mendi, with Palm trees, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p>[The Africans are now under the daily instruction of a number of young men
connected with Yale College, who are learning them to read the English language,
and teaching them the plain and important truths of Christianity. In this
laudable object, they receive much assistance from James Covey, the Interpreter.
By his aid, and that of John Ferry, a native of the Gissi country, a Mendi and
Gissi vocabulary has been made by Prof. Gibbs, and is published in the 38th vol.
of the American Journal of Science. The above engraving, copied partly from one
in Lander's travels, is recognized by the Africans as giving a correct
representation of the appearance of villages in their native country.]</p>
        <pb id="barber25" n="25"/>
        <p>[As there has been considerable interest felt by many persons in the moral and
religious welfare of tile Africans, it is presumed that the following account
furnished by Mr. Benjamin Griswold, of the Theological Seminary, will prove
interesting. Mr. G. with a number of other young gentlemen connected with Yale
College, have deeply interested themselves in the welfare of these captives.
Being in the habit of daily intercourse with them as teachers, they possess
great facilities in procuring correct information on the subjects here
introduced.]</p>
        <p>The reader of the preceding pages has observed, that the history of the captives
of the Amistad, as given by Mr. Barber, is confined to the circumstances of
their capture, the judicial proceedings relative to them, with short
biographical sketches. Friends of the Africans have expressed a desire that an
article might be added giving an account of the efforts made for their
intellectual and moral improvement, and some notice of the manners and customs
prevalent in their native country.</p>
        <p>Information relative to the Mendi country and people has been obtained from the
captives themselves, mostly through an interpreter; of late, however, they have
been able to converse in English. I rely with confidence upon their statements,
since a long and intimate acquaintance with them and the interpreter justifies
me in saying that I regard them generally as men of integrity.</p>
        <p>The limits of the Mendi country have not yet been defined with much certainty.
Never has it been visited, so far as we know, by a white man. Park's route lay
north; Winterbottom's excursions did not extend far enough into the interior;
the Messrs. Landers passed to the south and east. These Africans tell us that
they never saw a white man in their country. In attempting to tell one of the
teachers how he would be treated if he should return with them—at first they
showed signs of fear, then cautiously returned and presently ventured to touch
his clothes and hands, and soon proceeded to a minute investigation.</p>
        <p>When winter came, they appeared surprised, not so much at the sight of snow, as
at its depth. Inquiry was made if they had ever seen it in their native land.
“Yes,” was the reply, “<hi rend="italics">little, little, little,</hi>” accompanying the word with a sign of the same import, and adding, “<hi rend="italics">water, water, water.</hi>” That is, a very little snow falls, but very soon changes its form to water. This leads us to suppose their country mountainous and probably healthy.</p>
        <p>Their government appears to be despotic, and the power goes down from father to
son by hereditary descent. Each town appears to have a chief of its own.
Attempting once to explain to Cingue the nature of our government, when in
answer to his inquiries I informed him that our “<hi rend="italics">great man</hi>” was not great man
for life, but was elected once in four years, he seemed not a little astonished;
surprise however soon gave way to boisterous laughter at my expense, in which
nearly all his companions joined. The ideas of a democracy, and rotation in
office, seemed to him new, strange, and ridiculous. The king receives his
support from the contributions of his people. At the appearance of each new
moon, they bring their offerings, the rich and the poor according to their
ability.</p>
        <p>The apparel of both sexes is the same—the difference consists in the manner of wearing it. The man throws one end of his blanket (as it may perhaps be
called) <hi rend="italics">over</hi> the left shoulder <hi rend="italics">forward</hi>, the other end is brought around under
the right arm and thrown backward over the same shoulder, leaving the right
shoulder and arm uncovered. The cloth thus used, being three or four feet wide
and two or three yards long, reaches nearly to their feet, and, with the
exception just mentioned, envelopes the whole person. The female makes this same garment fast around the waist, and so leaves
<pb id="barber26" n="26"/>
herself partially unprotected. In youth the dress of both sexes consists merely
of a small piece of cloth like a handkerchief fastened around the waist. In childhood till eight or ten years of age, no clothing is worn. The dress of their “<hi rend="italics">great man</hi>” differs only in this, that his consists of “<hi rend="italics">plenty, plenty</hi>” of cloth.</p>
        <p>Ornaments are much esteemed; the natives adorn themselves with strings of
beads, shells, and the like. These tied around their wrists, arms, and ankles,
produce in their estimation a very pleasant rattling, when they walk or dance.
Many submit to the painful process of tattooing. The breasts and arms of some
of the captives display in every part the incision of the knife; both sexes
practice this custom in Mendi. We inquired the reason, and received for reply,
“<hi rend="italics">to make them proud,</hi>” i. e. to make them beautiful.</p>
        <p>Another custom extensively prevalent on the western coast of Africa is
common to them. No observing person can have visited these men without
noticing the want of one or two front teeth from the upper or under jaw, or
from both. A friend inquired how they were extracted; he was informed
that a knife was inserted between the teeth; thus the one they wished to
extract is loosened and removed. Sometimes two standing adjacent are cut
down so as to leave an opening between them in the form of V, and is done
with great skill. The papers designated one of the captives by the name of
<hi rend="italics">cannibal</hi>. The only reason for this appellation is, that his teeth, according
to our notions, not being very well arranged and a degree of emaciation leaving
him but a skeleton, made him in fact a frightful object. Some of the front teeth
of Konomo have been extracted, others have been sharpened, and made to project from his mouth like tushes. The tooth is pointed thus: a knife is placed upon it on the outside; some hard substance, as a stone or billet of wood, being held
against it on the inner side, the knife then receives a blow, and a part of the
tooth is thus chipped off. This operation continues till the object is
accomplished. This being the manner, he asked the reason. To this question was
replied “<hi rend="italics">to make the ladies love him.</hi>” It is proper to add, that the captives without distinction appear filled with horror of feasting upon human flesh.</p>
        <p>Their food consists of a great variety of vegetables and fruits, as corn,
rice, different kinds of nuts, and flesh furnished by their flocks, herds, and
poultry. Of milk they never taste, nor is it drawn from the cow; when informed
that it was much esteemed and extensively used among us, they appear greatly
amused, and one observed joking, “<hi rend="italics">white</hi> man, little cow, eat milk.” Reptiles, as snakes and frogs, sometimes form a part of their diet. No animals are used as beasts of burden; the traveller journeys on foot, and the trader transports his articles of traffic upon his back.</p>
        <p>Polygamy exists among them. The remark was made by them to one of
their friends that in case he returned with them, he should have ten wives,
expressing thus the honorable station he would probably hold. Matrimonial
matters are managed somewhat after this manner. The gentleman calls
upon the lady that pleases him, and presents her some small gift; if she does
not feel inclined to encourage his attentions, she refuses its acceptance, and
the matter is at an end. But if she receives it, thereby expressing satisfaction
with the giver, she carries it after his departure to her parents; they
hold a consultation, and if they approve, the suitor is made acquainted with
the fact at a subsequent call; then or soon after he makes a present to the
parents, and takes the daughter. In case the parents are dissatisfied, it is
the lady's duty to return the gift, and this closes the negotiation. In Mendi
<pb id="barber27" n="27"/>
the woman is made to feel herself inferior to her husband. Seldom does she eat
at the same time. To use the language of one of the captives, “man come, eat, eat—go; then woman come, eat, eat—go.” Cingue says that his wife eats at the same table and time with himself. The wife attends to the concerns of the house, and sometimes aids her husband in cultivating and often in securing his grain, especially his rice.</p>
        <p>The form of a Mendi dwelling is exhibited in the engraving on the 24th page,
Circular walls, frequently of mud or clay hardened by the sun, roof thatched
with leaves or covered with turf, without windows or chimney. The fire is
kindled in the center, and the smoke finds its way out through the single door
with which each house is provided.</p>
        <p>Their funeral customs resemble much those prevalent among other tribes
in Africa. Soon after a person dies, the body is wrapped in a mat, an
article somewhat like cloth, made from the fibrous bark of a certain tree
that grows in their country; in this, without any coffin, the body is carried
out at evening, within two or three days after the decease, and deposited in
a place set apart for this purpose with the head always lying to the west.
The function is attended with weeping and mourning, so loud that the stillness
attending exercises of this kind among us seems to them surprising, and to be
accounted for only on the ground of insensibility.</p>
        <p>The body deposited in the ground, it lies undisturbed, if that of a man till
the second day; if a woman, till the third. The reason for this difference is
that “<hi rend="italics">man was before the woman.</hi>” Going to the grave often in great numbers,
they remove the earth at the head of the corpse and deposit a vessel filled
with food, prepared for this purpose. In it is first placed boiled rice,
and palm-oil is then poured upon it, again rice and palm-oil, and so on until
the vessel is nearly full. At last the flesh of some animal is added; a spoon
is placed in it; a mat thrown over it, and thus is it conveyed and deposited at
the head of the deceased friend. “Why this?” was asked. “Because the person is hungry,” was replied. “But do you suppose the body will again come to life, and so want the food?” “No, but the spirit is hungry.” “How do you know?” “It
comes and says so if it is not thus provided for.” Often the chief issues his commands, and vast multitudes assemble from the distance of miles even to attend this ceremony. This custom, however, does not prevail in every village.</p>
        <p>This account having been given by some of the captives, others were called
and asked if it was true. One replied such ceremonies were not common where he
lived. The observation was then made, <hi rend="italics">you</hi> say, “<hi rend="italics">yes,</hi>” and <hi rend="italics">you</hi> say “<hi rend="italics">no,</hi>” here is
a contradiction; do you both tell the truth? Fuli after a moment's delay
replied, “<hi rend="italics">Merica all, all, all,</hi>”extending his right hand and turning round through half a circle, “so <hi rend="italics">Mendi, all, all, all,</hi>” accompanying the words with the same gesture
and motion of the body. The idea he wished to convey was this: “America here is a great country, so is Mendi; and because a custom is prevalent in <hi rend="italics">one</hi> part of it, it is not necessary to conclude that it is universal.” The explanation was satisfactory. Nothing has occurred of special interest at the funerals which
have taken place since their arrival in New Haven. It has been said that Shuma
addressed his companions as they were standing around the dead body of Tua. The interpreter informs us that it was merely the remark that “Tua was dead—God
had taken him,”&amp;c. They naturally feel themselves restrained, being among and in the hands of those whose manners and institutions are so entirely unlike their own.</p>
        <pb id="barber28" n="28"/>
        <p>At the funeral of Kaperi, a number of the clergymen from the city were
present. Prayer was offered in the room, and remarks made, the substance of
which was, “Ka-pe-ri is dead. His body is still, will be laid in the ground.
The soul of Ka-pe-ri is alive. It will never die. Our souls will never die.
They will live after our bodies are dead and cold. The Bible tells us how our
souls may go to the good place. You must learn to read the Bible. Pray to
God, become good, and then when your bodies die, God will take your souls to
the good place, and make you happy forever.” To this they listened with
serious attention. Accompanied by a large number of citizens, they then
walked in procession to the grave, when a hymn was read and sung, and a
prayer offered by Mr. Bacon. In all these exercises the captives appeared
interested and solemn.</p>
        <p>The Mendi language, so far as we have been able to learn, has never been
reduced to writing, nor have the natives characters by which they retain and
transmit passing events. Since the captives have been in New Haven, efforts
have been made to improve their minds and hearts, by some gentlemen connected with the theological seminary. From two to five hours each day have been spent in imparting instruction. At first their progress was slow and attended with some difficulties. They had been accustomed neither to the requisite effort of
mind nor fixedness of attention.</p>
        <p>In the first attempts to teach them the English language, the picture of some
animal, as a dog or horse, was presented to them, its name was mentioned, and
they required to repeat it after their teachers; then was added another and
another, their names told in the same way, and repeated till they could
readily distinguish one from the other. Then we showed the names printed
on separate cards in large characters, directing their attention to the
picture at the same time. Very soon we found them able to select and join each
picture to its name. This process was continued for some time before we
attempted to teach them the letters. When they began to read, it became
necessary to explain the meaning of every word. They manifested so deep an
interest, that though progress was slow, yet it was perceptible, and labor
was pleasant. Sometimes they complained because we did not come earlier, and
refused consent to our departure when, at noon or night, it became necessary
for us to leave. Their interest still continues, and never perhaps was
it greater than at the present time. Not unfrequently in their desire
to retain their teacher through the day, they attempt even to hold him,
grasping his hands and clinging to his person, and individuals offer to
give him their own dinner on condition of his remaining. Sometimes they may
be found gathered in two or three groups, all reading and aiding each other.
While the teacher is hearing one class, the interpreter is engaged in the
same duty with another, and one of the most advanced among the captives gives
instruction to another, and thus employed will they sit quietly for hours
in the most patient, persevering effort to learn “<hi rend="italics">Merica.</hi>” Especially do they seem anxious to learn that they may read the Bible—this is the great desire of their hearts.</p>
        <p>Their improvement is as great as could be expected. Some of them can read in
the New Testament. Their situation has been peculiarly unfavorable to progress
in speaking the English language. They have been confined exclusively by
themselves, and intercourse with each has been in their native tongue. Yet they
can converse with one upon any subject with which both have some acquaintance.</p>
        <pb id="barber29" n="29"/>
        <p>One of the most serious obstacles with which we have had to contend is
of the anxiety occasioned by the uncertainty that hangs over them in respect
to the future. They appear much distressed at the idea of going to Havana.</p>
        <p>Especial attention has been given to their moral improvement since they
have been in New Haven. We have sought to make them acquainted with
the truths of Christianity, and though we cannot say that they are
Christians, yet we can say that they have, some of them at least, manifested
a deep interest in the subject of religion.</p>
        <p>The system of religion prevalent in their native country appears to be the
Fetisch. They reverence the cotton tree. The inquiry was made if they
paid their devotions to it because they supposed the <hi rend="italics">tree</hi> could do them good
or evil. The reply was in the negative; but they added that there was a
“spirit in it,” and they worshipped him that “<hi rend="italics">they might be well.</hi>” They regard him however as a good deity. His favor is secured by suspending some offering, a fowl perhaps, to the limb, or placing the same at its roots.</p>
        <p>The mountain too receives their homage. Worship in this instance consists in
praying at its foot, and in depositing a dish of boiled rice or flesh—
something that serves the purposes of food. The spirit dwells on the
mountain. Water too, or the genius of the stream, has a place among their
deities. Respecting the ceremonies of their religion we do not feel confident,
for neither Cingue nor any of his companions can give us any other than
hear-say information. In such services they never took part—they were too
<hi rend="italics">young</hi>; only the <hi rend="italics">aged</hi> perform the duties of religion.</p>
        <p>Their teachers have religious exercises with them daily. In the morning
on their arrival they assemble for prayers—if the room is sufficiently
capacious they kneel. The teacher offers his petitions in English, the
interpreter translates sentence by sentence, and the captives respond in Mendi.
A prayer has been composed and translated into their language, which, in case
of the interpreter's absence, is sometimes read by the teacher and repeated by
them. Of this prayer I give a few of the first sentences. <hi rend="italics"><foreign>O ga-wa-wa</foreign></hi>,
O great God; <hi rend="italics"><foreign>bi-a-bi yan din go</foreign></hi>, thou art good; <hi rend="italics"><foreign>bi-a-bi ha-ni gbe-le ba-te-ni</foreign></hi>,
thou hast made all things; <hi rend="italics"><foreign>bi-a-bi fu-li ba-te-ni</foreign></hi>, &amp;c., thou hast made the
sun, &amp;c. After prayers, sometimes an half hour is spent in attempting
to impress religious truth upon the heart. At this exercise the captives are
attentive and solemn, the season is frequently of great interest. On the
Sabbath we have one, usually two exercises with them. They ever appear
interested in listening to the truths of the word of God. One Sabbath, on
account of the absence of the interpreter, the teacher was obliged to dispense
with the usual exercises; he left, and Cingue assembled his companions and
conducted the service himself. Many of them in their troubles and fears are
driven to the throne of grace. A lady in the family of the jailer informs me
that the little girls even are mindful of their hours for devotion, and that
too when the duty is not pressed upon them by the example of others.</p>
        <p>When listening to an explanation of the nature of an oath, on being informed
that God would visit the man who violated it with his displeasure,
they very naturally inquired, “What will be done to the people of the United
States if they send us back to Havana?”</p>
        <p>For those who have sought to do them good, and have proved themselves
friends, they feel an affection that displays itself in a thousand ways.</p>
        <p>The scene when information was given to them relative to the decision of
the District Court, was publicly noticed at the time. They were assembled and
seated in a commodious room—they knew that their case was pending—
<pb id="barber30" n="30"/>
some of them had been called to testify in court—they were of course deeply
anxious for the event. All being present and quiet, they were informed that
the judge had decree their return, not to Havana, but to their native land.
They leaped from their seats, rushed across the room, threw themselves
prostrate at the feet of those who brought them the glad tidings, while
“<hi rend="italics">thank you, thank you,</hi>” was the expression of every tongue.</p>
        <p>The succeeding day Mr. Baldwin, one of their counsel, entered the jail.
Cingue was seated behind a table, and members of his class on either side
of him . As Mr. B. approached, Cingue was told that he pleaded his cause;
said it would be wrong to send him to Havana. He dropped his book, rose
from his seat, seemed for a moment deliberating whether he should leap the
table. Seeing this to be attended with difficulty, he reached forward, and
seizing the extended hand of Mr. B. with a firm grasp, and looking him in
the face, his own countenance beaming with the most grateful emotion,
exclaimed, “We thank you, we bless you, this is all we can do for you.”</p>
        <p>During the winter, one of the teachers was called from the city. After an
absence of nearly two weeks, on his return he visited the captives, and the
reception he received can never be forgotten by him so long as memory
records one event of the past. The first who met him threw his arms around
his body, and clasped him to his bosom. Freed from his grasp, he was soon
met by others. Some were reading, some on their couches—all rose as soon as his name was announced, left books and beds, and rushing into the room
gathered around, a dense mass, all striving to reach him; some threw their
arms around his body, some around his neck, some seized his arms, some
pressed his hands, and all cried out, “<hi rend="italics">good, good</hi>, Mr.—come, Mr.—
come, good, good.” Their friend laughed and shouted with them, overcome
by this effort to express their joy. Such an outburst of grateful affection we
never witnessed before. After quiet was restored, one observed, “when we
see you, all of us act like children.”</p>
        <p>One of their friends received a message from Cingue requesting him to
call at the jail, for some of their number had been guilty of faults which
ought to be corrected. He went; Cingue said that two of the captives took
liberties which he regarded as stealing; that the rest of them were innocent
and disapproved of their conduct, and that they wished the two put into a room
by themselves. One of the culprits was summoned and questioned; he
confessed his crime, and gave assurances of better conduct, in accordance
with which, so far as I know, he has acted ever since. “O!” exclaimed
Fuli, who was standing by, “I cannot tell how much I hate a thief.” “But why,” said the friend, “would <hi rend="italics">you</hi> refuse to steal?” “Because it is wrong.”
“But suppose you were hungry?” “Then I would beg.” “Suppose no one would give you?” “<hi rend="italics">Then I would die,</hi>” was his decided answer. We know not that we have reason to question his sincerity.</p>
        <p>After the decision of the District Court, previous to the appeal, their
immediate return to Africa was confidently expected by themselves and their
friends. They expressed a very warm desire that some of their teachers
should go with, to instruct them and their people. Said Burna, addressing
one of their friends, and speaking the feelings of many, “If we should be
compelled to return without you, we shall all cry; but if you will go with us
then shall we all laugh.” It was asked how they would treat him. They
replied that they would “give him a house and abundance of food, take the
best care of him, and not let him be sick.” But, said the teacher, though
we go by water to Sierra Leone, from thence we shall be under the necessity
<pb id="barber31" n="31"/>
of making our journey on foot, since no horses go into your country. Now
in case I become wearied, what shall I do? how will you dispose of me?</p>
        <p>For a moment they seemed perplexed. Cingue soon rose from his seat—
called or a blanket—tied the corners of each end together—then putting the broom handle through under the knots—placed one end upon his own shoulder, rested the other upon that of one of his companions, then thrusting
his hand into the blanket, and crying out, “<hi rend="italics">Mr.</hi>—<hi rend="italics">in there, Mr.</hi>—<hi rend="italics">in
there,</hi>” commenced his march. This I doubt not is a faithful expression of
the feeling of their hearts. A friend might trust his safety in their hands
with the most perfect confidence, not doubting that they would sacrifice their
own lives before they would abandon one whom they respected and loved.
“Should I go with you,” said the teacher, “what good could I do you?” “Teach us, our brothers, sisters, and children,” was replied. “But,” said the teacher to test their affection, “if I go I must teach you truth. The Bible says that a man must have but <hi rend="italics">one</hi> wife; will you put away <hi rend="italics">all</hi> but <hi rend="italics">one</hi>?” All said, yes. “Well,” said the teacher, “suppose I accompany you, since you do not reside in the same town what will you do? I cannot go all over your country—with whom shall I live?” This difficulty was very speedily removed, and one replied, “You may go with whom you please. If you should return with Cingue, we would visit our parents a few days, and then remove with our wives and children, brothers and sisters, to your place of
residence, that we might avail ourselves of your instruction.”</p>
        <p>These men deserve sympathy—they ought to have protection. Let me ask
in their behalf, means to carry on their defense; let me ask the prayers of
those who care for them and the perishing millions of Africa, that God will
so order events as to deliver them from the bloody grasp of the executioner,
and that they may return missionaries to their native land to proclaim there
the truth of the everlasting Gospel.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <argument>
          <p>[The following facts relative to the case of the Africans are derived from
Document No. 185, published in accordance with a resolution of Congress,
Passed March 23d, 1840, calling on the President for information, &amp;c.]</p>
        </argument>
        <p>On the 6th of Sept. 1830, Mr. Calderon, the Spanish Minister at New York,
Addressed a letter to the Secretary of State, (Mr. Forsyth,) asking that the
Amistad, her cargo, including the slaves, should be immediately delivered up
without salvage, in accordance with the treaty of 1795. He expresses that
his fears that if the slaves are not delivered up to the Spanish authorities to
be punished for their crimes, it “would endanger the internal tranquillity and
the safety of the Island of Cuba,”&amp;c.—that it would interrupt the good feeling now existing between the people of that island and those of
the United States. Mr. <sic corr="Hollabird">Holabird</sic>, the U. S. District Attorney, in a letter to
Mr. Forsyth, dated Sept. 5, says, “the next term of our Circuit Court sits on
the 17th instant, at which time I suppose it will be my duty to bring them to
trial, unless they are in some other way disposed of.” In a letter dated
Sept. 9, he thus writes, “I would respectfully inquire, sir, whether there are
no treaty stipulations with the government of Spain that would authorize our
government to deliver them up to the Spanish authorities; and if so, whether it
could be done before our Court sits?” The Chevalier de Argaiz (the successor of Mr. Calderon) addressed a letter to Mr. Forsyth, Nov. 26, 1839, in which he complained that the treaty of 1795 had not been executed; that great injury had been done to the owners, “not the least being the imprisonment which Don Jose Ruiz is now undergoing;” that “no indemnification can fully recompense for the evils, physical and moral, which the persecutions and vexations occasioned by fanaticism may cause to an honorable man.” Another letter was addressed by him to the Secretary, Nov. 29, stating that the injuries of which the negroes complain, should be redressed in Cuba, and by “no means” by the Courts of the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Forsyth, in a letter of Jan. 6, 1840, to the Chevalier de Argaiz, states
that the President “will cause the necessary orders to be given for a vessel
of the United States to be held in readiness to receive the negroes and
convoy them to Cuba, with instructions
<pb id="barber32" n="32"/>
to the commander to deliver them up to the Captain General of the island. The
President has the more readily been inclined to accede to your request in
this particular, on account of one of the leading motives which prompted you to
make it; that the negroes, having asserted before the Court of Connecticut that
they are not slaves, may have an opportunity of proving the truth of their
allegation before the proper tribunals of the island of Cuba, by whose laws
alone, taking in connection with circumstances occurring before the arrival of
the negroes in the United States, the question of their condition can be legally
decided.”</p>
        <p>On the 6th of January, 1840, Mr. Forsyth, in a letter to the District Attorney
says, “the President has, agreeable to your suggestion, taken in connection with the request of the Spanish Minister, ordered a vessel to be in readiness to
receive the negroes from the custody of the Marshal as soon as their delivery
shall be ordered by the Court.”</p>
        <p>The following is the warrant of the President for this purpose.</p>
        <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1 type="letter">
                <p>“The Marshal of the United States for the district of Connecticut, will deliver
over to the Lieut. John S. Paine, of the U. S. Navy, and aid in conveying on
board the schooner Grampus, under his command, all the negroes, late of the
schooner Amistad, in his custody, under process now pending before the Circuit
Court of the United States for the District of Connecticut. For so doing, this
order will be his warrant. Given under my hand, at the city of Washington, this
7th day of January, A.D. 1840.</p>
                <closer><signed>M. VAN BUREN.</signed>
By the President: <signed>JOHN FORSYTH,</signed><hi rend="italics"> Secretary of State.</hi>”</closer>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <p>It appears by the following extract of a letter from Mr. <sic corr="Hollabird">Holabird</sic> to Mr.
Forsyth, dated Jan. 11, that there was a mistake in this warrant.</p>
        <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1 type="letter">
                <p>“<hi rend="italics">Sir</hi>—Lieut. Paine has shown me the Executive warrant to the Marshal of this
District for the delivery of the negroes of the Amistad, in which it is stated
that they are now holden in custody under a process from the “<hi rend="italics">Circuit Court;</hi>”
and also, in his instructions, the same term is used. They are not holden under
any order of the Circuit Court, but under an order from the <hi rend="italics">District Court</hi>, and
should have been so stated in the warrant and instructions. Should the pretended
friends of the negroes obtain a writ of <foreign lang="lat">habeas corpus</foreign>, the Marshal could not
justify under that warrant.”</p>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <p>The following is the reply of the Secretary to Mr. <sic corr="Hollabird">Holabird</sic>.</p>
        <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1 type="letter">
                <opener>“[CONFIDENTIAL.]<dateline><date><hi rend="italics">Department of State, Jan.</hi> 12, 1840.</date></dateline></opener>
                <p>Sir—Your letter of the 11th instant has just been received. The order for
the delivery of the negroes of the Amistad is herewith returned, corrected
agreeably to your suggestion. With reference to the inquiry from the Marshal, to
which you allude, I have to state, by direction of the President, that if the
decision of the Court is such as is anticipated, the order of the President is
to be carried into execution, unless an appeal shall actually have been
interposed. You are not to take it for granted that it will be interposed.
And if, on the contrary, the decision of the Court is different, you
are to take out an appeal, and allow things to remain as they are until the
appeal shall have been decided.</p>
                <closer><salute>I am, sir, your obedient servant, </salute><signed>JOHN FORSYTH.</signed>”</closer>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1 type="letter">
                <head>
                  <hi rend="italics">Memorandum from the Department of State to the Secretary of the Navy.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
<dateline>DEPARTMENT OF STATE, Jan. 2, 1840.</dateline></opener>
                <p>“The vessel destined to convey the negroes of the Amistad to Cuba, to be ordered to anchor off the port of New Haven, Connecticut, as early as the 10th of
January next, and be in readiness to receive said negroes from the Marshal of
the United States, and proceed with them to Havana, under instructions to be
hereafter transmitted.</p>
                <p>“Lieutenants Gedney and Meade to be ordered to hold themselves in readiness to
proceed in the same vessel, for the purpose of affording their testimony in
any proceedings that may be ordered by the authorities of Cuba in the matter.</p>
                <p>“Those orders should be given with special instructions that they are not to be communicated to any one.”</p>
                <p>There is in the document from which the foregoing is taken, a letter from
Messrs. Staples and Sedgwick, dated Sept. 13, addressed to the President,
stating the facts of the case, and praying that the Africans may not be given up
to the Spaniards till their claim is substantiated in a court of justice. In
answer, or in consequence of this, there is a letter addressed to Mr. Forsyth,
giving the opinion of the Attorney General, who says, that after a due
consideration of the case, he has come to the conclusion that the Amistad
captives ought to be given up to the Spaniards. This letter has no signature,
nor no date but 1839. In the document, the Spanish passport with a translation
is given: the word “<foreign lang="spa"><hi rend="italics">Ladinos</hi></foreign>” is incorrectly translated “<foreign lang="spa"><hi rend="italics">sound negroes.</hi></foreign>”
(See p. 18.)</p>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>