<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % external-entities SYSTEM "./extEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY % internal-entities SYSTEM "./intEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY freedmtp SYSTEM "freedmtp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY freedmvs SYSTEM "freedmvs.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>THE FREEDMAN'S STORY.</emph>
<emph>IN TWO PARTS:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Parker, William</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Bethany Ronnberg</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by</resp>
          <name>Bethany Ronnberg</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Carlene Hempel  and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1999</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca.  200K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1999.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, 
teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability 
is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note anchored="yes">Call number AP2 .A8 v.17 1866
(Davis Library, UNC-CH)</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>The Atlantic Monthly, vol. 17. </title>
<title>The Freedman's Story. In Two Parts</title>
<author>Parker, William</author><imprint><pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace><publisher>Ticknor and Fields</publisher><date>February and March, 1866</date></imprint></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>The electronic edition is transcribed from <hi rend="italics">The 
Atlantic Monthly</hi>, volume XVII, 
Feb. 1866, pp. 152-166; Mar. 1866, pp. 276-295.</p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and 
‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in 
lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text 
using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st 
edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Parker, William, fl. 1851.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Biography.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Christiana -- History -- 19th
century.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Maryland -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slave insurrections -- Pennsylvania -- Christiana -- History $ y
19th century.</item>
            <item>Kidnapping -- Pennsylvania -- History -- 19th century.</item>
            <item>Fugitive slaves -- Pennsylvania -- Christiana -- History -- 19th
century.</item>
            <item>Christiana (Pa.) -- Race relations.</item>
            <item>Riots -- Pennsylvania -- Christiana -- History -- 19th
century.</item>
            <item>Violence -- Pennsylavania -- Christiana -- History -- 19th
century.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>1999-05-17, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Sam McRae</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-04-28, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-04-23, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Carlene Hempel</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-04-09, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Bethany Ronnberg</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="title page image">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="freedmtp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="title page verso image">
        <p>
          <figure id="verso" entity="freedmvs">
            <p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">THE 
<lb/>
ATLANTIC MONTHLY.</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="main">A MAGAZINE OF
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Literature, Science, Art and Politics.</hi></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <docEdition>VOLUME XVII.</docEdition>
        <docImprint><pubPlace>BOSTON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>TICKNOR AND FIELDS,<lb/>
124 TREMONT STREET.
<lb/>
LONDON: TRÜBNER AND COMPANY.</publisher>
<docDate>1866.</docDate></docImprint>
        <pb id="freedmanverso" n="verso"/>
        <docImprint>Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1866, by
<lb/>
TICKNOR AND FIELDS,
<lb/>
 in the Clerk's Office of the District Court for the District of Massachusetts.
<lb/>
UNIVERSITY PRESS:
<lb/>
ELECTROTYPED BY WELCH, BIGELO, &amp; CO.,
<lb/>
CAMBRIDGE.</docImprint>
      </titlePage>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb id="freedman152" n="152"/>
      <div1 type="narrative">
        <head>THE FREEDMAN'S STORY.</head>
        <head>IN TWO PARTS.</head>
        <div2 type="part one">
          <head>PART I.
<lb/>
[Vol. XVII, February, 1866.]</head>
          <div3 type="introduction">
            <p>The manuscript of the following
pages has been handed to me with
the request that I would revise it for
publication, or weave its facts into a
story which should show the fitness of
the Southern black for the exercise of
the right of suffrage.</p>
            <p>It is written in a fair, legible hand;
its words are correctly spelled; its fact
are clearly stated, and—in most instances
—its sentences are properly constructed.
Therefore it needs no revision.
On reading it over carefully, I
also discover that it is in itself a stronger
argument for the manhood of the
negro than any which could be adduced
by one not himself a freedman; for it
is the argument of facts, and facts are
the most powerful logic. Therefore, if
I were to imbed these facts in the mud
of fiction, I should simply oblige the
reader to dredge for the oyster, which in
this narrative he has without the trouble
of dredging, fresh and juicy as it
came from the hand of Nature,—or
rather, from the hand of one of Nature's
noblemen,—and who, until he
was thirty years of age, had never put
two letters together.</p>
            <p>The narrative is a plain and unpretending
account of the life of a man whose
own right arm—to use his own expression
—won his rights as a free man. It is written
with the utmost simplicity, and has about
it the verisimilitude which belongs to
truth, and to truth only when told by one
who has been a doer of the deeds and an
actor in the scenes which he describes. It
has the further rare merit of being written
by one of the “despised race”; for
none but a negro can fully and correctly
depict negro life and character.</p>
            <p>General Thomas—a Southern man and
a friend of the Southern negro—was once in
conversation with a gentleman
who has attained some reputation
as a delineator of the black man, when a
long, lean, “poor white man,” then a scout
in the Union army, approached the latter,
and, giving his shoulder a familiar slap,
accosted him with,—</p>
            <p>“How are you, ole feller?”</p>
            <p>The gentleman turned about, and
forgetting, in his joy at meeting an old
friend, the presence of this most dignified
of our military men, responded to
the salutation of the scout in an equally
familiar and boisterous manner. General
Thomas “smiled wickedly,” and
quietly remarked,—</p>
            <p>“You seem to know each other.”</p>
            <p>“Know <hi rend="italics">him!</hi>” exclaimed the scout.
“Why, Gin'ral, I ha'n't seed him fur
fourteen year; but I sh'u'd know him,
ef his face war as black as it war one
night when we went ter a nigger shindy
tergether!”</p>
            <p>The gentleman colored up to the roots
of his hair, and stammered out,—</p>
            <p>“That was in my boy days, General,
I when I was sowing my wild oats.”</p>
            <p>“Don't apologize, Sir,” answered the
General, “don't apologize; for I see
that to your youthful habit of going to
negro shindies we owe your truthful
pictures of negro life.”</p>
            <p>And the General was right. Every
man and woman who has essayed to
depict the slave character has miserably
failed, unless inoculated with the genuine
spirit of the negro; and even those
who have succeeded best have done only
moderately well, because they have
not had the negro nature. It is reserved
to some black <sic corr="Shakespeare">Shakspeare</sic> or Dickens
to lay open the wonderful humor,
pathos, poetry, and power which slumber
in the negro's soul, and which now
and then flash out like the fire from a
thunder-cloud.</p>
            <p>I do not mean to say that this black
<pb id="freedman153" n="153"/>
prophet has come in this narrative. He
has not. This man is a doer, not a writer;
though he gives us—particularly in the
second part—touches of Nature, and little
bits of description, which are perfectly
inimitable. The prophet is still to come;
and he <hi rend="italics">will</hi> come. God never gives great
events without great historians; and for
all the patience and valor and heroic
fortitude and self-sacrifice and
long-suffering of the black man in
this war, there will come a singer—and
a black singer who shall set his deeds
to a music that will thrill the nations.</p>
            <p>But I am holding the reader at the
threshold.</p>
            <p>The author of this narrative—of every
line in it—is William Parker. He was an
escaped slave, and the principal actor in
the Christiana riot,—an occurrence which
cost the Government of the United States
fifty thousand dollars, embittered the
relations of two “Sovereign States,”
aroused the North to the danger of the
Fugitive-Slave Law, and, more than any
other event, except the raid of John
Brown, helped to precipitate the two
sections into the mighty conflict which
has just been decided on the battle-field.</p>
            <p>Surely the man who aided towards such
results must be a man, even if his
complexion be that of the ace of spades;
and what he says in relation to the events
in which he was an actor, even if it have
no romantic interest,—which, however, it
has to an eminent degree,—must be an
important contribution to the history of
the time.</p>
            <p>With these few remarks, I submit the
evidence which he gives of the manhood
of his race to that impartial grand-jury,
the American people.</p>
            <closer>
              <signed>E. K.</signed>
            </closer>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="narrative">
            <head>EARLY PLANTATION LIFE.</head>
            <p>I WAS born opposite to Queen Anne, in
Anne Arundel County, in the State of
Maryland, on a plantation called Rowdown.
My master was Major William
Brogdon, one of the wealthy men of that
region. He had two sons,—William, a
doctor, and David, who held some
office at Annapolis, and for some years
was a member of the Legislature.</p>
            <p>My old master died when I was very
young; so I know little about him, except
from statements received from my
fellow-slaves, or casual remarks made
in my hearing from time to time by white
persons. From those I conclude that he
was in no way peculiar, but should be
classed with those slaveholders who are
not remarkable either for the severity or
the indulgence they extend to their people.</p>
            <p>My mother, who was named Louisa
Simms, died when I was very young, and
to my grandmother I am indebted for the
very little kindness I received in my early
childhood; and this kindness could only be
shown me at long intervals, and in a
hurried way, as I shall presently show.</p>
            <p>Like every Southern plantation of
respectable extent and pretensions, our
place had what is called the “Quarter,” or
place where the slaves of both sexes are
lodged and fed. With us the Quarter was
composed of a number of low buildings,
with an additional building for single
people and such of the children as were
either orphans or had parents sold away or
otherwise disposed of. This building was a
hundred feet long by thirty wide, and had a
large fireplace at either end, and small
rooms arranged along the sides. In these
rooms the children were huddled from day
to day, the smaller and weaker subject to
the whims and caprices of the larger and
stronger. The largest children would
always seize upon the warmest and best
places, and say to us who were smaller,
“Stand back, little chap, out of my way”;
and we had to stand back or get a thrashing.</p>
            <p>When my grandmother, who was cook
at the “great house,” came to look after
me, she always brought me a morsel
privately; and at such times I was entirely
free from annoyance by the older ones.
But as she could visit me only once in
twenty-four hours, my juvenile days
enjoyed but little rest from my
domineering superiors in years and
strength.</p>
            <pb id="freedman154" n="154"/>
            <p>When my grandmother would inquire of
the others how her “little boy” was
getting on, they would tell her that I was
doing well, and kindly invite me to the fire
to warm myself. I was afraid to complain
to her of their treatment, as, for so doing,
they would have beaten me, after she had
gone to the “great house” again. I was
thus compelled to submit to their
misrepresentation, as well as to their abuse
and indifference, until I grew older, when,
by fighting first with one and then with
another, I became “too many” for them,
and could have a seat at the fire as well as
the best. This experience of my boyhood
has since been repeated in my manhood.
My rights at the fireplace were won by my
child-fists; my rights as a freeman were,
under God, secured by my own right arm.</p>
            <p>Old master had seventy slaves, mostly
field-hands. My mother was a field-hand.
He finally died; but after that everything
went on as usual for about six years, at the
end of which time the brothers, David and
William, divided the land and slaves.
Then, with many others, including my
brother and uncle, it fell to my lot to go
with Master David, who built a house on
the southeast part of the farm, and called
it Nearo.</p>
            <p>Over the hands at Nearo an overseer
named Robert Brown was placed; but as he
was liked by neither master nor slaves, he
was soon discharged. The following
circumstance led to his dismissal sooner,
perhaps, than it would otherwise have
happened.</p>
            <p>While master was at Annapolis, my
mistress, who was hard to please, fell out
with one of the house-servants, and sent
for Mr. Brown to come and whip her.
When he came, the girl refused to be
whipped, which angered Brown, and he
beat her so badly that she was nearly killed
before she gave up. When Master David
came home, and saw the girl's condition,
he became very angry, and turned Brown
away at once.</p>
            <p>Master David owned a colored man
named Bob Wallace. He was a trusty man;
and as he understood farming
thoroughly, he was installed foreman in
place of Brown. Everything went on very
well for a while under Wallace, and the
slaves were as contented as it is possible
for slaves to be.</p>
            <p>Neither of our young masters would
allow his hands to be beaten or abused, as
many slaveholders would; but every year
they sold one or more of them,—sometimes
as many as six or seven at a time. One
morning word was brought to
the Quarter that we should not work that
day, but go up to the “great house.” As we
were about obeying the summons, a
number of strange white men rode up to
the mansion. They were negro-traders.
Taking alarm, I ran away to the woods
with a boy of about my own age, named
Levi Storax; and there we remained until
the selections for the sale were made, and
the traders drove away. It was a serious
time while they remained. Men, women,
and children, all were crying, and general
confusion prevailed. For years they had
associated together in their rude way,—the
old counselling the young, recounting their
experience, and sympathizing in their
trials; and now, without a word
of warning, and for no fault of their
own, parents and children, husbands
and wives, brothers and sisters, were
separated to meet no more on earth.
A slave sale of this sort is always as
solemn as a funeral, and partakes of its
nature in one important particular,—the
meeting no more in the flesh.</p>
            <p>Levi and I climbed a pine-tree, when we
got to the woods, and had this
conversation together.</p>
            <p>“Le,” I said to him, “our turn will come
next; let us run away, and not be sold like
the rest.”</p>
            <p>“If we can only get clear this time,”
replied Le, “may-be they won't sell us. I
will go to Master William, and ask him
not to do it.”</p>
            <p>“What will you get by going to Master
William?” I asked him. “If we see him,
and ask him not to sell us, he will do as he
pleases. For my part, I think the best
thing is to run away to the Free States.”</p>
            <p>“But,” replied Levi, “see how many
<pb id="freedman155" n="155"/>
start for the Free States, and are brought
back, and sold away down South. We could
not be safe this side of Canada, and we
should freeze to death before we got there.”</p>
            <p>So ended our conversation. I must have
been about ten or eleven years old then;
yet, young as I was, I had heard of Canada
as the land far away in the North, where
the runaway was safe from pursuit; but, to
my imagination, it was a vast and
cheerless waste of ice and snow. So the
reader can readily conceive of the effect
of Levi's remarks. They were a damper
upon our flight for the time being.</p>
            <p>When night came, Levi wanted to go
home and see if they had sold his mother;
but I did not care about going back, as I
had no mother to sell. How desolate I
was! No home, no protector, no mother,
no attachments. As we turned our faces
toward the Quarter,—where we might at
any moment be sold to satisfy a debt or
replenish a failing purse,—I felt myself to
be what I really was, a poor, friendless
slave-boy. Levi was equally sad. His
mother was not sold, but she could afford
him no protection.</p>
            <p>To the question, “Where had we been?”
we answered, “Walking around.” Then
followed inquiries and replies as to who
were sold, who remained, and what
transpired at the sale.</p>
            <p>Said Levi,—</p>
            <p>“Mother, were you sold?”</p>
            <p>“No, child; but a good many were sold;
among them, your Uncles Anthony and
Dennis.”</p>
            <p>I said,—</p>
            <p>“Aunt Ruthy, did they sell Uncle
Sammy?”</p>
            <p>“No, child.”</p>
            <p>“Where, then, is Uncle Sammy?”</p>
            <p>I thought, if I could be with Uncle
Sammy, may-be I would be safe. My Aunt
Rachel, and her two children, Jacob and
Priscilla, were among the sold, who
altogether comprised a large number of
the servants.</p>
            <p>The apologist for slavery at the North,
and the owner of his fellow-man at the
South, have steadily denied that the
separation of families, except for
punishment, was perpetrated by Southern
masters; but my experience of slavery
was, that separation by sale was a part
of the system. Not only was it resorted to
by severe masters, but, as in my own case,
by those generally regarded as mild. No
punishment was so much dreaded by the
refractory slave as selling. The atrocities
known to be committed on plantations in
the Far South, tidings of which reached the
slave's ears in various ways, his utter
helplessness upon the best farms and under
the most humane masters and overseers,
in Maryland and other Northern Slave
States, together with the impression that
the journey was of great extent, and
comfortless even to a slave, all
combined to make a voyage down the
river or down South an era in the life of
the poor slave to which he looked forward
with the most intense and bitter
apprehension and anxiety.</p>
            <p>This slave sale was the first I had ever
seen. The next did not occur until I was
thirteen years old; but every year, during
the interval, one or more poor souls were
disposed of privately.</p>
            <p>Levi, my comrade, was one of those
sold in this interval. Well may the good
John Wesley speak of slavery as the sum
of all villanies; for no resort is too
despicable, no subterfuge too vile, for its
supporters. Is a slave intractable, the most
wicked punishment is not too severe; is he
timid, obedient, attached to his birthplace
and kindred, no lie is so base that it may
not be used to entrap him into a change of
place or of owners. Levi was made the
victim of a stratagem so peculiarly
Southern, and so thoroughly the
outgrowth of an institution which holds
the bodies and souls of men as of no more
account, for all moral purposes, than the
unreasoning brutes, that I cannot refrain
from relating it. He was a likely lad, and,
to all appearance, fully in the confidence
of his master. Prompt and obedient, he
seemed to some of us to enjoy high favor
at the “great house.” One morning he was
told to take a letter to Mr. Henry
<pb id="freedman156" n="156"/>
Hall, an acquaintance of the family; and it
being a part of his usual employment to
bring and carry such missives, off he
started, in blind confidence, to learn at the
end of his journey that he had parted with
parents, friends, and all, to find in Mr.
Hall a new master. Thus, in a moment, his
dearest ties were severed.</p>
            <p>I met him about two months afterwards
at the Cross-Road Meeting-House, on
West River; and, after mutual recognition,
I said to him,—</p>
            <p>“Levi, why don't you come home?”</p>
            <p>“I am at home,” said he; “I was sold by
Master William to Mr. Henry Hall.”</p>
            <p>He then told me about the deception
practised upon him. I thought that a
suitable opportunity to remind him of our
conversation when up the pine-tree, years
before, and said,—</p>
            <p>“You told me, that, if you could escape
the big sale, Master William would not sell
you. Now you see how it was: the big sale
was over, and yet you were sold to a
worse master than you had before. I told
you this would be so. The next time I hear
from you, you will be sold again. Master
Mack will be selling me one of these days,
no doubt; but if he does, he will have to do
it running.”</p>
            <p>Here ended our conversation and our
association, as it was not in our power to
meet afterward.</p>
            <p>The neighbors generally called Master
David, Mack, which was one of his
Christian names; and the slaves called
him Master Mack; so the reader will
understand, that, whenever that name
occurs, Master David is meant.</p>
            <p>After the sale of Levi, I became greatly
attached to Alexander Brown, another
slave. Though not permitted to learn to
read and write, and kept in profound
ignorance of everything, save what
belonged strictly to our plantation duties,
we were not without crude perceptions of
the dignity and independence belonging to
freedom; and often, when out of hearing
of the white people, or certain ones
among our fellow-servants, Alexander and
I would talk the subject over in our simple
way.</p>
            <p>Master Mack had a very likely young
house-servant named Ann. She was
between sixteen and eighteen years old;
every one praised her intelligence and
industry; but these commendable
characteristics did not save her. She was
sold next after Levi. Master told the
foreman, Bob Wallace, to go to
Annapolis, and take Ann with him. When
Wallace told me he was going, I had a
presentiment that the purpose was to sell
the girl, and I told him so; but, man as he
was, he had no fear about it. Wallace and
Ann started for the city on horseback,
and journeyed along pleasantly until
they reached the town and were near the
market-place, when a man came up to
them, took Ann off the horse without
ceremony, and put her into jail.
Wallace, not suspecting the manœuvre,
attacked the man, and came well-nigh
getting into difficulty. When Wallace
returned, he said to Master Mack, “Why
did you not tell me that Ann was sold, and
not have me fighting for her? They might
have put me in jail.” But his master did
not appear to hear him.</p>
            <p>Poor Uncle Henry followed Ann. His
wife lived in Annapolis, and belonged to a
Mr. George McNear, residing there. Uncle
Henry went one Saturday night to see her,
when Master William put him into jail for
sale; and that was the last we saw or heard
of him.</p>
            <p>Alex Brown's mother followed next.
After the poor woman was gone, I said to
Alex,—</p>
            <p>“Now that your mother has been sold,
it is time that you and I studied out a plan
to run away and be free.”</p>
            <p>But so thoroughly had his humanity
been crushed by the foul spirit of
Slavery, so apathetic had he—though in
the vigor of youth—become from long
oppression, that he would not agree to
my suggestion.</p>
            <p>“No,” he said, “'t is no use for you and
I to run away. It is too far to the Free
States. We could not get there. They
would take us up and sell us; so we had
better not go. Master Mack can't sell
any more of his hands; there are no more
than can carry on his farm.”</p>
            <pb id="freedman157" n="157"/>
            <p>“Very well,” said I, “trust to that, and
you will see what will come of it.”</p>
            <p>After that I said no more to him,
but determined to be free. My brother
Charles was of like mind; but we kept our
thoughts to ourselves. How old I was then I
do not know; but from what the neighbors
told me, I must have been about seventeen.
Slaveholders are particular to keep the
pedigree and age of favorite horses and dogs,
but are quite indifferent about the age of
their servants, until they want to purchase.
Then they are careful to select young
persons, though not one in twenty can tell
year, month, or day. Speaking of births,—it is
the time of “corn-planting,” “corn-husking,”
“Christmas,” “New Year,” “Easter,” “the Fourth
of July,” or some similar indefinite date. My
own time of birth was no more exact; so that to
this day I am uncertain how old I am.</p>
            <p>About the time of the conversation last
narrated, Jefferson Dorsey, a planter near by,
had a butchering. One of Dorsey's men met
me, and said that they wanted more help,
and that Master Mack said I might go and
lend a hand. Thinking that he spoke truth, I
did not ask permission, but went, and stayed
until noon. I soon learned, however, that the
man had deceived me.</p>
            <p>Master Mack, when told by some of
the people where I was, sent my brother
John after me, with the threat of a
whipping. On reaching home, the women
also told me that master would almost
kill me. This excited me greatly, and I replied,—</p>
            <p>“Master Mack is 'most done whipping
me.”</p>
            <p>When I went in to see him, I saw
plainly enough that his face foretold a
storm.</p>
            <p>“Boy,” said he, “yoke up the oxen, and
haul a load of wood.”</p>
            <p>I went at once, and did the task;
but, to my dismay, there he stood at
the stable. I had to drive near to him;
and as he evidently intended to catch
me, I was all vigilance.</p>
            <p>“When you unload that wood, come
to me, Sir,” he said.</p>
            <p>I made no reply, but unloaded the wood,
left the oxen standing, and stole away to
Dorsey's, where I staid until the next day.
Then I prevailed upon Samuel Dorsey to
go home with me. Master Mack told me to
go to my work, and he would forgive me;
but the next time he would pay me for
“the new and the old.” To work I went; but
I determined not to be paid for “the new
and the old.”</p>
            <p>This all occurred in the month of May.
Everything went on well until June; when
the long-sought-for opportunity presented
itself. I had been making preparations to
leave ever since Master Mack had
threatened me; yet I did not like to go
without first having a difficulty with him.
Much as I disliked my condition, I was
ignorant enough to think that something
besides the fact that I was a slave was
necessary to exonerate me from blame
in running away. A cross word, a blow, a
good fright, anything, would do, it
mattered not whence nor how it came. I
told my brother Charles, who shared my
confidence, to be ready; for the time was at
hand when we should leave Old Maryland
forever. I was only waiting for the first
crooked word from my master.</p>
            <p>A few days afterwards all hands were
ordered to the fields to work; but I stayed
behind, lurking about the house. I was tired
of working without pay. Master Mack saw
me, and wanted to know why I did not go
out. I answered, that it was raining, that I
was tired, and did not want to work. He
then picked up a stick used for an ox-gad,
and said, if I did not go to work, he would
whip me as sure as there was a God in
heaven. Then he struck at me; but I
caught the stick, and we grappled, and
handled each other roughly for a time,
when be called for assistance. He was badly
hurt. I let go my hold, bade him good-bye,
and ran for the woods. As I went by the
field, I beckoned to my brother, who left
work, and joined me at a rapid pace.</p>
            <p>I was now at the beginning of a now and
important era in my life. Although
<pb id="freedman158" n="158"/>
upon the threshold of manhood, I had,
until the relation with my master was
sundered, only dim perceptions of the
responsibilities of a more independent
position. I longed to cast off the chains of
servitude, because they chafed my free
spirit, and because I had a notion that my
position was founded in injustice; but it
has only been since a struggle of many
years, and, indeed, since I settled upon
British soil, that I have realized fully the
grandeur of my position as a free man.</p>
            <p>One fact, when I was a slave, often
filled me with indignation. There were
many poor white lads of about my own
age, belonging to families scattered
around, who were as poor in personal
effects as we were; and yet, though our
companions, (when we chose to tolerate
them,) they did not have to be controlled
by a master, to go and come at his
command, to be sold for his debts, or
whenever he wanted extra pocket-money.
The preachers of a slave-trading gospel
frequently told us, in their sermons, that
we should be “good boys,” and not break
into master's hen-roost, nor steal his bacon;
but they never told this to these poor
white people, although they knew very
well that they encouraged the slaves to
steal, trafficked in stolen goods, and stole
themselves.</p>
            <p>Why this difference? I felt I was the
equal of these poor whites, and naturally I
concluded that we were greatly wronged,
and that all this talk about obedience,
duty, humility, and honesty was, in the
phrase of my companions, “all gammon.”</p>
            <p>But I was now on the high-road to
liberty. I had broken the bonds that held
me so firmly; and now, instead of fears of
recapture, that before had haunted my
imagination whenever I thought of
running away, I felt as light as a feather,
and seemed to be helped onward by an
irresistible force.</p>
            <p>Some time before this, I had been able,
through the instrumentality of a friend, to
procure a pass, for which I paid five
dollars,—all the money I had saved in a
long time; but as my brother
determined to go with me, and as we
could not both use it safely, I destroyed
it.</p>
            <p>On the day I ceased working for
master, after gaining the woods, we
lurked about and discussed our plans
until after dark. Then we stole back
to the Quarter, made up our bundles,
bade some of our friends farewell, and
at about nine o'clock of the night set
out for Baltimore. How shall I describe
my first experience of free life? Nothing
can be greater than the contrast it
affords to a plantation experience, under
the suspicious and vigilant eye of a
mercenary overseer or a watchful master.
Day and night are not more unlike. The
mandates of Slavery are like leaden sounds,
sinking with dead weight into the very soul,
only to deaden and destroy. The impulse of
freedom lends wings to the feet, buoys up
the spirit within, and the fugitive catches
glorious glimpses of light through rifts and
seams in the accumulated ignorance of
his years of oppression. How briskly
we travelled on that eventful night and
the next day!</p>
            <p>We reached Baltimore on the following
evening, between seven and eight
o'clock. When we neared the city, the
patrols were out, and the difficulty was
to pass them unseen or unsuspected. I
learned of a brick-yard at the entrance
to the city; and thither we went at
once, took brick-dust and threw it upon
our clothes, hats, and boots, and
then walked on. Whenever we met a
passer-by, we would brush off some of
the dust, and say aloud, “Boss gave
us such big tasks, we would leave him.
We ought to have been in a long time
before.” By this ruse we reached quiet
quarters without arrest or suspicion.</p>
            <p>We remained in Baltimore a week,
and then set out for Pennsylvania.</p>
            <p>We started with the brightest visions
of future independence; but soon they
were suddenly dimmed by one of those
unpleasant incidents which annoy the
fugitive at every step of his onward
journey.</p>
            <p>The first place at which we stopped
to rest was a village on the old York
<pb id="freedman159" n="159"/>
road, called New Market. There nothing
occurred to cause us alarm; so, after
taking some refreshments, we proceeded
towards York; but when near
Logansville, we were interrupted by three
white men, one of whom, a very large
man, cried,—</p>
            <p>“Hallo!”</p>
            <p>I answered,—</p>
            <p>“Hallo to you!”</p>
            <p>“Which way are you travelling?” he
asked.</p>
            <p>We replied,—</p>
            <p>“To Little York.”</p>
            <p>“Why are you travelling so late?”</p>
            <p>“We are not later than you are,” I
answered.</p>
            <p>“Your business must be of
consequence,” he said.</p>
            <p>“It is. We want to go to York to
attend to it; and if you have any
business, please attend to it, and don't be
meddling with ours on the public
highway. We have no business with you,
and I am sure you have none with us.”</p>
            <p>“See here!” said he; “you are the
fellows that this advertisement calls for,”
at the same time taking the paper out of
his pocket, and reading it to us.</p>
            <p>Sure enough, there we were, described
exactly. He came closely to us, and said,—</p>
            <p>“You must go back.”</p>
            <p>I replied,—</p>
            <p>“If I must, I must, and you must take
me.”</p>
            <p>“Oh, you need not make any big talk
about it,’ he answered; “for I have taken
back many a runaway, and I can take
you. What's that you have in your
hand?’</p>
            <p>“A stick.’</p>
            <p>He put his hand into his pocket, as if
to draw a pistol, and said,—</p>
            <p>“Come! give up your weapons.”</p>
            <p>I said again,—</p>
            <p>“'T is only a stick.’</p>
            <p>He then reached for it, when I stepped
back and struck him a heavy blow on the
arm. It fell as if broken; I think it was.
Then he turned and ran, and I after him.
As he ran, he would look back over his
shoulder, see me coming, and then run
faster, and halloo with all his might. I
could not catch him, and it seemed, that,
the longer he ran, the faster he went.
The other two took to their heels at the
first alarm,—thus illustrating the valor
of the chivalry!</p>
            <p>At last I gave up the chase. The whole
neighborhood by that time was aroused,
and we thought best to retrace our steps to
the place whence we started. Then we
took a roundabout course until we reached
the railroad, along which we travelled. For
a long distance there was unusual stir and
commotion. Every house was lighted up;
and we heard people talking and horses
galloping this way and that way, with
other evidences of unusual excitement.
This was between one and two o'clock in
the morning. We walked on a long
distance before we lost the sounds; but
about four o'clock the same morning,
entered York, where we remained during
the day.</p>
            <p>Once in York, we thought we should be
safe, but were mistaken. A similar mistake
is often made by fugitives. Not
accustomed to travelling, and
unacquainted with the facilities for
communication, they think that a few
hours' walk is a long journey, and foolishly
suppose, that, if they have few opportunities
of knowledge, their masters can have
none at all at such great distances. But
our ideas of security were materially lessened
when we met with a friend during the day,
who advised us to proceed farther, as we
were not out of imminent danger.</p>
            <p>According to this advice we started that
night for Columbia. Going along in the
dark, we heard persons following. We went
very near to the fence, that they might
pass without observing us. There were two,
apparently in earnest conversation. The
one who spoke so as to be distinctly heard
we discovered to be Master Mack's
brother-in-law. He remarked to his companion
that they must hurry and get to the bridge before
we crossed. He knew that we had not gone
over yet. We were then near enough to
have killed them, concealed as we were
by the
<pb id="freedman160" n="160"/>
darkness; but we permitted them to
pass unmolested, and went on to
Wrightsville that night.</p>
            <p>The next morning we arrived at
Columbia before it was light, and
fortunately without crossing the bridge,
for we were taken over in a boat. At
Wrightsville we met a woman with whom
we were before acquainted, and our
meeting was very gratifying, We there
inclined to halt for a time.</p>
            <p>I was not used to living in town, and
preferred a home in the country; so to
the country we decided to go. After
resting for four days, we started towards
Lancaster to try to procure work. I got a
place about five miles from Lancaster,
and then set to work in earnest.</p>
            <p>While a slave, I was, as it were, groping
in the dark, no ray of light penetrating
the intense gloom surrounding me. My
scanty garments felt too tight for me, my
very respiration seemed to be restrained
by some supernatural power. Now, free as
I supposed, I felt like a bird on a pleasant
May morning. Instead of the darkness of
slavery, my eyes were almost blinded by
the light of freedom.</p>
            <p>Those were memorable days, and yet
much of this was boyish fancy. After a
few years of life in a Free State, the
enthusiasm of the lad materially sobered
down, and I found, by bitter experience,
that to preserve my stolen liberty I must
pay, unremittingly, an almost sleepless
vigilance; yet to this day I have never
looked back regretfully to Old Maryland,
nor yearned for her flesh-pots.</p>
            <p>I have said I engaged to work; I hired
my services for three months for the
round sum of three dollars per month. I
thought this an immense sum. Fast work
was no trouble to me; for when the work
was done, the money was mine. That was
a great consideration. I could go out on
Saturdays and Sundays, and home when I
pleased, without being whipped. I thought
of my fellow-servants left behind, bound
in the chains of slavery,—and I was free! I
thought, that, if I had the power, they
should soon be as free as I was; and I
formed a resolution that I would assist
in liberating every one within my reach
at the risk of my life, and that I would
devise some plan for their entire liberation.</p>
            <p>My brother went about fifteen miles
farther on, and also got employment. I
“put in” three months with my employer,
“lifted” my wages, and then went to visit
my brother. He lived in Bart Township,
near Smyrna; and after my visit was over,
I engaged to work for a Dr. Dengy, living
near by. I remained with him thirteen
months. I never have been better treated
than by the Doctor; I liked him and the
family, and they seemed to think well of
me.</p>
            <p>While living with Dr. Dengy, I had, for
the first time, the great privilege of seeing
that true friend of the slave, William
Lloyd Garrison, who came into the
neighborhood, accompanied by Frederick
Douglass. They were holding anti-slavery
meetings. I shall never forget the impression
that Garrison's glowing words made upon
me. I had formerly known Mr. Douglass as
a slave in Maryland; I was therefore not
prepared for the progress he then showed,
neither for his free-spoken and manly
language against slavery. I listened with
the intense satisfaction that only a refugee
could feel, when hearing, embodied in earnest,
well-chosen, and strong speech, his own crude
ideas of freedom, and his own hearty censure
of the man-stealer. I believed, I knew, every word
he said was true. It was the whole truth,—nothing
kept back,—no trifling with human rights, no trading
in the blood of the slave extenuated, nothing
against the slaveholder said in malice. I have
never listened to words from the lips of mortal
man which were more acceptable to me; and
although privileged since then to hear many able
and good men speak on slavery, no doctrine has
seemed to me so pure, so unworldly, as his.
I may here say, and without offence, I trust, that,
since that time, I have had a long experience of
Garrisonian Abolitionists, and have always
<pb id="freedman161" n="161"/>
found them men and women with hearts
in their bodies. They are, indeed and
in truth, the poor slave's friend. To shelter
him, to feed and clothe him, to help him
on to freedom, I have ever found them
ready; and I should be wanting in gratitude,
if I neglected this opportunity—the only
one I may ever have—to say thus much of
them, and to declare for myself and for the
many colored men in this free country whom I
know they have aided in their journey to
freedom, our humble confidence in them.
Yes, the good spirit with which he is
imbued constrained William Lloyd
Garrison to plead for the dumb; and for
his earnest pleadings all these years, I say,
God bless him! By agitation, by example,
by suffering, men and women of like spirit
have been led to adopt his views, as the
great necessity, and to carry them out
into actions. They, too, have my heartfelt
gratitude. They, like Gideon's band,
though few, will yet rout the enemy
Slavery, make him flee his own camp, and
eventually fall upon his own sword.<ref targOrder="U" id="ref1" n="1" rend="sc" target="note1">*</ref></p>
            <p>One day, while living at Dr. Dengy's, I
was working in the barn-yard, when a
man came to the fence, and, looking at
me intently, went away. The Doctor's
son, observing him, said,—</p>
            <p>“Parker, that man, from his movements,
must be a slaveholder or kidnapper.
This is the second time he has been
looking at you. If not a kidnapper, why
does he look so steadily at you and
not tell his errand?”</p>
            <p>I said,—</p>
            <p>“The man must be a fool! If he should
come back and not say anything to me, I
shall say something to him.”</p>
            <p>We then looked down the road and saw
him coming again. He rode up to the
same place and halted. I then went to the
fence, and, looking him steadily in the
eye, said,—</p>
            <p>“Am I your slave?”</p>
            <p>He made no reply, but turned his horse
and rode off, at full speed, towards
the valley. We did not see him again; but
that same evening word was brought that
kidnappers were in the valley, and if we
were not careful, they would “hook”
some of us. This caused a great excitement
among the colored people of the
neighborhood.</p>
            <p>A short while prior to this, a number of
us had formed an organization for mutual
protection against slaveholders and
kidnappers, and had resolved to prevent
any of our brethren being taken back into
slavery, at the risk of our own lives. We
collected together that evening, and went
down to the valley; but the kidnappers had
gone. We watched for them several nights
in succession, without result; for so much
alarmed were the tavern-keepers by our
demonstration, that they refused to let
them stop over night with them. Kidnapping
was so common, while I lived with the
Doctor, that we were kept in constant fear.
We would hear of slaveholders or kidnappers
every two or three weeks; sometimes a party
of white men would break into a house and take a
man away, no one knew where; and, again,
a whole family would be carried off. There
was no power to protect them, nor prevent it.
So completely roused were my feelings, that
I vowed to let no slaveholder take back a fugitive,
if I could but get my eye on him.</p>
            <p>One day word was sent to me that slaveholders
had taken William Dorsey, and had put him
into Lancaster jail to await a trial. Dorsey had
a wife and three or four children; but what was
it to the slaveholder, if the wife and children
should starve? We consulted together, as to
what course to take to deliver him; but no plan
that was proposed could be worked. At last
we separated, determining to get him away
some way or other on the day of trial. His
case caused great excitement. We attended
the trial, and eagerly watched all the movements
from an outside position, and had a man to
tell us how proceedings were going on within.
He finally came out and said that the case
would go against Dorsey. We then formed in
a column at the court-house
<note id="note1" n="1" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref1"><p>* This sentence was written before the beginning of our civil war. Viewed in the light of subsequent events, it is somewhat remarkable.— E.K.</p></note>
<pb id="freedman162" n="162"/>
door, and when the slaveholders and
Dorsey came out, we walked close to
them,—behind and around them,—trying to
separate them from him. Before we had
gone far towards the jail, a slaveholder
drew a pistol on Williams Hopkins, one of
our party. Hopkins defied him to shoot;
but he did not. Then the slaveholder drew
the pistol on me, saying, he would blow
my black brains out, if I did not go away. I
doubled my fists to knock him down, but
some person behind caught my hand; this
started a fracas, and we got Dorsey loose;
but he was so confused that he stood stock
still, until they tied him again. A general
fight followed. Bricks, stones, and sticks
fell in showers. We fought across the road
and back again, and I thought our brains
would be knocked out; when the whites,
who were too numerous for us,
commenced making arrests. They got me
fast several times, but I succeeded in
getting away. One of our men was
arrested, and afterwards stood trial; but
they did not convict him. Dorsey was put
into jail, but was afterwards bought and
liberated by friends.</p>
            <p>My friends now said that I had got
myself into a bad difficulty, and that my
arrest would follow. In this they were
mistaken. I never was disturbed because of
it, nor was the house at which I lodged
ever searched, although the neighbors
were repeatedly annoyed in that way. I
distinctly remember that this was the
second time that resistance had been made
to their wicked deeds. Whether the
kidnappers were clothed with legal
authority or not, I did not care to inquire,
as I never had faith in nor respect for the
Fugitive-Slave Law.</p>
            <p>The whites of that region were
generally such negro-haters, that it was a
matter of no moment to them where
fugitives were carried,—whether to
Lancaster, Harrisburg, or elsewhere.</p>
            <p>The insolent and overbearing conduct
of the Southerners, when on such errands
to Pennsylvania, forced me to my course
of action. They did not hesitate to break
open doors, and to enter, without
ceremony, the houses of colored
men; and when refused admission, or
when a manly and determined spirit was
shown, they would present pistols, an
strike and knock down men and women
indiscriminately.</p>
            <p>I was sitting one evening in a friend's
house, conversing about these marauding
parties, when I remarked to him that a stop
should be put to such “didos,” and
declared, that, the next time a slaveholder
came to a house where I was, I would
refuse to admit him. His wife replied, “It
will make a fuss.” I told her, “It is time a
fuss was made.” She insisted that it would
cause trouble and it was best to let them
alone and have peace. Then I told her we
must have trouble before we could have
peace “The first slaveholder that draws a
pistol on me I shall knock down.”</p>
            <p>We were interrupted, just at this stage
of the conversation, by some one rapping
at the door.</p>
            <p>“Who's there?” I asked.</p>
            <p>“It's me! Who do you think? Open the
door!” was the response, in a gruff tone.</p>
            <p>“What do you want?” I asked.</p>
            <p>Without replying, the man opened the
door and came in, followed by two others.</p>
            <p>The first one said,—</p>
            <p>“Have you any niggers here?”</p>
            <p>“What have we to do with your niggers?”
said I.</p>
            <p>After bandying a few words, he drew his
pistol upon me. Before he could bring the
weapon to bear, I seized a pair of heavy
tongs, and struck him a violent blow
across the face and neck, which knocked
him down. He lay for a few minutes
senseless, but afterwards rose, and walked
out of the house without a word, followed
by his comrades, who also said nothing to
us, but merely asked their leader, as they
went out, if he was hurt.</p>
            <p>The part of Lancaster County in which
I lived was near Chester County. Not far
away, in the latter county, lived Moses
Whitson, a well-known Abolitionist, and a
member of the Society of Friends. Mr.
Whitson had a colored girl living in his
family, who
<pb id="freedman163" n="163"/>
was pounced upon by the slaveholders,
awhile after the Dorsey arrest. About
daylight three men went to Mr.
Whitson's house and told him that the
girl he had living with him was their
property, and that they intended to have
her. Friend Whitson asked the girl if she
knew any of the men, and if any of
them was her master. She said, “No!” One
of the slaveholders said he could prove
that she was his property; and
then they forcibly tied her, put her into a
carriage, and started for Maryland.</p>
            <p>While the kidnappers were contending
with Moses Whitson for the girl,
Benjamin Whipper, a colored man, who
now lives in this country, sounded the
alarm, that “the kidnappers were at
Whitson's, and were taking away his girl.”
The news soon reached me, and with six
or seven others, I followed them. We
proceeded with all speed to a place called
the Gap-Hill, where we overtook them,
and took the girl away. Then we beat the
kidnappers, and let them go. We learned
afterwards that they were all wounded
badly, and that two of them died in
Lancaster, and the other did not get
home for some time. Only one of our
men was hurt, and he had only a slight
injury in the hand.</p>
            <p>Dr. Duffield and Squire Henderson, two
respectable citizens of the town, were
looking on during this entire engagement;
and after we had stopped firing, they
went up to the slaveholders, and the
following conversation took place:—</p>
            <p><hi rend="italics">Squire Henderson</hi>. What's the matter?</p>
            <p><hi rend="italics">Slaveholder</hi>. You may ask, what's the
matter! Is this the way you allow your
niggers to do?</p>
            <p><hi rend="italics">Squire</hi>. Why did you not shoot them?</p>
            <p><hi rend="italics">Slaveholder</hi>. We did shoot at them, but
it did not take effect.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italics">Squire</hi>. There's no use shooting at our
niggers, for their heads are like iron pots;
the balls will glance off. What were you
doing?</p>
            <p><hi rend="italics">Slaveholder</hi>. Taking our property,
when the niggers jumped on us and
nearly killed some of the men.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italics">Squire</hi>. Men coming after such
property ought to be killed.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italics">Slaveholder</hi>. Do you know where we
can find a doctor?</p>
            <p><hi rend="italics">Squire</hi>. Yes; there are plenty of doctors
South.</p>
            <p>Being much disabled, and becoming
enraged, they abruptly left, and journeyed
on until they reached McKenzie's tavern,
where their wounds were dressed and their
wants attended to. So strongly was
McKenzie in sympathy with these
demons, that he declared he would never
employ another nigger, and actually
discharged a faithful colored woman who
had lived a long time in his employ. Dr.
Lemmon, a physician on the road to
Lancaster, refused to attend the
slaveholders; so that by the time they got
to the city, from being so long without
surgical aid, their limbs were past setting,
and two of them died, as before stated,
while the other survived but a short time
after reaching Maryland.</p>
            <p>A large reward was offered by the
Maryland authorities for the
perpetrators of the flogging, but without
effect.</p>
            <p>McKenzie, the tavern-keeper referred
to, boasted after this that he would
entertain all slaveholders who came along,
and help them recapture their slaves. We
were equally determined he should not, if
we could prevent it.</p>
            <p>The following affliction was eventually
the means, under Providence, by which he
was led to adopt other views, and become
a practical Abolitionist.</p>
            <p>A band of five men stood off, one dark
night, and saw with evident satisfaction
the curling flames ascend above his barn,
from girder to roof, and lap and lash their
angry tongues in wild license, until every
vestige of the building was consumed.</p>
            <p>After that mysterious occurrence, the
poor fugitive had no better friend than the
publican McKenzie.</p>
            <p>Shortly after the incidents just related, I
was married to Eliza Ann Elizabeth
Howard, a fugitive, whose experience of
slavery had been much more bitter than
my own. We commenced housekeeping,
renting a room from Enoch
<pb id="freedman164" n="164"/>
Johnson for one month. We did not like
our landlord, and when the time was up
left, and rented a house of Isaac Walker
for one year. After the year was out, we
left Walker's and went to Smyrna, and
there I rented a house from Samuel D.
Moore for another year. After the year
was out we left Smyrna also, and went to
Joseph Moore's to live. We lived on his
place about five years. While we were
living there, several kidnappers came into
the neighborhood. On one occasion, they
took a colored man and started for
Maryland. Seven of us set out in pursuit,
and, soon getting on their track, followed
them to a tavern on the Westchester
road, in Chester County. Learning that
they were to remain for the night, I went
to the door and asked for admittance. The
landlord demanded to know if we were
white or colored. I told him colored. He
then told us to be gone, or he would blow
out our brains. We walked aside a little
distance, and consulted about what we
should do. Our men seemed to dread the
undertaking; but I told them we could
overcome them, and that I would go in.
One of them said he would follow at the
risk of his life. The other five said we
should all get killed,—that we were men
with families,—that our wives and children
needed our assistance,—and that they did
not think we would be doing our families
justice by risking our lives for one man.
We two then went back to the tavern,
and, after rapping, were told again by the
landlord to clear out, after he found that
we were colored. I pretended that we
wanted something to drink. He put his
head out of the window, and threatened
again to shoot us; when my comrade
raised his gun and would have shot him
down, had I not caught his arm and
persuaded him not to fire. I told the
landlord that we wanted to come in and
intended to come in. Then I went to the
yard, got a piece of scantling, took it to
the door, and, by battering with it a short
time, opened it. As soon as the door flew
open, a kidnapper shot at us, and the ball
lodged in my ankle, bringing
me to the ground. But I soon rose, and my
comrade then firing on them, they took
to their heels. As they ran away, I heard
one say, “We have killed one of them.”</p>
            <p>My companion and I then rushed into
the house. We unbound the man, took him
out, and started for home; but had hardly
crossed the door-sill before people from
the neighboring houses began to fire on us.
At this juncture, our other five came up,
and we all returned the compliment. Firing
on both sides was kept up for ten or
fifteen minutes, when the whites called
for quarter, and offered to withdraw, if we
would stop firing. On this assurance we
started off with the man, and reached
home safely.</p>
            <p>The next day my ankle was very
painful. With a knife I extracted the ball,
but kept the wound secret; as long before
we had learned that for our own security it
was best not to let such things be generally
known.</p>
            <p>About ten o'clock of a Sabbath night,
awhile after the event last narrated, we
were aroused by the cry of “Kidnappers!
kidnappers!” and immediately some one
halloed under my window,—</p>
            <p>“William! William!”</p>
            <p>I put my head out and demanded his
errand. He said,—</p>
            <p>“Come here!”</p>
            <p>I answered,—</p>
            <p>“You must be a fool to think I am
going to you at this time of the night,
without knowing who you are and what
you want.”</p>
            <p>He would not satisfy me, so I took my
gun, and went out to him. I was then
informed that kidnappers had been at
Allen Williams's; that they had taken
Henry Williams, and gone towards
Maryland. I called one of our party, who
dressed and proceeded to arouse our men.
Two of us then started for the Nine
Points, in Lancaster County, and left
instructions for the other men to meet us
in the valley. They did so, and we hurried
on to our destination. We had not gone
far before we heard some one calling,
“Kidnappers! kidnappers!” Going back
some distance, we
<pb id="freedman165" n="165"/>
found the cry came from a man who had
fallen into a lime quarry. He was in a bad
situation, and unable to get out without
assistance, and, hearing us pass,
concluded we were kidnappers and raised
the cry. We were delayed for a time in
helping him out, and it provoked me very
much, as it was important we should be in
haste.</p>
            <p>We started again for the Nine Points,
but, arriving there, learned to our dismay,
that the kidnappers had passed an hour
before. The chase was given up, but with
saddened feelings. A fellow-being had
been dragged into hopeless bondage, and
we, his comrades, held our liberty as
insecurely as he had done but a few short
hours before! We asked ourselves the
question, “Whose turn will come next,” I
was delegated to find out, if possible, who
had betrayed him, which I accordingly
did.</p>
            <p>Lynch law is a code familiar to the
colored people of the Slave States. It is
of so diabolical a character as to be
without justification, except when
enforced by men of pure motives, and
then only in extreme cases, as when the
unpunished party has it in his power to
barter away the lives and liberties of those
whose confidence he possesses, and who
would, by bringing him before a legal
tribunal, expose themselves to the same
risks that they are liable to from him.
The frequent attacks from slaveholders
and their tools, the peculiarity of our
position, many being escaped slaves, and
the secrecy attending these kidnapping
exploits, all combined to make an appeal
to the Lynch Code in our case excusable,
if not altogether justifiable. Ourselves,
our wives, our little ones, were insecure,
and all we had was liable to seizure. We
felt that something must be done, for
some one must be in our midst with whom
the slaveholders had communication. I
inquired around, quietly, and soon learned
that Allen Williams, the very man in
whose house the fugitive was, had
betrayed him. This information I
communicated to our men. They met at
my house and talked the matter over;
and, after most solemnly weighing all
the facts and evidence, we resolved that
he should die, and we set about executing
our purpose that evening. The difficulty
was, how to punish him. Some were for
shooting him, but this was not feasible.
I proposed another plan, which was agreed to.</p>
            <p>Accordingly, we went to his house and
asked if a man named Carter, who lived
with him, was at home, as rumor said that
he had betrayed Henry Williams. He
denied it, and said that Carter had fought
for Henry with him, but the slaveholders
being too strong for them, they had to
give him up. He kept beyond reach, and
the men apologized for intruding upon
him, while I stepped up to the door and
asked for a glass of water. He gave it to
me, and to the others. When he was giving
water to one of the party, I caught him by
the throat, to prevent his giving the
alarm, and drew him over my head and
shoulders. Then the rest beat him until we
thought we heard some one coming, which
caused us to flee. If we had not been
interrupted, death would have been his
fate. At that time I was attending a
threshing-machine for George Whitson
and Joseph Scarlot.</p>
            <p>It must have been a month after the
Williams affray, that I was sitting at home
one evening, talking with Pinckney and
Samuel Thompson about how I was getting
on with my work, when I thought I heard
some one call my name. I went out, but all
was quiet. When I went in, Pinckney and
Thompson laughed at me, and said that I
had become so “scary” that I could not
stay in the house. But I was not satisfied. I
was sure some one had called me. I said so,
and that I would go to Marsh
Chamberlain's to see if anything was
wrong. They concluded to go also, and we
started.</p>
            <p>Arriving near the house, I told
Pinckney and Thompson to stop outside,
and I would go in, and if anything was
wrong, would call them. When I reached
the house, I saw a chair broken to pieces,
and knew that something had happened. I
said,—</p>
            <pb id="freedman166" n="166"/>
            <p>“Hallo, Marsh!”</p>
            <p>“Who is that?” said he.</p>
            <p>And his wife said,—</p>
            <p>“Parker, is that you?”</p>
            <p>“Yes,” I said.</p>
            <p>“Oh, Parker, come here!” she called.</p>
            <p>I called Pinckney and Thompson and
we went in. Marsh met us, and said that
kidnappers had been there, had taken John
Williams, and gone with him towards Buck
Hill. They had then been gone about
fifteen minutes. Off we started on a rapid
run to save him. We ran to a stable, got
out two horses, and Pinckney and I rode
on. Thompson soon got the rest of our
party together and followed. We were going
at a pretty good gait, when Pinckney's
horse stumbled and fell, fastening his
rider's leg; but I did not halt. Pinckney got
his horse up and caught up with me.</p>
            <p>“You would not care,” said he, “if a
man were to get killed! You would not
help him!”</p>
            <p>“Not in such a case as this,” I replied.</p>
            <p>We rode on to the Maryland line, but
could not overtake them. We were obliged
to return, as it was near daybreak. The
next day a friend of ours went to
Maryland to see what had been done with
Williams. He went to Dr. Savington's, and
the Doctor told him that the fugitive
could not live,—the kidnappers had broken
his skull, and otherwise beaten him very
badly; his ankle, too, was out of place. In
consequence of his maimed condition, his
mistress refused to pay the men anything
for bringing him home. That was the last
we ever heard of poor John Williams; but
we learned afterwards why we failed to
release him on the night he was taken.
The kidnappers heard us coming, and went
into the woods out of the way, until we
had passed them.</p>
            <p>Awhile before this occurrence, there
lived in a town not far away from
Christiana a colored man who was in the
habit of decoying fugitives fresh from
bondage to his house on various pretexts,
and, by assuming to be their friend, got
from them the name of their master,
his residence, and other needed particulars.
He would then communicate with the
master about his slave, tell him at what
time the man would be at his house, and
when he came at the appointed hour, the
poor refugee would fall into the merciless
clutches of his owner. Many persons,
mostly young people, had disappeared
mysteriously from the country, from
whom nothing could be heard. At last the
betrayer's connection with these
transactions was clearly traced; and it was
decided to force him to quit the nefarious
business.</p>
            <p>He was too wary to allow himself to be
easily taken, and a resort was had to
stratagem. I, with others, thought he
deserved to be shot openly in his
daughter's house, and was willing to take
the consequences.</p>
            <p>At last this man's outrages became so
notorious that six of our most reliable
men resolved to shoot him, if they had to
burn him out to do it. After I had sworn
the men in the usual form, we went to his
barn, took two bundles of wheat-straw,
and, fastening them under the eaves with
wisps, applied a lighted match to each. We
then took our stations a few rods off, with
rifles ready and in good condition,—mine
was a smooth-bore, with a heavy charge.</p>
            <p>The house burned beautifully; and half
an hour after it ignited the walls fell in, but
no betrayer showed himself. Instead of
leaving the house by the rear door, as we
had expected, just before the roof fell in,
he broke out the front way, rushed to his
next neighbor's, and left his place without
an effort to save it. We had built the fire
in the rear, and looked for him there; but
he ran in the opposite direction, not only
as if his life was in danger, but as if the
spirit of his evil deeds was after him.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="part two">
          <pb id="freedman276" n="276"/>
          <head>PART II.
<lb/>
[Vol. XVII, March, 1866.]</head>
          <div3 type="introduction">
            <p>AS the Freedman relates only events
which came under his own observation, it
is necessary to preface the remaining
portion of his narrative with a brief
account of the Christiana riot. This I
extract mainly from a statement made at
the time by a member of the
Philadelphia bar, making only a few
alterations to give the account greater
clearness and brevity.</p>
            <p>On the 9th of September, 1851, Mr.
Edward Gorsuch, a citizen of Maryland,
residing near Baltimore, appeared before
<pb id="freedman277" n="277"/>
Edward D. Ingraham, Esquire, United
States Commissioner at Philadelphia,
and asked for warrants under the act of
Congress of September 18, 1850, for
the arrest of four of his slaves, whom
he had heard were secreted somewhere
in Lancaster County. Warrants were
issued forthwith, directed to H. H. Kline,
a deputy United States Marshal,
authorizing him to arrest George
Hammond, Joshua Hammond, Nelson
Ford, and Noah Buley, persons held to
service or labor in the State of
Maryland, and to bring them before
the said Commissioner.</p>
            <p>Mr. Gorsuch then made arrangements
with John Agin and Thompson Tully,
residents of Philadelphia, and police
officers, to assist Kline in making the
arrests. They were to meet Mr.
Gorsuch and some companions at
Penningtonville, a small place on the
State Railroad, about fifty miles from
Philadelphia. Kline, with the warrants,
left Philadelphia on the same day, about
2 P. M., for West Chester. There he hired
a conveyance and rode to Gallagherville,
where he hired another conveyance to
take him to Penningtonville. Before he
had driven very far, the carriage breaking
down, he returned to Gallagherville, procured
another, and started again. Owing to
this detention, he was prevented from
meeting Mr. Gorsuch and his friends at
the appointed time, and when he
reached Penningtonville, about 2 A. M.
on the 10th of September, they had gone.</p>
            <p>On entering the tavern, the place of
rendezvous he saw a colored man whom
he recognized as Samuel Williams, a
resident of Philadelphia. To put Williams
off his guard, Kline asked the landlord
some questions about horse thieves.
Williams remarked that he had seen the
“horse thieves,” and told Kline he had
come too late.</p>
            <p>Kline then drove on to a place called the
Gap. Seeing a person he believed to be
Williams following him, he stopped at
several taverns along the road and made
inquiries about horse thieves. He reached
the Gap about 3 A. M., put up his horses,
and went to bed. At half past four he rose,
ate breakfast, and rode to Parkesburg,
about forty-five miles from Philadelphia,
and on the same railroad. Here he found Agin
and Tully asleep in the bar-room. He awoke
Agin, called him aside, and inquired for Mr.
Gorsuch and his party. He was told they
had gone to Sadsbury, a small place on
the turnpike, four or five miles from
Parkesburg.</p>
            <p>On going there, he found them, about
9 A. M. on the 10th of September. Kline told
them he had seen Agin and Tully, who had
determined to return to Philadelphia, and
proposed that the whole party should
return to Gallagherville. Mr. Gorsuch,
however, determined to go to Parkesburg
instead, to see Agin and Tully, and
attempt to persuade them not to return.
The rest of the party were to go to
Gallagherville, while Kline returned to
Downingtown, to see Agin and Tully,
should Mr. Gorsuch fail to meet them at
Parkesburg. He left Gallagherville about 11
A. M., and met Agin and Tully at
Downingtown. Agin said he had seen Mr.
Gorsuch, but refused to go back. He
promised, however, to return from
Philadelphia in the evening cars. Kline
returned to Downingtown, and then met
all the party except Mr. Edward Gorsuch,
who had remained behind to make the
necessary arrangements for procuring a
guide to the houses where he had been
informed his negroes were to be found.</p>
            <p>About 3 P. M., Mr. Edward Gorsuch
joined them at Gallagherville, and at 11
P. M. on the night of the 10th of September
they all went in the cars to Downingtown,
where they waited for the evening train
from Philadelphia.</p>
            <p>When it arrived, neither Agin nor Tully
was to be seen. The rest of the party went
on to the Gap, which they reached about
half past one on the morning of the 11th
of September. They then continued their
journey on foot towards Christiana, where
Parker was residing, and where the slaves
of Mr. Gorsuch were supposed to be living.
The party then consisted of Kline, Edward
Gorsuch, Dickinson Gorsuch, his son,
Joshua M. Gorsuch, his nephew,
<pb id="freedman278" n="278"/>
Dr. Thomas Pierce, Nicholas T. Hutchings,
and Nathan Nelson.</p>
            <p>After they had proceeded about a
mile they met a man who was represented
to be a guide. He is said to
have been disguised in such a way that
none of the party could recognize him,
and his name is not mentioned in any
of the proceedings. It is probable that
he was employed by Mr. Edward Gorsuch,
and one condition of his services
may have been that he should be allowed
to use every possible means of
concealing his face and name from the
rest of the party. Under his conduct,
the party went on, and soon reached a
house in which they were told one of
the slaves was to be found. Mr. Gorsuch
wished to send part of the company after
him, but Kline was unwilling to divide
their strength, and they walked on,
intending to return that way after
making the other arrests.</p>
            <p>The guide led them by a circuitous
route, until they reached the Valley
Road, near the house of William Parker,
the writer of the annexed narrative,
which was their point of destination.
They halted in a lane near by, ate some
crackers and cheese, examined the
condition of their fire-arms, and consulted
upon the plan of attack. A short walk
brought them to the orchard in front of
Parker's house, which the guide pointed
out and then left them. He had no desire
to remain and witness the result of
his false information. His disguise and
desertion of his employer are strong
circumstances in proof of the fact that
he knew he was misleading the party.
On the trial of Hanway, it was proved
by the defence that Nelson Ford, one
of the fugitives, was not on the ground
until after the sun was up. Joshua
Hammond had lived in the vicinity up
to the time that a man by the name of
Williams had been kidnapped, when he
and several others departed, and had
not since been heard from. Of the
other two, one at least, if the evidence
for the prosecution is to be relied upon,
was in the house at which the party first
halted, so that there could not have
been more than one of Mr. Gorsuch's
slaves in Parker's house, and of this
there is no positive testimony.</p>
            <p>It was not yet daybreak when the party
approached the house. They made
demand for the slaves, and threatened
to burn the house and shoot the
occupants, if they would not surrender.
At this time, the number of besiegers
seems to have been increased, and as
many as fifteen are said to have been
near the house. About daybreak, when
they were advancing a second or third
time, they saw a negro coming out, whom
Mr. Gorsuch thought he recognized as
one of his slaves. Kline pursued him
with a revolver in his hand, and stumbled
over the bars near the house. Some
of the company came up before Kline,
and found the door open. They entered,
and Kline, following, called for the
owner, ordered all to come down, and
said he had two warrants for the arrest
of Nelson Ford and Joshua Hammond.
He was answered that there were no
such men in the house. Kline, followed
by Mr. Gorsuch, attempted to go up
stairs. They were prevented from ascending
by what appears to have been an ordinary
<hi rend="italics">fish gig</hi>. Some of the witnesses described
it as “like a pitchfork with blunt prongs,”
and others were at a loss what to call this,
the first weapon used in the contest. An
axe was next thrown down, but hit no one.</p>
            <p>Mr. Gorsuch and others then went
outside to talk with the negroes at the
window. Just at this time Kline fired
his pistol up stairs. The warrants were
then read outside the house, and
demand made upon the landlord. No
answer was heard. After a short interval,
Kline proposed to withdraw his
men, but Mr. Gorsuch refused, and said
he would not leave the ground until he
had made the arrests. Kline then in
a loud voice ordered some one to go to
the sheriff and bring a hundred men,
thinking, as he afterwards said, this
would intimidate them. The threat
appears to have had some effect, for
the negroes asked time to consider.
The party outside agreed to give fifteen
minutes.</p>
            <p>While these scenes were passing at
<pb id="freedman279" n="279"/>
the house, occurrences transpired
elsewhere that are worthy of attention,
but which cannot be understood without
a short statement of previous events.</p>
            <p>In the month of September, 1850, a
colored man, known in the neighborhood
around Christiana to be free, was seized
and carried away by men known to be
professional kidnappers, and had not been
seen by his family since. In March, 1851,
in the same neighborhood, under the roof
of his employer, during the night,
another colored man was tied, gagged,
and carried away, marking the road along
which he was dragged with his blood. No
authority for this outrage was ever
shown, and the man was never heard
from. These and many other acts of a
similar kind had so alarmed the
neighborhood, that the very name of
kidnapper was sufficient to create a
panic. The blacks feared for their own
safety; and the whites, knowing their
feelings, were apprehensive that any
attempt to repeat these outrages would be
the cause of bloodshed. Many good
citizens were determined to do all in their
power to prevent these lawless
depredations, though they were ready to
submit to any measures sanctioned by
legal process. They regretted the
existence among them of a body of
people liable to such violence; but
without combination had, each for
himself, resolved that they would do
everything dictated by humanity to resist
barbarous oppression.</p>
            <p>On the morning in question, a colored
man living in the neighborhood, who
passing Parker's house at an early hour,
saw the yard full of men. He halted, and
was met by a man who presented a
pistol at him, and ordered him to leave
the place. He went away and hastened to
a store kept by Elijah Lewis, which, like
all places of that kind, was probably the
head-quarters of news in the neighborhood.
Mr. Lewis was in the act of opening his
store when this man told him that “Parker's
house was surrounded by <hi rend="italics">kidnappers</hi>,
who had broken into the house, and <hi rend="italics">were
trying to get him away</hi>.” Lewis, not
questioning the truth of the statement,
repaired immediately to the place. On the
way he passed the house of Castner
Hanway, and, telling him what he had
heard, asked him to go over to Parker's.
Hanway was in feeble health and unable to
undergo the fatigue of walking that
distance; but he saddled his horse, and
reached Parker's during the armistice.</p>
            <p>Having no reason to believe he was
acting under legal authority, when Kline
approached and demanded assistance in
making the arrests, Hanway made no
answer. Kline then handed him the
warrants, which Hanway examined, saw
they appeared genuine, and returned.</p>
            <p>At this time, several colored men, who
no doubt had heard the report that
kidnappers were about, came up, armed
with such weapons as they could suddenly
lay hands upon. How many were on the
ground during the affray it is <hi rend="italics">now</hi>
impossible to determine. The witnesses on
both sides vary materially in their
estimate. Some said they saw a dozen or
fifteen; some, thirty or forty; and others
maintained, as many as two or three
hundred. It is known there were not two
hundred colored men within eight miles of
Parker's house, nor half that number
within four miles; and it would have been
almost impossible to get together even
thirty at an hour's notice. It is probable
there were about twenty-five, all told, at
or near the house from the beginning of
the affray until all was quiet again. These
the fears of those who afterwards testified
to larger numbers might easily have
magnified to fifty or a hundred.</p>
            <p>While Kline and Hanway were in
conversation, Elijah Lewis came up.
Hanway said to him, “Here is the
Marshal.” Lewis asked to see his
authority, and Kline handed him one of
the warrants. When he saw the signature
of the United States Commissioner, “he
took it for granted that Kline had
authority.” Kline then ordered Hanway
and Lewis to assist in arresting the alleged
fugitives. Hanway refused
<pb id="freedman280" n="280"/>
to have anything to do with it, The
negroes around these three men seeming
disposed to make an attack, Hanway
“motioned to them and urged them back.”
He then “advised Kline that it would be
dangerous to attempt making arrests, and
that they had better leave.” Kline, after
saying he would hold them accountable
for the fugitives, promised to leave, and
beckoned two or three times to his men
to retire.</p>
            <p>The negroes then rushed up, some
armed with guns, some with corn-cutters,
staves, or clubs, others with stones
or whatever weapon chance offered.
Hanway and Lewis in vain endeavored
to restrain them.</p>
            <p>Kline leaped the fence, passed through
the standing grain in the field, and for a
few moments was out of sight. Mr.
Gorsuch refused to leave the spot, saying
his “property was there, and he would
have it or perish in the attempt.” The rest
of his party endeavored to retreat when
they heard the Marshal calling to them,
but they were too late; the negroes rushed
up, and the firing began. How many times
each party fired, it is impossible to tell.
For a few moments everything was
confusion, and each attempted to save
himself. Nathan Nelson went down the
short lane, thence into the woods and
towards Penningtonville. Nicholas
Hutchings, by direction of Kline, followed
Lewis to see where he went. Thomas
Pierce and Joshua Gorsuch went down the
long lane, pursued by some of the negroes,
caught up with Hanway, and, shielding
themselves behind his horse, followed him
to a stream of water near by. Dickinson
Gorsuch was with his father near the house.
They were both wounded; the father
mortally. Dickinson escaped down the
lane, where he was met by Kline, who had
returned from the woods at the end of the
field. Kline rendered him assistance, and
went towards Penningtonville for a
physician. On his way be met Joshua M.
Gorsuch, who was also wounded and
delirious. Kline led him over to
Penningtonville and placed him on the
upward train from Philadelphia. Before
this time several persons living in the
neighborhood had arrived at Parker's
house. Lewis Cooper found Dickinson
Gorsuch in the place where Kline had left
him, attended by Joseph Scarlett.
He placed him in his dearborn, and carried
him to the house of Levi Pownall, where
he remained till he had sufficiently
recovered to return home. Mr. Cooper
then returned to Parker's, placed the body
of Mr. Edward Gorsuch in the same
dearborn, and carried it to Christiana.
Neither Nelson nor Hutchings rejoined
their party, but during the day went by
the railroad to Lancaster.</p>
            <p>Thus ended an occurrence which was
the theme of conversation throughout
the land. Not more than two hours
elapsed from the time demand was first
made at Parker's house until the dead
body of Edward Gorsuch was carried to
Christiana. In that brief time the blood
of strangers had been spilled in a sudden
affray, an unfortunate man had been
killed, and two others badly wounded.</p>
            <p>When rumor spread abroad the result of
the affray, the neighborhood was
appalled. The inhabitants of the
farmhouses and the villages around,
unused to such scenes, could not at first
believe that it had occurred in their midst.
Before midday, exaggerated accounts had
reached Philadelphia, and were
transmitted by telegraph throughout the
country.</p>
            <p>Many persons were arrested for
participation in the riot; and, after a
long imprisonment, were arraigned for
trial, on the charge of treason, before Judges
Grier and Kane, of the United States
Court, sitting at Philadelphia.</p>
            <p>Every one knows the result. The
prisoners were all acquitted; and the
country was aroused to the danger of a
law which allowed bad men to incarcerate
peaceful citizens for months in prison,
and put them in peril of their lives, for
refusing to aid in entrapping, and sending
back to hopeless slavery, men struggling
for the very same freedom we value as the
best part of our birthright.</p>
            <p>The Freedman's narrative is now resumed.</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="freedman281" n="281"/>
          <div3 type="narrative">
            <p>A short time after the events narrated
in the preceding number, it was
whispered about that the slaveholders
intended to make an attack on my house;
but, as I had often been threatened, I
gave the report little attention. About
the same time, however, two letters
were found thrown carelessly about, as if
to attract notice. These letters stated
that kidnappers would be at my house on
a certain night, and warned me to be on
my guard. Still I did not let the matter
trouble me. But it was no idle rumor.
The bloodhounds were upon my track.</p>
            <p>I was not at this time aware that in the
city of Philadelphia there was a band of
devoted, determined men,—few in
number, but strong in purpose,—who
were fully resolved to leave no means
untried to thwart the barbarous and
inhuman monsters who crawled in the
gloom of midnight, like the ferocious
tiger, and, stealthily springing on their
unsuspecting victims, seized, bound, and
hurled them into the ever open jaws of
Slavery. Under the pretext of enforcing
the Fugitive Slave Law, the slaveholders
did not hesitate to violate all other laws
made for the good government and
protection of society, and converted the
old State of Pennsylvania, so long the
hope of the fleeing bondman, wearied
and heartbroken, into a common
hunting-ground for their human prey.
But this little band of true patriots in
Philadelphia united for the purpose of
standing between the pursuer and the
pursued, the kidnapper and his victim,
and, regardless of all personal
considerations, were ever on the alert,
ready to sound the alarm to save their
fellows from a fate far more to be
dreaded than death. In this they had
frequently succeeded, and many times
had turned the hunter home bootless of
his prey. They began their operations at
the passage of the Fugitive Slave Law,
and had thoroughly examined all matters
connected with it, and were perfectly
cognizant of the plans adopted to carry
out its provisions in Pennsylvania, and,
through a correspondence with reliable
persons in various sections of the South,
were enabled to know these hunters of men,
their agents, spies, tools, and betrayers.
They knew who performed this work in
Richmond, Alexandria, Washington,
Baltimore, Wilmington, Philadelphia,
Lancaster, and Harrisburg, those principal
depots of villany, where organized bands
prowled about at all times, ready to entrap
the unwary fugitive.</p>
            <p>They also discovered that this nefarious
business was conducted mainly through
one channel; for, spite of man's
inclination to vice and crime, there are
but few men, thank God, so low in the
scale of humanity as to be willing to
degrade themselves by doing the dirty
work of four-legged bloodhounds. Yet such
men, actuated by the love of gold and
their own base and brutal natures, were
found ready for the work. These fellows
consorted with constables, police-officers,
aldermen, and even with learned members
of the legal profession, who disgraced
their respectable calling by low,
contemptible arts, and were willing to
clasp hands with the lowest ruffian in
order to pocket the reward that was the
price of blood. Every facility was offered
these bad men; and whether it was night or
day, it was only necessary to whisper in a
certain circle that a negro was to be
caught, and horses and wagons, men and
officers, spies and betrayers, were ready,
at the shortest notice, armed and
equipped, and eager for the chase.</p>
            <p>Thus matters stood in Philadelphia on
the 9th of September, 1851, when Mr.
Gorsuch and his gang of Maryland
kidnappers arrived there. Their presence
was soon known to the little band of true
men who were called “The Special Secret
Committee.” They had agents faithful and
true as steel; and through these agents the
whereabouts and business of Gorsuch and
his minions were soon discovered. They
were noticed in close converse with a
certain member of the Philadelphia bar,
who had lost the little reputation he ever
had by continual dabbling in negro-catching,
as well as by association with and support
of the notorious Henry H.
<pb id="freedman282" n="282"/>
Kline, a professional kidnapper of the
basest stamp. Having determined as to the
character and object of these Marylanders,
there remained to ascertain the spot
selected for their deadly spring; and this
required no small degree of shrewdness,
resolution, and tact.</p>
            <p>Some one's liberty was imperilled; the
hunters were abroad; the time was short,
and the risk imminent. The little band
bent themselves to the task they were
pledged to perform with zeal and devotion;
and success attended their efforts. They
knew that one false step would jeopardize
their own liberty, and very likely their
lives, and utterly destroy every prospect
of carrying out their objects. They knew,
too, that they were matched against the
most desperate, daring, and brutal men in
the kidnappers' ranks,—men who, to
obtain the proffered reward, would rush
willingly into any enterprise, regardless
alike of its character or its consequences.
That this was the deepest, the most
thoroughly organized and best-planned
project for man-catching that had been
concocted since the infamous Fugitive
Slave Law had gone into operation, they
also knew; and consequently this nest of
hornets was approached with great care.
But by walking directly into their camp,
watching their plans as they were
developed, and secretly testing every inch
of ground on which they trod, they
discovered enough to counterplot these
plotters, and to spring upon them a mine
which shook the whole country, and put
an end to man-stealing in Pennsylvania
forever.</p>
            <p>The trusty agent of this Special
Committee, Mr. Samuel Williams, of
Philadelphia,—a man true and faithful to
his race, and courageous in the highest
degree,—came to Christiana, travelling
most of the way in company with the
very men whom Gorsuch had employed to
drag into slavery four as good men as ever
trod the earth. These Philadelphia roughs,
with their Maryland associates, little
dreamed that the man who sat by their
side carried with him their inglorious
defeat, and the death-warrant of at least
one of their party. Williams listened to
their conversation, and marked well their
faces, and, being fully satisfied by their
awkward movements that they were heavily
armed, managed to slip out of the cars at
the village of Downington unobserved,
and proceeded to Penningtonville, where
he encountered Kline, who had started
several hours in advance of the others.
Kline was terribly frightened, as he knew
Williams, and felt that his presence was
an omen of ill to his base designs. He
spoke of horse thieves; but Williams
replied,—“I know the kind of horse
thieves you are after. They are all gone;
and you had better not go after them.”</p>
            <p>Kline immediately jumped into his
wagon, and rode away, whilst Williams
crossed the country, and arrived at
Christiana in advance of him.</p>
            <p>The manner in which information of
Gorsuch's designs was obtained will probably
ever remain a secret; and I doubt if any
one outside of the little band who so
masterly managed the affair knows
anything of it. This was wise; and I would
to God other friends had acted thus. Mr.
Williams's trip to Christiana, and the many
incidents connected therewith, will be
found in the account of his trial; for he
was subsequently arrested and thrown into
the cold cells of a loathsome jail for this
good act of simple Christian duty; but,
resolute to the last, he publicly stated that
he had been to Christiana, and, to use his
own words, “I done it, and will do it
again.” Brave man, receive my thanks!</p>
            <p>Of the Special Committee I can only
say that they proved themselves men;
and through the darkest hours of the trials
that followed, they were found faithful to
their trust, never for one moment
deserting those who were compelled to
suffer. Many, many innocent men
residing in the vicinity of Christiana, the
ground where the first battle was fought
for liberty in Pennsylvania, were seized,
torn from their families, and, like
Williams, thrown into prison for long,
weary months, to be tried for their lives.
By them this Committee
<pb id="freedman283" n="283"/>
stood, giving them every
consolation and comfort,
furnishing them with clothes, and
attending to their wants, giving
money to themselves and families,
and procuring for them the best
legal counsel. This I know, and
much more of which it is not wise,
even now, to speak: 't is enough to
say they were friends when and
where it cost something to be
friends, and true brothers where
brothers were needed.</p>
            <p>After this lengthy digression, I
will return, and speak of the riot
and the events immediately
preceding it.</p>
            <p>The information brought by Mr.
Williams spread through the
vicinity like a fire in the prairies;
and when I went home from my
work in the evening, I found
Pinckney (whom I should have
said before was my brother-in-law),
Abraham Johnson, Samuel
Thompson, and Joshua Kite at my
house, all of them excited about
the rumor. I laughed at them, and
said it was all talk. This was the
10th of September, 1851. They
stopped for the night with us, and
we went to bed as usual. Before
daylight, Joshua Kite rose, and
started for his home. Directly, he
ran back to the house, burst open
the door, crying, “O William!
kidnappers! kidnappers!”</p>
            <p>He said that, when he was just
beyond the yard, two men crossed
before him, as if to stop him, and
others came up on either side. As
he said this, they had reached the
door. Joshua ran up stairs, (we slept
up stairs,) and they followed him;
but I met them at the landing, and
asked, “Who are you?”</p>
            <p>The leader, Kline, replied, “I am
the United States Marshal.”</p>
            <p>I then told him to take another
step, and I would break his neck.</p>
            <p>He again said, “I am the United
States Marshal.”</p>
            <p>I told him I did not care for him
nor the United States. At that he
turned and went down stairs.</p>
            <p>Pinckney said, as he turned to
go down,—“Where is the use in
fighting? They will take us.”</p>
            <p>Kline heard him, and said, “Yes,
give up, for we can and will take
you anyhow.”</p>
            <p>I told them all not to be afraid, nor
to give up to any slaveholder, but to
fight until death.</p>
            <p>“Yes,” said Kline, “I have heard
many a negro talk as big as you, and
then have taken him; and I'll take
you.”</p>
            <p>“You have not taken me yet,” I
replied; “and if you undertake it you
will have your name recorded in
history for this day's work.”</p>
            <p>Mr. Gorsuch then spoke, and said,—
“Come, Mr. Kline, let's go up stairs
and take them. We <hi rend="italics">can</hi> take them.
Come, follow me, I'll go up and get
my property. What's in the way? The
law is in my favor, and the people are
in my favor.”</p>
            <p>At that he began to ascend the
stair; but I said to him,—“See here,
old man, you can come up, but you
can't go down again. Once up here,
you are mine.”</p>
            <p>Kline then said,—“Stop, Mr.
Gorsuch. I will read the warrant, and
then, I think, they will give up.”</p>
            <p>He then read the warrant, and said,
“Now, you see, we are commanded
to take you, dead or alive; so you may
as well give up at once.”</p>
            <p>“Go up, Mr. Kline,” then said
Gorsuch, “you are the Marshal.”</p>
            <p>Kline started, and when a little
way up said, “I am coming.”</p>
            <p>I said, “Well, come on.”</p>
            <p>But he was too cowardly to show
his face. He went down again and
said,—“You had better give up without
any more fuss, for we are bound to
take you anyhow. I told you before
that I was the United States Marshal,
yet you will not give up. I'll not
trouble the slaves. I will take you and
make you pay for all.”</p>
            <p>“Well,” I answered, “take me and
make me pay for all. I'll pay for all.”</p>
            <p>Mr. Gorsuch then said, “You have
my property.”</p>
            <p>To which I replied,—“Go in the room
down there, and see if there is
anything there belonging to you.
There are beds and a bureau, chairs,
and other things. Then go out to the
barn; there you will find a cow and
some hogs. See if any of them are
yours.”</p>
            <p>He said,—“They are not mine; I
<pb id="freedman284" n="284"/>
want my men. They are here, and I am
bound to have them.”</p>
            <p>Thus we parleyed for a time, all
because of the pusillanimity of the
Marshal, when he, at last, said,—“I am
tired waiting on you; I see you are not
going to give up. Go to the barn and fetch
some straw,” said he to one of his men. “I
will set the house on fire, and burn them
up.”</p>
            <p>“Burn us up and welcome,” said I.
“None but a coward would say the like.
You can burn us, but you can't take us;
before I give up, you will see my ashes
scattered on the earth.”</p>
            <p>By this time day had begun to dawn; and
then my wife came to me and asked if she
should blow the horn, to bring friends to
our assistance. I assented, and she went to
the garret for the purpose. When the horn
sounded from the garret window, one of
the ruffians asked the others what it
meant; and Kline said to me, “What do
you mean by blowing that horn?”</p>
            <p>I did not answer. It was a custom with
us, when a horn was blown at an unusual
hour, to proceed to the spot promptly to
see what was the matter. Kline ordered his
men to shoot any one they saw blowing
the horn. There was a peach-tree at that
end of the house. Up it two of the men
climbed; and when my wife went a second
time to the window, they fired as soon as
they heard the blast, but missed their aim.
My wife then went down on her knees,
and, drawing her head and body below the
range of the window, the horn resting on
the sill, blew blast after blast, while the
shots poured thick and fast around her.
They must have fired ten or twelve times.
The house was of stone, and the windows
were deep, which alone preserved her life.</p>
            <p>They were evidently disconcerted by
the blowing of the horn. Gorsuch said
again, “I want my property, and I will
have it.”</p>
            <p>“Old man,” said I, “you look as if you
belonged to some persuasion.”</p>
            <p>“Never mind,” he answered, “what
persuasion I belong to; I want my
property.”</p>
            <p>While I was leaning out of the
window, Kline fired a pistol at me, but
the shot went too high; the ball broke
the glass just above my bead. I was
talking to Gorsuch at the time. I seized
a gun and aimed it at Gorsuch's breast
for he evidently had instigated Kline to
fire; but Pinckney caught my arm and
said, “Don't shoot.” The gun went
off, just grazing Gorsuch's shoulder.
Another conversation then ensued
between Gorsuch, Kline, and myself,
when another one of the party fired at
me but missed. Dickinson Gorsuch, I
then saw, was preparing to shoot; and
I told him if he missed, I would show
him where shooting first came from.</p>
            <p>I asked them to consider what they
would have done, had they been in our
position. “I know you want to kill us,”
I said, “for you have shot at us time and
again. We have only fired twice, although
we have guns and ammunition, and could
kill you all if we would, but we do not
want to shed blood.”</p>
            <p>“If you do not shoot any more,” then
said Kline, “I will stop my men from
firing.”</p>
            <p>They then ceased for a time. This was
about sunrise.</p>
            <p>Mr. Gorsuch now said,—“Give up and
let me have my property. Hear what the
Marshal says; the Marshal is your friend.
He advises you to give up without more
fuss, for my property I will have.”</p>
            <p>I denied that I had his property, when
he replied, “You have my men.”</p>
            <p>“Am I your man?” I asked.</p>
            <p>“No.”</p>
            <p>I then called Pinckney forward.</p>
            <p>“Is that your man?”</p>
            <p>“No.”</p>
            <p>Abraham Johnson I called next, but
Gorsuch said he was not his man.</p>
            <p>The only plan left was to call both
Pinckney and Johnson again; for had I
called the others, he would have
recognized them, for they were his slaves.</p>
            <p>Abraham Johnson said, “Does such a
shrivelled up old slaveholder as you own
such a nice, genteel young man as I am?”</p>
            <pb id="freedman285" n="285"/>
            <p>At this Gorsuch took offence, and
charged me with dictating his language. I
then told him there were but five of us,
which he denied, and still insisted that I
had his property. One of the party then
attacked the Abolitionists, affirming
that, although they declared there could
not be property in man, the Bible was
conclusive authority in favor of property
in human flesh.</p>
            <p>“Yes,” said Gorsuch, “does not the
Bible say, ‘Servants, obey your masters’?”</p>
            <p>I said that it did, but the same Bible
said, “Give unto your servants that
which is just and equal.”</p>
            <p>At this stage of the proceedings, we
went into a mutual Scripture inquiry, and
bandied views in the manner of garrulous
old wives.</p>
            <p>When I spoke of duty to servants,
Gorsuch said, “Do you know that?”</p>
            <p>“Where,” I asked, “do you see it in
Scripture, that a man should traffic in
his brother's blood?”</p>
            <p>“Do you call a nigger my brother?”
said Gorsuch.</p>
            <p>“Yes,” said I.</p>
            <p>“William,” said Samuel Thompson,
“he has been a class-leader.”</p>
            <p>When Gorsuch heard that, he hung his
head, but said nothing. We then all joined
in singing,—</p>
            <lg type="poem">
              <l>“Leader, what do you say</l>
              <l>About the judgment day?</l>
              <l>I will die on the field of battle,</l>
              <l>Die on the field of battle,</l>
              <l>With glory in my soul.”</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Then we all began to shout, singing
meantime, and shouted for a long while.
Gorsuch, who was standing head bowed,
said, “What are you doing now?”</p>
            <p>Samuel Thompson replied, “Preaching
a sinner's funeral sermon.”</p>
            <p>“You had better give up, and come
down.”</p>
            <p>I then said to Gorsuch,—“ ‘If a brother
see a sword coming, and he warn not his
brother, then the brother's blood is
required at his hands; but if
the other see the sword coming, and
warn his brother, and his brother flee
then his brother's blood is required
at his own hand.’ I see the sword coming,
and, old man, I warn you to flee; if
you flee not, your blood be upon your
own hand.”</p>
            <p>It was now about seven o'clock.</p>
            <p>“You had better give up,” said old Mr.
Gorsuch, after another while, “and come
down, for I have come a long way this
morning, and want my breakfast; for my
property I will have, or I'll breakfast in
hell. I will go up and get it.”</p>
            <p>He then started up stairs, and came far
enough to see us all plainly. We were just
about to fire upon him, when Dickinson
Gorsuch, who was standing on the old
oven, before the door, and could see into
the up-stairs room through the window,
jumped down and caught his father,
saying,—“O father, do come down! do come
down! They have guns, swords, and all
kinds of weapons! They'll kill you!
Do come down!”</p>
            <p>The old man turned and left. When
down with him, young Gorsuch could
scarce draw breath, and the father looked
more like a dead than a living man, so
frightened were they at their supposed
danger. The old man stood some time
without saying anything; at last he said,
as if soliloquizing, “I want my property,
and I will have it.”</p>
            <p>Kline broke forth, “If you don't give
up by fair means, you will have to by
foul.”</p>
            <p>I told him we would not surrender on
any conditions.</p>
            <p>Young Gorsuch then said,—“Don't ask
them to give up,—<hi rend="italics">make</hi> them do it. We
have money, and can call men to take
them. What is it that money won't buy?”</p>
            <p>Then said Kline,—“I am getting tired
waiting on you; I see you are not going
to give up.”</p>
            <p>He then wrote a note and handed it to
Joshua Gorsuch, saying at the same
time,—“Take it, and bring a hundred men
from Lancaster.”</p>
            <p>As he started, I said,—“See here!
When you go to Lancaster, don't bring a
hundred men,—bring five hundred. It will
take all the men in Lancaster to change
our purpose or take us alive.”</p>
            <pb id="freedman286" n="286"/>
            <p>He stopped to confer with Kline, when
Pinckney said, “We had better give up.”</p>
            <p>“You are getting afraid,” said I.</p>
            <p>“Yes,” said Kline, “give up like men.
The rest would give up if it were not for
you.”</p>
            <p>“I am not afraid,” said Pinckney;
“but where is the sense in fighting
against so many men, and only five
of us?”</p>
            <p>The whites, at this time, were coming
from all quarters, and Kline was enrolling
them as fast as they came. Their numbers
alarmed Pinckney, and I told him to go
and sit down; but he said, “No, I will go
down stairs.”</p>
            <p>I told him, if he attempted it, I should
be compelled to blow out his brains.
“Don't believe, that any living man can
take you,” I said. “Don't give up to any
slaveholder.”</p>
            <p>To Abraham Johnson, who was near
me, I then turned. He declared he was not
afraid. “I will fight till I die,” he said.</p>
            <p>At this time, Hannah, Pinckney's wife,
had become impatient of our persistent
course; and my wife, who brought me her
message urging us to surrender, seized a
corn-cutter, and declared she would cut off
the head of the first one who should
attempt to give up.</p>
            <p>Another one of Gorsuch's slaves was
coming along the highroad at this time,
and I beckoned to him to go around.
Pinckney saw him, and soon became more
inspirited. Elijah Lewis, a Quaker, also
came along about this time; I beckoned to
him, likewise; but he came straight on,
and was met by Kline, who ordered him to
assist him. Lewis asked for his authority,
and Kline handed him the warrant. While
Lewis was reading, Castner Hanway came
up, and Lewis handed the warrant to him.
Lewis asked Kline what Parker said.</p>
            <p>Kline replied, “He won't give up.”</p>
            <p>Then Lewis and Hanway both said to
the Marshal,—“If Parker says they will
not give up, you had better let them
alone, for he will kill some of you. We are
not going to risk our lives”; and they
turned to go away.</p>
            <p>While they were talking, I came down
and stood in the doorway, my men
following behind.</p>
            <p>Old Mr. Gorsuch said, when I appeared,
“They'll come out, and get away!” and
he came back to the gate.</p>
            <p>I then said to him,—“You said you could
and would take us. Now you have the
chance.”</p>
            <p>They were a cowardly-looking set of
men.</p>
            <p>Mr., Gorsuch said, “You can't come out
here.”</p>
            <p>“Why?” said I. “This is my place. I pay
rent for it. I'll let you see if I can't
come out.”</p>
            <p>“I don't care if you do pay rent for it,”
said he. “If you come out, I will give you
the contents of these”;—presenting, at
the same time, two revolvers, one in each
hand.</p>
            <p>I said, “Old man, if you don't go away,
I will break your neck.”</p>
            <p>I then walked up to where he stood, his
arms resting on the gate, trembling as if
afflicted with palsy, and laid my hand on
his shoulder, saying, “I have seen pistols
before to-day.”</p>
            <p>Kline now came running up, and
entreated Gorsuch to come away.</p>
            <p>“No,” said the latter, “I will have my
property, or go to hell.”</p>
            <p>“What do you intend to do?” said
Kline to me.</p>
            <p>“I intend to fight,” said I. “I intend
to try your strength.”</p>
            <p>“If you will withdraw your men,” he
replied, “I will withdraw mine.”</p>
            <p>I told him it was too late. “You would
not withdraw when you had the chance,
—you shall not now.”</p>
            <p>Kline then went back to Hanway and
Lewis. Gorsuch made a signal to his men,
and they all fell into line. I followed his
example as well as I could; but as we were
not more than ten paces apart, it was
difficult to do so. At this time we
numbered but ten, while there were
between thirty and forty of the white
men.</p>
            <p>While I was talking to Gorsuch, his son
said, “Father, will you take all this from a
nigger?”</p>
            <p>I answered him by saying that I
<pb id="freedman287" n="287"/>
respected old age; but that, if he would
repeat that, I should knock his teeth
down his throat. At this he fired upon
me, and I ran up to him and knocked
the pistol out of his hand, when he let
the other one fall and ran in the field.</p>
            <p>My brother-in-law, who was standing
near, then said, “I can stop him”;—and
with his double-barrel gun he fired.</p>
            <p>Young Gorsuch fell, but rose and ran
on again. Pinckney fired a second time,
and again Gorsuch fell, but was soon up
again, and, running into the cornfield,
lay down in the fence corner.</p>
            <p>I returned to my men, and found
Samuel Thompson talking to old Mr.
Gorsuch, his master. They were both
angry.</p>
            <p>“Old man, you had better go home to
Maryland,” said Samuel.</p>
            <p>“You had better give up, and come
home with me,” said the old man.</p>
            <p>Thompson took Pinckney's gun from
struck Gorsuch, and brought him  to his
knees. Gorsuch rose and signalled to
his men. Thompson then knocked
him down again, and he again rose.
At this time all the white men opened
fire, and we rushed upon them; when
they turned, threw down their guns,
and ran away. We, being closely
engaged clubbed our rifles. We were
too closely pressed to fire, but we found
a good deal could be done with empty
guns.</p>
            <p>Old Mr. Gorsuch was the bravest of his
party; he held on to his pistols until the
last, while all the others threw away
their weapons. I saw as many as three at
a time fighting with him. Sometimes he
was on his knees, then on his back, and
again his feet would be where his head
should be. He was a fine soldier and a
brave man. Whenever he saw the least
opportunity, he would take aim. While
in close quarters with the whites, we
could load and fire but two or three
times. Our guns got bent and out of
order. So damaged did they become,
that we could shoot with but two or
three of them. Samuel Thompson bent
his gun on old Mr. Gorsuch so badly,
that it was of no use to us.</p>
            <p>When the white men ran, they
scattered. I ran after Nathan Nelson, but
could not catch him. I never saw a man
run faster. Returning, I saw Joshua
Gorsuch coming, and Pinckney behind
him. I reminded him that he would like
“to take hold of a nigger,” told him that
now was his “chance,” and struck him a
blow on the side of the head, which
stopped him. Pinckney came up behind,
and gave him a blow which brought him to
the ground; as the others passed, they
gave him a kick or jumped upon him, until
the blood oozed out at his ears.</p>
            <p>Nicholas Hutchings, and Nathan Nelson
of Baltimore County, Maryland, could
outrun any men I ever saw. They and
Kline were not brave, like the Gorsuches.
Could our men have got them, they would
have been satisfied.</p>
            <p>One of our men ran after Dr. Pierce, as
he richly deserved attention; but Pierce
caught up with Castner Hanway, who rode
between the fugitive and the Doctor, to
shield him and some others. Hanway was
told to get out of the way, or he would
forfeit his life; he went aside quickly, and
the man fired at the Marylander, but
missed him,—he was too far off. I do not
know whether he was wounded or not; but
I do know, that, if it had not been for
Hanway, he would have been killed.</p>
            <p>Having driven the slavocrats off in
every direction, our party now turned
towards their several homes. Some of us,
however, went back to my house, where
we found several of the neighbors.</p>
            <p>The scene at the house beggars
description. Old Mr. Gorsuch was lying in
the yard in a pool of blood, and confusion
reigned both inside and outside of the
house.</p>
            <p>Levi Pownell said to me, “The weather
is so hot and the flies are so bad, will you
give me a sheet to put over the corpse?”</p>
            <p>In reply, I gave him permission to get
anything he needed from the house.</p>
            <p>“Dickinson Gorsuch is lying in the
fence-corner, and I believe he is dying.
Give me something for him to drink,”
<pb id="freedman288" n="288"/>
said Pownell, who seemed to be acting the
part of the Good Samaritan.</p>
            <p>When he returned from ministering to
Dickinson, he told me he could not live.</p>
            <p>The riot, so called, was now entirely
ended. The elder Gorsuch was dead; his
son and nephew were both wounded, and I
have reason to believe others were,—how
many, it would be difficult to say. Of our
party, only two were wounded. One
received a ball in his hand, near the wrist;
but it only entered the skin, and he pushed
it out with his thumb. Another received a
ball in the fleshy part of his thigh, which
had to be extracted; but neither of them
were sick or crippled by the wounds.
When young Gorsuch fired at me in the
early part of the battle, both balls passed
through my hat, cutting off my hair close
to the skin, but they drew no blood. The
marks were not more than an inch apart.</p>
            <p>A story was afterwards circulated that
Mr. Gorsuch shot his own slave, and in
retaliation his slave shot him; but it was
without foundation. His slave struck him
the first and second blows; then three or
four sprang upon him, and, when he
became helpless, left him to pursue
others. <hi rend="italics">The women put an end to him</hi>.
His slaves, so far from meeting death at
his hands, are all still living.</p>
            <p>After the fight, my wife was obliged to
secrete herself, leaving the children in
care of her mother, and to the charities of
our neighbors. I was questioned by my
friends as to what I should do, as they
were looking for officers to arrest me. I
determined not to be taken alive, and told
them so; but, thinking advice as to our
future course necessary, went to see some
old friends and consult about it. Their
advice was to leave, as, were we captured
and imprisoned, they could not foresee
the result. Acting upon this hint, we set
out for home, when we met some female
friends, who told us that forty or fifty
armed men were at my house, looking for
me, and that we had better stay away
from the place, if we did not want
to be taken. Abraham Johnson and
Pinckney hereupon halted, to agree upon
the best course, while I turned around and
went another way.</p>
            <p>Before setting out on my long journey
northward, I determined to have an
interview with my family, if possible,
and to that end changed my course. As we
went along the road to where I found
them, we met men in companies of three
and four, who had been drawn together by
the excitement. On one occasion, we met
ten or twelve together. They all left the
road, and climbed over the fences into
fields to let us pass; and then, after we
had passed, turned, and looked after us as
far as they could see. Had we been
carrying destruction to all human kind,
they could not have acted more absurdly.
We went to a friend's house and stayed for
the rest of the day, and until nine o'clock
that night, when we set out for Canada.</p>
            <p>The great trial now was to leave my
wife and family. Uncertain as to the result
of the journey, I felt I would rather die
than be separated from them. It had to be
done, however; and we went forth with
heavy hearts, outcasts for the sake of
liberty. When we had walked as far as
Christiana, we saw a large crowd, late as it
was, to some of whom, at least, I must
have been known, as we heard distinctly,
“A'n't that Parker?”</p>
            <p>“Yes,” was answered, “that's Parker.”</p>
            <p>Kline was called for, and he, with some
nine or ten more, followed after. We
stopped, and then they stopped. One said
to his comrades, “Go on,—that's him.” And
another replied, “You go.” So they
contended for a time who should come to
us. At last they went back. I was sorry to
see them go back, for I wanted to meet
Kline and end the day's transactions.</p>
            <p>We went on unmolested to
Penningtonville; and, in consequence of
the excitement, thought best to continue
on to Parkersburg. Nothing worth
mention occurred for a time. We
proceeded to Downingtown, and thence
six miles beyond, to the house of a friend.
<pb id="freedman289" n="289"/>
We stopped with him on Saturday
night, and on the evening of the 14th
went fifteen miles farther. Here I
learned from a preacher, directly
from the city, that the excitement in
Philadelphia was too great for us to risk
our safety by going there. Another man
present advised us to go to Norristown.</p>
            <p>At Norristown we rested a day. The
friends gave us ten dollars, and sent us
in a vehicle to Quakertown. Our driver,
partly intoxicated, set us down at the
wrong place, which obliged us to
stay out all night. At eleven o'clock
the next day we got to Quakertown.
We had gone about six miles out of the
way, and had to go directly across the
country. We rested the 16th, and set
out in the evening for Friendsville.</p>
            <p>A friend piloted us some distance, and
we travelled until we became very tired,
when we went to bed under a haystack.
On the 17th, we took breakfast at an
inn. We passed a small village, and
asked a man whom we met with a
dearborn, what would be his charge to
Windgap. “One dollar and fifty cents,”
was the ready answer. So in we got, and
rode to that place.</p>
            <p>As we wanted to make some inquiries
when we struck the north and south
road, I went into the post-office, and
asked for a letter for John Thomas,
which of course I did not get. The
postmaster scrutinized us closely,—more
so, indeed, than any one had done on
the Blue Mountains,—but informed us
that Friendsville was between forty
and fifty miles away. After going about
nine miles, we stopped in the evening
of the 18th at an inn, got supper, were
politely served, and had an excellent
night's rest. On the next day we set out
for Tannersville, hiring a conveyance
for twenty-two miles of the way. We
had no further difficulty on the entire
road to Rochester,—more than five
hundred miles by the route we travelled.</p>
            <p>Some amusing incidents occurred,
however, which it may be well to relate
in this connection. The next morning,
after stopping at the tavern, we took
the cars and rode to Homerville, where,
after waiting an hour, as our landlord of
the night previous had directed us, we took
stage. Being the first applicants for
tickets, we secured inside seats, and, from
the number of us, we took up all of the
places inside; but, another traveller
coming, I tendered him mine, and rode
with the driver. The passenger thanked me;
but the driver, a churl, and the most
prejudiced person I ever came in contact
with, would never wait after a stop until I
could get on, but would drive away, and
leave me to swing, climb, or cling on to
the stage as best I could. Our traveller, at
last noticing his behavior, told him
promptly not to be so fast, but let all
passengers get on, which had the effect to
restrain him a little.</p>
            <p>At Big Eddy we took the cars. Directly
opposite me sat a gentleman, who, on
learning that I was for Rochester, said he
was going there too, and afterwards proved
an agreeable travelling-companion.</p>
            <p>A newsboy came in with papers, some
of which the passengers bought. Upon
opening them, they read of the fight at
Christiana.</p>
            <p>“O, see here!” said my neighbor;
“great excitement at Christiana; a—a
statesman killed, and his son and nephew
badly wounded.”</p>
            <p>After reading, the passengers began to
exchange opinions on the case. Some said
they would like to catch Parker, and get
the thousand dollars reward offered by the
State; but the man opposite to me said,
“Parker must be a powerful man.”</p>
            <p>I thought to myself, “If you could tell
what I can, you could judge about that.”</p>
            <p>Pinckney and Johnson became alarmed,
and wanted to leave the cars at the next
stopping-place; but I told them there was
no danger. I then asked particularly about
Christiana, where it was, on what railroad,
and other questions, to all of which I
received correct replies. One of the men
became so much attached to me, that,
when we would go to an eating-saloon, he
would
<pb id="freedman290" n="290"/>
pay for both. At Jefferson we thought of
leaving the cars, and taking the boat;
but they told us to keep on the cars, and
we would get to Rochester by nine o'clock
the next night.</p>
            <p>We left Jefferson about four o'clock in
the morning, and arrived at Rochester at
nine the same morning. Just before
reaching Rochester, when in conversation
with my travelling friend, I ventured to
ask what would be done with Parker,
should he be taken.</p>
            <p>“I do not know,” he replied; “but the
laws of Pennsylvania would not hang him,—
they might imprison him. But it would be
different, very different, should they get
him into Maryland. The people in all the
Slave States are so prejudiced against
colored people, that they never give them
justice. But I don't believe they will get
Parker. I think he is in Canada by this
time; at least, I hope so,—for I believe he
did right, and, had I been in his place, I
would have done as he did. Any good
citizen will say the same. I believe Parker
to be a brave man; and all you colored
people should look at it as we white
people look at our brave men, and do as
we do. You see Parker was not fighting for
a country, nor for praise. He was fighting
for freedom: he only wanted liberty, as
other men do. You colored people should
protect him, and remember him as long as
you live. We are coming near our parting-place,
and I do not know if we shall ever
meet again. I shall be in Rochester some
two or three days before I return home;
and I would like to have your company
back.”</p>
            <p>I told him it would be some time before
we returned.</p>
            <p>The cars then stopped, when he bade
me good by. As strange as it may appear,
he did not ask me my name; and I was
afraid to inquire his, from fear he would.</p>
            <p>On leaving the cars, after walking two
or three squares, we overtook a colored
man, who conducted us to the house of—a
friend of mine. He welcomed me at once,
as we were acquainted before, took me up
stairs to wash and comb, and prepare, as
he said, for company.</p>
            <p>As I was combing, a lady came up and
said, “Which of you is Mr. Parker?”</p>
            <p>“I am,” said I,—“what there is left of
me.”</p>
            <p>She gave me her hand, and said, “And
this is William Parker!”</p>
            <p>She appeared to be so excited that she
could not say what she wished to. We
were told we would not get much rest, and
we did not; for visitors were constantly
coming. One gentleman was surprised that
we got away from the cars, as spies were
all about, and there were two thousand
dollars reward for the party.</p>
            <p>We left at eight o'clock that evening,
in a carriage, for the boat, bound for
Kingston in Canada. As we went on board,
the bell was ringing. After walking about a
little, a friend pointed out to me the
officers on the “hunt” for us; and just as
the boat pushed off from the wharf, some
of our friends on shore called me by
name. Our pursuers looked very much like
fools, as they were. I told one of the
gentlemen on shore to write to Kline that
I was in Canada. Ten dollars were
generously contributed by the Rochester
friends for our expenses; and altogether
their kindness was heartfelt, and was most
gratefully appreciated by us.</p>
            <p>Once on the boat, and fairly out at sea
towards the land of liberty, my mind
became calm, and my spirits very much
depressed at thought of my wife and
children. Before, I had little time to think
much about them, my mind being on my
journey. Now I became silent and
abstracted. Although fond of company,
no one was company for me now.</p>
            <p>We landed at Kingston on the 21st of
September, at six o'clock in the morning,
and walked around for a long time,
without meeting any one we had ever
known. At last, however, I saw a colored
man I knew in Maryland. He at first
pretended to have no knowledge of me,
but finally recognized me. I made known
our distressed condition,
<pb id="freedman291" n="291"/>
when he said he was not going home
then, but, if we would have breakfast, he
would pay for it. How different the
treatment received from this man—himself
an exile for the sake of liberty, and in its
full enjoyment on free soil—and the
self-sacrificing spirit of our Rochester
colored brother, who made haste to
welcome us to his ample home,—the
well-earned reward of his faithful
labors!</p>
            <p>On Monday evening, the 23d, we
started for Toronto, where we arrived
safely the next day. Directly after
landing, we heard that Governor
Johnston, of Pennsylvania, had made a
demand on the Governor of Canada for
me, under the Extradition Treaty.
Pinckney and Johnson advised me to go
to the country, and remain where I should
not be known; but I refused. I
intended to see what they would do with
me. Going at once to the Government
House, I entered the first office I came
to. The official requested me to be
seated. The following is the substance of
the conversation between us, as near as I
can remember. I told him I had heard
that Governor Johnston, of
Pennsylvania, had requested his
government to send me back. At this he
came forward, held forth his hand, and
said, “Is this William Parker?”</p>
            <p>I took his hand, and assured him I
was the man. When he started to
come, I thought he was intending to
seize me, and I prepared myself to knock
him down. His genial, sympathetic
manner it was that convinced me he
meant well.</p>
            <p>He made me sit down, and said, “Yes,
they want you back again. Will you go?”</p>
            <p>“I will not be taken back alive,” said
I. “I ran away from my master to be
free,—I have run from the United States
to be free. I am now going to stop
running.”</p>
            <p>“Are you a fugitive from labor?” he
asked.</p>
            <p>I told him I was.</p>
            <p>“Why,” he answered, “they say you
are a fugitive from justice.” He then
asked me where my master lived.</p>
            <p>I told him, “In Anne Arundel County,
Maryland.”</p>
            <p>“Is there such a county in Maryland?”
he asked.</p>
            <p>“There is,” I answered.</p>
            <p>He took down a map, examined it, and
said, “You are right.”</p>
            <p>I then told him the name of the farm,
and my master's name. Further questions
bearing upon the country towns near, the
nearest river, etc., followed, all of which I
answered to his satisfaction.</p>
            <p>“How does it happen,” he then asked,
“that you lived in Pennsylvania so long,
and no person knew you were a fugitive
from labor?”</p>
            <p>“I do not get other people to keep my
secrets, sir,” I replied. “My brother and
family only knew that I had been a
slave.”</p>
            <p>He then assured me that I would not, in
his opinion, have to go back. Many
coming in at this time on business, I was
told to call again at three o'clock, which I
did. The person in the office, a clerk, told
me to take no further trouble about it,
until that day four weeks. “But you are as
free a man as I am,” said he. When I told
the news to Pinckney and Johnson, they
were greatly relieved in mind.</p>
            <p>I ate breakfast with the greatest relish,
got a letter written to a friend in Chester
County for my wife, and set about
arrangements to settle at or near Toronto.</p>
            <p>We tried hard to get work, but the task
was difficult. I think three weeks elapsed
before we got work that could be called
work. Sometimes we would secure a small
job, worth two or three shillings, and
sometimes a smaller one; worth not more
than one shilling; and these not oftener
than once or twice in a week. We became
greatly discouraged; and, to add to my
misery, I was constantly hearing some
alarming report about my wife and
children. Sometimes they had carried her
back into slavery,—sometimes the
children, and sometimes the entire party.
Then there would come a contradiction. I
was soon so completely worn down by my
fears for them, that I thought, my heart
<pb id="freedman292" n="292"/>
would break. To add to my disquietude, no
answer came to my letters, although I
went to the office regularly every day. At
last I got a letter with the glad news that
my wife and children were safe, and would
be sent to Canada. I told the person
reading for me to stop, and tell them to
send her “right now,”—I could not wait to
hear the rest of the letter.</p>
            <p>Two months from the day I landed in
Toronto, my wife arrived, but without the
children. She had had a very bad time.
Twice they had her in custody; and, a
third time, her young master came after
her, which obliged her to flee before day,
so that the children had to remain behind
for the time. I was so glad to see her that
I forgot about the children.</p>
            <p>The day my wife came, I had nothing
but the clothes on my back, and was in
debt for my board, without any work to
depend upon. My situation was truly
distressing. I took the resolution, and went
to a store where I made known my
circumstances to the proprietor, offering
to work for him to pay for some
necessaries. He readily consented, and I
supplied myself with bedding, meal, and
flour. As I had selected a place before, we
went that evening about two miles into
the country, and settled ourselves for the
winter.</p>
            <p>When in Kingston, I had heard of the
Buxton settlement, and of the Revds. Dr.
Willis and Mr. King, the agents. My
informant, after stating all the particulars,
induced me to think it was a desirable
place; and having quite a little sum of
money due to me in the States, I wrote for
it, and waited until May. It not being sent,
I called upon Dr. Willis, who treated me
kindly. I proposed to settle in Elgin, if he
would loan means for the first instalment.
He said he would see about it, and I should
call again. On my second visit, he agreed
to assist me, and proposed that I should
get another man to go on a lot with me.</p>
            <p>Abraham Johnson and I arranged to
settle together, and, with Dr. Willis's
letter to Mr. King on our behalf, I
embarked with my family on a schooner for
the West. After five days' sailing, we
reached Windsor. Not having the means
to take us to Chatham, I called upon
Henry Bibb, and laid my case before him.
He took us in, treated us with great
politeness, and afterwards took me with
him to Detroit, where, after an
introduction to some friends, a purse of
five dollars was made up. I divided the
money among my companions, and
started them for Chatham, but was
obliged to stay at Windsor and Detroit
two days longer.</p>
            <p>While stopping at Windsor, I went
again to Detroit, with two or three
friends, when, at one of the steamboats
just landed, some officers arrested three
fugitives, on pretence of being horse
thieves. I was satisfied they were slaves,
and said so, when Henry Bibb went to the
telegraph office and learned through a
message that they were. In the crowd and
excitement, the sheriff threatened to
imprison me for my interference. I felt
indignant, and told him to do so,
whereupon he opened the door. About
this time there was more excitement, and
then a man slipped into the jail, unseen
by the officers, opened the gate, and the
three prisoners went out, and made their
escape to Windsor. I stopped through
that night in Detroit, and started the next
day for Chatham, where I found my
family snugly provided for at a boarding-house
kept by Mr. Younge.</p>
            <p>Chatham was a thriving town at that
time, and the genuine liberty enjoyed by
its numerous colored residents pleased me
greatly; but our destination was Buxton,
and thither we went on the following day.
We arrived there in the evening, and I
called immediately upon Mr. King, and
presented Dr. Willis's letter. He received
me very politely, and said that, after I
should feel rested, I could go out and
select a lot. He also kindly offered to give
me meal and pork for my family, until I
could get work.</p>
            <p>In due time, Johnson and I each chose
a fifty-acre lot; for although when in
Toronto we agreed with Dr. Willis to
take one lot between us, when
<pb id="freedman293" n="293"/>
we saw the land we thought we could pay
for two lots. I got the money in a little
time, and paid the Doctor back. I built a
house, and we moved into it that same
fall, and in it I live yet.</p>
            <p>When I first settled in Buxton, the
white settlers in the vicinity were much
opposed to colored people. Their
prejudices were very strong; but the
spread of intelligence and religion in the
community has wrought a great change
in them. Prejudice is fast being uprooted;
indeed, they do not appear like the same
people that they were. In a short time I
hope the foul spirit will depart entirely.</p>
            <p>I have now to bring my narrative to a
close; and in so doing I would return
thanks to Almighty God for the many
mercies and favors he has bestowed upon
me, and especially for delivering me out
of the hands of slaveholders, and placing
me in a land of liberty, where I can worship
God under my own vine and fig-tree, with
none to molest or make me afraid. I am also
particularly thankful to my old friends and
neighbors in Lancaster County, Pennsylvania,
to the friends in Norristown, Quakertown,
Rochester, and Detroit, and to Dr. Willis of
Toronto, for their disinterested benevolence
and kindness to me and my family. When
hunted, they sheltered me; when hungry
and naked, they clothed and fed me; and
when a stranger in a strange land, they
aided and encouraged me. May the Lord
in his great mercy remember and bless
them, as they remembered and blessed me.</p>
            <p>The events following the riot at
Christiana and my escape have become
matters of history, and can only be
spoken of as such. The failure of Gorsuch
in his attempt; his death, and the terrible
wounds of his son; the discomfiture and
final rout of his crestfallen associates in
crime; and their subsequent attempt at
revenge by a merciless raid through
Lancaster County, arresting every one
unfortunate enough to have a dark skin,—is all 
to be found in the printed account
of the trial of Castner Hanway
and others for treason. It is true that some
of the things which did occur are spoken
of but slightly, there being good and valid
reasons why they were passed over thus at
that time in these cases, many of which
might be interesting to place here, and
which I certainly should do, did not the
same reasons still exist in full force for
keeping silent. I shall be compelled to let
them pass just as they are recorded.</p>
            <p>But one event, in which there seems no
reason to observe silence, I will introduce
in this place. I allude to the escape of
George Williams, one of our men, and the
very one who had the letters brought up
from Philadelphia by Mr. Samuel Williams.
George lay in prison with the others who
had been arrested by Kline, but was
rendered more uneasy by the number of
rascals who daily visited that place for the
purpose of identifying, if possible, some of
its many inmates as slaves. One day the
lawyer previously alluded to, whose chief
business seemed to be negro-catching, came
with another man, who had employed him
for that purpose, and, stopping in front of
the cell wherein George and old Ezekiel
Thompson were confined, cried out,
“<hi rend="italics">That's</hi> him!” At which the man exclaimed,
“<hi rend="italics">It is, by God! that is him!</hi>”</p>
            <p>These ejaculations, as a matter of
course, brought George and Ezekiel, who
were lying down, to their feet,—the first
frightened and uneasy, the latter stern and
resolute. Some mysterious conversation
then took place between the two, which
resulted in George lying down and covering
himself with Ezekiel's blanket. In the
mean time off sped the man and lawyer to
obtain the key, open the cell, and institute
a more complete inspection. They
returned in high glee, but to their surprise
saw only the old man standing at the door,
his grim visage anything but inviting.
They inserted the key, click went the
lock, back shot the bolt, open flew the
door, but old Ezekiel stood there firm, his
eyes flashing fire, his brawny hands
flourishing a stout oak stool furnished him
to rest on by friends of whom I
<pb id="freedman294" n="294"/>
have so often spoken, and crying out
in the most unmistakable manner, every
word leaving a deep impression on his
visitors, “The first man that puts his head
inside of this cell I will split to pieces.”</p>
            <p>The men leaped back, but soon recovered
their self-possession; and the lawyer
said,—“Do you know who I am? I
am the lawyer who has charge of this
whole matter, you impudent nigger.
I will come in whenever I choose.”</p>
            <p>The old man, if possible looking more
stern and savage than before, replied, “I
don't care who you are; but if you or any
other nigger-catcher steps inside of my
cell-door I will beat out his brains.”</p>
            <p>It is needless to say more. The old
man's fixed look, clenched teeth, and
bony frame had their effect. The man and
the lawyer left, growling as they went,
that, if there was rope to be had, that old
Indian nigger should certainly hang.</p>
            <p>This was but the beginning of poor
George's troubles. His friends were at work;
but all went wrong, and his fate seemed
sealed. He stood charged with treason,
murder, and riot, and there appeared no
way to relieve him. When discharged by
the United States Court for the first crime,
he was taken to Lancaster to meet the
second and third. There, too, the man and
the lawyer followed, taking with them that
infamous wretch, Kline. The Devil seemed
to favor all they undertook; and when
Ezekiel was at last discharged, with some
thirty more, from all that had been so
unjustly brought against him, and for
which he had lain in the damp prison for
more than three months, these rascals
lodged a warrant in the Lancaster jail, and
at midnight Kline and the man who
claimed to be George's owner arrested him
as a fugitive from labor, whilst the lawyer
returned to Philadelphia to prepare the
case for trial, and to await the arrival of
his shameless partners in guilt. This
seemed the climax of George's
misfortunes. He was hurried into a wagon,
ready at the door, and, fearing a rescue,
was driven at a killing pace to the town
of Parkesburg, where they were compelled to
stop for the night, their horses being completely
used up. This was in the month of January,
and the coldest night that had been known
for many years. On their route, these wretches,
who had George handcuffed and tied in the
wagon, indulged deeply in bad whiskey, with
which they were plentifully supplied, and by
the time they reached the public-house their
fury was at its height. 'T is said there is honor
among thieves, but villains of the sort I am
now speaking of seem to possess none. Each
fears the other. When in the bar-room, Kline
said to the other,—“Sir, you can go to sleep.
I will watch this nigger.”</p>
            <p>“No,” replied the other, “I will do
that business myself. You don't fool
me, sir.”</p>
            <p>To which Kline replied, “Take something,
sir?”—and down went more whiskey.</p>
            <p>Things went on in this way awhile,
until Kline drew a chair to the stove,
and, overcome by the heat and liquor,
was soon sleeping soundly, and, I
suppose, dreaming of the profits which
were sure to arise from the job. The other
walked about till the barkeeper went to
bed, leaving the hostler to attend in his
place, and he also, somehow or other,
soon fell asleep. Then he walked up
to George, who was lying on a bench,
apparently as soundly asleep as any of
them, and, saying to himself, “The
damn nigger is asleep,—I'll just take a
little rest myself,”—he suited the action
to the word. Spreading himself out on
two chairs, in a few moments he was
snoring at a fearful rate. Rum, the
devil, and fatigue, combined, had
completely prostrated George's foes. It
was now his time for action; and, true to
the hope of being free, the last to leave
the poor, hunted, toil-worn bondsman's
heart, he opened first one eye, then the
other, and carefully examined things
around. Then he rose slowly, and, keeping
step to the deep-drawn snores of the
miserable, debased wretch who claimed
him, he stealthily crawled towards the
door, when, to his consternation, he
<pb id="freedman295" n="295"/>
found the eye of the hostler on him.
He paused, knowing his fate hung by a
single hair. It was only necessary for the
man to speak, and he would be shot
instantly dead; for both Kline and his
brother ruffian slept pistol in hand. As
I said, George stopped, and, in the softest
manner in which it was possible for
him to speak, whispered, “A drink of
water, if you please, sir.” The man
replied not, but, pointing his finger to
the door again, closed his eyes, and
was apparently lost in slumber.</p>
            <p>I have already said it was cold; and, in
addition, snow and ice covered the
ground. There could not possibly be a
worse night. George shivered as he
stepped forth into the keen night air.
He took one look at the clouds above,
and then at the ice-clad ground below.
He trembled; but freedom beckoned, and
on he sped. He knew where he was,—the
place was familiar. On, on, he pressed,
nor paused till fifteen miles lay between
him and his drunken claimant; then he
stopped at the house of a tried friend to
have his handcuffs removed; but, with
their united efforts, one side only could
be got off, and the poor fellow, not
daring to rest, continued his journey,
forty odd miles, to Philadelphia, with
the other on. Frozen, stiff, and sore, he
arrived there on the following day, and
every care was extended to him by his
old friends. He was nursed and attended
by the late Dr. James, Joshua Gould
Bias, one of the faithful few, whose labors
for the oppressed will never be forgotten,
and whose heart, purse, and hand were
always open to the poor, flying slave.
God has blessed him, and his reward is
obtained.</p>
            <p>I shall here take leave of George,
only saying, that he recovered and
went to the land of freedom, to be safe
under the protection of British law. Of the
wretches he left in the <hi rend="italics">tavern</hi>, much might
be said; but it is enough to know that they
awoke to find him gone, and to pour
their curses and blasphemy on each other.
They swore most frightfully; and the
disappointed Southerner threatened to blow
out the brains of Kline, who turned his
wrath on the hostler, declaring he should be
taken and held responsible for the loss.
This so raised the ire of that worthy, that,
seizing an iron bar that was used to fasten
the door, he drove the whole party from
the house, swearing they were damned
kidnappers, and ought to be all sent after
old Gorsuch, and that he would raise the
whole township on them if they said one
word more. This had the desired effect.
They left, not to pursue poor George, but
to avoid pursuit; for these worthless
man-stealers knew the released men
brought up from Philadelphia and
discharged at Lancaster were all in the
neighborhood, and that nothing would
please these brave fellows—who had patiently
and heroically suffered for long and weary
months in a felon's cell for the cause of human
freedom—more than to get a sight at them; and
Kline, he knew this well,—particularly old
Ezekiel Thompson, who had sworn by his
heart's blood, that, if he could only get hold
of that Marshal Kline, he should kill him
and go to the gallows in peace. In fact, he
said the only thing he had to feel sorry
about was, that he did not do it when he
threatened to, whilst the scoundrel stood
talking to Hanway; and but for Castner
Hanway he would have done it, anyhow.
Much more I could say; but short stories
are read, while long ones are like the
sermons we go to sleep under.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>