<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY coxtp SYSTEM "coxtp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="Slave Narratives" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>Narrative of Dimmock Charlton, a British Subject, Taken from 
the Brig “Peacock”  by the U.S. Sloop
“Hornet,” Enslaved while a Prisoner of War, and Retained 
Forty-Five Years in Bondage:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <editor role="editor">Cox, Mary L. and Susan H. Cox, ed. by</editor>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Lee Ann Morawski</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Image scanned by</resp>
          <name>Ingrid Pohl</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Chris Hill and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>2000</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca.  70K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>2000.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal
 use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="title page"> Narrative of Dimmock Charlton, A British Subject, Taken from the Brig
 “Peacock” by the U. S. Sloop “Hornet,” Enslaved while a 
Prisoner of War, and Retained Forty-Five Years in Bondage.</title>
            <editor role="editor">Mary L. and Susan H. Cox</editor>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>  15  p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
            <date>1859</date>
            <authority/>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="yes"> Harvard University Library provided the text for the electronic publication 
of this title.</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>All footnotes are inserted at the point of reference within paragraphs.</p>
        <p>This electronic edition has been transcribed from a photocopy supplied by the Harvard University Library.</p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and 
Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Charlton, Dimmock, b. ca. 1801.</item>
            <item>Blacks -- Africa -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Georgia -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Hornet (Sloop)</item>
            <item>Peacock (Brig)</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2001-02-09, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2000-03-31, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2000-03-13, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Chris Hill</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2000-03-12, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Lee Ann Morawski</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="title page image">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="coxtp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">NARRATIVE<lb/>
of<lb/>
DIMMOCK CHARLTON,<lb/>
A BRITISH SUBJECT, 
<lb/><hi rend="italic">Taken from the Brig “Peacock” by the U. S. Sloop “Hornet,”</hi><lb/>
ENSLAVED WHILE A PRISONER OF WAR,<lb/>
AND RETAINED<lb/>
FORTY-FIVE YEARS IN BONDAGE.</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
      </titlePage>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="main body">
        <pb id="char1" n="1"/>
        <head>DIMMOCK CHARLTON.</head>
        <div2 rend="italic" type="chapter">
          <head>A DEFENCE.</head>
          <p>In the <hi rend="italic">Anti-Slavery Standard</hi> of Nov. 27th, 1858, a tissue of 
charges of the most severe and crushing character appeared, 
entitled “a caution,” respecting a colored man, a native 
African, styled John Bull. This name was given him by his 
British captors of the Peacock, in 1812, who took the Spanish 
slaver into which he was thrust, when first kidnapped from 
Sierra Leone, his native home. In the engagement with the 
Hornet, he became a prisoner of the United States, and was 
fraudulently retained as a slave, when demanded in the 
exchange of British prisoners, and with wilful falsehood 
reported dead of a fever. A series of gross injustice baffled 
every effort for freedom, and continued his slavery from 
youth to grey hairs; and he has but recently recovered his 
liberty, after 45 years of bondage in its most aggravated 
forms. Soon after the publication of the above named 
“caution,” a <hi rend="italic">most respectful appeal</hi> was made to the Editors 
of the <hi rend="italic">Anti-Slavery Standard</hi>, requesting them to reexamine 
the source of these charges. A minute account was also given 
of the CAUSES of the misrepresentation, and with the assurance 
that there was no intention on the part of his friends to 
screen him, if they should be found true. But, if on a fair 
review of the whole subject the charges proved to be without 
just foundation, his friends united with him in claiming an 
honorable acquittal, so far as the same press can produce it, 
which has been made the organ of injury to his character. 
Such expressions as these, “being wanting in principle,” 
“unwilling to work,” “collecting money in Philadelphia <hi rend="italic">under 
various false pretences,</hi>” &amp;c. Certainly his appeal for the 
emancipation of his wife, a free woman of Nassau,<ref id="ref1" n="1" rend="sc" target="note1" targOrder="U">*</ref> 
<note id="note1" n="1" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref1"><p>*Is there 
no method by which this fact, which can be well established 
may be made to give freedom to herself and her descendants, 
now in bondage? LEGAL justice would cause their fetters to 
fall.</p></note> in the British Isle of Providence, West Indies, and her 
four children and grandchildren, now in slavery, were <hi rend="italic">not</hi> 
“false pretences,” but facts fully confirmed<corr sic="no punctuation">.</corr> During his 
residence in this city since October last, he has applied to 
the friends of humanity for aid and employment, to assist him 
in obtaining his earnest wish, the freedom of his family in 
the South—ten persons in all—one grandchild, brought 
to New York by those holding her as a slave, has been 
liberated there by legal measures. Her freedom being 
established, he removed her to Canada, to prevent what he 
feared, her re-capture. This he accomplished with written 
as well as verbal authority, from two of the most respectable 
Attorneys in New York, John Jay and Charles E. Whitehead, 
they giving him the full assurance that he had the <hi rend="italic">sole right</hi> 
to dispose of her. He had steadfastly 
<pb id="char2" n="2"/>
declined to bind his little girl to one of the members of the 
Anti-Slavery Society, who had been interested in her 
emancipation, and this decision, and his removal of her to 
Canada, his eminent lawyer, John Jay, declares he believes to 
be the only charge they have against him. Can we wonder, 
after such sad experience, at his unwillingness to put any 
chain upon her newly enfranchised form and soul? They say he 
threatened to shoot a colored man sent to prevent his 
removing her—if he dared to lay a hand upon her. This he 
freely acknowledges, as prompted by his agony, and which he 
does not defend as right. He says, “I am sorry, but I was 
provoked;” he might have said, tortured at the thought of 
her being again in bonds.</p>
          <p>It will be only necessary here to add that his course in 
Philadelphia has been under strict observance of those make 
this appeal and defence. They are willing to show any 
inquirers who wish an honest explanation, the grounds of this 
attempt to vindicate his claim to sympathy and respect. His 
statements in this city, so far from being “<hi rend="italic">various false 
pretences,</hi>” are substantiated by respectable authority, and 
his character given by a gentleman who says, “I have known 
him for 30 years, ever since I was a boy, and I never knew a 
man more injured by being deprived of his liberty and the 
fruits of his toil, after the contracts for his freedom were, 
on his part, faithfully fulfilled. He was always sober, 
industrious, peaceable and polite.” This is briefly his warm 
and sympathetic language, given to us personally.</p>
          <p>No response being given by the Anti-Slavery Editors, the 
injured man feels compelled to make this statement in 
contradiction to their “caution,” in which they say they were 
requested “by his Philadelphia friends to denounce him.” We 
have no idea that such measures would be endorsed by the 
noble-minded friends of freedom in the Anti-Slavery Society, 
if they were acquainted with the particulars which “his 
friends in Philadelphia” have sought to place before them. 
There is one individual—the only one known to them who 
could have made such a request, whose statement in his own 
hand-writing, is, with other documents, retained as testimony 
that he threatened thus to publish him, and this, 
notwithstanding the kindest remonstrance and explanation on 
his part, previously given in the presence of his friends, 
who used their efforts also, and took all the blame from the 
accused, showing where the offence originated, and that no 
injury was done or intended.</p>
          <p>The charge against the accused was that he was going about 
injuring his character, and retaining a paper of 
recommendation from him of which he demanded the return. Of 
both these charges he was entirely innocent. An Anti-Slavery 
lady, of England, thought proper to call upon this person, 
whose name we omit, to expostulate with him on account of the 
charge he had made for board and washing for the accused. 
This was entirely her own act of kindness, not only 
unprompted, but without the knowledge of his other friends or 
himself. She had received the information in reply to her 
interrogatories of his expenses and the means of his support, 
without a word or look of complaint.</p>
          <p>As to the paper it was detained by THE UNDERSIGNED, to show 
to some friends as references, the inconsistency of charging 
the persecuted man with want of truth, and being an imposter 
as to his family being slaves, when the sole tenor of <hi rend="italic">this</hi> 
paper, dated the 19th of October, was to confirm <hi rend="italic">his</hi> 
identity, with the individual in the printed documents from 
the New York <hi rend="italic">Standard,</hi> and also from his British friends. 
After sending him with this paper to us, he came himself to
<pb id="char3" n="3"/>
manifest his interest in getting a pamphlet published and 
money subscribed, and <hi rend="italic">at the time</hi> he sent it, it was 
accompanied by his note requesting our efforts in his behalf. 
A few days, perhaps not more than a week elapsed, till this 
well meant expostulation of the English lady, changed the 
whole current of his proceedings. When we expostulated with 
him as to the date of this paper which he wished to recall 
before we had made it serve as a reference to vindicate the 
accused, we asked why did he send him to us as a person 
worthy of sympathetic aid, if certain letters which he then 
produced from New York, against him, were then in his 
possession, and which he now claimed an authority against him. 
He at first attempted to represent that they were not then 
received; he afterwards, when the dates were shown him as 
four and five days previous, said “the truth was because I 
placed no confidence in the charges they contained.” Now 
these, with further discrepancies, are <hi rend="italic">only narrated</hi> or 
retained for the removal of aspersions, which must crush his 
efforts to support himself, and to liberate his beloved and 
suffering family. That these particulars are reluctantly 
given in this form, will be evident to all who may read the 
statement presented before the close of last year, to the 
Editors in New York, the pacific tone and forbearing 
expostulations of which, we think, with the exigencies of the 
can, demanded a reply, other than silence.</p>
          <closer><signed>Mary L. &amp; Susan H. Cox.</signed>
S. E. cor. of Race and 7th Sts., opposite Franklin Square.<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Philada.,</hi> 5 <hi rend="italic">mo.</hi> 7<hi rend="italic">th,</hi> 1859.</closer>
          <closer>N. B.—Robert C. Beatty, Cashier of the Bank of Bristol, 
Penns., gives his name as a reference. During the temporary 
residence of his family in this city, thro' the past winter, 
he had with them an opportunity of knowing the injured man, 
and <hi rend="italic">his</hi> name was <hi rend="italic">one</hi> of 
<hi rend="italic">six signatures</hi> appended to the appeal 
to the Editors in New York. No application was made for more 
names, or, unquestionably, they might have been obtained, and 
of equal respectability.</closer>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head>From the New York Times.</head>
          <p>The history of Solomon Northrup—a free citizen of New 
York, who spent many years in Southern Slavery—is fresh 
in the memory of our readers. We yesterday heard narrated 
another slave history rivalling it in interest, though in 
many respects of it very different character. The subject of 
it is a venerable and intelligent native African, recently 
arrived here from Savannah, Georgia, where he was known as 
DIMMOCK CHARLTON, and served more than forty years as the 
slave of various parties, while he claims to have been a 
British subject, and entitled to British protection. The 
man's face is an honest one, and his integrity and 
reliability are so well vouched for that it would be found 
difficult to doubt or discredit his story. Indeed, he tells 
it in so straightforward, frank and simple a manner as to 
carry conviction with it. Although utterly uneducated, unable 
even to read or write, he displays a degree of intelligence 
and an amount of sagacity, sound sense and native shrewdness 
which would do no discredit to his former masters, however 
great their opportunities for mental
<pb id="char4" n="4"/>
culture. We propose to give his history as received from his 
own lips, trusting that it will not only interest the reader, 
but that it may stimulate efforts among the philanthropic to 
crown with well deserved happiness the declining years of 
this dark-skinned hero, by restoring to freedom those of his 
family who are still held in servitude.</p>
          <p>Our subject is now, as near as he can judge, 57 or 58 years 
of age, a native of Kissee, peopled by a tribe of the same 
name, settled on one of the great rivers in the interior of 
Africa—or, as he expresses it, “away up on the fresh 
water.” His name was TALLEN at that time. When 9 or 10 years 
of age, war was declared against his tribe by the Mandingos, 
who captured Kissee, and took its inhabitants prisoners of 
war. TALLEN, with six other boys of about the same age were 
a mile or so from the town at the time of the battle, but 
were pursued and taken prisoners. This, as well as he can 
calculate, was in 1811 or 1812. The prisoners of which there 
were a large number, were all sent down to the Coast, sold 
to a slave dealer, and stowed away with hundreds of other 
unfortunates on board a Spanish slaver. The distance they 
traveled in reaching the seashore may be estimated from the 
fact that the journey occupied about four weeks.</p>
          <p>The slaver put to sea with its human cargo, who began to 
suffer the horrors of the middle passage, many of them dying 
for want of fresh air and exercise during the three weeks 
they were stowed away in her suffocating “between decks.” At 
the end of this time the slaver was chased and captured by an 
English war-brig, but TALLEN does not remember the name of 
either of the vessels. The prize and her cargo were taken to 
England, where the Africans generally were sent ashore until 
they could be properly disposed of. TALLEN, however, who had 
meantime been christened “John Bull” on board the British 
vessel, was sent to the British brig <hi rend="italic">Peacock</hi>, to serve as 
cabin-boy. Several of the captured Spanish sailors were also 
transferred to that vessel. At this time the war between the 
United States and Great <sic corr="Britain">Britian</sic> was in progress, and sometime 
afterward the <hi rend="italic">Peacock</hi> was engaged in action by the little 
American schooner <hi rend="italic">Hornet,</hi> commanded by the gallant captain 
LAWRENCE, which, as will be remembered, speedily put her in a 
sinking condition, and forced his crew to surrender. This was 
on the 24th of February, 1813.</p>
          <p>Subsequently our hero was sent to Savannah, Ga., in charge of 
Lieut. WM. HENRY HARRISON, from whence the latter was to take 
him to Washington. Judge CHARLTON, of Savannah, proposed to 
HARRISON to leave TALLEN, or “John Bull,” with him, promising 
that he would raise him for HARRISON. The latter declined, 
relating the particulars of his history, and saying that he 
must take the boy as a prisoner of war to Washington, and let 
Congress decide what should be done with him, adding, as his 
own supposition, that he would follow the fortunes of the 
other prisoners in all respects. Judge CHARLTON then proposed 
to keep the boy with him until he should be wanted at 
Washington, promising Lieut. HARRISON that he would send him 
on whenever he should write for him.</p>
          <p>With this understanding, HARRISON left the boy with Judge 
CHARLTON. Two months afterward, HARRISON sent for “John 
Bull,” and CHARLTON replied that the boy had died—which 
of course ended the Lieutenant's interest in and care for 
him. The authority for this statement was Judge CHARLTON'S 
waiting-man or body servant, an old man named ISAAC, of whom 
John speaks in high
<pb id="char5" n="5"/>
terms. About the time this word was sent to Washington, 
CHARLTON called all his servants together and forbade them 
strictly ever to call TALLEN “John Bull” again, but ordered 
them to call him DIMMOCK CHARLTON, after—himself by which 
name he has since been known.</p>
          <p>The very next day after this <sic corr="occurrence">occurence</sic>, CHARLTON sold him to 
a French tailor of Savannah, named JOHN P. SETZ, who is still 
living at Augusts, Ga. He was sent down to SETZ's house in 
the morning, and staid there all day, but at night expressed 
his intention of “going home.” SETZ told him no,—to stay 
where he was, that he belonged to him now. DIMMOCK, as we 
shall now call him, replied, asserting that he was a free man 
and could not be sold. SETZ, in answer, said that CHARLTON 
bought clothes of him, and gave DIMMOCK in payment, and again 
ordered him to stay where he was and go to work. The boy 
attempted to run away, but SETZ caught and brought him back. 
Being sent down into the kitchen, he slipped out of the back 
door, went to CHARLTON'S and asked if he had sold him. The 
Judge replied in the negative. Just then SETZ, in pursuit, 
came into the house, and seized the boy to drag him off. 
CHARLTON interfered, took SETZ one side, had a short talk 
with him, and then told DIMMOCK that he wanted him to go and 
learn the tailor's trade with the Frenchman. Having become 
alarmed at the proceedings, he positively refused to stir a 
step, unless dragged away by force.</p>
          <p>CHARLTON then told SETZ that he had better take the boy away 
from the city. This information also was derived from the 
waiting-man ISAAC. As the Frenchman had a store in Augusta, 
he took DIMMOCK there. Thirteen months later he sold him to 
Captain DUBOIS, who was commander of the <hi rend="italic">Pulaski</hi> at the time 
of her wreck. At that time he commanded the steamer <hi rend="italic">Samuel 
Howard,</hi> but was building <hi rend="italic">General Washington,</hi> to run between 
Savannah and Augusta, and bought DIMMOCK to go on board of 
her as steward. After living with Captain DUBOIS two years, 
the latter sold him to Captain DAVIDSON, of Savannah, who, in 
turn, sold him to one WM. ROBINSON, of the same city. DIMMOCK's 
superior intelligence showed him that by hiring his time of 
his master, and working for himself, he could save money to 
purchase back the freedom of which he had been robbed. He 
formed his plans accordingly, and put them in execution, 
finding employment as a superintending stevedore, and earning 
liberal wages in loading cotton for export, at which he seems 
to have been very successful. He arranged with ROBINSON to 
purchase himself at the price of $800. This he soon saved by 
hard work and economy, paid the entire sum <sic corr="in">in in</sic> cash, and 
was then immediately sent to jail and kept there until his 
cruel master had found a purchaser to take him off his hands.</p>
          <p>His next master proved to be JAMES CARR, then and now 
employed in the Planters' Bank of Savannah. DIMMOCK ventured 
to express to CARR the hope that he would not serve him as 
ROBINSON had, and related how villainously he had been used 
by him. CARR replied that ROBINSON was a d——d scoundrel,
but that he would deal justly with him. Thus encouraged, 
DIMMOCK again hired his time, and proceeded to toil once more 
for liberty, agreeing with CARR that he should have the 
privilege of purchasing himself at the price which was paid 
to ROBINSON, which he supposed was $700. At the time of his 
purchase by ROBINSON, he carried the latter $300, and four 
months latter gave him $400 more. Subsequently, he ascertained from ROBINSON that all CARR paid <hi rend="italic">him</hi> was $450. Thus was the poor follow 
again swindled out of the gold for which he had toiled so 
faithfully.</p>
          <pb id="char6" n="6"/>
          <p>In the meantime he had married a slave woman [a free woman 
of Nassau, Providence Isle in the West Indies, enslaved by 
T. Pratt, senior, who took her and her parents and sisters to 
Savannah,] by whom he had two daughters. These all belonged 
to Mr. PRATT, of Savannah, of whom DIMMOCK speaks very 
gratefully. PRATT finding that he would be compelled to sell 
his servants told DIMMOCK, and said he would sell them 
reasonably to enable him to get some one to buy them who 
would not send them off. Not having yet learned that his 
master had deceived him, DIMMOCK went to CARR, told him the 
case, and solicited his aid to buy his wife and children, 
telling him that he had some little money,—that it would 
probably cost $2,000 to make the purchase, and that he would 
soon give him the balance. At this time he had $1,500, earned 
in stevedoring, hid away dollar by dollar in a tin case 
buried in the earth. This sum he carried to CARR, who 
purchased the family.</p>
          <p>When he met Mr. PRATT afterwards, DIMMOCK learned that he had 
sold the woman and children for $600 only, and had received 
that sum from CARR and no more, supposing that he was giving 
the difference between it and their actual value, to the 
husband and father. Upon his asking CARR what he had done 
with the $900 balance, the later laughed, told DIMMOCK that 
he had the money in Bank for him, and to say nothing to 
anybody, that he and his family were all free now, but to 
keep it to themselves, and live quietly with him. Thinking 
they were in reality free, and could not be sent off again 
among strangers at any man's will, which was what they most 
dreaded, DIMMOCK and his wife remained under CARR'S 
“protection,” quite contented for many years. Finally, by 
representations made to his wife, CARR caused a separation 
between the parties, and then sold the father to Mr. HUDSON, 
of Savannah, the wife to Mr. CUMMINGS, and the children,—
of whom there were now several,—each to a different 
purchaser, thus almost hopelessly breaking up the family.</p>
          <p>To this time DIMMOCK had carefully concealed from his makers 
his claim to liberty as a British subject. He foresaw that 
if it became known to them, they would be likely to sell him 
off into the interior somewhere, and that then he might bid 
farewell to all thought of ever regaining his liberty. So 
long as he could keep in a seaport like Savannah, he knew he 
could earn and save money, and then his chance of making good 
his claim to British protection would always be better than 
if upon an interior plantation isolated from the busy world. 
But when he found his family broken up, and all of them again 
in slavery, his heart was crushed, and he became reckless. He 
had repeatedly sought the protection of the British Consul at 
Savannah, Mr. MOLYNEAUX, but that <sic>functuary</sic> refused to 
interfere in his behalf, apparently fearing to do so, and 
probably looking upon slavery as a very satisfactory 
<sic corr="condition">condiiion</sic> for a man with a black skin—a theory which he 
illustrated by himself holding slaves. When HUDSON bought 
him, DIMMOCK asserted his right to freedom, and told him his 
story. HUDSON evidently was satisfied with the truth of his 
statement, and consequently that he was very insecure 
property to <hi rend="italic">hold;</hi> so he sent him to a trader for sale. Mr. 
DAVIDSON, a liquor dealer near the market in Savannah, 
became his purchaser. He lived with him two years, when 
DAVIDSON came to him one day, told him he had heard that he 
claimed to be a British subject, and asked him what were the 
facts. He, too, was convinced of the truth of the singular
history, and immediately sent him again to a slave-dealer, 
for sale at a purchaser's risk. Mr. BENJAMIN GARMAN bought 
him for $550, in order to give
<pb id="char7" n="7"/>
DIMMOCK another opportunity to purchase himself. This was a 
little more than a year ago, since which time the poor fellow 
has returned the purchase money, and a few days since came on 
here in the steamer <hi rend="italic">Alabama,</hi> lest some new device should be 
found to deprive him of the liberty he has been forty-five 
years in pursuit of.</p>
          <p>Among the Spanish sailors captured on board the <hi rend="italic">Peacock,</hi> with 
DIMMOCK, was one named MINGO. Between these two, a lasting 
friendship sprang up, and they have managed to work together 
during all their many years residence in Savannah. A year 
ago, by advice of a friend, DIMMOCK took MINGO before a 
lawyer, who prepared the necessary affidavits setting forth 
the facts, of his capture and his title to recognition as a 
British subject. To this MINGO made oath in due form. A day 
or two afterwards, he was arrested upon the charge of 
drunkenness, and thrown into prison, where he died very 
suddenly and mysteriously. The proofs however, are deemed 
ample to establish DIMMOCK's claim; and his purpose is, if 
possible, to bring suit to recover damages of CARR and others 
for his long detention in Slavery. Whatever means he can 
realize from this source, or from the donations of the 
charitable, he desires to appropriate to the release from 
Slavery of his wife and children and grandchildren. His 
oldest child VIRGINIA, is in Savannah with three children. 
The next, CHRISTIANA, has one child. The third, ELIZABETH, 
has two. Besides these, he has a son who belongs to lawyer 
O'BYRNE, of Savannah, who has befriended DIMMOCK in his 
recent undertakings.</p>
          <p>Since his arrival here, DIMMOCK has called upon the 
Acting-British Consul to make good his title to protection 
as a British subject, with a view to prosecuting his 
oppressors. That official sent him to his counsel, Mr. 
EDWARDS, who discourages him from attempting to do anything 
because the case has laid so long. If there is a statute of 
limitations which deprives a subject of redress for wrong, 
when he has been prevented by force from calling for it 
sooner, the British Government will probably announce the 
fact when this case is brought fairly before them. That 
DIMMOCK CHARLTON is entitled to redress from some quarter 
is certain—and the question remains for practical 
decision who is responsible for it. Either the government of 
the United States or that of Great <sic corr="Britain">Britian</sic> is bound by every 
consideration of humanity and justice to see that he receives 
some compensation for his life of oppression and cruel wrong.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head>From the Anti-Slavery Reporter.</head>
          <p>We venture too crave the attention of our friends to the 
following tale of a slave. It is extracted from the columns 
of the <hi rend="italic">National Anti-Slavery Standard,</hi> and we will, in due 
place, complete the history.</p>
          <p>“The fact was briefly stated, in last week's <hi rend="italic">Standard,</hi> of the 
freedom of a little girl, held as a slave, having been 
secured under a writ of <hi rend="italic">Habeas Corpus,</hi> before Judge 
Robertson, in West Chester county; and a promise was given 
that the details relating both to the child and its 
grandfather, who appeared on its behalf, should be given in a 
future number. We redeem the promise, in the hope that the 
story may be as interesting and instructive to our readers as 
it has been to ourselves.</p>
          <pb id="char8" n="8"/>
          <p>“Several weeks ago a black man called upon us to ask for aid 
and advice in getting possession of his grandchild, a little 
girl of five or six years, who, he said, was somewhere in 
this city, under the care of two ladies, sisters, by the name 
of Kerr, and who would, he feared, carry the child back to 
the South and to slavery, whence they had brought her a few 
months before. On inquiring further into his and her history, 
we learned that he had recently arrived hero from Savannah, 
having purchased his freedom of his master, Mr. Benjamin 
Garman; that all his kindred about whom he knew anything, 
wife, children, and grandchildren, were still slaves, except 
only this little one, now in New York, in the possession of 
the Misses Kerr; and that, for his own sake as well as hers, 
he was desirous of securing the child, and placing her where 
her freedom should be beyond the reach of either accident or 
hostile design, and where, by his exertions, he could fulfil 
to her the duties of a parent, and secure for her liberty, at 
any rate, and happiness as far as it should lie in his power.</p>
          <p>“It is hardly necessary to say that this statement was enough 
to enlist the sympathies and command the active exertions of 
any one professing to hold either principle or feeling in 
regard to slavery; but the appeal was irresistible when we 
came to hear from the man's own lips the romantic and 
touching history of his own life. To some of our readers, 
perhaps, this is already familiar, as it was told, at about 
the time we allude to, in a morning paper in this city. We 
have delayed relating it, as the less that was said about it 
publicly, till the fate of the grandchild was decided, the 
better; and we wished, moreover, to hear what contradiction 
or corroboration it might call forth, as undoubtedly it would 
provoke either one or the other within a short period. The 
event has justified the delay, and we are enabled now to 
record the story with more entire confidence than we hardly 
dared feel when we first heard it, while we have the 
satisfaction also of rounding off the tale with the 
successful appeal for the freedom of the child, and her 
restoration to the arms of her grandparent.</p>
          <p>“Dimmock Charlton, for by this name he has been known for 
most of his life, though he has now re-assumed an earlier 
one, is a native of Africa. One would hardly doubt this who 
looks upon his intensely black skin, and listened to his 
broken English, though it may be easy for him to mispronounce 
or the hearer to misapprehend the name by which he calls his 
people. He says, however, that he was born in a country 
called Kissee, on a great river in the interior of Africa—
‘away up on the fresh water.’ He is, he thinks, about 
fifty-eight years old, and he remembers vividly the first 
twelve years of his life, when he was called Tallen, and was 
a wild, untutored. and happy savage, and had never heard of 
Christian men or nations. But then a war broke out between 
his own and a neighboring tribe, and his people were 
conquered, and among the prisoners who were captured and 
driven to the coast to be sold to the slavers was Tallen.</p>
          <p>“They were about thirty days on this journey from Kissee to 
the sea coast; but once there, and they were huddled by 
hundreds, some from the tribe of Kissee and some from other 
tribes equally wretched, on board a Spanish vessel waiting 
for her cargo. Then came a voyage of three weeks—three 
weeks of horror. The little savage from the great ‘fresh 
water’ of Central Africa, who had never heard of civilization, 
and had never been taught to believe in any other God than 
Fetish, took now his first step in that great scheme whereby, 
our Doctors of Divinity teach us, the Heavenly Father is to 
lead his race to the blessed knowledge of Christian light and 
life. He met the horrors of the ‘Middle Passage.’ He 
listened, day and night, to the groans of the dying; he 
suffered the agonies of thirst and suffocation; he saw his 
fellow sufferers taken up to be thrown into the sea, and 
might have envied them the early and easier martyrdom which 
was accepted as their share in the sacrifice for the 
redemption of their race. At the end of three weeks, however, 
the Spaniard was captured by a British cruiser, and she and 
what was left of her human cargo were taken to England. 
Unfortunately Tallen cannot recall, if he ever knew, the 
names of either of these vessels.</p>
          <p>“On his arrival in England a pleasant prospect seemed, for a 
little while, to open 
<pb id="char9" n="9"/>
before him. On the dispersion of the Africans, it fell to his 
lot to be put on board the British brig <hi rend="italic">Peacock</hi> as a cabin 
boy, and that vessel soon after sailed on a cruise. The Dr. 
Southsides, perhaps, will think that it was only returning 
him into the true path of providential redemption that this 
happened to be the cruise in which the <hi rend="italic">Peacock</hi> fell in with 
the American schooner <hi rend="italic">Hornet,</hi> and in the memorable naval 
battle which followed that encounter she struck her flag to 
Captain Lawrence. Tallen or, as he was now called, John Bull, 
a second time in his short career a prisoner of war, was 
brought to this country.</p>
          <p>“Here he fell in charge of Lieut. (afterwards President) 
William Henry Harrison, and for some unexplained reason, was 
taken to Savannah, Ga. In that city he was left with Judge 
Charlton, until he should be ordered to Washington, to be 
disposed of with the other prisoners, the crew of the 
<hi rend="italic">Peacock.</hi> Judge Charlton proposed to <sic corr="Lieut.">Lient.</sic> Harrison that he 
should leave the boy with him to be brought up, but this the 
Lieutenant declined, as being a prisoner he was not within 
his control. Two months subsequently he sent to the Judge for 
his charge, and received for answer that the boy had died of 
the fever. Such was the statement made to John Bull by an old 
servant of Judge Charlton, named Isaac, and subsequent events 
seem to verify it.</p>
          <p>“The Lieutenant, John Bull never new or heard from, again; 
but at about the time that he must, if the statement be true, 
have been sent for to go to Washington, and when the Judge 
returned him as dead of fever, he—the Judge—called 
together his servants, and announced to them that it was his 
pleasure that hereafter the boy should no longer be known as 
‘John Bull,’ but thence forward be called by that same which 
belonged to himself; and he incited them to remember his 
orders by that incentive which slaveholders usually supply to 
their slaves—the threat of the cowhide. Thereafter ‘John 
Bull’ was known only as Dimmock Charlton, and by that name he 
has gone ever since.</p>
          <p>“As Judge Charlton was, during his lifetime, a very well 
known person, a man of high standing and great respectability, 
a lawyer of some eminence, an author of one or two law books, 
and one against whom we, at least, never heard any thing 
worse than that he published a volume of most dreary rhymes, 
it may seem incredible that he could be guilty of so 
despicable a crime as is here laid to his charge.<ref id="ref2" n="2" rend="sc" target="note2" targOrder="U">*</ref> <note id="note2" n="2" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref2"><p>*Judge 
Charlton was very intemperate.</p></note> But we must remember that the 
act is to be measured by the code of slaveholding morality, 
and not by that which obtains in more civilized communities. 
It might, indeed, be argued that man who steal men from 
themselves—the original owners—would not be very 
scrupulous in stealing from each other, were it not that the 
universal principle of ‘honor among thieves’ would operate as 
a sufficient restraint in a state of society where its 
infringement would lead to the wildest confusion. But in the 
case of this ‘John Bull’ there need enter no such 
consideration. He, according to the code which <sic corr="prevails">provails</sic> among 
our Southern brethren, belonged to nobody—was a mere waif 
and <sic>estray</sic> which the fortunes or war had landed upon our 
shores, from the coast of Africa, and anybody might pick it 
up who would be at the trouble. Some consideration, perhaps, 
might be due to Lieutenant Harrison, but he had no claim upon 
the property, as property, but simply upon the man as a 
prisoner. If discharged of his duty to him, in that regard, 
he had nothing further to do with him; and if persuaded of 
the truth of that convenient fiction, that the boy was dead, 
all remonstrance from him would be avoided; Judge Charlton 
would, in an easy way, be so much the richer, to the value of 
this particular piece of goods; nobody would lose anything 
except the Government, whose loss of a prisoner, who might be 
a burthen, would be a gain, and the poor boy himself would 
have somebody to take care of him. So, perhaps, reasoned the 
Judge; so, at least, only could he reason to any sort of 
self-justification. At any rate, he took care of the poor 
African by giving him his own name, and selling him the next 
day to a Frenchman.</p>
          <pb id="char10" n="10"/>
          <p>“The Frenchman's name was John P. Setz, and he is still 
living in Augusta, Ga. Dimmock, when told that he belonged to 
him, protested, as was natural enough in an untutored and 
heathen African, not yet made acquainted by any Savannah 
divine with the good things God had in store for his native 
land, nor what his particular share was to be in that great 
scheme of Christianization, that he was nobody's slave, but a 
freeman. Setz, on the other hand, condescending to reason on 
the subject, asserted that the Judge, Dimmock's late master, 
owed him—Setz was a tailor—for a bill of clothes, and 
that the boy was transferred for the value thereof. An appeal 
was made to the Judge. He denied to Dimmock that he had sold 
him, but had a talk aside with the tailor. The result Dimmock 
soon learned; for the particulars he was indebted to his 
friend Isaac, the Judge's body servant. He was taken by Setz, 
in accordance with the Judge's advice, to Augusta, where, 
about a year after, he sold him to a Mr. Dubois, a steamboat 
captain. With him he lived two years, and was then sold 
successively, to a Captain Davidson, and then to one Mr. 
Robinson, of Savannah.</p>
          <p>“In the course of these and subsequent years, and successive 
changes of ownership, Dimmock's mind became so far 
enlightened as, if not to reconcile himself to slavery, to 
suggest to him the expediency of recognizing it as his 
inevitable fate, and of finding some other way of escaping 
from it than merely protesting against it. He hired his time 
of his master, and being an industrious man, In the course of 
time made money enough in his business, as a stevedore, to 
purchase himself of Robinson, for the sum of eight hundred 
dollars. This man had no sooner received the money than he 
sent him to jail, and kept him there on sale till a new buyer 
was found for him. Here again we may think a sense of honor 
should have restrained this Robinson, as to our Northern 
sense, it might seem that Judge Charlton overstepped the 
boundaries of truth and justice; but the slave code 
distinctly says that a slave can possess nothing, and that 
all that he has, or can earn, belongs to his master. Strictly 
speaking, therefore, the eight hundred dollars, which Dimmock 
hoped would purchase his freedom, belonged to Robinson at any 
rate. To look at the subject in any other light would have 
been were magnanimity and gratuitous generosity in Robinson; 
and he, probably, is not a man who permits himself to be 
carried away by such enthusiastic impulses.</p>
          <p>“The purchaser this time was James Kerr, of Savannah, who 
expressed a great deal of indignation when told by Dimmock of 
the manner in which money had been made out of him by his 
former master. Encouraged by this sympathy, Dimmock again 
commenced the accumulation of a fund for a second purchase of 
his freedom. Kerr agreed to accept as a ransom the sum he had 
himself paid to Robinson, and Dimmock at length put into his 
hands seven hundred dollars, which he supposed was that sum. 
He afterwards learned that he had paid two hundred and fifty 
dollars too much, but of course he had no redress.</p>
          <p>“In the mean time, Dimmock had become a husband and father. A 
Mr. Pratt was the owner of his wife and children, and he 
consented to sell them at a moderate price to any one who 
would hold them for Dimmock till he could redeem them. He had 
at this time paid the price of himself to Kerr, but was not 
aware that that gentleman had quietly taken two hundred and 
fifty dollars more than the stipulated price. He interceded 
with him to become the purchaser of his wife and two 
children, with the understanding that it should be on account 
of the husband and father. Kerr consented and the purchase 
was made—Dimmock putting into his hands $1500, which in 
the course of time he had accumulated from his business, and 
hoarded away in the earth. The sum he supposed Pratt would 
ask was $2000, and this he promised to make good to his <hi rend="italic">kind</hi> 
master. His kind master accepted the trust, and went, as 
Dimmock afterwards ascertained, to Pratt and made the 
purchase for $600. When reproached with this breach of trust, 
and called to account for the balance of $900, he laughingly 
said it was safe in the bank, and gave his written obligation 
for it. This obligation Dimmock put in his trunk, but on one 
occasion, while he was absent from
<pb id="char11" n="11"/>
home, the trunk was broken open and the paper stolen. That 
the paper, alone, was the object of the thief was evident 
from the fact that he did not meddle with fifty dollars which 
laid beside it.</p>
          <p>“For many years Dimmock lived with Kerr, contentedly with his 
family, persuaded that his and their freedom were secure, and 
that they could not be again sold or separated from each 
other. That little money transaction between the man and his 
master was so entirely in accordance with the man's 
experience of its being in the usual way of business between 
white and black folks, that he took no special precaution 
against further knavery, nor even seemed to be aware that 
such precaution was possible. He trusted his master as if he 
had nothing to expect of him but the fairest and most 
generous dealing. But the time came when he was to be 
disabused of any such misapprehensions. At length Kerr sold 
him to one man, his wife to another, and scattered some of 
the children about among various owners. Then it was that 
despair seized him, and he returned again to his original 
assertion, that he was a British subject, and wrongfully held 
in Slavery—a fact about which he had thought for many 
years it was wisest and most prudent to keep silence, lest he 
should be sold into the interior, or to the South, be 
separated for ever from his family, and lose all chance of 
ever regaining his liberty. His story seems to have obtained 
credence. One Hudson, who bought him of Kerr, believed it, 
and, probably considering that he might have made an unsafe
investment, sent him to a trader for sale. A liquor dealer by 
the name of Davidson then bought him, but, on learning his 
story, put him again in the market. Lastly, he was bought by 
Mr. Garman a little more than a year ago, who honestly 
permitted him to purchase himself, and to leave Savannah a 
free man when the price was paid.</p>
          <p>“So strange a tale, when made public, has not been allowed to 
pass uncontradicted. The Savannah papers have declared it to 
be untrue; and a Mr. Fay—a northern man, but a resident 
of Savannah—has, in a letter to the <hi rend="italic">New York Times,</hi> 
avowed his disbelief in some of its essential points. That it 
would be acknowledged as true, however, was not to be 
expected. Those most concerned in it have an obvious and 
direct interest in its disapproval; and these, or some of 
these persons are undoubtedly responsible for the 
contradiction of the Savannah papers. The testimony of Mr. 
Fay may also, possibly, have an interested motive. He is 
known to have befriended Dimmock in Savannah, and being a 
Northern man it is, perhaps, best that he should free himself 
from any suspicion of having been privy to a statement made 
in a Northern paper so damaging to Southern morality and 
honor. But all these contradictions, be it observed, identify 
the man as the person he professes to be—as having been
a slave of some, at least, of the persons mentioned, from 
Judge Charlton down to Mr. Garman; and of having purchased 
himself of the last-named gentleman. His story is thus 
corroborated in some very essential particulars, and 
contradicted only where we can reasonably expect nothing but 
denial. Miss Kerr, moreover, in her testimony before Judge 
Robertson, in the case of the child Ellen, said, <hi rend="italic">she had long 
known that Dimmock claimed to be a British subject, and to 
have been taken a prisoner of war in the brig</hi> Peacock, <hi rend="italic">and 
she believed it to be true.</hi> And this testimony is the more 
important that it was made voluntarily, when there was no 
opportunity for consultation with others who had a direct 
interest in concealing a fact, not only important in itself, 
but one from which the subsequent transactions naturally 
spring. But besides all this there was, according to 
Dimmock's statement, a Spaniard—long resident in 
Savannah, Mingo by name—who was a fellow-prisoner with 
him on board the <hi rend="italic">Peacock,</hi> and ever after a firm friend. This 
man was familiar with the whole story, and, by the advice of 
a friend, he was taken before a magistrate and made affidavit 
to the 
<pb id="char12" n="12"/>
facts within his knowledge. Mingo is dead, but the papers are 
now, as Dimmock believes, in the hands of a certain lawyer in 
Savannah. This gentleman has been written to at different 
times by two different persons, but no reply has been 
received by either of them. If no such papers are in his 
hands, why does he not say so. If there were any, even merely 
negative evidence, that could be produced to disprove a tale 
inculpating so many Southern persons, and especially showing 
so conclusively how utterly destructive slavery is of all 
sense of honor and every dictate of honesty, such evidence, 
we believe, would be eagerly sought for and instantly 
produced.</p>
          <p>“We come now to Ellen, the grandchild. Dimmock believed that 
she was in this city when he arrived, and he was informed, as 
he thought, precisely where, by one who professed to be his 
friend. It was soon ascertained that the information was 
incorrect, and the person was sought for from whom it was 
received. He carefully kept out of the way, however, and 
evidently avoided both Dimmock and a messenger who went with 
him. For the purpose, apparently, of getting rid of them 
both, he gave them another, a second direction, which turned 
out to be as false as the first. All inquiries were baffled, 
and it seemed impossible to get any clue to the child.</p>
          <p>“So matters stood when Dimmock's story appeared in the 
<hi rend="italic">Morning Times</hi>. Whoever had possession of the child would, it 
was supposed, when thus warned of the presence of the 
grandfather, be careful to put her beyond his reach. It was 
afterwards ascertained that the conjecture was well founded, 
as the Misses Kerr left town the morning after the appearance 
of the article in the <hi rend="italic">Times.</hi> Without then knowing this fact, 
however, but little hope was entertained of the recovery of 
Ellen.</p>
          <p>“But, as it happened, that which it was feared would be a 
serious obstacle in the way of the search, turned out to be a 
fortunate incident in aid of it. Information reached us—how, 
 it would not be proper thus publicly to say—but 
information as complete as authentic, and as direct as we 
could possibly wish for, in relation to the Misses Kerr, 
their past movements, their present residence, and their 
plans for the future. Their intentions, we were led to 
believe, were good: their only wish was to secure the 
happiness of the little girl, and to this end they had 
instituted a subscription for the purpose of raising the sum 
of 250 dollars, for which amount, it was said, their brother 
James Kerr, of Savannah, Dimmock's former master, was willing 
to emancipate her. A portion of this sum had already been 
raised, but a <hi rend="italic">quietus</hi> was given to this plan by the 
publication of the story; for the benevolent individuals who 
had been disposed to aid in it were no longer willing to 
contribute to any fund which was to go to Mr. Jas. Kerr, 
whose gains out of the Dimmock Charlton family were thought 
to be already rather in advance of his claims. If the money 
was not raised, however, it was understood that the child was 
not to be returned to him; and as his sisters were not 
supposed to be able to pay such a sum for her freedom, 
however well disposed they might and were believed to be 
toward her, the necessity of taking her from their custody 
was imperative. Mr. John Jay, the District-Attorney for this 
district, his father and grandfather have been before him, of 
all held in or threatened with slavery, was consulted, and it 
was determined that a writ of <hi rend="italic">habeas corpus</hi> be asked of the 
Hon. Wm. H. Robertson, Judge of the County of Westchester.</p>
          <p>“The writ was issued and the parties sought for at Sing-Sing. 
They were only found, however, after a diligent search of an 
entire day, as there were some mistakes of names, which, 
there is some reason to suppose, where put in the way of any 
inquiry that <sic>might might</sic> be made as to the locality of the 
Misses Kerr and <sic corr="their">there</sic> <hi rend="italic">protege,</hi> for the purpose of misleading. 
But they were at last found, and on the 12th inst. a hearing 
was had before Judge Robertson at Katonah. After the usual 
preliminary proceedings, Miss Kerr, who declined to appear by 
counsel, was called as a witness by Mr. Jay, and 
testified as follows:</p>
          <p>“’I reside in Savannah, Georgia; I am the sister of Mr. James 
Kerr, of Savannah;
<pb id="char13" n="13"/>
he is the trustee for myself and my sister; the child Ellen, 
now present in Court, is one of a large family of slaves 
belonging to my brother and sister. I cannot say in whom in 
particular the title to her is vested; I think in my sister, 
Eugenia M. Kerr, who is now staying with me at Mr. David A. 
Griffin's, in the town of Sing Sing. I came on from the South 
the last Spring, arriving in New York about the 14th of 
April; my sister Eugenia was already there, having come on 
last October; I brought Ellen with me with my sister's 
approval, and Ellen has lived with us ever since, at New York 
and Sing Sing; my brother know that Ellen was coming on, and 
approved it; her mother had been sold by my brother, and her 
grandmother neglected her, and we took an interest in her on 
this <sic corr="account;">occount;</sic> Ellen was valued at four hundred dollars; <hi rend="italic">her 
light complexion increased her value;</hi> slaves of that 
complexion <sic corr="usually">usally</sic> make clever servants; my brother consented 
to take three hundred and fifty dollars; the child's 
grandmother has frequently been at the North, and could not 
be persuaded to remain; the mother of Ellen is the youngest 
daughter to Dimmock, who calls himself John Bull; Dimmock 
once belonged to my brother, Mr. James Kerr; Dimmock is now 
free; he was freed by his last Master, Mr. Benjamin Garman—
his price being raised in part by Dimmock himself, and in 
part by contribution; Ellen is about five years and six 
months old; I brought her to the North because I did not know 
what would become of her; I had her entered on our departure 
from Savannah as my slave or servant; my sister and myself 
proposed to remain at the north for an indefinite time—
for several years—visiting the South occasionally; I have 
no wish that the child should be returned to slavery, but I 
did wish to raise the money, that we should not lose her 
whole value; my brother having thrown off fifty dollars, and 
being in embarrassed circumstances, could not afford to throw 
off any more; I am very reluctant to have the child taken 
away from me; I am attached to her, and wish to keep her with 
me; I have already commenced to educate her; her grandfather, 
Dimmock, knows how to read; I long since heard of his having 
been on board of the <hi rend="italic">Peacock</hi> when taken by the <hi rend="italic">Hornet,</hi> and I 
believe that part of his story is true.’</p>
          <p>“Mr. Jay then briefly submitted to the Court that upon the 
evidence there could be no doubt as to the rights of the 
child and law of the case, and moved that she be declared to 
be free. The Judge reviewed the facts and applied the 
statute, and without hesitation granted the motion. He 
remanded the child, however, into the can of the constable 
till Monday, the 17th, as he wished to take time to consider 
the question of guardianship. A good deal of emotion was 
shown by Miss Kerr and the child at parting, the former 
feeling unquestionably a warm interest in one whom she had, 
we hope, the will, though not the power, to protect from 
those who might at any moment return her to bondage, while 
the child only knew in a kind mistress an all-sufficient 
friend.</p>
          <p>“On Monday, the 17th, the case again came up on the question 
of guardianship. Mr. Jay took the ground that the power to 
appoint a guardian did not lie with a County Court, and the 
Judge concurring in this view of the case, signed an order 
for the delivery of the child into the hands of its 
grandfather. A little scene had again to be gone through with 
when she parted from her kind friend, Mr. Hoyt, the 
constable; but she soon forgot her griefs in two happy hours 
in the family of her counsel, who sent her on her way 
rejoicing with more gifts than probably her little hands ever 
clasped before. And she has been ever since among some new 
found friends, as contented and as good a child as if she had 
never known a parting or a change of place.</p>
          <p>“We may as well say, now and here, that the intention is to 
place her in some family, when she will be kindly, 
judiciously, and carefully brought up. If among our readers 
there are any who are disposed to take upon themselves such a 
charge, we shall be glad to hear from them. Ellen is a bright 
mulatto, very intelligent, very tractable, good tempered and 
winning. She cannot fail, we think, to well repay the friends 
who shall be at the trouble of her nurture and education. Any 
letters in regard to her may be addressed to S. H. Gay, at 
this office.”</p>
          <pb id="char14" n="14"/>
          <p>John Bull, otherwise Dimmock Charlton, believing himself to 
be a British subject, or, at any rate, imagining that he had 
some claim to be considered such, having served on board a 
British man-of-war, and been taken prisoner whilst in the 
British service, was anxious to come to England, especially 
as there lacked an important link in the chain of evidence 
necessary to establish his identity. He obtained a letter of 
introduction to Mr. John Cropper of Liverpool from the son of 
Judge Jay, who rescued John Bull's grandchild from Slavery 
under the circumstances narrated above, and was referred to 
us. Fortunately he succeeded, discovering in Greenwich 
Hospital a pensioner who was serving on board the <hi rend="italic">Peacock</hi> at 
the time she was captured. The following is the declaration 
of this important witness:</p>
          <p>“‘I, THOMAS TRETHOWAN, aged 61, native of Kenwen, near 
Truro, in the county of Cornwall, formerly an board the 
<hi rend="italic">Peacock,</hi> an English brig of war, and now an inmate of 
Greenwich Hospital, do solemnly and sincerely declare, that
I was serving in the capacity of servant to Captain William 
Peek, commander of the <hi rend="italic">Peacock,</hi> an eighteen gun English brig 
of war, in February, One thousand eight hundred and twelve, 
when she was attacked off the Spanish Main and sunk, by the 
<hi rend="italic">Hornet,</hi> a twenty gun ship, belonging to the United States of
America, and commanded by Captain Lawrence; that I was rated 
as a boy on the ship's books; that there was on board a 
colored boy, who, to the best of my recollection at this 
distance of time, came on board at Demerara; that during the 
engagement he remained in the captain's cabin, which was used 
as a cockpit; that I remember his uttering several shrieks 
when our mainmast fell overboard; that I saw that boy again 
on board the <hi rend="italic">Hornet</hi>—he having been saved with others of 
the <hi rend="italic">Peacock's</hi> crew as she went down; that we were all 
conveyed as prisoners to New York, except the boy aforesaid, 
our colored cook (whose name was Gould,) and an American 
seamen who had been impressed and taken on board the Peacock. 
That I heard, when in prison, that these three <sic corr="persons">per-</sic> had been 
conveyed away South, and that the boy was going to be taken 
to a place in Georgia they called Savannah; that from the 
conversations I have had with the colored man, John Bull, 
otherwise Dimmock Charlton, and from the answers he has 
returned to the questions I have put to him I firmly believe 
him to be the same individual who came on board the <hi rend="italic">Peacock</hi> 
at Demerara, was on board of her when she was sunk, and was 
taken to New York, and thence conveyed to Savannah in 
Georgia. And I make this solemn Declaration, conscientiously 
believing the same to be true; and by virtue of the 
provisions of an Act made and passed in the sixth year of the 
reign of His Majesty King William the Fourth, <sic corr="entitled">intituled</sic> An 
Act to repeal an Act of the present session of Parliament,
<sic corr="intitled">intituled</sic> An Act for the more effectual abolition of oaths 
and affirmations taken and made in various departments of the 
State, and to substitute declarations in lieu thereof, and 
for the more entire suppression of voluntary and 
extra-judicial oaths and affidavits, and to make other 
provisions for the abolition of unnecessary oaths. </p>
          <signed>“THOMAS TRETHOWAN.</signed>
          <closer>“Declared at the Mansion House, in the City of London, this 
tenth day of December 1857, before me,</closer>
          <signed>“WILLIAM CUBITT. Alderman.”</signed>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <pb id="char15" n="15"/>
          <p>[The following testimonials are appended in support of 
Dimmock Charlton's good character. For obvious reasons the 
signature to the last one is omitted. Many others are in his 
possession, voluntarily given by those who had known him in 
Savannah, Ga., New York, London, Eng., and other places:]</p>
          <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
            <text>
              <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
                  <opener>
                    <dateline>51 PINE STREET, NEW YORK,
<date>November 17th, 1859.</date></dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I have known John Bull, alias Dimmock Charlton, for about 
eighteen months, and from all I have seen of him, believe him 
to be an honest, sober man, and that a life of hardships and 
sufferings, gives him some claim upon the benevolent.</p>
                  <closer>
                    <signed>N. SANDS.</signed>
                  </closer>
                </div1>
              </body>
            </text>
          </q>
          <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
            <text>
              <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
                  <opener>
                    <dateline>20 NASSAU STREET, N. Y.,
<date>July 15th, 1858.</date></dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>JOHN BULL—<hi rend="italic">Dear Sir</hi>—You have a perfect right to take 
your child where you please, without the consent of any one. 
There is no one but yourself to have any right over her. </p>
                  <closer><salute>Yours, &amp;c.,</salute>
<signed>CHAS. E. WHITEHEAD.</signed></closer>
                </div1>
              </body>
            </text>
          </q>
          <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
            <text>
              <body>
                <div1 type="letter">
                  <opener>
                    <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, <date>January 20th, 1858.</date></dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I hereby certify that the bearer, Dimmock Charlton, has been 
known to me for over twenty-five years, as a slave in the 
city of Savannah, state of Georgia; has always maintained a 
good character for honesty and sobriety.</p>
                  <p>His wife and children are at present in bondage as slaves in 
the city of Savannah, but can no doubt be ransomed at fair 
prices, upon proper steps or application being resorted to, 
or addressed to the respective owners.</p>
                  <closer>
                    <signed>
—— ———<lb/><hi rend="italic">Formerly of Savannah, Ga.</hi></signed>
                  </closer>
                  <closer>P. S.—The wife of Dimmock is owned by G. B. Cumming,<lb/>
Daughter     [of Dimmock is owned by] W. H. May,<lb/>
Son     [of Dimmock is owned by] D. O'Byrne,<lb/>
Daughter     [of Dimmock is owned by] J. M. Tison,<lb/>
  [Daughter] [of Dimmock is owned by] Some party unknown, but the wife
can tell by whom.</closer>
                </div1>
              </body>
            </text>
          </q>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>