<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY fostebk SYSTEM "fostebk.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY fostercv SYSTEM "fostercv.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>Uncle Johnson, The Pilgrim of Six Score Years:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Foster, G. L.  (Gustavus Lemuel), 1818 - 1876</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Christopher  Hill</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by</resp>
          <name>Christopher  Hill</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">  Fiona Mills and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1999</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca.     50K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1999.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="cover"> Uncle Johnson, The Pilgrim of Six Score
Years.</title>
            <author>The Rev. Gustavus L. Foster</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent> 25     p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
            <publisher>Presbyterian Board of Publication</publisher>
            <date>[1867]</date>
            <authority/>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="yes">Call number 15518 (Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections
Library, Duke University Libraries) </note>
            <note anchored="yes">At head of title: No. 96</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>All footnotes are inserted at the point of reference within paragraphs. </p>
        <p>The original text begins with page 61.</p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Johnson, Uncle, 1745?-1864.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Freedmen -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Biography.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Religion.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2000-04-06, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-11-11, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-11-05, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Fiona Mills</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-11-03, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Chris Hill</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="cover">
        <p>
          <figure entity="fostercv"/>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="backcover">
        <p>
          <figure entity="fostebk"/>
        </p>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="text">
        <pb id="foster61" n="61"/>
        <head>UNCLE JOHNSON,
<lb/>
THE PILGRIM OF SIX SCORE YEARS.</head>
        <docAuthor>
BY THE REV. GUSTAVUS L. FOSTER.</docAuthor>
        <p>IT is still the custom in some towns of the
West, as well as in New England, to announce
the death of individuals by measured
strokes of the bell, each stroke marking a
year of the life of the dead. This practice,
though originating in superstition, the ringing
of the bell being held as efficacious for
the driving away of evil spirits, in its
continuance is not without profit.</p>
        <p>Many can testify to the blessed influence
of such announcements. Many can remember
the thoughts and purposes that were inspired
thus—whether the solemn tones fell
upon their ear at early morn, telling that
one had passed through the valley of the shadow
of death during the night, or whether
they were heard just as evening's lengthened
<pb id="foster62" n="62"/>
shadows, or the hush of twilight's hour made
them impressive. It is well that thus, amid
the hurry and strife of life, mortals shall be
made to pause and think whither they are tending.</p>
        <p>Not long since the inhabitants of Y —  ,
wearied and wondered in counting the strokes
of the bell, as the iron-tongued accountant
told first the numbers of infancy, then of
childhood, then of manhood, then of old age,
and still tolled on in a number beyond even
old age. But the wonder — “Who has died?”
passed away ere the counting had reached
<hi rend="italics">one hundred and twenty</hi>, telling the number
of the years of some ended pilgrimage. All
knew that
<lb/>
“UNCLE JOHNSON”
<lb/>
had at last gone home.</p>
        <p>Since his departure, we have thought of
many things concerning that venerable relic
of a former generation, things of so much
interest to us that we are constrained to tell
them to others. He was one of our most intimate
neighbors for years, living in a humble
cabin upon a lot which joined the back end
of our own. From our study-window we
could look down upon his garden, and in the
<pb id="foster63" n="63"/>
summer season we had no difficulty in being
familiar with the tenor of his life.</p>
        <p>Before “Uncle Johnson” <ref id="ref1" n="1" rend="sc" target="note1" targOrder="U">*</ref>
<note id="note1" n="1" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref1"><p>* He was of purely African descent. His full name was
<hi rend="italics">Johnson Harrison</hi>—the <hi rend="italics">Harrison</hi>, as he said, being his
master's name in Virginia, and the <hi rend="italics">Johnson</hi> his own. For this
reason he preferred being called Johnson.</p></note>
 came to dwell in
the cabin it changed its occupants frequently,
and at each change we were glad and hopeful.
Hearing that the place had now been
purchased by <hi rend="italics">a colored man</hi>, though free from
any special prejudice against his race, our
hopes on the score of good neighborhood
were not raised high.</p>
        <p>We soon found that we were subject to no
annoyance from the cabin; that all was quiet
and orderly there. We heard little except
that at times more frequent than morning
and evening the voice of praise and prayer
ascended with a peculiar fervor from within
its walls. Listening once to these sounds,
we heard these words:
“O Lord, dy servant has been a pilgrim
<hi rend="italics">more dan a hundred years</hi>, when will he get
home?”</p>
        <p>Such a declaration induced us to think that
our new neighbor might be both an aged and
good man. At any rate it led to an intimate
<pb id="foster64" n="64"/>
acquaintance in which we found that in both
of these respects he was a man most rare.</p>
        <p>By frequent conversations concerning his
age we judge that his death occurred in his
<hi rend="italics">one hundred and twentieth year</hi>.</p>
        <p>His first master felt that his servants were
in some sense members of his family, and
recorded their names in the family Bible. The
old man remembered seeing opposite his name
1745. The month he could not recall. In
confirmation of the great age which such a
date would give him, as he lived to the
year 1864, he said that he was a man
grown when sent out to throw fire-balls in
the evening because of the joyful news of the
signing of the Declaration of Independence.
Concerning the events of the revolutionary
war, so far as they occurred upon the line of
the James' River, Virginia, he was familiar.
General Washington was frequently at his
master's house, and his master was a member
of the first Assembly. He said: “De
last time I seed de General 'twas when de
war was ober. I bated de General's horse in
de yard, while he takes dinner wid de masser.”</p>
        <p>He stated also that he was about thirty
before he was allowed to have a wife; that
<pb id="foster65" n="65"/>
he lived with her fifty years; then for several
years had no wife, and his last wife, who died
two years before him, said that she had lived
with him twenty-eight years. He also stated
that he was set free by his last master and
sent to Canada, partly because he was more
than one hundred years old, and by right of
age deserved to be his own man. He delighted
in telling of the scenes of his early
life, and his narrations would so accord with
the pages of history as to make it evident
that he had lived as far off from the present
as he asserted. Certainly he was a wonderful
man as an “ante-revolutionary relic.”</p>
        <p>But he was still more interesting and wonderful
because of his <hi rend="italics">religion</hi>. He accounted
for his long life in part by saying: “I neber
worked bery hard. When I was a boy I
chored 'bout house, and den for about sixty
years I blowed de gospel trumpet on de
plantation for 'bout six months ob de year, to
make de slaves good and 'ligious, and I tell
ye, massa, when I was in my prime, say along
<hi rend="italics">'bout eighty</hi>, I could blow de old trumpet so
dat dey could hear me for miles.” His own
account of his early religious knowledge and
experience was about as follows:</p>
        <pb id="foster66" n="66"/>
        <p>“I was quite a chunk of a boy afore I
hearn much about 'ligion, afore I hearn much
about dis glorious gospel.</p>
        <p>“Once in 'bout a year one o' dem clergy
dat com'd ober de big water com'd round and
preached up all de funerals ob de slaves dat
died sen he com'd afore, and sometimes I
feels very bad den. But after a bit dere
com'd round one ob de big men from de college
in de Jarseys,<ref id="ref2" n="2" rend="sc" target="note2" targOrder="U">*</ref>
<note id="note2" n="2" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref2">* This it seems probable was the 
eloquent President Davies.</note> and he telled us 'bout de
matter werry solemn.   But I know nothing
den about Jesus.” And now the tears began
to trickle down the old man's cheeks.</p>
        <p>“An' den dar com'd along dat man dat
died an' den com'd to life again, an' he telled
de slaves 'bout Jesus. Oh, wat was he name?
I don't mind now.” I suggested <hi rend="italics">William
Tennent</hi>. “Oh, yes, massa! <hi rend="italics">Willie Tennent</hi>!
Glory to God! I been tryin to tink ob dat
name dese many years. I knowed I should
know him in glory, but now I will call him by
name jus as soon as I sees him. After I
heard him how I did feel! Wen I was walking
on de ground it would keep sayin' ‘<hi rend="italics">Unworthy!
unworthy!</hi>’ Wen I took a bit ob
<pb id="foster67" n="67"/>
bread, or a cup ob water, dey keep sayin'
‘<hi rend="italics">Unworthy! unworthy!</hi>’ Wen I goes into
de field all de trees keep sayin' ‘<hi rend="italics">Unworthy!
unworthy!</hi>’ Wen I goes into de yard I sees
dat all de cattle kneels down afore dey lies
down, an' I neber done dat. O massa,
I thought I should die. I feels so bad.”
(Then he would go on in various terms to tell
of his utter despair.) “But bimbye dere
com'd along a colored man who telled me des
no use in my libin' dat way. He telled me
ob de passage dat says: ‘Behold de Lamb
of God dat takes away de sins ob de world;’
an' den I goes into de woods, an' all night I
cries, ‘O Lamb of God, hab mercy on dis
poor man;<corr sic="missing ’ ">’</corr> an' I cries an' prays dis ober an'
ober; an', O massa! just as de light was coming
ober de mountains ob ole Virginia de light
of Jesus shined into dis poor soul, an' from
dat day on, now about a hundred years, I've
been tryin' to tell to saints and sinners round
what a dear Saviour I have found.”</p>
        <p>He was ever magnifying the grace that
rescued such a sinner as he, and that had
sustained and comforted him in his long and
weary pilgrimage. We have never known
one whose soul would so soon melt and flow
<pb id="foster68" n="68"/>
down in the presence of the great facts of
infinite love and mercy. The name of Jesus
was the greatest and best of all names to
him. Not unfrequently he would utter that
dear name over and over, with tones, and
tears, and gestures of gratitude and praise.</p>
        <p>The old man was favorably situated for
enjoying ejaculatory worship; and he 
diligently improved and richly enjoyed his
opportunities. For about five days in each week
he was alone in the most of the day; his wife,
who was sixty years younger than himself,
having gone out to work in neighboring families,
and his two children, born after he was
one hundred years old, having gone to school
or to play. During their absence he would
often spend hours in talking, and praying, and
singing. Sometimes, as one of my children
said, he appeared to “play meeting.” Sitting
in his chair by the side of his house
with his Bible on his knee he would slowly
read (without glasses) and expound and
preach as if a congregation were present;
then would follow singing and prayer in a
manner which would indicate that Christ himself
were present. We called upon him one
day just as he closed one of these services.
<pb id="foster69" n="69"/>
As soon as he saw us he cried out, with tears
flowing down his face: “O massa! Jesus
has been here, an' I tought I was in glory;
but I will be dere bimbye.”</p>
        <p>“You mean to be faithful to the end, Uncle
Johnson?” I said.</p>
        <p>“O massa, I'se bound for de kingdom.
I'se not been holding on all dis way to fail
jus at de gate.”</p>
        <p>Once, as I interrupted him upon one of
these occasions, he exclaimed:</p>
        <p>“O massa! de Lord is passing by; does
you want to speak to him?”</p>
        <p>I can call to mind many interesting incidents
concerning him, but will mention only
a few of such as made the most impression
upon my mind at the time. His voice and
manner were such as to give his declarations
a power that they cannot have upon the lifeless
page. The reader needs to imagine his
earnest manner and emotional utterance with
the tone common among preachers and exhorters
at the South many years ago. The
fact, too, that he did not appear to know that
he had said anything interesting when he had
uttered thoughts as rich as human language
can express, gave to his words a peculiar
<pb id="foster70" n="70"/>
charm. They would come forth as spontaneously
as if they were the natural outflow
of his soul, as if they were specimens of the
rich quarry within, or as if God would thus
show what can be wrought in a heart that
gives him entire dominion.</p>
        <p>One day while he was at work in his
garden, singing and shouting, I said: “You
seem happy to-day.”</p>
        <p>“Yes, massa, I'se jus tinking.”</p>
        <p><sic>‘</sic>What are you thinking of?”</p>
        <p>“Oh I'se jus tinking;” (and then his emotions
prevented utterance.) “I'se jus tinking
dat ef de crumbs dat fall from de Master's
table, in dis world, am so good, wat will
de GREAT LOAF in glory be! I tells ye, massa,
dar will be nuff an' to spare dare.”</p>
        <p>At another time when he seemed very
happy and I had heard him shout, “Lord
Jesus, will dere be one for me?” I said, “You
are having a good time to-day, uncle?” He
answered:</p>
        <p>“O massa, I was meditatin' about Jesus
bein' <hi rend="italics">de Carpenter</hi>; an' so he can make
mansions for his people in glory.” And then
with uplifted face and with tears he cried
out, “O Jesus, will dar be one for me?”
<pb id="foster71" n="71"/>
Once I said to him, “Uncle Johnson, why
don't you go to church once in awhile?” He
answered, “Massa, I wants to be dere, but I
can't '<hi rend="italics">have</hi>.”</p>
        <p>“You can't <hi rend="italics">behave</hi>?”</p>
        <p>“Well, massa, you knows, late years, de
flesh be weak; an' when dey 'gins to talk and
sing about Jesus I 'gins to fill up, and putty
soon I has to holler, and den dey say, ‘Carry
dat man to de door, he 'sturb de meetin’.”</p>
        <p>“But you should hold in until you get home.”</p>
        <p>“O massa, I can't hold in—I <hi rend="italics">bust</hi> if I don't holler.”</p>
        <p>Once, after hearing him pray and sing at
midnight while a thunder-storm was passing,
in the morning I said, “Was that you shouting
so last night?”</p>
        <p>“Yes, massa, I 'spose.”</p>
        <p>“Well, I thought the thunder made noise
enough without your hallooing.”</p>
        <p>He looked up, and with astonishment said:
“Massa, do you tink I'se goin' to lie dere on
my bed like a great pig, wen de Lord com'd
along shakin' de earth and de heavens? No,
massa, when I hears de thun'er coming, I
says, ‘Ellen, Ellen, wake up here, <hi rend="italics">we's goin'
to hear from home ag'in</hi>.’ ”</p>
        <pb id="foster72" n="72"/>
        <p>One morning when I had heard him for an
hour or two, I went carefully to his door and
saw him sitting at the end of his table with a
humble repast before him, while his hands
were lifted high in gratitude and praise. I
said, “You seem happy this morning?”</p>
        <p>“Oh, yes, Ellen went away to her work,
and so I gets me breakfast and den begins
to say grace; an', O massa, de Lord am <hi rend="italics">so
good</hi>, seems I neber will be done sayin'
grace!”</p>
        <p>What a rebuke to those who sit down to
loaded tables with no thought of their Benefactor!</p>
        <p>Gratitude to God for his daily mercies was
one of his most distinct peculiarities. If he
received a gift from his neighbor he ever
evinced an appreciation of the kindness of
the giver; and then, at once, his eye would
be lifted toward heaven, and some expressions
would clearly indicate his heart's response
to Him from whom we receive every
good and perfect gift. Many things, received
from time to time, were regarded by him, and
spoken of as if they came in answer to prayer.
He said, “When I wants anything I asks de
Lord, and he's sure to send it, sometimes
<pb id="foster73" n="73"/>
afore I done asking, an' sometimes he waits
jus to see if I trusts him.”</p>
        <p>Once when we indicated a little skepticism
upon this subject, he said:</p>
        <p>“Massa, don't you know dat de Lord send
de ravens to feed de prophet? Him is jus
as good now as den.”</p>
        <p>We chanced to be present when one called
with whom he was not acquainted. After
entering and shaking the old man by the
hand, he said: “Is this Uncle Johnson? I
have often heard of you, and have meant
sometime to see you. But as I was passing
just now something said to me, ‘Go in there
and give the old man a dollar.’ I said, ‘I
can't do it;’ and again something said: ‘Go
in there, I tell you, and give him a dollar.’
So here it is, get anything you please with
it.”</p>
        <p>“Yes, massa, thank you, thank you. I
tought de Lord would send you dis afternoon.
Sit down, sit down.”</p>
        <p>“No, not now, I am in a hurry. I hope
you are getting along comfortably.
Good-bye.”</p>
        <p>“Hold! hold! Massa! Afore you go I
wants to know if you are bound for de
<pb id="foster74" n="74"/>
kingdom? May-be I'll neber see you again. Am
you bound for dat land of pure delight, where
saints immortal reign? Hab you de passport?”</p>
        <p>“The what?”</p>
        <p>“De <hi rend="italics">passport</hi> all signed and sealed wid de
blood of Jesus. You must hab dat, massa, or
you neber will get fru de gates ob de city.”</p>
        <p>In some such manner as this he would improve
every opportunity of doing good to
those who came in his way. He would with
perfect naturalness run all conversation into
a religious channel. “Out of the abundance
of the heart the mouth speaketh.” He was
perpetually saying such things as declared
plainly that he was seeking a country, that
is, an heavenly.</p>
        <p>His anticipations of the heavenly inheritance
were such that at times he thought himself
in full possession. Said he: “Sometimes
when I'se walking up and down in dis
cabin, praising de Lord, I thinks I am in
heaven; I thinks dis is one ob de mansions
dat Jesus gives his people. Den dis world
is under my feet. I jus sees it a great way
off, and I jus cries: O my God! am I in
glory?”</p>
        <pb id="foster75" n="75"/>
        <p>“But how do you feel when you find that you are not there?”</p>
        <p>“I has a long crying, and den I says, I will wait my appointed time.”</p>
        <p>“How long would you be willing to wait?”</p>
        <p>“I will wait anuder hundred Years, <hi rend="italics">if de Lord please</hi>.”</p>
        <p>Realizing his need of fitness for heaven
we heard him praying one night: “O Lord,
anoint our souls with angels' balm, that
when we have done with dis world we may
be at home in glory.”</p>
        <p>His voice was so strong and his soul so
fervent that he was heard in his devotions
for a great distance around, especially at
evening, in the season of summer. Many
were necessitated to hear the accents of
prayer and praise, though themselves never
uttered them. Some persons doubtless were
annoyed by this, and yet in various ways they
would indicate their approbation of his manner
of life. Many a wicked man laid himself
down and rested all the more quietly,
by reason of the sense of safety inspired by
the prayer he was compelled to hear, before
retiring; and many a one was waked to the
active duties of a new day by the early
<pb id="foster76" n="76"/>
praises of this aged pilgrim who seemed to
welcome each coming morning as bringing
him nearer home.</p>
        <p>He uniformly rose early, but especially
early on the Sabbath. When we asked him
why he did so he said: “De Lord get up
early <hi rend="italics">dat day</hi>. De women dat went to de
<sic corr="sepulchre">sepulcre</sic> got dere early, and den de Lord
was not dere. De earlier I gets up de more
I sees ob Jesus.”</p>
        <p>By reason of his infirmities he could not
attend upon the services of the sanctuary,
but said he: “I <hi rend="italics">puts up</hi> for you ebery day;
I always pray den for all dat blows de gospel
trumpet.”</p>
        <p>Nothing rejoiced him more than to hear
that sinners were inquiring the way to the
Saviour. Such tidings would make him weep
for joy. Once, lifting his hands, he cried:
“O Lord, call dem in. Ho Lord! Make
dem willing in de day of dy power.”</p>
        <p>Once, in illustrating that sinners should be
more in earnest, he said: “Many tink dey
be seeking and seeking 'ligion, and dey be
jus putting it off all de time; dey must <hi rend="italics">lay
right down to it</hi>,  jus as de hos would to de
dray, or dey neber can get free. You
<pb id="foster77" n="77"/>
know de gate is narrow —  <hi rend="italics">'tis mighty narrow</hi>!”</p>
        <p>His confidence in the word of God was
unbounded. Let him be sure that the Lord
had said anything, and nothing could shake
his faith in it. We were mentioning this
fact to a friend one day just as we were going
over to call on the old man. So, after having
been there a while, my friend said:</p>
        <p>“Uncle Johnson, you believe so and so,”
naming some fundamental doctrine of the
gospel.</p>
        <p>“Yes, massa, I believes dat.”</p>
        <p>“What makes you believe that?”</p>
        <p>“'Cause, massa, you knows dat de Lord
says so,” quoting a passage or two.</p>
        <p>“Well, Uncle Johnson, you believe so and
so,” (naming another doctrine, seemingly
antagonistic to the former.)</p>
        <p>“Yes, massa, I believes dat, too, 'cause
de Lord said,” and then he quoted again.</p>
        <p>“But see here, uncle, both of those things
can't be true; you said you believed so and
so, and also <hi rend="italics">so and so</hi>. Now how do you <hi rend="italics">reconcile</hi>
these two things? They can't both
be true, in the nature of things; it is not
philosophical that both should be true.” And
<pb id="foster78" n="78"/>
thus my friend went on attempting to confuse
the old man with metaphysical subtleties.</p>
        <p>Uncle Johnson heard him for a while, and
then lifting himself from his chair, and in a
manner indicating grief and impatience, said:</p>
        <p>“Massa, I knows nothing about your <hi rend="italics">philosophies</hi>
and your <hi rend="italics">natur ob tings</hi>, but I knows
dat de Lord said dem tings, an' I hab tried
de Lord more dan a hundred years,
(weeping,) and I'se not going now to gib up <hi rend="italics">one
ting dat he said</hi>.”</p>
        <p>Having said this he sat down. My friend
turned and said to me, in a low tone: “That
will do; I give it up.”</p>
        <p>He seemed to have so long rested upon
the simple declarations of God, and to have
had so many fulfilments of the promises in
his own experience, that anything intimated
or said in a manner indicating distrust of
these things was regarded with no degree of
allowance. It seemed hard for him to believe
that a man can be a Christian and
indulge in any measure of skepticism concerning
anything that is clearly revealed. For
“the philosophies of religion” he cared
nothing. Its grand and glorious <hi rend="italics">facts</hi> were
<pb id="foster79" n="79"/>
great enough and rich enough for his capacities.
He had a confidence in God so strong
as to believe that there are good reasons for
all his assertions, and that he need not
trouble himself with an endeavor to look into
them. Oh! how well it would have been
for many if they had been like poor old Uncle
Johnson! Very few know enough to
make it worth while to be curiously inquisitive
of divine secrets. Simply <hi rend="italics">to trust</hi> is the
most profitable way of learning the things
of the divine kingdom. God makes his most
blessed revelations to those who most completely
confide. This we often thought when
staggering home under the weight of some
of Uncle Johnson's simple but almost
inspired utterances.</p>
        <p>But while we were marking the general
tenor of that life of faith and prayer, we
gave it a new attention, as it revealed itself,
under the chastenings of affliction. A great
sorrow overtook him in the death of his wife,
about two years before his own release. She
rapidly but very trustfully went into the valley
of the shadow of death. Returning from
an evening appointment we were told that
she was dying. Hastening over we found
<pb id="foster80" n="80"/>
that the spirit had just taken its departure,
and then we saw and heard what we can
never adequately describe. What a figure
of grief and triumph in the presence of the
stillness and solemnity of death!</p>
        <p>This aged one, standing by the bedside of
the lifeless form of his wife, with uplifted
face and hands, was crying: “Farewell,
Ellen —  farewell, my dear Ellen; must you
leave me! must you leave me! O Jesus!
my dear Ellen is coming! Gib her one ob
de mansions till I come; Lord Jesus! How
can I wait? Send de chariot again.”</p>
        <p>Such like expressions were numerous until
the tide of his emotions had subsided; then,
kneeling by the bedside, he breathed his
sorrows into the ear of his Saviour in such a
prayer as we never expect to hear again.</p>
        <p>From that hour on, through the funeral
occasion and in the days following, his spirit
and manner were beautiful beyond description.
Being human he often felt lonely, and
believing that he would ultimately attain
heaven, he greatly longed to be there. We
said to him one day:</p>
        <p>“Uncle Johnson, don't you feel lonely
since Ellen left you?”</p>
        <pb id="foster81" n="81"/>
        <p>“Oh yes, massa, I feels berry lonely, but
den de Lord comes round ebery day and
gives me a taste ob de kingdom, jus as de
nus would wid de spoon; but, oh! how <hi rend="italics">I
wants to get hold ob de dish</hi>,” (suiting the
manner to the words.)</p>
        <p>Ever after Ellen's death he seemed only
waiting as he said “for dat chariot to come
again.” Once, after he had been ill for a
few days, as he began to get out again, I
said: “I thought that your appointed time
had about come.” He replied: “Oh, yes, I
tought dat day dat I could see de dust ob de
chariot coming ober de mountains, an' den
somethin' said, ‘Hold on, Johnson, a little
longer; I'll come round directly.’ Yes,
massa, an' I will hold on, if de Lord please,
anoder hundred years! for I'se bound for
Canaan.” Then he broke out singing:
<q direct="unspecified"><lg type="song"><l>“But this I do find we two am so jin'd,</l><l>He'll not live in glory and leave me behind.”</l></lg></q></p>
        <p>During those days he would often bid his
friends farewell, “till we meets in glory.”</p>
        <p>One day the Rev. Dr. H — called on
him with me. After a conversation which,
surely my friend will never forget, he said:
“I must now go; good-bye, Uncle Johnson;
<pb id="foster82" n="82"/>
I shall probably hear soon that you have
gone over Jordan, but we will follow on.”</p>
        <p>“Oh, yes massa, great many years ago
young men like you tell me dat, an' den
after a bit I'd hear dat dey had gone home,
an' I am a pilgrim yet, but I always manages
to send word.”</p>
        <p>“Well if I should die first,” said Dr. H  —,
“what word would you send?”</p>
        <p>“O massa, if you get home afore I do,”
(weeping,)“<hi rend="italics">tell 'em to keep de table standin'</hi>,
for Johnson is holding on his way. <hi rend="italics">I'se
bound to be dere</hi>.”</p>
        <p>We might record other incidents and
expressions, but they would be like those
already given. Many who have visited him,
and who may see these pages, will wonder
that we have not told of what he said when
they were present. We have narrated only
such things as made the deepest impression
upon our own mind, and which we have
retained by notes made at the time, or by
repeating them.</p>
        <p>Since the death of his wife the old man
has been almost wholly dependent upon his
neighbors for daily bread. Those women
who have ministered to his comfort, or more
<pb id="foster83" n="83"/>
distant friends who have supplied his wants,
will not lose their reward. They have been
already rewarded in having had an interest
in the prayers of this man of God.</p>
        <p>Uncle Johnson fasted and prayed as very
few in these days have done. His fasting, as
well as praying, were thorough and earnest.
For more than seventy years he entirely
abstained from food on Fridays. He said, “Dem
am de days wen I says to do body‘stan'
back dere; I'se going to feed do soul today.’”
When I asked, “Don't you sometimes
feel very weak and faint before night?”
he said, “Yes, massa, but den I must have
de body keep he place.” In speaking of
these days of fasting and prayer he once
said: “Dese are de days when I spreads
de big tings afore de Lord and begs.”</p>
        <p>Of his death we know but little. His
illness was brief. In such an hour as he
thought not the Son of Man came. But
that he was ready when “the chariot” came,
and that “its wheels rolled in fire,” as when
Elijah was born to heaven, we may not doubt.</p>
        <p>As we have marked this old man's life it
has often seemed as if “one of the prophets
<pb id="foster84" n="84"/>
had risen again.” He had a faith like that
of Abraham, a firmness like that of Daniel,
a fire like that of Isaiah, tears like those of
Jeremiah, and he fasted and prayed like them
all. We rejoice in having known such a man,
and in having seen in him so many of the
excellent things of the kingdom of God. He
was a living witness 
of the power and glory
of the gospel of the blessed God. Often
looking on him have we asked, “What would
this aged African have been but for the divine
plan of elevating and saving men?” And then
again we have asked, “If it doth not yet
appear what we shall be, what will <hi rend="italics">he</hi> be <hi rend="italics">ages
hence</hi>?”</p>
        <p>Grace has its wonders. God is yet choosing
the weak things of the world to confound
the mighty, and it will be seen more
distinctly by-and-by than now, that there are
first which shall be last, and last that shall
be first. Nothing but simple trust in Christ
can endue man with true greatness. Little
child-likeness goes before, and is essential to
the stature of a perfect manhood.</p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>