<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>Reuben Maddison:  A True Story:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>[Stuart, Charles, 1783?-1865]</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Laura Button</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Chris Hill and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1999</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca.    60K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1999.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note anchored="yes">Call number  E 444 M3 1835a        
(Smith College, Northampton, Mass. )</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>Reuben Maddison</title>
          <author>[Charles Stuart, 
1783?-1865]</author>
          <imprint>
            <pubPlace>Birmingham</pubPlace>
            <publisher>B. Hudson</publisher>
            <date>[1835]</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>The electronic edition is transcribed from a photocopy from Smith College, 
 Northampton, Mass.</p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘
 respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been 
preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor
 (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st 
edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Maddison, Reuben.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Kentucky -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- United States -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- Jamaica.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>1999-11-03, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-06-28, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-06-24, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Chris Hill </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-06-19, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Laura Button</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">REUBEN MADDISON:</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="main">A True Story.</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <epigraph>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>Forget her not! Forget her not!</l>
            <l>Her wrongs are your country's foulest blot!</l>
            <l>When ye list your children's shouts of play,</l>
            <l>When ye soothe their transient griefs away,</l>
            <l>When ye bend above the couch of pain,</l>
            <l>Or watch where the dying head is lain,</l>
            <l>But most of all when you kneel in prayer,</l>
            <l>To seek your father's daily care,</l>
            <l>Never should Africa be forgot,</l>
            <l>Till your land is cleansed from its foulest blot.</l>
          </lg>
          <bibl>SIBYL. Verses from America.</bibl>
        </epigraph>
        <docImprint><pubPlace>BIRMINGHAM:</pubPlace>
<publisher>PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY B. HUDSON:</publisher>
<hi>And supplied at trade price to Anti-Slavery Associations,
by </hi>JOSEPH PHILLIPS, 18 <hi>Aldermanbury,
London.</hi></docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="preface">
        <pb id="madd3" n="3"/>
        <head>PREFACE.</head>
        <p>WHICH of us is not pleased with a tale of <hi rend="italics">fiction</hi>
from a far country?—I trust my fellow countrymen and
countrywomen will be as much interested in a <hi rend="italics">true</hi> story
coming from a far country. If you are a lover of truth you
shall behold her in these pages.—Truth is the harbinger of
freedom, and the friend of the oppressed.</p>
        <q direct="unspecified">
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>Like to an armed Knight</l>
            <l>Prepared for the field,</l>
            <l>With Slavery do I fight,</l>
            <l>And truth shall be my shield.</l>
          </lg>
          <bibl>
            <hi rend="italics">(The Martyr Anne Askew's lines, altered.)</hi>
          </bibl>
        </q>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="main text">
        <pb id="madd5" n="5"/>
        <head>REUBEN MADDISON.</head>
        <div2 type="section">
          <p>ABOUT five years ago one of the religious
newspapers of New York called the attention
of its readers to a distressed family of pious
coloured people. Captain Stuart, by following
the direction given in the paper, easily
discovered this family, and found it to consist
of a Negro of a most frank and pleasant
deportment, his wife confined to her bed by
severe rheumatic fever, but exceedingly happy
through the comforts which religion afforded
her, and a female companion, suffering from
rheumatic pains, but able to go about the work
of the house.</p>
          <p>At different times Captain Stuart learnt from
this Negro man, whose name was
<pb id="madd6" n="6"/>
Reuben Maddison, the following particulars of
his history. Reuben was born a slave in
Kentucky; his master being a cruel and artful
man, but his mistress kind and good. He was
allowed the privilege of seeking his
employment where he would, being only
required to bring his master yearly the sum of
120 dollars, reserved from what he might be
able to earn. The kindness of Reuben's heart
prompted such willing and obliging behaviour,
that every one in whose way he came was
pleased to be served by him, and he found
plenty of work, especially at * * *, a
neighbouring watering-place, and lived very
happily with his wife, and their family of young
children.</p>
          <p>One evening Reuben was returning from
some work at a distance, when he met a fellow-
slave, whose unusually sad look occasioned
him alarm and who asked him where he was
going. Reuben answered,
<pb id="madd7" n="7"/>
he was going home to his wife and
children. To this the other replied,
“Going home to your wife and children!
Don't you know that you have no more a wife
or children? They are all gone; sent off by
massa to be sold.”</p>
          <p>Poor Reuben hastened to the cottage that
had been his happy home, and finding that it
was indeed as his companion had said, he
flew, half distracted to Frankfort, the capital
of the state, whence he knew they would be
embarked on the Ohio, to go down it, and the
<sic corr="Mississippi">Missisipi</sic>, to New Orleans, the capital of
Louisiana, and the principal United States'
mart for slaves. He hoped to be in time to see
his treasures once more; but they were
already gone, and he returned in hopeless
despair.</p>
          <p>After a dark and dreadful period, however,
the thought came suddenly into his
mind, “Reuben, do you love your wife
<pb id="madd8" n="8"/>
and children? And if you do, is this the way to
act? Instead of wandering about mourning, and
doing nothing, why don't you set to work, and
work harder than ever, that you may get
enough to buy your freedom, and go and seek
after your wife and children, and perhaps buy
their freedom too?”</p>
          <p>The hopes inspired by these thoughts
revived his spirit; he set to work with
redoubled vigour; and soon after, as he was
passing along the streets of * * *, a
Quaker, who knew his history, stopped
him, and said that he could tell him something
much for his advantage. The Friend then
informed him, that a gentleman in the
neighbourhood was about to establish
some paper-mills, and that as the
trade of rag-gathering was new in the
country, if he, who had so many kind
friends and acquaintances about, were to
furnish a hawker's box, and undertake the
<pb id="madd9" n="9"/>
collecting of rags, he would be sure to find it
a very lucrative concern.</p>
          <p>After consulting with some of his friends,
who were Lawyers and Merchants, Reuben
made up his mind, and did as the Quaker
advised him; and God, whose child he had
before this time become, blessed him, so that
he made money very fast.</p>
          <p>About 400 dollars were laid by, when
Reuben's mistress, who knew how anxious he
was to be free, one day told him that his
master had at last consented to treat with him
respecting his freedom, and that if he would go
to him while he was in the humour, he would
most likely obtain favourable terms.</p>
          <p>Reuben went accordingly, and being asked
by his master whether it was true that he
wished to be free, he answered that he desired
it above every thing else on earth. Upon this he
was informed,
<pb id="madd10" n="10"/>
that he might, if he pleased, be freed for
700 dollars, half to be paid at one time,
and the remaining half at the end of
eighteen months: and the poor man,
exceedingly delighted to find that what he
had so ardently desired was put, apparently,
within his reach, exclaimed immediately,
that he could pay all the 350 that very 
day.<ref id="ref1" n="1" rend="cr" target="note1" targOrder="U">*</ref></p>
          <p>The master looked well pleased at hearing
this, and desired that they might be fetched,
which Reuben went to do. While on his way,
he thought to himself that he should not be wise
to part with his money without witnesses, and
on his return he begged that he might be
allowed to procure some. His master's
countenance fell upon hearing his request, but
he gave his consent, and the four most faithful
friends Reuben had in the village were
<note id="note1" n="1" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref1"><p>* Reuben at this time had laid up 400, but the
first payment was only 350.</p></note>
<pb id="madd11" n="11"/>
summoned by him, and allowed to be witness
to a paper of agreement and receipt drawn up
by the master, read aloud to them all for their
approval, and then signed by him, and
delivered to the poor overjoyed Negro.</p>
          <p>Reuben continued to get money so fast that
he would soon have offered the remaining 350
dollars, had not his friends dissuaded him from
doing so, by telling him that he had better take
care of his master, or he would be over-reached
at last; and that he should by no means
pay any thing more till the appointed
time came, and he should receive a legal deed
of manumission. Reuben then, conceiving it
would be a good and safe plan to use his
money as he got it, only taking care that the
right sum should be in readiness at the end of
the eighteen months, bought a lot of ground, on
which he built a brick cottage, and sunk a
well; he also laid out a
<pb id="madd12" n="12"/>
pretty garden, delighting the while in the idea
that before so very long, he might have his
wife and family back to live there with him.</p>
          <p>About six months before the time when
Reuben was, as he thought, to be made free, he
was roused from his dream of happiness by his
master's sending for him, and saying, that as he
could afford to build brick houses, sink wells,
and lay out gardens, he could certainly afford
to pay the 350 dollars, and that he must do so
immediately, or he should never be free at all.</p>
          <p>This was a frightful threat, for Reuben had
not above 25 dollars in hand, and he gently
remonstrated and ventured to hint at the
written agreement he had received.</p>
          <p>“I gave you that, because I saw you
were in a suspicious humour,” said his master
with a malignant smile; “but as to its being of
any use, your friends the lawyers will fast
enough tell you, if you
<pb id="madd13" n="13"/>
choose to take the trouble to ask them, that
your body is mine, and your house is mine, and
your garden, and all that you have, and that no
one can force me to part with you.”</p>
          <p>Reuben would in all probability, have
continued in the hopeless condition of a slave
to the day of his death, had not the odium cast
upon his master, as the <sic corr="(duplicate word)">the</sic> story became
known, caused him at last to retract his cruel
threat; though still he refused to release his
bondsman, unless he should receive from him,
instead of the 350 dollars, his house, well, and
garden, which had perhaps cost 1000.</p>
          <p>Reuben prized his freedom too highly to
hesitate a moment about parting with
his all to obtain, it, and as soon as he received
his manumission papers, he set off to New
Orleans, feeling as if he had
escaped from the grasp of a demon. After
making diligent enquiry about his wife
<pb id="madd14" n="14"/>
and children, he found that the former was
dead, and his children equally lost to him,
being sold and sent away, and he could
never gain any further intelligence of
them.</p>
          <p>After some time, Reuben married a pious
coloured woman. It was soon after this event
that, as they were one day passing together by
the slave market, they found their sympathy
strongly excited by the appearance of a female
slave, sitting dejectedly on the ground, exhibited
for sale. Maria, so she was called, belonged
to a Virginian planter, who was a determined
persecutor of all such of his slaves
as desired to be followers of Jesus. These
poor creatures were accustomed to meet
every Wednesday night, when their hours
of work were over, in a hut on the plantation,
to speak to each other of Jesus, and
to pray and sing hymns together. When
this was found out by the overseer, and
<pb id="madd15" n="15"/>
reported to their master, he ordered that the
drivers should be placed at the door of the hut,
and that when the meeting broke up, they
should follow the slaves with their whips, and
send them lacerated and bleeding to their
homes. This did not induce the poor Negroes
to forsake the assembling of themselves
together, though it was regularly continued
every meeting-night. Maria was one of these
persecuted people, and on each succeeding
Thursday morning she was taunted with such
questions as these.—“Well, Maria, you were at
meeting last night; and you mean to go again
next Wednesday night, do you?”—
“Yes, Massa.”—“And you go that you may
enjoy the love of your Saviour, and you hope
that he will one day give you a crown of glory?”—
“Yes, Massa.”—“And he was crowned with
thorns, and scourged, and crucified for your
sake, was not he?” “Yes, Massa.”—“Well, we
shall take
<pb id="madd16" n="16"/>
care that, if you share the crown of glory, you
shall share the thorns too.”</p>
          <p>At last, in anger, and probably in despair of
altering the determination of his negroes, their
master sent them to New Orleans, to be sold
like beasts, and there Reuben and his wife,
meeting with poor Maria, and finding her to be
a sister in Jesus, formed the resolution of
purchasing her freedom, which they
accomplished by uniting the savings each had
made previous to their marriage; and they then
took her home to live with them.</p>
          <p>In New Orleans they might have settled
comfortably, had not the unhappy prejudice
which exists there against their colour caused
them perpetual uneasiness. When they walked
in the streets, they were cursed and pushed out
of their way by white people passing along.
Even when they assembled together, in their
own house, or in that of some of their
<pb id="madd17" n="17"/>
christian friends, for religious worship, they
could have no peace at all from the
annoyances of the white men.</p>
          <p>It was chiefly in the hope of enjoying
religious liberty in a free State that they resolved
upon removing to New York. Reuben engaged
two berths on board a vessel bound there,
commanded by a Captain Russell, and having
paid 70 dollars for them, he, with his wife and
Maria, soon bid adieu to the land of slavery;
but not, as they soon found, to the sorrow,
which the wicked pride of the white man makes
so frequent an attendant on a coloured skin.</p>
          <p>When Reuben, after enjoying the fine day on
deck, rose to go to his berth in the steerage,
the captain, with oaths and curses, told him that
a <hi rend="italics">black</hi> fellow should never be allowed to go
near the white people's berth in his ship; and to
all Reuben's remonstrances, he only replied that
<pb id="madd18" n="18"/>
they might push aside the wood in the long
boat, and get room among the pigs to sleep, if
they liked.</p>
          <p>At the entreaty of some ladies on board, the
blankets which Reuben had provided for his
berths, were fetched from them; and, wrapped
in these, the oppressed <sic corr="family">fa-family</sic> sheltered as
well as they could each night in the long boat.
But the voyage proved a tempestuous one,
cold, and with almost constant heavy rain; so
that they reached New York in a most pitiable
condition, <sic corr="though">thoug</sic> they had all been in good
health at the commencement of the voyage.</p>
          <p>Maria in time recovered, but the illness of
poor Reuben's wife ended in her death.</p>
          <p>Captain Russell was put on his trial in New
York, for his injustice and cruelty, but though
he was found guilty, and fined 40 dollars, yet
he never chose to pay the fine imposed, saying
he had no objection to go to prison, if any one
should choose
<pb id="madd19" n="19"/>
to take the trouble to send him there. After the
death of Reuben's wife, Maria went into
service—and when Captain Stuart was last in
New York, in 1828, Reuben was in very
favourable circumstances, labouring diligently,
and evidently blessed of God.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="section">
          <p>As we have introduced to English readers
some American enormities, we think it
right, before we conclude, to point at our
<hi rend="italics">own</hi>—to what Bible England not only
<hi rend="italics">permits,</hi> but supports and <hi rend="italics">encourages.</hi> May
He who alone can hasten that day, soon and
for ever part asunder our enormous system of
oppression from the professors of the gospel of
the Lord Jesus Christ.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <pb id="madd20" n="20"/>
          <head>SLAVERY IN JAMAICA EXEMPLIFIED.</head>
          <p>The following instance of cruel oppression,
practised with impunity on an unoffending
female slave, affords most conclusive
evidence of the impossibility of effectually
mitigating the evils of slavery. So long as man
is allowed to hold his fellow-man as property,
and buy and sell him, it is but too evident the
grossest abuses must and will arise. The only
certain cure for the evils of slavery is the
extermination of the system, root and branch.
We trust the Government and people of this
country will no longer be gulled with any
plausible schemes for mitigation; these like the
so called Council of Protection, will prove a
mere mockery and delusion. West India
slavery being
<pb id="madd21" n="21"/>
based on principles essentially opposed to all
right law and justice, its evils cannot be
eradicated by any legislative provisions or
enactments.</p>
          <div3 type="subsection  -  letter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Copy of Mr. Wildman's Letter to Viscount
Goderich.</hi>
            </head>
            <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
              <text>
                <body>
                  <div1 type="letter">
                    <opener>
                      <dateline>“Chilham Castle, Canterbury,<lb/>
December 27, 1830.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>“MY LORD,—I beg to call your Lordship's
attention to the papers I have the honour of
transmitting to you with this letter; they contain
the statement of an act of most atrocious
barbarity, committed on one of my slaves by a
neighbouring planter. Every attempt has been
made in Jamaica to obtain redress through the
Courts for the Protection of Slaves, the Criminal
Courts, his Majesty's Attorney-General, and his
Excellency the Governor, but in vain; I am,
therefore, compelled to
<pb id="madd22" n="22"/>
submit the case to your Lordship, requesting
that justice from the Secretary of State for
the Colonies in England, which has been
refused me by the authorities of the Island of
Jamaica, where the offence was committed.</p>
                    <closer>
                      <salute>“I have the honour to be, &amp;c.</salute>
                      <lb/>
                      <signed> (Signed) JAMES B. WILDMAN.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <trailer>“To the Rt. Hon. Viscount Goderich, &amp;c.</trailer>
                  </div1>
                </body>
              </text>
            </q>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subsection">
            <argument>
              <p>Papers presented to Parliament, by his
Majesty's command, in explanation of the
measures adopted by his Majesty's
Government, for the melioration of the
condition of the Slave population, No. 230, of
Session 1831. (Ordered by the House of
Commons to be printed, 10th. March; 1831.)</p>
            </argument>
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Extracts from a <sic corr="dispatch">despatch</sic> from Viscount<lb/>
Goderich to the Bart of Belmore, dated<lb/>
“Downing Street, Feb. 23, 1831.”</hi>
            </head>
            <p>“MY LORD,—I <sic corr="enclose">inclose</sic> to your Lordship
herewith copies of a communication
<pb id="madd23" n="23"/>
which I have received from Mr. James B.
Wildman, the owner of an estate called Low
Ground, in the parish of Clarendon, in Jamaica,
complaining of cruelties committed by a person
named Mr. M'Donald, the proprietor of an
estate called North Hall, upon an elderly
female slave, named Eleanor James, belonging
to Mr Wildman's estate.</p>
            <p>“Your Lordship will perceive, by the
documents annexed to Mr. Wildman's letter,
that the circumstances stated are as follows:—
Eleanor James states, that ‘Butler, a negro man,
belonging to Mr. M'Donald, bought a
hog from her for his master: the payment having
been delayed, she dunned the man, and he told
her his master would not pay, unless she
applied to himself. She accordingly went to
North Hall, in the evening of the 28th of
November, accompanied by another negro
woman, named Joanna Williams, also
<pb id="madd24" n="24"/>
belonging to Low Ground, and applied to Mr.
M'Donald for payment of the hog. He instantly
ordered her to be taken a short distance from
his dwelling-house, and there (he himself
superintending) to be laid down and flogged.
She was flogged by two drivers in succession;
the first used a whip, the second used switches;
she was afterwards raised and washed with
salt pickle. Mrs. M'Donald and her sister were
in the dwelling-house, and heard the order
given to flog her: the sister interceded. There
was also a white young man present, who was
walking in or near the piazza when the order
was given. The morning after, M'Donald sent
her two dollars, and ordered her to leave the
property; she did so, and went immediately to
Low Ground, and showed herself to Francis
Smith, a free black man, who is permitted to
reside on the estate.</p>
            <p>“Joanna Williams, a slave on the same
<pb id="madd25" n="25"/>
plantation with Eleanor James, states that ‘she
went with Eleanor James to North Hall, and
heard M'Donald order E. James to be flogged;
she (Joanna Williams) instantly concealed
herself among the bushes, and thus escaped
being noticed. Saw Mr. M'Donald, her
sister, and a young man whose name she
thinks is M'Leay; heard Mrs. M'Donald's
sister intercede. The flogging took place so
near the house that those in it must have
heard the screams. She kept a tally of the
stripes, and counted 200, that is, she counted
10 for each finger on both hands, and went
over both hands twice. She saw the salt pickle
applied to the wounds. The lash of the whip
was dipped in water.’</p>
            <p>“The same person, Joanna Williams, states,
in a deposition made on the third of April,
1830, that he, ‘Mr. M'Donald, observing that
Butler did not flog her to his satisfaction, called
a brown man, named
<pb id="madd26" n="26"/>
Edward, who then flogged her. As Eleanor
James was getting the flogging she asked for
water, when he, M'Donald, told her, the devil a
drop of water he would give her; he did not
care if she died on the spot; he did not care
about her master, for if he was put in the
jail-house, he would have to maintain him, as he,
her master, (meaning Mr. Wildman), had
plenty of money. After the flogging had
ceased, he ordered her to be washed with a
salt mixture, which being done, ordered them
to take her and throw her away at the negro
houses.’”</p>
            <p>The above case was brought before a
Council of Protection, assembled in Clarendon
Parish, at the instance of Mr. Taylor, attorney
of Mr. Wildman's property, on the 19th of
April, 1830. There were eight magistrates
present, (among whom were the Hon. William
Power French, and the Rev. Mr. Fearon), and
<pb id="madd27" n="27"/>
six vestrymen, who unanimously came to a
resolution that “the complaint was not properly
cognizable” by them. This decision of the
Council of Protection was referred by Mr.
Taylor to Hugo James, Esq. Attorney-General
of Jamaica, who expressed “his inability to
comprehend the principle upon which such a
resolution was framed”—and adds that it was
thus “rendered a mere nominal institution,
without the slightest benefit resulting to that
class of our society to whom it is especially
intended by the legislature that it should be, as
its name purports, a Council of Protection.”</p>
            <p>
              <hi rend="italics">(Mr. Wildman's letter, as given above, will
fill up the Narrative.)</hi>
            </p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subsection">
            <p>On this portion of the case, Viscount
Goderich, in the above-quoted despatch,
observes:—“Thus every effort was abortive
<pb id="madd28" n="28"/>
and thus it has been proved that an
Attorney for an absentee proprietor may for
months persevere in his attempt to obtain
redress for an act of oppression committed on
a slave under his charge, but unavailingly. The
strong impression made upon my mind, by the
conduct of the Clarendon Magistracy, coupled
with similar proceedings in other parochial
authorities, is that Councils of Protection are
a mockery.” And his Lordship concludes his
despatch in the following words:—“It only
remains for me to observe, with reference to
the present case, that a stronger illustration can
scarcely be supposed of the inefficacy of the
law in force in Jamaica for the protection of
slaves by the instrumentality of a numerous and
irresponsible Council.”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subsection">
            <pb id="madd29" n="29"/>
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Extract from the Christian Record of
Jamaica, <lb/>published in that Island, Oct.
1830, in further illustration of the wretched<lb/>
condition of the slaves in the British Colonies.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>One principal object of our publication is to
draw the attention of our fellow-colonists
themselves to the debasing nature of these
evils, to the end, that seeing them in their true
light, they may be induced to adopt measures
for their removal. We allude to the right, which
the owner of a slave has, to inflict corporal
punishment upon him, at his own sovereign
will and pleasure: a right held under the
Consolidated Slave Law, passed in 1816, still
in force, and which would have been
confirmed by the slave enactments of the
legislature in 1826 and 1829, had they
received the royal sanction. That this cruel and
unjust right is generally, nay almost
<pb id="madd30" n="30"/>
universally, exercised, no one, well acquainted
with the state of society in our Island,
will venture to deny. For our part, we
firmly believe that there are very few
estates, on which the slave is not in daily
dread of the lash, and that in many families
corporal punishment is commonly inflicted.
The power of punishing is vested
in the slave-owner, or his representative,
who, by the same law, is constituted the
judge of what offences require corporal
punishment, not exceeding thirty-nine
lashes. Be it understood, too, that the
law stipulates for the exemption of no age
nor sex. It merely prescribes the number
of stripes, and provides that no second
punishment shall take place in the same
day, nor until the effects of the first are
recovered from. Nay, the pregnant
female is not by law exempted. One would
have thought that our legislators, moved
by the common feelings of our common
<pb id="madd31" n="31"/>
nature would have interposed the
protecting arm of the law to shield the female
when thus situated, from the brutal power of
ferocious man. But no—even she can be laid
down—exposed, and flogged, in the presence of
the assembled population of the estate! It is
true that public feeling, in this case more
humane and merciful in its restrictions than the
law—has, in a great measure, shielded the
pregnant woman, known to be such, from so
shocking an outrage; but still, instances of such
barbarity we believe too often occur;
ruining the unfortunate woman's health, and
destroying her unborn child.</p>
            <p>The evil of corporal punishment is also shewn
in a way truly painful to every friend to the
spread of christianity. We allude to the effect
it produces, in respect to the ordinance of marriage
It consists with our knowledge, that slaves
have preferred concubinage to marriage on the
<pb id="madd32" n="32"/>
ground, that <hi rend="italics">their wives</hi> might be indecently
exposed, and cruelly flogged. And here it is to
be observed, in explanation and support of this
statement, that slaves, however licentious they
may be, regard the marriage tie with a reverence
and respect approaching to superstition. With
whatever indifference they regard the
degradation of <hi rend="italics">a concubine</hi> we know that
they look with horror on the degradation of <hi rend="italics">a
wife!</hi> Again, what kind of feeling can be
expected to exist in the mind of a child, who
witnesses the shameless punishment of a
parent? Filial respect must be weakened, if not
altogether destroyed.</p>
            <p>And must not the feelings of the parent, who
is constrained. to witness the miserable
sufferings of a child, if not hardened in criminal
indifference, be exquisitely painful. While we
are upon this part of the subject, we cannot
avoid recounting, as a proof that these
things are not the chimeras
<pb id="madd33" n="33"/>
of a distempered imagination, but sad
realities of truth and experience, the particulars
of an instance of corporal punishment,
recently inflicted in one of our workhouses by
order of the magistrates. It has been
communicated to us, by an eye-witness, on
whose veracity we can stake our own credit,
and truly, it reflects indelible disgrace upon the
community. Be it understood, however, that
we introduce this statement, not in illustration of
the main subject of the present article, viz. the
dangerous power of inflicting corporal
punishment entrusted by the law to private
individuals, but in proof that the shameless, the
unnatural, exposure of the parent's nakedness
to the child, and vice versa, are no uncommon
occurrences in our island. A memorandum was
taken by our informant, soon after witnessing
the scene, which he described, of which the
following is nearly a verbatim copy.
<pb id="madd34" n="34"/>
We omit names, but our informant has
authorized us to supply them if required.
* * *, a female, apparently about twenty-two years 
of age, was then laid down, with her
face downwards; her wrists were secured by
cords, run into nooses; her ankles were
brought together, and placed in another noose;
the cord composing this last one, passed
through a block, connected with a post. The
cord was tightened, and the young woman was
thus stretched, to her utmost length. A female
then advanced, and raised her clothes towards
her head, leaving the person indecently
exposed The boatswain of the workhouse, a
tall athletic man, flourished his whip four or five
times round his head, and proceeded with the
punishment. The instrument of punishment was
a cat, formed of knotted cords. The blood
sprang from the wounds it inflicted. The poor
creature shrieked in agony, and
<pb id="madd35" n="35"/>
exclaimed, ‘I don't deserve this!’ She became
hysterical, and continued so until the
punishment was completed. Four other
delinquents were successively treated in the
same way. One was a woman about thirty-six
years of age—another, a girl of fifteen—another, a
boy of the same age; and lastly, an old woman
about sixty, who really appeared scarcely to
have strength to express her agonies by cries.”
The boy of fifteen as our informant
subsequently ascertained, was the son of the
woman of thirty-six! She was indecently
exposed, and cruelly flogged, in the presence
of her son! and then had the additional pain, to
see him also exposed, and made to writhe
under the lash!</p>
            <p>It is to be observed, to complete the
hideous, but faithful picture, of the system of
slave government, presented to us by the
narrative of this transaction, that these
unfortunates received this punishment, for
<pb id="madd36" n="36"/>
an offence which their owner, it was strongly
suspected, had compelled them to commit;
and that too, under the terror of the lash—a
circumstance accounting for the cry—‘I don't
deserve this.’</p>
            <p>Painful and melancholy as is the above
detail, we know it to be but too faithful a
picture of what is transacted, from week to
week, by order of the magistrates, within
those abodes of misery and 
degradation—the workhouses of our island.</p>
            <p>But let us revert to the especial subject of
the present article. The most appalling evil,
resulting from the power, entrusted by the law
to individuals, of inflicting the severest corporal
punishment upon the slave, is unquestionably
the extensive, and systematic destruction of
unborn children! The helpless pregnant woman,
as we have said, may, under the sanction of
the law, be subjected to the lash! We are enabled to
state, from respectable medical testimony,
<pb id="madd37" n="37"/>
that in nine cases out of ten, such inflictions
are followed by the destruction of the unborn
child.”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subsection">
            <p>After giving from the Christian Record of Jamaica
the foregoing picture of <hi rend="italics">British</hi> Slavery, we would
claim the attention of our readers to what we desire
should be the practical result which we wish to
ensue from the painful contemplation of so great
an evil, and which may be gathered from an extract
from the speech of the Rev. Mr. Legge, given in
the Cork Advertiser, for June 2, 1831. He says that—</p>
            <p>“An individual in a respectable church in
the west of Scotland, some time ago, became
heir to an estate in the West Indies. He was
requested to emancipate his slaves; he was
asked how much he would be a loser by the
act, and I believe means would have been
taken to remunerate him. He refused to do so,
and the members, exercising the right with
which they were
<pb id="madd38" n="38"/>
invested, excommunicated him from their
fellowship. Let every church act in the same
manner:—let every church cast from its bosom
every member who refuses to do justly by his
fellow-man, and the success of manumission is
at once sealed.”</p>
            <p>The Rev. James Massey (the deputation
from the Dublin Negro Friend's Society)
alluded to the circumstance mentioned by Mr.
Legge; said “he could refer to many churches
in America—Primitive Presbyterian churches—
which had come to a resolution that no slave-
proprietor should be a member of their
communion.”</p>
            <p>Without any comment of ours, we would
present another extract to our readers. “If
ever there was a time which, more imperiously
than any other, called upon the Clergy of the
Church of England to put away from
themselves, and from their Church, every
thing that can be offensive in the sight of God, or
<pb id="madd39" n="39"/>
oppressive and demoralizing to man, <hi rend="italics">this
is that time.</hi>—‘You, the Bishops and Clergy of
this Church,’ are the ministers of the God of
love, of the gospel of peace, of the religion of
mercy! You, then, above all others are called
upon—loudly called upon—not only to set the
example of ceasing yourselves to do evil, but
to warn, to exhort, to command all others, as
they value the favour of a justly offended God,
to put away from them, from this polluted
kingdom, this vile abomination.”</p>
            <p>“There seems to be something peculiarly
horrible, in a Society consisting principally, I
believe, of Christian Ministers, whose
professed object is ‘the <hi rend="italics">propagation of the
gospel,</hi>’ continuing, more than one hundred
years, the owners and oppressors of their
fellow creatures. They say, that the trust being
accepted, they cannot relinquish it; but there is
nothing in the trust to compel them to <hi rend="italics">continue
slavery.</hi></p>
            <pb id="madd40" n="40"/>
            <p>“They affirm, that to emancipate the
slaves would be to injure them; and
that, before that can be done with good
effect, preparatory steps must be taken
Now this, or something like this,
was said by bishops, members of this
society, when preaching for the benefit of it,
more than <hi rend="italics">one hundred years</hi> ago. These
assertions have been repeated many times by
other bishops, and yet the task of preparation,
it seems, is still to be begun;”— that even for
slaves on the Society's estates—<hi rend="italics">these</hi> are not
yet <hi rend="italics">fit</hi> to be elevated into the condition of
human creatures, they are still <hi rend="italics">chattels</hi>—
notwithstanding all the moral and religious
advantages which they have been favoured
with under the <sic corr="superintendence">superintendance</sic> of a religious
society whose special object is the propagation
of the gospel.</p>
            <p>Much of the above has been quoted from a
small work, that has recently issued
<pb id="madd41" n="41"/>
from the Sheffield press. May this
remonstrance, administered with no gentle
hand in the original, sink deep into the heart of
every member of the Church of England, who
has part or lot in enslaving his fellow-creatures
and fellow-subjects, and who may take up the
story of Reuben Maddison and blame <hi rend="italics">his</hi>
master.</p>
            <p>A <hi rend="italics">National Church</hi> should feel peculiarly
concerned <hi rend="italics">to put away</hi> a <hi rend="italics">national</hi> sin: but
many members of the Church of England, alas!
<hi rend="italics">have slaves,</hi> and 300 are still held in trust at
this time, belonging to the Bishops
Archbishops, and Clergy of the Church of
England. And have they a more just title to
property in their fellow-men than the master of
Reuben Maddison?—like him do they not
condemn to perpetual slavery the young,
unoffending children of the Negroes, and also
make the Negroes labour for the
purchase of that freedom to which they, like
Reuben, are already entitled? and even
<pb id="madd42" n="42"/>
when they offer the purchase money, as he
did, <hi rend="italics">it may be rejected</hi>—their bondsman may
yet find they cannot escape the grasp of this
society: for the society has resolved (and these
are their own words), “that manumissions be
granted from time to time to such slaves as
shall have recommended themselves to
favourable notice <hi rend="italics">by continued good conduct;</hi>
preference, in case of <hi rend="italics">equally</hi> good conduct,
being given to those who have purchased for
themselves the greatest number of days.” If
then, the conduct of the rejected number is as
good as that of the happy few whose chains
are broken, what must the feelings of those be
who are condemned to remain in the miserable
estate of slavery? They will wish, no doubt, as
Reuben did, to part with their <hi rend="italics">all,</hi> but they will
not obtain their freedom from the Society for
the <hi rend="italics">Propagation of the Gospel; they</hi> will still
refuse to release their bondsman and
bondswomen, and no doubt these will, in
<pb id="madd43" n="43"/>
that case, be made to feel as Reuben did, that
although they have recommended themselves,
<hi rend="italics">“by continued good conduct,”</hi> they
are still “under the grasp of a demon.” But there
is one strong feature of difference—the money
wrung from Reuben, was to be added to the
cankered gains of his master:—the money of the
Codrington Negro <hi rend="italics">will be put into the
Treasury of God!!!!</hi></p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subsection">
            <head><hi rend="italic">Extract from the Evening Mail,</hi>
August <lb/>19, 1831. <hi rend="italics">House of
Commons, Wednesday,<lb/>
August</hi> 17, 1831.</head>
            <head>SLAVERY.</head>
            <p>“MR. BURGE asked the noble Under
Secretary for the Colonies, whether
Government had taken proper measures for the
regulation and maintenance of the Crown
Slaves, who had been emancipated in the West
India Islands.”</p>
            <pb id="madd44" n="44"/>
            <p>“LORD HOWICK said, that Government
had not issued orders for the emancipation of
the Crown Slaves, until they had taken all
necessary precautions to guard against
unfortunate consequences. It was, however,
gratifying to find that these precautions were
<hi rend="italics">unnecessary.</hi> He had received a
despatch from the Governor of Antigua, which
stated, that during the five months which had
elapsed since the emancipation of the Crown
Slaves, they had been occupied industriously in
providing for their own support, and that
although their number was three hundred and
seventy-one, no case of crime had occurred
amongst them, nor were there any complaints
of poverty.”</p>
            <p>Here, then, we have irrefragable proof,
that large numbers of Slaves, de facto,
who have undergone no previous process
of preparation, may be liberated at once,
without detriment either to the public or
<pb id="madd45" n="45"/>
themselves. After this, it is to be hoped the
Codrington Trustees will no longer
persist in believing, that to enfranchise their
bondsman at once “would be followed by
more suffering and crime than have ever yet
been witnessed under the most galling
bondage.” If to make assurance double sure,
they would wish, before they liberate their
three hundred captives to take the same
precautions which Government took before
they emancipated the three hundred and
seventy one Crown Slaves in Antigua, no
doubt Lord Howick would be most happy to
inform them what those precautions were,
though in the event <hi rend="italics">they proved unnecessary.</hi>
It is hardly to be supposed, that the Negroes
under the care of the Society for the
Propagation of the Gospel are in a more
unprepared state for the enjoyment of freedom
than were the Negroes who were
held to belong to the Crown. If, therefore
the latter could safely and beneficially
<pb id="madd46" n="46"/>
be put in possession of the rights they had
so long been robbed of, no reasonable man
will say, that any injurious consequences
could be apprehended from the Society's
doing the same act of justice to those
unhappy beings, whom, by the law of the
strongest, they have held, from the hour of
their birth to this very day, in a miserable,
unchristian, and degrading bondage.</p>
            <p>Shall it be said now in the broad blaze of
gospel light, what the prophet Micah said so
long ago, “They buildup Zion with blood and
Jerusalem with iniquity.” Let the apostle James
also address them, “Behold, the hire of the
labourers who have reaped down your fields,
which is of you kept back by fraud, crieth:
and the cries of them which reaped are entered
into the ears of the Lord of Sabaoth. James v. 4.
But our Lord's words are the most remarkable and
are best adapted to the case of the Society for the
<pb id="madd47" n="47"/>
<hi rend="italics">Propagation of the Gospel in Foreign Parts.</hi>—“If thou
bring thy gift to the altar, and there rememberest
that thy brother hath ought against thee, leave
there thy gift before the altar and go thy way;
FIRST be reconciled to thy brother, <hi rend="italics">and then</hi>
come and offer thy gift.” Matt. v. 23, 24.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subsection">
            <p>In conclusion, the following interesting lines are
presented to the readers of Reuben Maddison, from the
Genius of Universal Emancipation, edited and
published by Benjamin Lundy, Baltimore, the 4th. No. of
the 1st. vol. of the 3rd. series, July, 1830, and shew,
together with the practice of the Primitive Presbyterian
Churches, that right views on the subject of slavery are
spreading in America. May they be increased in Great
Britain, especially amongst those who should be
ensamples to the flock!</p>
            <q type="quoted verse" direct="unspecified">
              <text>
                <body>
                  <head>“OUR FATHER.”</head>
                  <epigraph>
                    <p>“—As the little fellow walked by the side of my horse, I
asked him if there was any church that the slaves attended
on Sunday. He said no, there was none near enough, and
he had never seen one. I asked him if he knew where
people went to when they died, and was much affected
by the simple, earnest look with which he pointed to the
sky, and said, ‘to Fader dere.’ ” Adam Hodgson.</p>
                  </epigraph>
                  <lg>
                    <l>THAT dearest name! ay even thou, poor slave, may'st lift thine eye,</l>
                    <l>Nor dread a chilling glance of scorn will meet thee from the sky:</l>
                    <pb id="madd48" n="48"/>
                    <l>Go bend the knee, and raise the soul, and lift thy hopes above,</l>
                    <l>The God of Heaven is even to thee, a Father in his love.</l>
                    <l>The earth-worm, man, may crush thee down to slavery and shame,</l>
                    <l>And in his puny pride, usurp a <hi rend="italics">Master's</hi> haughty name;</l>
                    <l>But He, Lord God, Omnipotent, disdaineth not to bear</l>
                    <l>A <hi rend="italics">parent's</hi> cherished name to thee, to yield a parent's care.</l>
                    <l>And thou, with child-like confidence, may'st spring to his embrace,</l>
                    <l>Nor shrink in shame before the glance of that paternal face;</l>
                    <l>
                      <hi rend="italics">Thou art not yet an ingrate vile—thou hast not in thy pride</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                      <hi rend="italics">Returned him falsehood for his love, his holiest laws defied.</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                      <hi rend="italics">Thou never like a thief hast spoiled the nurslings of his fold,</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                      <hi rend="italics">Thou ne'er hast given thy brother's form to be enslaved and sold;</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l>No wrathful thunders seem to thee to clothe his vengeful arm,</l>
                    <l>Nor fearful lightnings in his eye, awake thy wild alarm.</l>
                    <l>Our Father! oh how deeply dear that holy name should be—</l>
                    <l>How should <hi rend="italics">we love</hi> the meanest one who thus may call on Thee!</l>
                    <l>And yet—Thou just and righteous God! if Thou wert <hi rend="italics">not</hi> our sire,</l>
                    <l>Long since we had been swept away by thy consuming ire.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <bibl>MARGARET.</bibl>
                </body>
              </text>
            </q>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
    <back>
      <titlePage>
        <docImprint>
          <publisher>HUDSON, PRINTER,</publisher>
          <pubPlace> BIRMINGHAM.</pubPlace>
        </docImprint>
      </titlePage>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI.2>