<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % external-entities SYSTEM "./extEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY % internal-entities SYSTEM "./intEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY brownfp SYSTEM "brownfp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY browntp SYSTEM "browntp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY browncv SYSTEM "browncv.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph> Narrative of the Life of Henry Box Brown, Written by Himself:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Henry Box Brown,  b. 1816</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Lee Ann Morawski</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by</resp>
          <name>Lee Ann Morawski</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Chris Hill and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1999</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca. 100 K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1999.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note anchored="yes">Call number  (T) E450 .B769 1851   
(Treasure Room Collection, James E. Shepard Memorial Library, North Carolina Central University)</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>Narrative of the Life of Henry Box Brown</title>
          <author>Henry Box Brown</author>
          <imprint>
            <pubPlace>Manchester:</pubPlace>
            <publisher>Printed by Lee and Glynn</publisher>
            <date>1851</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Brown, Henry Box, b. 1816.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Virginia -- Richmond -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Virginia -- Richmond -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Fugitive slaves -- Virginia -- Richmond -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- Virginia -- Richmond -- History -- 19th
century.</item>
            <item>Plantation life -- Virginia -- Richmond -- History -- 19th
century.</item>
            <item>Slavery and the church -- Virginia -- Richmond -- History --
19th
century.</item>
            <item>Slaves' writings, American -- Virginia -- Richmond.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- Law and legislation -- United States.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2000-03-13, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-08-31, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-08-27, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Chris Hill</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-08-23, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Lee Ann Morawski</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="cover image">
        <p>
          <figure id="cover" entity="browncv">
            <p>[Cover Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="frontispiece image">
        <p>
          <figure id="frontis" entity="brownfp">
            <p>RESURRECTION OF HENRY BOX BROWN, AT PHILADELPHIA.<lb/>[Frontispiece Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="title page image">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="browntp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">NARRATIVE<lb/>
OF THE
<lb/>
LIFE OF HENRY BOX BROWN,</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="main">WRITTEN BY HIMSELF.</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <docEdition>FIRST ENGLISH EDITION.</docEdition>
        <epigraph>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>Forget not the unhappy,</l>
            <l>Though sorrow may annoy,</l>
            <l>There's something then for memory,</l>
            <l><hi rend="italics">Hereafter</hi> to enjoy!</l>
            <l>Oh! still from Fortune's garland,</l>
            <l>Some flowers <hi rend="italics">for others strew;</hi></l>
            <l>And forget not the unhappy,</l>
            <l>For, ah! their <sic corr="friends are">friendsare</sic> few.</l>
          </lg>
        </epigraph>
        <docImprint><pubPlace>MANCHESTER:</pubPlace>
<publisher>PRINTED BY LEE AND GLYNN, 8, CANNON STREET.</publisher>
<docDate>1851.</docDate></docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="preface">
        <pb id="bprefi" n="i"/>
        <head>PREFACE</head>
        <p>So much has already been written concerning the evils of slavery,
and by men so much more able to portray its horrid form than I
am, that I might well be excused if I were to remain altogether
silent on the subject; but however much has been written,
however much has been said, and however much has been done,
I feel impelled by the voice of my own conscience, from the recent
experience which I have had of the alarming extent to which the
traffic in human beings is carried on, and the cruelties, both bodily
and mental, to which men in the condition of slaves are continually
subjected, and also from the hardening and blasting influences
which this traffic produces on the character of those who thus
treat as goods and chattels the bodies and souls of their fellows,
to add yet one other testimony of, and protest against, the foul
blot on the state of morals, of religion, and of cultivation in the
American republic. For I feel convinced that enough has not been
written, enough has not been said, enough has not been done,
while nearly four millions of human beings, possessing immortal
souls, are, in chains, dragging out their existence in the southern
states. They are keenly alive to the heaven born voice of liberty, and
require the illumination of the grace of Almighty God. Having,
myself, been in that same position, but by the blessing of God
having been enabled to snap my chains and escape to a land of
liberty—I owe it as a sacred duty to the cause of humanity, that
I should devote my life to the redemption of my fellow men.</p>
        <p>The tale of my own sufferings is not one of great interest to
those who delight to read of hair-breadth adventures, of <sic corr="tragical">tragica</sic>
occurrences, and scenes of blood:—my life, even in slavery, has
been in many respects comparatively comfortable. I have 
experienced a continuance of such kindness, as slaveholders have to
bestow; but though my body has escaped the lash of the whip,
<pb id="bprefii" n="ii"/>
my mind has groaned under tortures which I believe will never
be related, because, language is inadequate to express them, but
those know them who have them to endure, The whip, the
cowskin, the gallows, the stocks, the paddle, the prison, the 
perversion of the stomach—although bloody and barbarous in their
nature—have no comparison with those internal pangs which are
felt by the soul when the hand of the merciless tyrant plucks from
one's bosom the object of one's ripened affections, and the darlings
who in requiring parental care, confer the sweet sensations of
parental bliss. I freely admit I have enjoyed my full share of all
those blessings which fall to the lot of a slave's existence. I have
felt the sweet influence of friendships' power, and the still more
delightful glow of love; and had I never heard the name of liberty
or seen the tyrant lift his cruel hand to smite my fellow and my
friend, I might perhaps have dragged my chains in quietude to the
grave, and have found a tomb in a slavery-polluted land; but thanks
be to God I heard the glorious sound and felt its inspiring influence
on my heart, and having satisfied myself of the value of freedom
I resolved to purchase it whatever should be its price.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="introduction">
        <pb id="bintroi" n="i"/>
        <head>INTRODUCTION.</head>
        <p>While America is boasting of her freedom and making the world
ring with her professions of equality, she holds millions of her 
inhabitants in bondage. This surely must be a wonder to all who
seriously reflect on the subject of man holding property in man, in
a land of republican institutions. That slavery, in all its phases,
is demoralizing to every one concerned, none who may read the
following narrative, can for a moment doubt. In my opinion
unless the Americans purge themselves of this stain, they will have
to undergo very severe, if not protracted suffering. It is not at
all unlikely that the great unsettledness which of late has attached
to the prices of cotton; the very unsatisfactory circumstance of
that slaveholding continent being the principal field employed in
the production of that vegetable, by the dealing in, and the 
manufacture of, which, such astonishing fortunes have been amassed—
will lead to arrangements being entered into, through the operation
of which the bondmen will be made free. The popular mind is,
in every land becoming impatient of its chains; and soon the 
American captives will be made to taste of that freedom, which by
right, belongs to man. The manner in which this mighty change
will be <sic corr="accomplished">accompished</sic>, may not be at present understood, but with
the Lord all things are possible. It may be, that the very means
which are being used by those who wish to perpetuate slavery,
and to recapture those who have by any plans not approved of by
those dealers in human flesh, become free, will be amongst the 
instruments which God will employ to overturn the whole system.</p>
        <p>Another means which, in addition to the above, we think,
will contribute to the accomplishment of this desirable object—the
destruction of slavery—is the simple, but natural narrations of
those who have been long under the yoke themselves. It is a
lamentable fact that some ministers of religion are contaminated
with the foulness of slavery. Those men, in the southern states,
who ascend the pulpit to proclaim the world's jubilee, are 
themselves, in fearful numbers, the holders of slaves! When we reflect
on the bar which slavery constituted to the advancement of the
objects at one time contemplated by the almost defunct “Evangelical
Alliance”; when we consider that Great Being who beheld the
Israelites in their captivity, and beholding, came down to deliver
<pb id="bintroii" n="ii"/>
them is still the same; have we not reason to believe that he will
in his Providence raise up another Moses, to guide the now enslaved
sons of Ham to the privileges which humanity, irrespective of
colour or clime, is always at liberty to demand. While the British
mind retain its antipathy to slavery in all its kinds, and send forth
its waves of audibly expressed opinion on the subject, that opinion; 
meeting with one nearly allied in character to itself in the
Northern States; and while both unite in tending towards the
South the reiterated demand for an honest acting, one those turgid
profession of equality peculiar to all American proceedings—in 
every thing but slavery—the Southern states must yield to the 
pressure from without; even the slaves will feel themselves growing
beyond the dimensions which their chains can enclose, and
backed by the roar of the British Lion, and supported by Northern
Americans in their just demand for emancipation, the long
downtrodden and despised bondmen will arise; and by a united voice 
assert their title to freedom. It may be that the subject of the 
following narrative has a mission from God to the human family.
Certainly the deliverance of Moses, from destruction on the 
Nile, was scarcely more marvellous than was the deliverance of
Mr. Henry Box Brown from the horrors of slavery. For any
lengthy observations, by which the reader will be detained from
the subject of the following pages, there can be no necessity
whatever.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown was conveyed from Richmond<corr sic=".">,</corr> Virginia, to 
Philadelphia in a box, three feet long, and two feet six inches deep.
For twenty-seven hours he was enclosed in this box. The following
copy of a letter which was written by the gentleman to whom it
was directed; will explain this part of the subject:—</p>
        <p>Copy of a Letter respecting Henry Box Brown's escape from
Slavery—a verification of Patrick Henry's Speech in Virginia
Legislature, March, 1775, when he said, <hi rend="italics">“Give me Liberty or
give me Death.”</hi></p>
        <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1 type="letter">
                <opener><dateline>Philadelphia, March 26th, 1849.</dateline>
<salute>DEAR——</salute></opener>
                <p>Here is a man who has been the hero of one of the most
extraordinary achievements I ever heard of;—he came to me on
Saturday Morning last, in a box tightly hooped, marked “THIS
SIDE UP,” by <hi rend="italics">overland express, from the city of Richmond!!</hi> Did
you ever hear of any thing in all your life to beat that? Nothing
that was done on the barricades of Paris exceeded this cool and
deliberate intrepidity. To appreciate fully the boldness and risk
of the achievement, you ought to see the box and hear all the 
circumstances. The box is in the clear three feet one inch long,
two feet six inches deep, and two feet wide. It was a regular old
store box such as you see in Pearl-street;—it was grooved at the
<pb id="bintroiii" n="iii"/>
joints and braced at the ends, leaving but the very slightest 
crevice to admit the air. Nothing saved him from suffocation but
the free use of water—a quantity of which he took in with him in
a beef's bladder, and with which he bathed his face—and the 
constant fanning of himself with his hat. He fanned himself 
unremittingly all the time. The “this side up” on the box was not
regarded, and he was twice put with his head downward, resting
with his back against the end of the box, his feet braced against
the other,—the first time he succeeded in shifting his position;
but the second time was on board of the steam boat, where people
were sitting and standing about the box, and where any motions
inside would have been overheard and have led to discovery; he
was therefore obliged to keep his position <hi rend="italics">for twenty miles</hi>. This
nearly killed him. He says the veins in his temples were as thick
as his finger. I had been expecting him for several days, and was
in mortal fear all the time lest his arrival should only be a signal
for calling in the coroner. You can better imagine than I can
describe my sensations, when, in answer to my rap on the box
and question, “<hi rend="italics">all right</hi>,” the prompt response came “all right,
sir.” The man weighs 200 pounds, and is about five feet eight
inches in height; and is, as you will see, a noble looking fellow.
He will tell you the whole story. Please send him on to Mr.
McGleveland, Boston, with this letter, to save me the time it
would take to write another. He was boxed up in Richmond, at
five, A.M. on Friday shipped at eight, and I opened him up at
six (about daylight) next morning. He has a sister in New
<sic corr="Bedford.">Bedford..</sic></p>
                <closer><salute>Yours, truly,</salute>
<signed>M. McROY.</signed></closer>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <p>The report of Mr. Brown's escape spread far and wide, so that
he was introduced to the Anti-Slavery Society in Philadelphia,
from the office of which society a letter, of which the following is
a copy, was written.</p>
        <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1 type="letter">
                <opener><dateline>Anti-Slavery Office,<lb/>
Philadelphia, April 8th, 1850.</dateline>
<salute>H. BOX BROWN,</salute></opener>
                <p>MY DEAR SIR,—I was pleased to learn, by your letter, that
it was your purpose to publish a narrative of the circumstances of
your escape from slavery; such a publication, I should think,
would not only be highly interesting, but well adapted to help on
the cause of anti-slavery. Facts of this kind illustrate, without
comment, the cruelty of the slave system, the fitness of its victims
for freedom, and, at the game time, the guilt of the nation that
tolerates its existence.</p>
                <p>As one privy to many of the circumstances of your escape, I
consider it one of the most remarkable exploits on record. That a
<pb id="bintroiv" n="iv"/>
man should come all the way from Richmond to Philadelphia, by
the overland route, packed up in a box three feet long, by
two and an half feet wide and deep, with scarcely a perceptible
crevice for the admission of fresh air, and subject, at that time, to
the rough handling and frequent shiftings of other freight, and
that he should reach his destination alive, is a tale scarcely to be 
believed on the most irresistible testimony. I confess, if I had not
myself been present at the opening of the box on its arrival, and
had not witnessed with my own eyes, your resurrection from your
living tomb, I should have been strongly disposed to question the
truth of the story. As it was, however, seeing was believing,
and believing was with me, at least, to be impressed with the
diabolical character of American Slavery, and the obligation that
rests upon every one to labour for its overthrow.</p>
                <p>Trusting that this maybe the impression produced by your 
narrative, wherever it is read, and that it may be read wherever the
evils of slavery are felt, I remain,</p>
                <closer><salute>Your friend. truly,</salute>
<signed>J. McKIM.</signed></closer>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <p>Were Mr. Brown in quest of an apology for publishing the
following <sic corr="Narrative, the">Narrative. the the</sic> letter of Mr. 
<sic corr="McKim">Mc.Kim</sic> would form that
apology. The Narrative was published in America, and an edition of
8,000 copies sold in about two months, such was the interest excited
by the astounding revelations made by Mr. Brown as to the real
character of slavery, and the hypocrisy of those professors of
religion who have any connection with its infernal proceedings.</p>
        <p>Several ministers of religion took a great interest in Mr. Brown,
and did what they could to bring the subject of his escape properly 
before the public. The Rev. Mr. Spauldin, of Dover, N. H.
was at the trouble to write to two of his brethren in the ministry,
a letter, of which the following is a copy. The testimonials 
subjoining Mr. <sic corr="Spauldin's">Spauldins</sic> letter were given by persons who had
witnessed the exhibition.</p>
        <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1 type="letter">
                <head>TO THE REV. MESSRS. PIKE AND BROOKS.</head>
                <opener><dateline>Dover, 12th July, 1850</dateline>
<salute>DEAR BRETHREN,</salute></opener>
                <p>A coloured gentleman, Mr. H. B. Brown, purposes to visit
your village for the purpose of exhibiting his splendid PANORAMA.
or MIRROR OF SLAVERY. I have had the pleasure of seeing it,
and am prepared to say, from what I have myself seen, and known
in times past, of slavery and of the slave trade, in my opinion, it is
almost, it not quite, a perfect fac simile of the workings of that
horrible and fiendish system. The real <hi rend="italics">life-like</hi> scenes presented
in this PANORAMA, are admirably calculated to make an unfading
impression upon the heart and memory, such as no lectures,
books, or colloquial correspondence can produce, especially on the
<pb id="bintrov" n="v"/>
minds of children and young people, who should every where be
brought before the altar of Hannibal, to swear eternal hate to
slavery, and love of rational freedom. If you can spare the time
to witness the exhibition, I am quite certain you will feel 
yourselves amply rewarded. I know very well, there are a great
many impostors and cheats going about through the is country 
deceiving and picking up the people's money, but this is of another
class altogether.</p>
                <closer><salute>Yours, very truly,</salute>
<signed>JUSTIN SPAULDING.</signed></closer>
                <trailer> I hereby certify that I have attended the exhibition of H. B.
Brown's Panorama, in this village, with very deep interest; and
most cordially subscribe my name, as an expression of my full
concurrence with the sentiment of the recommendation above.</trailer>
                <signed>A. LATHAM.</signed>
                <trailer>I agree cordially in the above testimonials.</trailer>
                <signed>A. CAVERNO.</signed>
                <trailer>I am not an experienced judge in paintings of this kind; but
am only surprised that this is so well done and so much of it
true to the life.</trailer>
                <signed>OLIVER AYER PORRER.<lb/>
Of Franklin-street, Baptist Minister.</signed>
                <trailer>Dover, N. H. July 15th, 1850.</trailer>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <p>Although the following letter, as to date, should have occupied a
place before the others, as it was addressed to the public and not to
any particular person, its present position will answer every 
purpose of its publication.</p>
        <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1 type="letter">
                <opener><dateline>Syracuse, April 26th, 1850.</dateline>
<salute>TO THE PUBLIC,</salute></opener>
                <p>There are few facts, connected with the terrible history of
American Slavery, that will be longer remembered, than that a
man escaped from the house of bondage, by coming from Richmond,
Virginia, to Philadelphia, in a box <hi rend="italics">three feet, one inch long, two
feet wide, and two feet six inches deep.</hi> Twenty-seven hours he
was closely packed within those small dimensions, and was
tumbled along on drays, railroad cars, steam-boat, and horse
carts, as any other box of merchandize would have been, 
sometimes on his feet, sometimes on his side, and once, for an hour or
two, actually on his head.</p>
                <p>Such is the well attested fact, and this volume contains the
biography of the remarkable man, Henry Box Brown, who thus
attained his freedom. Is there a man in our country, who better
deserves his liberty? And is there to be found in these northern
states, an individual base enough to assist in returning him to
<pb id="bintrovi" n="vi"/>
slavery! Or to stand quietly by and consent to his recapture?</p>
                <p>The narrative of such a man cannot fail to be interesting, and I
cordially commend it to all who love liberty and hate oppression.</p>
                <closer>
                  <signed>SAMUEL J. MAY.</signed>
                </closer>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <p>After Mr. Brown's arrival in the Free States and the recovery of
his health, in addition to the publishing of his Narrative he began
to prepare the Panorama, which has been exhibited with such
success both in America and in England.</p>
        <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1 type="letter">
                <opener>
                  <dateline>January, 1851.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>WE, the Teachers of St. John's Sunday School, Blackburn,
having seen the exhibition in our School-room, called the 
“Panorama of American Slavery,” feel it our duty to call upon all our
christian brethren, who may have an opportunity, to go and 
witness this great mirror of slavery for themselves, feeling assured
ourselves that it is calculated to leave a lasting impression upon
the mind, and particularly that of the young.</p>
                <p>We recommend it more especially on account of the exhibitor, 
Mr. Henry Box Brown, being himself a fugitive <sic corr="slave,">saave,</sic> and, therefore 
able to give a true account of all the horrors of American 
Slavery, together with his own miraculous escape.</p>
                <closer>
                  <hi rend="italics">Signed,</hi>
                  <signed>
John Francis,<lb/>
John Parkinson,<lb/>
Henry Ainsworth,<lb/>
John Tomlinson,<lb/>
Henry Wilkinson,<lb/>
John Hartley,<lb/>
James Grooves,<lb/>
John Roberts,<lb/>
Francis Broughton,<lb/>
John Alston,<lb/>
George Fielding,<lb/>
Thomas Higham,<lb/>
Daniel Tomlinson,<lb/>
Benjamin Cliff,<lb/>
John Howcutt,<lb/>
James Holt,<lb/>
Mark Shaw<corr sic=".">,</corr>
<lb/>Christopher Higham.</signed>
                </closer>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <p>Mr. Brown continued to travel in the United States until the 
Fugitive Slave Bill—which passed into law last year—
rendered it necessary for him to seek an asylum on British ground.
Such was the vigilance with which the search for victims was
pursued, that Mr. Brown had to travel under an assumed name,
and by the most secret means shift his panorama to prevent
suspicion and capture.</p>
        <closer><signed>THOMAS G. LEE,<lb/>
Minister of New Windsor Chapel, Salford.</signed>
<dateline>April 8, 1851.</dateline></closer>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="main text">
        <pb id="brown1" n="1"/>
        <head>NARRATIVE<lb/>
OF THE
<lb/>
LIFE OF HENRY BOX BROWN.</head>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
          <p>I WAS born about forty-five miles from the city of
Richmond, in Louisa County, in the year 1815.
I entered the world a slave—in the midst of a country
whose most honoured writings declare that all men
have a right to liberty—but had imprinted upon my
body no mark which could be made to signify that my
destiny was to be that of a bondman. Neither was
there any angel stood by, at the hour of my birth, to
hand my body over, by the authority of heaven, to be
the property of a fellow-man; no, but I was a slave
because my countrymen had made it lawful, in utter
contempt of the declared will of heaven, for the strong
to lay hold of the weak and to buy and to sell them as
marketable goods. Thus was I born a slave; tyrants—
remorseless, destitute of religion and every principle
of humanity—stood by the couch of my mother and as
I entered into the world, before I had done anything to
<pb id="brown2" n="2"/>
<sic corr="forfeit">orfeit</sic> my right to liberty, and while my soul was yet
undefiled by the commission of actual sin, stretched 
forth their bloody arms and branded me with the mark 
of bondage, and by such means I became their own
property. Yes, they robbed me of myself before I 
could know the nature of their wicked arts, and ever 
afterwards—until I forcibly wrenched myself from their 
hands—did they retain their stolen property.</p>
          <p>My father and mother of course, were then slaves,
but both of them are now enjoying such a measure
of liberty, as the law affords to those who have made
recompense to the tyrant for the right of property he
holds in his fellow-man. It was not my fortune to be
long under my mother's care; but I still possess a vivid
recollection of her affectionate oversight. Such
lessons as the following she would frequently give me.
She would take me upon her knee and, pointing to the
forest trees which were then being stripped of their
foliage by the winds of autumn, would say to me, my
son, as yonder leaves are stripped from off the trees of
the forest, so are the children of the slaves swept away
from them by the hands of cruel tyrants; and her voice
would tremble and she would seem almost choked with
her deep emotion, while the tears would find their way
down her saddened cheeks. On those occasions she
fondly pressed me to her heaving bosom, as if to save
me from so dreaded a calamity, or to feast on the 
enjoyments of maternal feeling while she yet retained
possession of her child. I was then young, but I well
<pb id="brown3" n="3"/>
recollect the sadness of her countenance, and the mournful
sacredness of her words as they impressed themselves
upon my youthful mind—never to be forgotten.</p>
          <p>Mothers of the North! as you gaze upon the fair 
forms of your idolised little ones, just pause for a 
moment; how would you feel if you knew that at any 
time the will of a tyrant—who neither could nor would 
sympathise with your domestic feelings—might separate 
them for ever from your embrace, not to be laid in the 
silent grave “where the wicked cease from troubling 
and where the weary are at rest,” but to live under the 
dominion of tyrants and avaricious men, whose cold
hearts cannot sympathise with your feelings, but who 
will mock at any manifestation of tenderness, and 
scourge them to satisfy the cruelty of their own 
disposition; yet such is the condition of hundreds of 
thousands of mothers in the southern states of America.</p>
          <p>My mother used to instruct me in the principles of 
morality, according to her own notion of what was good and
pure; but I had no means of acquiring proper conception of 
religion in a state of slavery, where all those who professed 
to be followers of Jesus Christ evinced more of the 
disposition of demons than of men; and it is really a matter 
of wonder to me now, considering the character of my
position that I did not imbibe a strong and lasting hatred 
of everything pertaining to the religion of Christ. My
lessons in morality were of the most simple kind. I
was told not to steal, not to tell lies, and to behave
myself  in a becoming manner towards everybody. My
<pb id="brown4" n="4"/>
mother, although a slave, took great delight in watching
the result of her moral training in the character of my 
brother and myself, whilst—whether successful or 
unsuccessful in the formation of superior habits in us it is 
not for me to say—there were sown for her a blissful 
remembrance in the minds of her children, which will be 
cherished, both by the bond and the free, as long as
life shall last.</p>
          <p>As a specimen of the religious knowledge of the slave, 
I may here state what were my <sic corr="impressions">impression</sic> in regard to 
my master; assuring the reader that I am not joking 
but stating what were the opinions of all the slaves' children 
on my <sic corr="master's">masters</sic> plantation, so that some 
judgment may be formed of the care which was taken 
of our religious instruction. I really believed my old 
master was Almighty God, and that the young master 
was Jesus Christ! The reason of this error seems to 
have been that we were taught to believe thunder to be 
the voice of God, and when it was about to thunder my
old master would approach us, if we were in the yard, 
and say, all you children run into the house now, for it
is going to thunder; and after the thunder storm was
over he would approach us smilingly and say, “what a
fine shower we have had,” and bidding us look at the flowers 
would observe how prettily they appeared; we children
seeing this so frequently, could not avoid the idea that 
it was he that thundered and made the rain to fall, in
order to make his flowers look beautiful, and I was nearly
eight years of age before I got rid of this childish
<pb id="brown5" n="5"/>
superstition. Our master was uncommonly kind, (for
even a slaveholder may be kind) and as he moved about in
his dignity he seemed like a god to us, but notwithstanding 
his kindness although he knew very well what 
superstitious notions we formed him, he never made the least
attempt to correct our erroneous impression, but rather
seemed pleased with the reverential feelings which we
entertained towards him. All the young slaves called
his son saviour, and the manner in which I was 
undeceived was as follows.—One Sabbath after preaching time
my mother told my father of a woman who wished to join
the church. She had told the preacher that she had
been baptised by one of the slaves at night—a practice
which is quite common. After they went from their
work to the minister he asked her if she believed that
our Saviour came into the world and had died for the
sins of men? And she said “yes.” I was listening
anxiously to the conversation, and when my mother
had finished, I asked her if my young master was not
the saviour whom the woman said was dead? She said
he was not, but it was our Saviour in heaven. I then
asked her if there was a saviour there too; when she
told me that young master was not our Saviour;—which
astonished me very much. I then asked her if old
master was not he? to which she replied he was not, and
began to instruct me more fully in reference to the God
of heaven. After this I believed there was a God who
ruled the world, but I did not previously entertain the 
least idea of any such Being; and however <sic corr="dangerous">dangerou</sic>
<pb id="brown6" n="6"/>
my former notions were, they were not at all out of 
keeping with the blasphemous teachings of the hellish 
system of slavery.</p>
          <p>One of my sisters became anxious to have her soul
converted, and for this purpose had the hair cut from
her head, because it is a notion which prevails amongst
the slaves, that unless the hair be cut the soul cannot
be converted. My mother reproved her for this and
told her that she must pray to God who dwelled in
heaven, and who only could convert her soul; and said
if she wished to renounce the sins of the world she
should recollect that it was not by outside show, such as
the cutting of the hair, that God measured the <sic>worthi-</sic>
or unworthiness of his servants. “Only ask of God,”
she said, “with an humble heart, forsaking your sins
in obedience to his divine commandment, and whatever 
mercy is most fitting for your condition he will
graciously bestow.”</p>
          <p>While quite a lad my principal employment was
waiting upon my master and mistress, and at intervals
taking lessons in the various kinds of work which was
carried on on the plantation: and I have often, there—
where the hot sun sent forth its scorching rays upon my
tender head—looked forward with dismay to the time
when I, like my fellow slaves, should be driven by the
taskmaster's cruel lash, to separate myself from my
parents and all my present associates, to toil without
reward and to suffer cruelties, as yet unknown. The
slave has always the harrowing idea before him—however
<pb id="brown7" n="7"/>
kindly he may be treated for the time being—that the
auctioneer may soon set him up for public sale and
knock him down as the property of the person who,
whether man or demon, would pay his master the
greatest number of dollars for his body.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
          <p>My brother and myself were in the habit of carrying 
grain to the mill a few times in the year, which was 
the means of furnishing us with some information 
respecting other slaves, otherwise we would have known 
nothing whatever of what was going on anywhere in 
the world, excepting on our master's plantation. The 
mill was situated at a distance of about 20 miles from 
our residence, and belonged to one <sic corr="Colonel">Colonol</sic> Ambler,
in Yansinville county. On these occasions we
used to <sic corr="acquire">aquire</sic> some little knowledge of what was going 
on <sic corr="around">aronnd</sic> us, and we neglected no opportunity of 
making ourselves acquainted with the condition of other
slaves.</p>
          <p>On one occasion, while waiting for grain, we entered
a house in the neighbourhood, and while resting
ourselves there, we saw a number of forlorn looking beings
pass the door, and as they passed we noticed they gazed
earnestly upon us; afterwards about fifty did the very 
same, and we heard some of them remarking that we
<pb id="brown8" n="8"/>
had shoes, vests, and hats. We felt a desire to talk
with them, and, accordingly after receiving some bread
and meat from the mistress of the house we followed those
abject beings to their quarters, and such a sight we had
never witnessed before, as we had always lived on our 
<sic corr="master's">masters</sic> plantation, and this was the first of our journeys
to the mill. These Slaves were dressed in shirts made
of coarse bagging such as coffee sacks are made from,
and some kind of light substance for pantaloons, and
this was all their clothing! They had no shoes, hats,
vests, or coats, and when my brother spoke of their
poor clothing they said they had never before seen colored
persons dressed as we were; they looked very hungry,
and we <sic corr="divided">devided</sic> our bread and meat among them. They
said they never had any meat given them by their master. 
My brother put various questions to them, such
as if they had wives? did they go to church? &amp;c.,
they said they had wives, but were obliged to marry
persons who worked on the same plantation, as the
master would not allow them to take wives from other
plantations, consequently they were all related to each
other, and the master obliged them to marry their 
relatives or to remain single. My brother asked one of
them to show him his sisters:—he said he could not
distinguish them from the rest, as they were all his 
sisters. Although the slaves themselves entertain 
considerable respect for the law of marriage as a moral 
principle, and are exceedingly well pleased when they 
can obtain the services of a minister in the performance
<pb id="brown9" n="9"/>
of the ceremony, yet the law recognizes no right in
slaves to marry at all. The relation of husband and
wife, parent and child, only exists by the toleration of
their master, who may insult the slave's wife, or violate
her person at any moment, and there is no law to 
punish him for what he has done. Now this not only may
be as I have said, but it <sic corr="actually">actualy</sic> is the case to an
alarming extent; and it is my candid opinion, that one
of the strongest motives which operate upon the 
slaveholders in inducing them to <sic corr="maintain">mantain</sic> their iron grasp
upon the unfortunate slaves, is because it gives them
such unlimited control over the person of their female
slaves. The greater part of slaveholders are licentious
men, and the most respectable and kind masters keep
some of these slaves as mistresses. It is for their
pecuniary <sic corr="interest">inerrest</sic> to do so, as their progeny is equal
to so many dollars and cents in their pockets, instead of
being a source of expense to them, as would be the
case, if their slaves were free. It is a horrible idea,
but it is no less true, that no slave husband has any
certainty whatever of being able to retain his wife a
single hour; neither has any wife any more certainty
of her husband: their fondest affection may be utterly
disregarded, and their devoted attachment cruelly
ignored at any moment a brutal slave-holder may
think fit.</p>
          <p>The slaves on Col. Ambler's plantation were never
allowed to attend church, but were left to manage their
religious affairs in their own way. An old slave whom
<pb id="brown10" n="10"/>
they called John, decided on their religious profession
and would baptize the approved parties during the
silent watches of the night, while their master was
asleep. We might have got information on many
things from these slaves of Col. Ambler, but, while we
were thus engaged, we perceived the overseer directing
his steps towards us like a bear for its prey: we had
however, time to ask one of them if they were ever
whipped? to which he replied that not a day passed
over their heads without some of them being brutally
punished; “and” said he “we shall have to suffer for
this talk with you. It was but this morning,” he 
continued, “that many of us were severely whipped for
having been baptized the night before!” After we left
them we heard the screams of these poor creatures while
they were suffering under the blows of the hard treatment 
received from the overseers, for the crime, as we
supposed, of talking with us. We felt thankful that we
were exempted from such treatment, but we had no
certainty that we should not, ere long be placed in a
similar position.</p>
          <p>On returning to the mill we met a young man, a 
relation of the owner of this plantation, who for some
time <sic corr="had">bad</sic> been eyeing us very attentively. He at
length asked us if we had ever been whipped? and
when I told him we had not, he replied, “well neither
of you will ever be of any value”. He expressed a good
deal of surprise that we were allowed to wear hats and
shoes, supposing that slaves had no business to wear
<pb id="brown11" n="11"/>
such clothing as their master wore. We had carried
our fishing lines with us and requested the privilege
of fishing in his stream, which he roughly denied us, 
saying “we do not allow niggers to fish”. Nothing 
daunted, however, by the rebuff, my brother went to 
another place, where, without asking permission of any
one, he succeeded in obtaining a plentiful supply of
fish and on returning, the young slave-holder seemed
to be displeased at our success, but, knowing that we
caught them in a stream which was not under his
control, he said nothing. He knew that our master was 
a rich slave-holder and, probably, he guessed from our 
appearance that we were favourites of his, so perhaps 
he was somewhat induced, from that consideration, to 
let us alone, at any rate he did not molest us any more.</p>
          <p>We afterwards carried our corn to a mill 
belonging to a Mr. Bullock, only about ten miles 
distant from our plantation. This man was very kind to
us; if we were late at night he would take us into his
house, give us beds to sleep upon, and take charge of 
our horses. He would even carry our grain himself 
into the mill; and he always furnished us in the morning 
with a good breakfast. We were rather astonished,
for some time, that this <sic corr="man">mau</sic> was so kind to us—until we
learned that he was not a slave-holder. This miller
allowed us to catch as many fishes as we chose, and
even furnished us with fishing implements when we had 
none, or only very imperfect ones, of our own.</p>
          <pb id="brown12" n="12"/>
          <p>While at this mill we became acquainted with a 
coloured man from a northern part of the country; and
as our desire was strong to learn how our brethren fared
in other places, we questioned him respecting his treatment. 
He complained much of his hard fate; he said
he had a wife and one child, and begged for some of our
fish to carry to his wife, which we gladly gave him.
He told us he had just sent a few hickory nuts to market 
for which he had received 36 cents, and that he had
given the money to his wife, to furnish her with some
little articles of comfort.</p>
          <p>On our return from their place, one time, we met
with a coloured man and woman, who were very cross
to each other<corr sic="(no punctuation)">.</corr> We inquired as to the cause of their
disagreement and the man told us that the woman had
such a tongue, and that some of them and taken a sheep
<sic corr="because"/> they did not get enough to eat, and this woman,
after eating of it, went and told their master, and they
had all received a severe whipping. This man enjoined
upon his slaves never to steal from him again, but to
steal as much as they chose from any other person:
and if they took care to do it in such a manner, as the
owner could not catch them in the act, nor be able to
swear to the property after they had fetched it, he would
shield them from punishment provided they would give
him a share of the meat. Not long after this the slaves
availing themselves of their masters protection, stole a
pig from a neighbouring plantation, and, according to
their agreement, furnished their master with his share.
<pb id="brown13" n="13"/>
The owner of the missing animal, however, having
heard something to make him suspect what had become
of his property, came rushing into the house of the man
who had just eaten of the stolen food, and in a very 
excited manner demanded reparation from him for the
beast which his slaves had stolen; and the villain, rising
from the table where he had just been eating of the
stolen property, said, my servants know no more about
your stolen hog than I do, which indeed was perfectly
true, and the loser of the swine went away without saying 
any more; but although the master of this slave
with whom we were talking, had told him that it was
no sin to steal from others, my brother took good care
to let him know, before we separated, that it was as
much a sin in the sight of God to steal from the one as
the other, “Oh”, said the master, “niggers has nothing to
do with God,” and indeed the whole feature of slavery
is so utterly inconsistent with the principles of religion,
reason, and humanity, that it is no wonder that the
very mention of the word God grates upon the ear as
if it <sic corr="typified">typefied</sic> the degeneracy of this hellish system.</p>
          <lg type="verse">
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>Turn! great Ruler of the skies!</l>
              <l>Turn from their sins thy searching eyes;</l>
              <l>Nor let the offences of their hand,</l>
              <l>Within thy book recorded stand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>There's not a sparrow or a worm</l>
              <l>O'erlooked in thy decrees,</l>
              <pb id="brown14" n="14"/>
              <l>Thou raisest Monarchs to a throne—</l>
              <l>They sink with equal ease.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <l>May Christ's example, all divine</l>
              <l>To us a model prove!</l>
              <l>Like his, O God! our hearts incline,</l>
              <l>Our enemies to love!</l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
          <p>My Master's son Charles, at one time, became 
impressed with the evils of slavery, and put his notion
into practical effect by emancipating about forty of his
slaves, and paying their <sic corr="expenses">expences</sic> to a free state. Our
old master, about this time, being unable to attend to
all his affairs himself, employed an overseer whose, 
disposition was so cruel as to make many of the slaves run
away. I fancy the neighbours began to clamour about
our masters mild treatment to his slaves, for which 
reason he was induced to employ an overseer. The change 
in our treatment was so great, and so much for the
worse, that we could not help lamenting that the master
had adopted such a change. There is no telling what
might have been the result of this new method amongst
slaves, so unused to the lash as we were, if in the midst
of the experiment our old master had not been called
upon to go the way of all the earth. As he was about
to expire he sent for my mother and me to come to his
<pb id="brown15" n="15"/>
bedside; we ran with beating hearts and highly elated
feelings, not doubting, in the<sic>,</sic>  least, but that he was 
about to confer upon us the boon of freedom—for we 
had both expected that we should be set free when 
master died—but imagine our deep disappointment 
when the old man called me to his side and said, Henry 
yon, will make a good Plough-boy, or a good gardener, 
now you must be an honest boy and never tell an untruth.</p>
          <p>I have given you to my son William, and you must 
obey him; thus the old gentleman deceived us by his 
former kind treatment and raised expectation in our 
youthful minds which were doomed to be overthrown.
He went to stand before the great Jehovah to give an 
account of the deeds done in the body, and we, 
disappointed in our expectations, were left to mourn, not so
much our <sic corr="master's">masters</sic> death, as our galling bondage. If 
there is any thing which tends to buoy up the spirit 
of the slave, under the pressure of his severe toils, more
than another, it is the hope of future freedom: by this
his heart is cheered and his soul is lighted up in the 
midst of the fearful scenes of agony and suffering which
he has to <sic corr="endure">endnre</sic>. Occasionally, as some event approaches
from which he can calculate on a relaxation of his
sufferings, his hope burns with a bright blaze: but 
most generally the mind of the slave is filled with 
gloomy apprehension of a still harder fate. I have 
known many slaves to labour unusually hard with the 
view of obtaining the price of their own redemption, 
and, after they had paid for themselves over and over
<pb id="brown16" n="16"/>
again, were—by the unprincipled tyranny and fiendish
mockery of moral principle in which their barbarous
masters delight to indulge—still refused what they had
so fully paid for, and what they so ardently desired.
Indeed a great many masters hold out to their slaves the
object of purchasing their own freedom—in order to 
induce them to <sic corr="labour">labonr</sic> more—without at the same time, 
entertaining the slightest idea of ever fulfilling their
promise.</p>
          <p>On the death of my old master, his property was 
inherited by four sons, whose names were, Stronn, Charles,
John, and William Barret; so the human as well
as every other kind of property, came to be divided
equally amongst these four sons, which division—as it
separated me from my father and mother, my sister
and brother, with whom I had hitherto been allowed
to live—was the most severe trial to my feelings which
I had ever <sic corr="endured">eudured</sic>. I was then only 15 years of age,
but it is as present in my mind as if but yesterday's
sun had shone upon the dreadful exhibition. My
mother was separated from her youngest child, and it
was not till after she had begged most <sic corr="piteously">pitiously</sic> for its
restoration, that she was allowed to give it one farewell 
embrace, before she had to let it go for ever. This 
kind of torture is a thousand fold more cruel and 
barbarous than the use of the lash which lacerates the
back; the gashes which the whip, or the cow skin 
makes may heal, and the place which was marked, in 
a little while, may cease to exhibit the signs of what
<pb id="brown17" n="17"/>
it had endured, but the pangs which lacerate the soul
in consequence of the forcible disruption of parent and
the dearest family ties, only grow deeper and more
piercing, as memory fetches from a greater distance the
horrid acts by which they have been produced. And
there is <sic corr="no">uo</sic> doubt but they under the weighty infirmities
of declining life, and the increasing force and vividness 
with which the mind retains the memoranda of the 
agonies of former years—which form so great a part 
of memory's possessions in the minds of most slaves 
—hurry thousands annually from off the stage of life.</p>
          <p>Mother, my sister Jane, and myself, fell into the 
hands of William Barret. My sister Mary and her 
children went another way; Edward, another, and John 
and Lewis and my sister Robinnet another. William 
Barret took my sister Martha for his “keep Miss.” 
It is a difficult thing to divide all the slaves on a
plantation; for no person wishes for all children, or all old
people; while both old, young, and middle aged have to 
be divided:—but the tyrant slave-holder regards not 
the social, or domestic feelings of the slave, and makes 
his division according to the <hi rend="italics">moneyed</hi> value they possess, 
without giving the slightest consideration to the domestic 
or social ties by which the <sic corr="individuals">indlviduals</sic> are bound to 
each other; indeed their common expression is, that 
“dniggers have no feelings.”</p>
          <p>My father and mother were left on the plantation; 
but I was taken to the city of Richmond, to work in a
tobacco manufactory, owned by my old master's son
<pb id="brown18" n="18"/>
William, who had received a special charge from his 
father to take good care of me, and which charge my
new master endeavoured to perform. He told me if I 
would behave well he would take good care of me and
give me money to spend; he talked so kindly to me 
that I determined I would exert myself to the utmost 
to please him, and do just as he wished me in every 
respect. He furnished me with a new suit of clothes, 
and gave me money to buy things to send to my mother. 
One day I overheard him telling the overseer that <hi rend="italics">his 
father had raised me</hi>—that I was a smart boy and that 
he must never whip me. I tried exceedingly hard to 
perform what I thought was my duty, and escaped the 
lash almost entirely, although I often thought the <sic>over 
seer</sic> would have liked to have given me a whipping, 
but my master's orders, which he dared not altogether 
to set aside, were my defence; so under these
circumstances my lot was comparatively easy.</p>
          <p>Our Overseer at that time was a coloured man, whose
name was Wilson Gregory; he was generally
considered a shrewd and sensible man, especially to be a 
man of colour; and, after the orders which my master
gave him concerning me, he used to treat me very 
kindly indeed, and gave me board and lodgings in his
own house. Gregory acted as book-keeper also to my
master, and was much in favour with the merchants
of the <sic corr="city">ciiy</sic> and all who knew him; he instructed me
how to judge of the qualities of tobacco, and with the
view of making me a more proficient judge of that 
<pb id="brown19" n="19"/>
article, he advised me to learn to chew and to smoke 
which I therefore <sic corr="did.">did,</sic></p>
          <p>About eighteen months after I came to the city of
Richmond, an extraordinary <sic corr="occurance">occurence</sic> took place which
caused great excitement all over the town. I did not then
know precisely what was the cause of this excitement, 
for I could got no satisfactory information from my 
master, only he said that some of the slaves had plotted 
to kill their owners. I have since learned that it was 
the famous <sic corr="Nat.">Mat.</sic> Turner's insurrection. Many slaves 
were whipped, hung, and cut down with the swords in 
the streets; and some that were found away from their 
quarters after dark, were shot; the whole city was in 
the utmost excitement, and the whites seemed terrified 
beyond measure, so true it is that the “wicked flee when 
no man pursueth.” Great numbers of slaves were loaded
with irons; some were half hung as it was termed 
—that is they were suspended from some tree with a 
rope about their necks, so adjusted as not quite to
strangle them—and then they were pelted by men and 
boys with rotten eggs. This half-hanging is a refined 
species of punishment peculiar to slaves! This 
insurrection took place some distance from the city, and was
the occasion of the enacting of that law by which more
than five slaves were forbidden to meet together unless 
they were at work; and also of that, for the silencing 
all coloured preachers. One of that class in our city, 
refused to obey the impious mandate, and in 
consequence of his refusal, was severely whipped. His
<pb id="brown20" n="20"/>
religion was, however, found to be too deeply rooted for 
him to be silenced by any mere power of man, and 
consequently, no efforts could avail to extort from his 
lips, a promise that he would cease to proclaim the glad 
tidings of the gospel to his enslaved and perishing 
fellow-men.</p>
          <p>I had now been about two years in Richmond city, 
and not having, during that time, seen, and very seldom 
heard from, my mother, my feelings were very much tried 
by the separation which I had thus to endure. I missed 
severely her welcome smile when I returned from my 
daily task; no one seemed at that time to sympathise 
with me, and I began to feel, indeed, that I really was 
alone in the world; and worse than all, I could console 
myself with no hope, not even the most distant, that I 
should ever see my beloved parents again.</p>
          <p>About this time Wilson Gregory, who was our overseer,
died, and his place was supplied by a man named 
Stephen Bennett, who had a wooden leg; and who used 
to creep up behind the slaves to hear what they had to 
talk about in his absence; but his wooden leg generally 
betrayed him by coming into contact with something 
which would make a noise, and that would call the 
attention of the slaves to what he was about. He 
was a very mean man in all his ways, and was very 
much disliked by the slaves. He used to whip them,
often, in a shameful manner. On one occasion I saw 
him take a slave, whose name was Pinkney, and make 
him take him off his shirt; he then tied his hands and
<pb id="brown21" n="21"/>
gave him one hundred lashes on his bare back; and all
this, because he lacked three pounds of his task, which
was valued at six cents. I saw him do many other 
things which were equally cruel, but it would be useless
to multiply instances here, as no rational being doubts
that slavery, even in its mildest forms is a hard and cruel
fate. Yet with all his barbarities and cruelties this man
was generally reckoned a very sensible man in religious
subjects, and he used to be frequently talking about
things of that sort, but sometimes he spoke with very 
great levity indeed. He used to say that if he died and 
went to hell, he had enough of sense to fool the devil 
and get out. He did take his departure at last, to that
bower, whence borne, no traveller returns, and whether
well or ill prepared for the change, I will not say.</p>
          <p>Bennet was followed as overseer, by one Henry 
Bedman, and he was the best that we had. He neither 
used the whip nor cheated the hands of what little they
had to receive, and I am confident that he had more
work done by equal numbers of hands, than had been
done under any overseer either before or since his 
appointment to office. He possessed a much greater 
influence by his kindness than any overseer did by his
lash. He was altogether a very good man; was very
fond of sacred music, and used to ask me and some of
the other slaves, who were working in the same room
to sing for him—something “smart” as he used to say,
which we were generally as well pleased to do, as he 
was to ask us: it was not our fate however to enjoy his
<pb id="brown22" n="22"/>
kindness long, he too very soon died, and his death was 
looked upon as a misfortune by all who had been slaves
under him.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
          <p>After the death of our lamented overseer we were 
placed under the care of one of the meanest and cruelest 
men that I ever knew; but before alluding 
particularly to his conduct, it may be interesting to describe 
the circumstances and condition of the slaves he had to
superintend. The building in which I worked was about
three hundred feet in length, and three stories high;
affording room for two hundred people to work, but only
one hundred and fifty were kept. One hundred and
twenty of the persons employed were slaves, and the 
remainder free coloured people. We were obliged to
work fourteen hours a day in the summer, and sixteen
in the winter. One week consisted in separating the
stems from the leaves of Tobacco; the leaves were then
moistened with a fluid made from Liquorice and Sugar,
which renders it not perfectly <sic corr="abhorrent">abhorent</sic> to the taste of
those who work it. These operations were performed
by the women and boys, and after being thus moistened 
the leaves were then taken by the men and with the
hands pressed into lumps and then twisted; it was then
sent to what is called the machine house, and pressed
into boxes and casks, whence it went to the sweat house
<pb id="brown23" n="23"/>
and after lying about thirty days there, are taken out
and shipped for the market.</p>
          <p>The name of our overseer was John F. Allen, he was
a thorough-going villain in all his modes of doing 
business; he was a savage looking sort of man; always
apparently ready for any work of barbarity or
cruelty to which the most depraved despot might call
him. He understood how to turn a penny for his own
advantage as well as any man. No person could match
him in making a bargain; but whether he had acquired
his low cunning from associating with that clan, or
had it originally as one of the inherent properties of
his diabolical disposition, I could not discover, but he
excelled all I had ever seen in low mean trickery and
artifice. He used to boast that by his shrewdness in
managing the slaves, he made enough to support himself 
and family—and he had a very large family which I
am sure consumed not less than one hundred dollars
per annum—without touching one farthing of his own
salary, which was fifteen hundred dollars per annum.</p>
          <p>Mr. Allen used to rise very early in the morning,
not that he might enjoy sweet communion with his own
thoughts, or with his God; nor that he might further
the <hi rend="italics">legitimate</hi> interest of his master, but in order to
look after matters which principally concerned himself;
that was to rob his master and the poor slaves that were
under his <sic corr="control,">controul,</sic> by every means in his power. His
early rising was looked upon by our master as a token
of great devotedness to his business; and as he was <sic corr="withal">withall</sic>
<pb id="brown24" n="24"/>
very pious and a member of the Episcopalian Church, 
my master seemed to place great confidence in him. It 
was therefore no use for any of the workmen to 
complain to the master of anything the overseer did, for he 
would not listen to a word they said, but gave his sanction 
to his barbarous conduct in the fullest extent, no 
matter how <sic corr="tyrannical">tyranical</sic> or unjust that conduct, or how cruel 
the punishments which he inflicted; so that that demon 
of an overseer was in reality our master.</p>
          <p>As a specimen of Allen's cruelty I will mention the
revolting case of a coloured man, who was frequently in
the habit of singing. This man was taken sick, and
although he had not made his appearance at the factory
for two or three days, no notice was taken of him; no
medicine was provided nor was there any physician 
employed to heal him. At the end of that time Allen 
ordered three men to go to the house of the invalid and
fetch him to the factory; and of course, in a little while
the sick man appeared; so feeble was he however from
disease, that he was scarcely able to stand. Allen, 
notwithstanding, desired him to be stripped and his hands
tied behind him; he was then tied to a large post and
questioned about his singing; Allen told him that his
singing consumed too much time, and that it hurt him
very much, but that he was going to give him some 
medicine that would cure him; the poor trembling man
made no reply and immediately the pious overseer Allen, 
for no other crime than sickness, inflicted two-hundred 
lashes upon his bare back; and even this might probably
<pb id="brown25" n="25"/>
have been but a small part of his punishment, had
not the poor man fainted away: and it was only then 
the blood-thirsty fiend ceased to apply the lash! I 
witnessed this transaction myself, but I durst not venture 
to say that the tyrant was doing wrong, because I was 
a slave and any <sic corr="interference">interferance</sic> on my part, would have 
led to a similar punishment upon myself. This poor 
man was sick for four weeks afterwards, during which 
time the weekly allowance, of seventy cents, for the 
hands to board themselves with, was <sic corr="withheld,">witheld,</sic> and the 
poor man's wife had to support him in the best way 
she could, which in a land of slavery is no easy matter.</p>
          <p>The advocates of slavery will sometimes tell us, that
the slave is in better circumstances than he would be in
a state of freedom, because he has a master to provide
for him when he is sick; but even if this doctrine were
true it would afford no argument whatever in favor of
slavery; for no amount of kindness can be made the
lawful price of any man's liberty, to infringe which is
contrary to the laws of humanity and the decrees of God.
But what is the real fact? In many instances the 
severe toils and exposures the slave has to endure at
the will of his master, brings on his disease, and even
then he is liable to the <hi rend="italics">lash for medicine</hi>, and to live,
or die by starvation as he may, without any support
from his owner; for there is no law by which the 
master may be punished for his cruelty—by which he 
may be compelled to support his suffering slave.</p>
          <pb id="brown26" n="26"/>
          <p>My master knew all the circumstances of the case
which I have just related, but he never interfered, nor 
even reproved the cruel overseer for what he had done; 
his motto was, Mr. Allen is always right, and so, right 
or wrong, whatever he did was law, and from his will 
there was no appeal.</p>
          <p>I have before stated, that Mr. Allen was a very pious 
man—he was also a church member, but was much 
addicted to the habit of profane swearing—a vice which 
is, in slave countries, not at all uncommon in church 
members. He used particularly to expend his swearing 
breath in denunciation of the whole race of negroes—
using more bad terms than I could here employ, without 
polluting the pen with which I write. Amongst 
the best epithets, were; “hogs,” “dogs,” “pigs,” &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
          <p>At one time he was busily engaged in reading the
bible, when a slave came in who had been about <sic>**n</sic>
minutes behind his time—precious time! Allen 
depended upon the <sic corr="punctuality">punctuallity</sic> of his slaves, for the
support of his family, in the manner previously noticed:
his anxiety to provide for his household, led him to 
indulge in a boisterous outbreak of anger; so that when 
the slave came in, he said, what are you so late for you
black scamp? The poor man endeavoured to apologize 
for his lateness, but it was to no purpose. This professing
christian proceeded to try the effects of the Bible on
the slave's body, and actually dealt him a heavy blow 
in the face with the sacred book! But that not answering 
his purpose, and the man standing silent, he caught
<pb id="brown27" n="27"/>
up a stick, and beat him with that. The slave afterwards
complained to the master of the overseer's 
conduct, but was told that Mr. Allen would not do 
anything wrong.</p>
          <p>Amongst Mr. Allen's other religious offices, he held
that of <sic corr="superintendent">superintendant</sic> of the sunday school, where he
used to give frequent exhortations to the slaves' children,
in reference to their duty to their master. He told
them they must never disobey their master, nor lie, nor
steal, for if they did any of these, they would be sure to
go to hell. But notwithstanding the deceitfulness of
his character, and the fiendishness of his disposition,
he was not, himself, perfectly proof against the influence
of fear. One day it came on a heavy thunder storm;
the clouds lowered heavily, and darkness usurped the
dominion of day—it was so dark that the hands could
not see to work, and I then began to converse with Mr.
Allen about the storm. I asked him if it was not
dangerous for the hands to work while the lightning
flashed so terribly? He replied, he thought so, but
he was placed there to keep them at their work, and he
could not do otherwise. Just as we were speaking a
flash of lightning appeared to pass so close to us, that
Mr. Allen jumped up from where he was sitting, and
ran and locked himself up in a small room, where he 
supposed the lightning would not harm him. Some of
the slaves said, they heard him praying that God would
spare his life. That was a very severe storm, and a
little while afterwards, we heard that a woman had been
<pb id="brown28" n="28"/>
killed by the lightning. Although in the thunderstorm 
alluded to Mr. Allen seemed to be alarmed; at other 
times he did not appear to think seriously about such 
things, for I have heard him say, that he did not think 
God had anything to do with thunder and lightning. 
This same official had much apparent zeal in the cause 
of the sunday school; he used to pray with, and for the 
children, and was indefatigable in teaching them the 
catechism after him; he was very particular, however, 
in not allowing them to hold the book in their own 
hands. His zeal did not appear to have any higher 
object than that of making the children more willing
slaves; for he used frequently to tell his visitors that
coloured people were never converted—that they had no 
souls, and could not go to heaven, but it was his duty 
to talk to them as he did! His liberality to the white 
people, was co-extensive with his denunciation of the
coloured race; he said a white man may do what he 
pleased, and he could not be lost; he might lie, and 
rob the slaves, and do anything else, provided he read 
the bible and joined the church!</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
          <p>It may now be proper to say a little about the state
of the churches in slave countries. There was a baptist
minister in the city of Richmond, whose name was
John Cave. I have heard this man declare in public
that he had preached six years before he was converted
<pb id="brown29" n="29"/>
and the reason of his conversion was as follows. He 
was in the habit of taking his glass of mint julep 
directly after prayers, or after preaching, which he thought 
wonderfully refreshed his soul and body; he would 
repeat the dram three or four times during the day. But
an old slave of his, who had observed his practice hinted
to him something about alternately drinking and preaching
to the people; and, after thinking seriously on
what the slave told him, he <sic corr="began">begau</sic> to repent, and was
converted. And now; he says he is truly converted,
because his conscience reproved him for having made
human beings articles of traffic; but I believe his
second conversion is just about as complete as his first
for although he owed the second change to one of 
his own slaves, and ever confessed that the first effect
of his conversion, was, to open up to his conscience the
evil of the traffic in human beings, instead of letting
those at liberty which he had under his control—and
which might <sic corr="have">bave</sic> been at once expected, as a natural
consequence of his conviction—he endeavoured to
apologize for the want of conscience, by finding, what
he called, a good master for them, and selling them all
to him.</p>
          <p>But the religion of the slave-holder is everywhere
a system of mere delusion, got up expressly for the
purpose of deceiving the poor slaves, for everywhere
the leading doctrine in the slave-holder's religion is,
that it is the duty of the slave to obey his master in all
things.</p>
          <pb id="brown30" n="30"/>
          <p>When <sic corr="Mr.">Mr</sic> Carr left the city he was succeeded by a 
Mr. <sic corr="Jeter">Teter</sic>, who remained for many years; but at the 
time when he commenced his ministerial duties, many 
of the slaves were running away to free states; on the 
learning of which Mr. Jeter's first object was to devise 
some plan by which the masters could more effectively 
prevent their negroes from escaping; and the result of 
his ingenuity was as follows. He got the deacons and 
many more of the good christians of his church, whether 
to believe or not I do not know, but to hold out that the 
place of meeting which they then <sic corr="occupied">occupyed</sic> was not large 
enough for them; and he seemed not relish being in the
same church with the negroes, but, however that was, 
he managed, with the assistance of his church members, 
to get the negroes all round the district to believe that 
out of love for them, and from pure regard to their 
spiritual interests, it had been agreed that the old meeting 
house was to be given to the negroes for their own 
use, on their paying a small portion of the price at 
which it was estimated. The church was valued at 
13,000 dollars, but they would only be required to pay
3,000 dollars in order to have it for themselves. The
negroes were pleased with the idea of having a place 
of meeting for themselves, and so were induced to save 
every cent they could to buy the chapel. They 
were thus provided with a strong motive for remaining
where they were, and also by means of this pious fraud,
which it afterwards proved itself to be, they were deprived
of such little sums of money as might occasionally drop
<pb id="brown31" n="31"/>
into their hands, and with which they might have been
assisted in effecting their escape. These resolutions
were punctually carried into effect; a splendid new
church was built for the whites; and it was made a rule
of that church, that if any coloured person entered it,
without special business, he was liable to be taken to the
watch-house and to receive 39 lashes! The negroes 
paid what was at first demanded of them for the old 
building, but when they wished to get it placed entirely 
in their hands, they were charged with a still further 
sum; and after they had paid that, they had still more 
to pay, and never, so long <sic corr="as I">asI</sic> was there, got possession 
of the church, and probably never will. A minister 
was, however, appointed to preach for them beside the 
one that preached for the white people.</p>
          <p>A man named Knopp who came from the north
preached once in the church of the negroes. He took
for his text, “<hi rend="italics">O! Jerusalem, Jerusalem which killest
the prophets and stonest them that are sent unto thee,
how often would I have gathered thee as a hen gathereth
her <sic>chidkens</sic> under her wings, and ye would not.</hi>”
Mr. Jeter and the members of the whites' church were
so offended at this man's sermon, that they went in a
body to his lodgings and were about to mob him, if he
had not been defended by a number of his own friends;
but I believe if he been left to the tender mercies
of this professed servant of the Most High, and his
christian associates, he would never have escaped with
his life.</p>
          <pb id="brown32" n="32"/>
          <p>The Rev. R<corr sic="(no punctuation)">.</corr> Ryland, who preached for the coloured
people, was professor at the Baptist seminary near the
city of Richmond, and the coloured people had to pay
him a salary of 700 dollars per annum, although they
neither chose him nor had the least <sic corr="control">controul</sic> over him. 
He did not consider himself bound to preach regularly,
but only when he was not otherwise engaged, so he
preached about 40 sermons a year and was a zealous
supporter of the slave-holders' cause; and, so far as I
could judge, he had no notion whatever of the pure
religion of Jesus Christ. He used to preach from such
texts as that in the epistle to the Ephesians, where St.
Paul says, “servants be obedient to them that are your
masters and mistresses according to the flesh, and 
submit to them with fear and trembling”; he was not
ashamed to <sic corr="invoke">iuvoke</sic> the authority of heaven in support
of the slave degrading laws under which masters could
with impunity abuse their fellow creatures.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
          <p>I now began to think of entering the matrimonial 
state; and with that view I had formed an acquaintance 
with a young woman named Nancy, who was a slave 
belonging to a Mr. Leigh a clerk in the Bank, and, like many
more slave-holders, professing to be a very pious man.
We had made it up to get married, but it was necessary
<pb id="brown33" n="33"/>
in the first place, to obtain our masters' permission, as 
we could do nothing without their consent. I therefore 
went to Mr. Leigh, and made known to him my wishes, 
when he told me he never meant to sell Nancy, and if 
my master would agree never to sell me, I might marry 
her. He promised faithfully that he would not sell her, 
and pretended to entertain an extreme horror of 
separating families. He gave me a note to my master, and
after they had discussed the matter over, I was allowed 
to marry the object of my choice. When she became
my wife she was living with a Mr. Reevs, a minister of 
the gospel, who had not long come from the north, 
where he had the character of being an Anti-slavery 
man; but he had not been long in the south when all 
his anti-slavery notions vanished and he became a 
staunch advocate of slave-holding doctrines, and even 
wrote articles in favour of slavery which were published 
in the <hi rend="italics">Richmond Republican.</hi></p>
          <p>My wife was still the property of Mr<corr sic=",">.</corr> Leigh and, from
the apparent sincerity of his promises to us, we felt
confident that he would not separate us. We had not,
however, been married above twelve months, when his
conscientious scruples vanished, and he sold my wife to
a Mr. Joseph H. Colquitt, a saddler, living in the city
of Richmond, and a member of Dr. Plummer's church
there. This Mr. Colquitt was an exceedingly cruel
man, and he had a wife who was, if possible, still more
cruel. She was very contrary and hard to be pleased
she used to abuse my wife very much, not because she
<pb id="brown34" n="34"/>
did not do her duty, but because, it was said, her manners 
were too refined for a slave. At this time my wife had a 
child and this vexed Mrs. Colquitt very much; she 
could not bear to see her nursing her baby and used to 
wish some great calamity to happen to my wife. Eventually 
she was so much displeased with my wife that she 
induced Mr. <sic corr="Colquitt">Colqnitt</sic> to sell her to one Philip M. Tabb, 
Junr. for the sum of 450 dollars; but coming to see the 
value of her more clearly after she tried to do without 
her, she could not rest till she got Mr. Colquitt to
repurchase her from Mr. Tabb, which he did in about four
months after he had sold her, for 500 dollars, being 50 
more than he had sold her for.</p>
          <p>Shortly after this Mr. Colquitt was taken sick, and
his minister, the Rev. Dr. Plummer, was sent for to
visit him; the doctor came and prayed for him and so
did other members of the church; but he did not get any
better so that they all thought he must soon die; the
doctors had given up all hopes of him, and his wife and
children, and friends, stood round his bedside in tears,
expecting every minute he would breathe his last. All
the servants were in readiness lest they should be called
to go on some message. I had just then got home from
labouring for my master; my wife was waiting for me,
but she said she expected, every minute, that some
person would be calling to tell her that master was gone,
when, to my surprise, Joseph Colquitt sent to my wife
to tell me to come and speak with him. I immediately
left my room and went to his bed-side; and as soon as
<pb id="brown35" n="35"/>
he saw me he caught hold of my hand and said;—
“Henry will you pray for me and ask the Lord to spare 
my life, and restore me to health?” I felt it my duty 
to do the best I could in asking the Lord to have mercy 
upon him, because, although he was a slave-holder, 
and a very cruel man, and had used my wife very badly, 
yet I had no right to judge between him and his God, 
so I knelt down by his bed-side and prayed for him. 
After I got up he caught hold of my arm again and said,
“one more favour I have to ask of you—go and tell all
my slaves that belong to the church to come and 
pray for me.” I went, according to his request, and we 
prayed three nights with him, after our work was done, 
and although we needed rest ourselves, yet at the earnest 
desire of the apparently dying man we were induced to 
forego our rest, and to spend our time in comforting 
him. At the end of this time he began to get a little 
better, and in a few weeks he was able to sit at table,
and to take his meals with the family. I happened
to be at his house one day, at our breakfast hour,
after he got quite well, and his wife appeared as if she
wished to joke her husband about the coloured people
praying for him when he was sick. Mrs. Colquitt had 
been expelled from the baptist church, and since that
time she had disliked religion. She pretended that she 
did not believe either in God or Devil, and went on at 
such a rate, plaguing Mr. Colquitt, about the negroes
praying for him, that he grew angry at last and 
exclaimed with an oath that it was all lies about the negroes
<pb id="brown36" n="36"/>
praying for him; he denied asking any person to pray
for him, and he said if he did ask the negroes to pray
for him he must have been out of his senses, and did
not, at the time he spoke, remember anything about
it; but his wife still persisting in what she said, he
went to the back door and calling his slaves one at a
time, asked them who it was that prayed for him, until
he got the names of all those who had been concerned
in the affair, and when he had done so, he whipped
every one of them which said he had prayed as Mrs.
Colquitt had stated<corr sic=",">.</corr> He seemed wishful to whip me
also, <sic corr="but">bnt</sic>, as I did not belong to him, he was deprived
of the pleasure of paying me for my services in the
manner, in which others had been rewarded. Mr. 
Colquitt, however, determined that I should suffer too,
and for that purpose he proceeded to sell my wife to 
one Samuel Cottrell, who wished to purchase her. 
Cottrell was a saddler and had a shop in Richmond. 
This man came to me one day and told me that Mr. 
Colquitt was going to sell my wife<corr sic=".">,</corr> and stated that he 
wanted a woman to wait upon his wife, and he thought
my wife would precisely suit her; but he said her 
master asked 650 dollars for her and her children, and
he had only 600 that he could conveniently spare
but if I would let him have fifty, to make up the price,
he would prevent her from being sold away from me.
I was, however, a little suspicious about being fooled
out of my money, and I asked him if I did advance the
money what security I could have that he would not
<pb id="brown37" n="37"/>
sell my wife as the others had done; but he said to me 
“do you think if you allow me to have that money, 
that I could have the heart to sell your wife to any other 
person but yourself, and particularly knowing that your 
wife is my sister and you my brother in the Lord;
while all of us are members of the church? <hi rend="italics">Oh! no,</hi>
I never could have the heart to do such a deed as that.”
After he had shown off his religion in this manner,
and lavished it upon me, I thought I would let him
have the money, not that I had implicit faith in his promise,
but that I knew he could purchase her if he wished
whether I were to assist him or not, and I thought by
thus bringing him under an obligation to me it might
at least be somewhat to the advantage of my wife and
to me; so I gave him the 50 dollars and he went off
and bought my wife and children:—and that very same 
day he came to me and told me, that my wife and 
children were now his property, and that I must hire a
house for them and he would allow them to live there 
if I would furnish them with everything they wanted,
and pay him 50 dollars, a year; “if you dont do this,”
he said, “I will sell her as soon as I can get a buyer
for her.” I was struck with astonishment to think
that this man, in one day, could exhibit himself in two
such different characters. A few hours ago filled with
expressions of love and kindness, and now a monster
tyrant, making light of the most social ties and
imposing such terms as he chose on those whom, but a 
little before, had begged to conform to his will<corr sic=",">.</corr> Now,
<pb id="brown38" n="38"/>
being a slave, I had no power to hire a house, and what 
this might have resulted in I do not know, if I had not 
met with a friend in the time of need, in the person of 
James C. A. Smith, Jr. He was a free man and I went 
to him and told him my tale and asked him to go and hire 
a house for me, to put my wife and children into; which 
he immediately did. He hired one at 72 dollars per 
annum, and stood master of it for me; and, notwithstanding 
the fearful liabilities under which I lay, I now 
began to feel a little easier, and might, perhaps, have 
managed to live in a kind of a way if we had been let 
alone here. But Mr. S. Cottrell had not yet done with 
robbing us; he no sooner saw that we were thus 
comfortably situated, than he said my wife must do some of 
his washing. I still had to pay the house hire, and the
hire of my wife; to find her and the children with 
everything they required, and she had to do his <sic corr="washing">washiug</sic>
beside. Still we felt ourselves more comfortable 
than we had ever been before. In this way, we went 
on for some time: I paid him the hire of my wife 
regularly, whenever he called for it—whether it was due
or not—but he seemed still bent on robbing me more
thoroughly than he had the previous day; for one
pleasant morning, in the month of August, 1848, when
my wife and children, and myself, were sitting at table,
about to eat our breakfast, Mr. Cottrell called, and said,
he wanted some money to day, as he had a demand for 
a large amount. I said to him, you know I have no 
money to spare, because it takes nearly all that I make
<pb id="brown39" n="39"/>
for myself, to pay my wife's hire, the rent of my house, 
my own ties to my master, and to keep ourselves in
meat and clothes; and if at any time, I have made 
anything more than that, I have paid it to you in advance, 
and what more can I do? Mr. Cottrell, however said, 
“I want money, and money I will have.” I could
make him no answer; he then went away. I then said
to my wife, “I wonder what Mr<corr sic="(no punctuation)">.</corr> Cottrell means by saying 
I want money and money I will have,” my poor
wife burst into tears and said perhaps he will sell one of
our little children, and our hearts were so full that 
neither of us could eat any breakfast, and after mutually
embracing each other, as it might be our last meeting,
and fondly pressing our little darlings to our bosoms,
I left <sic corr="the">the the</sic> house and went off to my daily labour
followed by my little children who called after me to
come back soon. I felt that life had joys worth living
for if I could only be allowed to enjoy them, but my
heart was filled with deep anguish from the awful 
calamity, which I was thus obliged to contemplate, as not
only a possible but a highly probable occurrence. I
now went <sic>hway</sic> to my work and I could as I went see
many other slaves hastening in the same direction. I
began to consider their lot and mine, and although my
heart was filled with sorrow I felt still disposed to look 
upon the bright side of the future. I could still see
some alleviation to my case of sorrow; it was true that 
the greater portion of my earnings were stolen from me
by the unscrupulous hand of my master; that I was
<pb id="brown40" n="40"/>
entirely at his mercy, and might at any moment be 
snatched from those enjoyments as well as those I thought
were open to me; that if he chose he might still further gratify
his robbing propensities and demand a larger portion of 
my earnings; so that the pleasures of intellect would be
completely closed to my mind, but I could enjoy myself 
with my family about me while I listened to the pleasing 
prattle of my children, and experience the kindness 
of a wife, which were privileges that every slave could 
not enjoy.</p>
          <p>I had not been many hours at my work, when I was
informed that my wife and children were taken from 
their home, sent to the auction mart and sold, and then 
lay in prison ready to start away the next day for 
North Carolina with the man who had purchased them. 
I cannot express, in language, what were my feelings 
on this occasion<corr sic=",">.</corr> My master treated me kindly but he 
still retained me in a state of slavery. His kindness 
however did not keep me from feeling the smart of this 
awful deprivation. I had left my wife and children at 
home in the morning as well situated as slaves could be;
I was not anticipating their loss, not on account of the 
feigned piety of their owner, for I had long ago learned 
to look through such hollow pretences in those who 
held slaves, but because of the obligation to me for
money I had advanced to him, <hi rend="italics">on the expressed condition
that he should not sell her to any person but myself;</hi>
such, however was the case, and as soon as I could get
away, I went and purchased some things to take to the
<pb id="brown41" n="41"/>
jail to them I so much loved; and to have one farewell
embrace before parting for ever. I had not proceeded
far however when I met with a gentleman who perceiving
my anguish of heart, as depicted in my countenance, 
inquired what was the matter with me. I had no sooner 
hinted at my circumstances, however, than he knew all 
about it, having heard it<sic>,</sic> before. He advised me not to 
go the jail, “for” said he “the man that bought your 
wife and family has told your master some falsehoods 
and has ordered the jailor to seize you and put you in 
prison if you should make your appearance there;
when you would most likely be sold separately from 
them, because the <hi rend="italics">Methodist Minister</hi> that bought 
your wife, does not want any men,” so being thus advised 
I thought it better not to go to the jail myself, but 
I <sic>grocured</sic> a friend to go in my stead, and take some 
money and the things which I had purchased for my 
wife, and tell her how it was that I could not come 
myself. And it turned out in the end to be much better that
I did not go, for as soon as the young man arrived at
the jail he was seized and put in prison, the jailor 
mistaking him for me: but when he discovered his mistake
he was very angry and vented his rage upon the 
innocent youth by kicking him out of the prison. He 
discovered his mistake by asking my wife if that were not
her husband, she said he was not; but he was not satisfied 
with her answer for he asked the children also if he 
were not their father, and as they too said no he was
<pb id="brown42" n="42"/>
convinced, and then proceeded to abuse the young man 
in the manner before mentioned.</p>
          <p>After I had heard of these things, I went to my 
<hi rend="italics">christian</hi> master and informed him how I was served, 
but he shoved me away from him as if I was not human<corr>.</corr> 
I could not rest with this however, I went to him a 
second time and implored him to be kind enough to buy 
my wife and to save me from so much trouble of mind; 
still he was inexorable and only answered me by telling 
me to go to my work and not bother him any more. I
went to him a <hi rend="italics">third</hi> time, which would be about ten 
o'clock and told him how Cottrell had robbed me, as 
this scoundrel was not satisfied with selling my wife 
and children, but he had no sooner got them out of the 
town than he took everything which he could find in 
my house and carried it off to be sold; the things which
he then took had cost me nearly three hundred dollars. 
I begged master to write Cottrell and make him give me 
up my things, but his answer was Mr. Cottrell is a 
gentleman I am afraid to meddle with his business. So 
having satisfied myself that the master would do nothing 
for me, I left him and went to two young gentlemen
with whom I was acquainted to try if I could induce 
them to buy my wife; but when I had stated my case 
to them they gave me to understand that they did not 
deal in slaves so they could not do that, but they 
expressed their willingness to do anything else that I 
might desire of them; so finding myself unsuccessful 
here, I went sorrowfully back to my own deserted home,
<pb id="brown43" n="43"/>
and found that what I had heard was quite true; not 
only had my wife and children been taken away<corr sic=".">,</corr> but
every article of furniture had also been removed to the
auction mart to be sold. I then made inquiry as to
where my things had been put; and having found this
out went to the <sic corr="sheriff's">sherriff's</sic> office and informed him, that
the things Mr<corr sic=",">.</corr> Cottrell had brought to be sold did not
belong to him, but that they were mine, and I hoped he
would return them to me. I was then told by the
<sic corr="sheriff">sherriff</sic> that Mr. Cottrell had left the things to be
sold in order to pay himself a debt of seventeen dollars
and twenty-one cents, which he said if I would pay he
would let me take away the things. I then went to my
good friend Doctor Smith who was always ready and
willing to do what he could for me, and having got the
money, I paid it to the <sic corr="sheriff">sherriff</sic> and took away the things 
which I was obliged to do that night, as far as I was 
able, and what were left I removed in the morning. 
When I was taking home the last of my things I met
Mr. Cottrell, and two of his Christian brethren, in the
street. He stopped me and said he had heard I had
been to the <sic corr="sheriff's">sherriff's</sic> office and got <sic corr="away">awa</sic> my things. Yes 
I said I have been and got away <hi rend="italics">my things</hi> but I 
could not get away <hi rend="italics">my wife and children</hi> whom you
have put beyond my power to redeem. He then began
to give me a round of abuse, while his two Christian
friends stood by and heard him, but they did not
seem to be the least offended at the terrible barbarity
which was there placed before them.</p>
          <pb id="brown44" n="44"/>
          <p>I now left Mr<corr sic="(no punctuation)">.</corr> Cottrell and his friends, and going home,
endeavoured to court a little rest by lying down in a
position so as to induce sleep. I had borne too heavy
a load of grief on my mind to admit of me even closing
my eyes for an hour during the whole night<corr sic="(no punctuation)">.</corr> Many
schemes for effecting the redemption of my family passed
through my mind, but when the <sic corr="morning's">mornings</sic> sun arose I
found myself on my way towards my <sic corr="master's">masters</sic> house, to
make another attempt to induce him to purchase my
wife. But although I besought him, with tears in my
eyes, I did not succeed in making the least impression
on his obdurate heart, and he utterly refused to advance
the smallest portion of the 5000 dollars I had paid him
in order to relieve my sufferings, and yet he was a
<sic corr="church">chnrch</sic> member of considerable standing in Richmond.
He even told me that I could get another wife and so
I need not trouble myself about that one; but I told him
those that God had joined together let no man put <sic corr="asunder,">assunder,</sic> 
and that I did not want another wife, but my own
whom I had loved so long. The mentioning of the 
<sic corr="passage">passape</sic> of scripture seemed to give him much offence for 
he instantly drove me from his house saying he did not 
wish to hear that!</p>
          <p>My agony was now complete, she with whom I had
travelled the journey of life <hi rend="italics">in chains</hi>, for the space of
twelve years, and the dear little <sic corr="pledges God">pledgesGod</sic> had given us
I could see plainly must now be separated from me for 
ever, and <sic corr="I must">Imust</sic> continue, desolate and alone, to drag my 
chains through the world. O dear, I thought shall my
<pb id="brown45" n="45"/>
wife and children no more greet my sight with their
cheerful looks and happy smiles! for far away in the
North <sic corr="Carolina swamps">Carolinaswamps</sic> are they henceforth to toil beneath
the scorching rays of a hot sun deprived of a husband's 
and a father's care! Can I endure such agony—shall I 
stay behind while they are thus driven with the tyrant's 
rod? I must stay, I am a slave, the law of men gives
me no power to ameliorate my condition; it shuts up
every avenue of hope; but, thanks be to God, their is a
law of heaven which senates' laws cannot controul!</p>
          <p>While I was thus musing I received a message, that
if I wished to see my wife and children, and bid
them the last farewell, I could do so, by taking my
stand on the street where they were all to pass on their way
for North Carolina. I quickly availed myself of this
information, and placed myself by the side of a street,
and soon had the melancholy satisfaction of witnessing
the approach of a gang of slaves, amounting to three
hundred and fifty in number, marching under the
direction of a methodist minister, by whom they were
purchased, and amongst which slaves were my wife and
children. I stood in the midst of many who, like myself,
were mourning the loss of friends and relations and had
come there to obtain one parting look at those whose
company they but a short time before had imagined they
should always enjoy, but who were, without any regard
to their own wills, now driven by the tyrant's voice and
the smart of the whip on their way to another scene of
toil, and, to them, another land of sorrow in a far off
<pb id="brown46" n="46"/>
southern country<corr sic="(no punctuation)">.</corr> These beings were marched with
ropes about their necks, and staples on their arms, and,
although in that respect the scene was no very novel
one to me, yet the peculiarity of my own circumstances
made it assume the appearance of unusual horror.
This train of beings was accompanied by a number of
waggons loaded with little children of many different
families, which as they appeared rent the air with their
shrieks and cries and vain endeavours to resist the
separation which was thus forced upon them, and the
cords with which they were thus bound; but what should
I now see in the very foremost waggon but a little
child looking towards me and pitifully calling, father!
father! This was my eldest child, and I was obliged
to look upon it for the last time that I should, perhaps,
ever see it again in life; if it had been going to the
grave and this gloomy procession had been about to
return its body to the dust from whence it sprang,
whence its soul had taken its departure for the land
of spirits, my grief would have been nothing in
comparison to what I then felt; for then I could have
reflected that its sufferings were over and that it would
never again require nor look for a father's care;
but now it goes with all those tender feelings riven, by
which it was endeared to a father's love; it must still live
subjected to the deprivation of paternal care and to the
chains and wrongs of slavery, and yet be dead to the
pleasure of a father from whose heart the impression
of its early innocence and love will never be effaced<corr sic="(no punctuation)">.</corr>
<pb id="brown47" n="47"/>
Thus passed my child from my presence—it was my own
child—I loved it with all the fondness of a father; but
things were so ordered that I could only say, farewell,
and leave it to pass in its chains while I looked for the
approach of another gang in which my wife was also
loaded with chains. My eye soon caught her precious
face, but, gracious heavens! that glance of agony may
God spare me from ever again enduring! My wife,
under the influence of her feelings, jumped aside; I
seized hold of her hand while my mind felt unutterable
things, and my tongue was only able to say, we shall
meet in heaven! I went with her for about four miles
hand in hand, but both our hearts were so overpowered
with feeling that we could say nothing, and when at
last we were obliged to part, the look of mutual love
which we exchanged was all the token which we could
give each other that we should yet meet in heaven.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
          <p>I had for a long while been a member of the choir
in the Affeviar church in Richmond, but after the severe 
family affliction to which I have just alluded in the 
last chapter and the knowledge that these cruelties were
perpetrated by ministers and church members, I began
strongly to suspect the christianity of the slave-holding
church members and hesitated much about maintaining,
<pb id="brown48" n="48"/>
my connection with them. The suspicion of these 
slave-dealing christians was the means of keeping me 
absent from all their churches from the time that my 
wife and children were torn from me, until Christmas 
day in the year 1848; and I would not have gone then 
but being a leading member of the choir, I yielded to 
the entreaties of my associates to assist at a concert of 
sacred music which was to be got up for the benefit of 
the church. My friend Dr. Smith, who was the
conductor of the under-ground railway, was also a 
member of the choir, and when I had consented to 
attend he assisted me in selecting twenty four pieces to 
be sung on the occasion.</p>
          <p>On the day appointed for our concert I went along 
with Dr. Smith, and the singing commenced at half-past 
three o'clock, p.m. When we had sung about ten pieces 
and were engaged in singing the following verse—
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg><l>Again the day returns of holy rest,</l><l>Which, when he made the world, Jehovah blest;</l><l>When, like his own, he bade our labours cease,</l><l>And all be piety, and all be peace,</l></lg></q>
the members were rather astonished at Dr<corr sic=",">.</corr> Smith, who
stood on my right hand, suddenly closing his book, and
sinking down upon his seat his eyes being at the same time
filled with tears. Several of them began to inquire 
what was the matter with him, but he did not tell them. 
I guessed what it was and afterwards found out that I 
had judged of the circumstances correctly. Dr. Smith's 
feelings were overcome with a sense of doing wrongly
<pb id="brown49" n="49"/>
in singing for the purpose of obtaining money to assist 
those who were buying and selling their fellow-men. 
He thought at that moment he felt reproved by Almighty 
God for lending his aid to the cause of slave-holding 
religion; and it was under this impression he closed 
his book and formed the resolution which he still acts 
upon, of never singing again or taking part in the 
services of a pro-slavery church. He is now in New 
England publicly advocating the cause of emancipation.</p>
          <p>After we had sung several other pieces we commenced 
the anthem, which run thus—
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg><l>Vital spark of heavenly flame,</l><l>Quit, O! quit the mortal frame,—</l></lg></q>
these words awakened in me feelings in which the 
sting of former sufferings was still sticking fast, and 
stimulated by the example of Dr. Smith, whose feelings 
I read so correctly, I too made up my mind that I would 
be no longer guilty of assisting those bloody dealers in 
the bodies and souls of men; and ever since that time 
I have steadfastly kept my resolution.</p>
          <p>I now began to get weary of my bonds; and earnestly
panted after liberty. I felt convinced that I should be 
acting in accordance with the will of God, if I could 
snap in sunder those bonds by which I was held body 
and soul as the property of a fellow man. I looked 
forward to the good time which every day I more and 
more firmly believed would yet come, when I should 
walk the face of the earth in full possession of all that
freedom which the finger of God had so clearly written
<pb id="brown50" n="50"/>
on the constitutions of man, and which was common to 
the human race; but of which, by the cruel hand of 
tyranny, I, and millions of my fellow-men, had been 
robbed.</p>
          <p>I was well acquainted with a store-keeper in the city
of Richmond, from whom I used to purchase my 
provisions; and having formed a favourable opinion of his
integrity, one day in the course of a little conversation
with him, I said to him if I were free I would be able
to do business such as he was doing; he then told me
that my occupation (a tobacconist) was a money-making
one, and if I were free I had no need to change for
another. I then told him my circumstances in regard
to my master, having to pay him 25 dollars per month,
and yet that he <sic corr="refused">refnsed</sic> to assist me in saving my wife
from being sold and taken away to the South, where I
should never see her again; and even refused to allow
me to go and see her until my hours of labour were
over. I told him this took place about five months ago,
and I had been meditating my escape from slavery since,
and asked him, as no person was near us, if he could 
give me any information about how I should proceed. 
I told him I had a little money and if he would assist 
me I would pay him for so doing. The man asked me 
if I was not afraid to speak that way to him; I said no,
for I imagined he believed that every man had a right 
to liberty. He said I was quite right, and asked me
how much money I would give him if he would assist
me to get away. I told him that I had <sic corr="166">I66</sic> dollars and
<pb id="brown51" n="51"/>
that I would give him the half; so we ultimately agreed 
that I should have his service in the attempt for 86. 
Now I only wanted to fix upon a plan. He told me of 
several plans by which others had managed to effect 
their escape, but none of them exactly suited my taste.
I then left him to think over what would be best to be
done, and, in the mean time, went to consult my friend
Dr. Smith, on the subject. I mentioned the plans which
the <sic corr="store-keeper">stor-ekeeper</sic> had suggested, and as he did not 
approve either of them very much, I still looked for some 
plan which would be more certain and more safe, but 
I was determined that come what may, I should have 
my freedom or die in the attempt.</p>
          <p>One day, while I was at work, and my thoughts were
eagerly feasting upon the idea of freedom, I felt my
soul called out to heaven to breathe a prayer to 
Almighty God. I prayed fervently that he who seeth in 
secret and knew the inmost desires of my heart, would 
lend me his aid in bursting my fetters asunder, and in
restoring me to the <sic corr="possession">posession</sic> of those rights, of which 
men had robbed me; when the idea suddenly flashed 
across my mind of shutting myself <hi rend="italics">up in a box</hi>, and 
getting myself conveyed as dry goods to a free state.</p>
          <p>Being now satisfied that this was the plan for me, I
went to my friend Dr. Smith and, having <sic corr="acquainted">aquainted</sic> him
with it, we agreed to have it put at once into execution
not however without calculating the chances of danger
with which it was attended; but buoyed up by the 
prospect of freedom and increased hatred to slavery I was
<pb id="brown52" n="52"/>
willing to dare even death itself rather than endure
any longer the clanking of those galling chains<corr sic="(no punctuation)">.</corr> It
being still necessary to have the assistance of the 
store-keeper, to see that the box was kept in its right
position on its passage, I then went to let him know my
intention, but he said although he was willing to serve 
me in any way he could, he did not think I could live 
in a box for so long a time as would be necessary to 
convey me to Philadelphia, but as I had already made 
up my mind, he consented to accompany me and keep 
the box right all the way.</p>
          <p>My next object was to procure a box, and with the
assistance of a carpenter that was very soon accomplished,
and taken to the place where the packing was to be
performed. In the mean time the storekeeper had
written to a friend in Philadelphia, but as no answer
had arrived, we resolved to carry out our purpose as best
we could. It was deemed necessary that I should get
permission to be absent from my work for a few days,
in order to keep down suspicion until I had once fairly
started on the road to liberty; and as I had then a
gathered finger I thought that would form a very
good excuse for obtaining leave of absence; but when I
showed it to one <sic corr="overseer">everseer</sic>, Mr. Allen, he told me it was
not so bad as to prevent me from working, so with a
view of making it bad enough, I got Dr. Smith to
procure for me some oil of vitriol in order to drop a little
of this on it, but in my hurry I dropped rather much
and made it worse than there was any occasion for, in
<pb id="brown53" n="53"/>
fact it was very soon eaten in to the bone, and on 
presenting it again to Mr. Allen I obtained the permission
required, with the advice that I should go home and get
a poultice of flax-meal to it, and keep it well poulticed
until it got better. I took him instantly at his word
and went off directly to the store-keeper who had by
this time received an answer from his friend in 
Philadelphia, and had obtained permission to address the
box to him, this friend in that city, arranging to call for
it as soon as it should arrive. There being no time to
be lost, the store-keeper, Dr. Smith, and myself, agreed
to meet next morning at four o'clock, in order to get
the box ready for the express train. The box which I
had procured was three feet one inch wide, two feet six
inches high, and two feet wide: and on the morning of
the 29th day of March, 1849, I went into the box—
having previously bored three gimlet holes opposite my
face, for air, and provided myself with a bladder of
water, both for the purpose of quenching my thirst and
for wetting my face, should I feel getting faint. I took
the gimlet also with me, in order that I might bore
more holes if I found I had not sufficient air. Being
thus equipped for the battle of liberty, my friends
nailed down the lid and had me conveyed to the Express
Office, which was about a mile distant from the place
where I was packed. I had no sooner arrived at the
office than I was turned heels up, while some person
nailed something on the end of the box. I was then
put upon a waggon and driven off to the depôt with my
<pb id="brown54" n="54"/>
head down, and I had no sooner arrived at the depôt,
than the man who drove the waggon tumbled me roughly
into the baggage car, where, however, I happened to fall
on my right side.</p>
          <p>The next place we arrived at was Potomac Creek,
where the baggage had to be removed from the cars, to
be put on board the steamer; where I was again placed
with my head down, and in this dreadful position had
to remain nearly an hour and a half, which, from the
sufferings I had thus to endure, seemed like an age to
me, but I was forgetting the battle of liberty, and I
was resolved to conquer or die. I felt my eyes swelling 
as if they would burst from their sockets; and the veins
on my temples were dreadfully distended with pressure 
of blood upon my head. In this position I attempted 
to lift my hand to my face but I had no power to move
it; I felt a cold sweat coming over me which seemed to
be a warning that death was about to terminate my
earthly miseries, but as I feared even that, less than
slavery, I resolved to submit to the will of God, and
under the influence of that impression, I lifted up my
soul in prayer to God, who alone, was able to deliver
me. My cry was soon heard, for I could hear a man
saying to another, that he had travelled a long way and
had been standing there two hours, and he would like
to get somewhat to sit down; so perceiving my box,
standing on end, he threw it down and then two sat upon
it. I was thus relieved from a state of agony which
may be more easily imagined than described<corr sic="(no punctuation)">.</corr> I could
<pb id="brown55" n="55"/>
now listen to the men talking, and heard one of them 
asking the other what he supposed <hi rend="italics">the box contained</hi>;
his companion replied he guessed it was “THE MAIL.” 
I too thought it was a mail but not such a mail as he 
supposed it to be.</p>
          <p>The next place at which we arrived was the city of
Washington, where I was taken from the steam-boat, 
and again placed upon a waggon and carried to the 
depôt right side up with care; but when the driver 
arrived at the depôt I heard him call for some person 
to help to take the box off the waggon, and some one 
answered him to the effect that he might throw it off; 
but, says the driver, it is marked “this side up with 
care;” so if I throw it off I might break something,
the other answered him that it did not matter if 
he broke all that was in it, the railway company were 
able enough to pay for it. No sooner were these words 
spoken than I began to tumble from the waggon, and 
falling on the end where my head was, I could bear my 
neck give a crack, as if it had been snapped asunder 
and I was knocked completely insensible. The first 
thing I heard after that, was some person saying, “there 
is no room for the box, it will have to remain and be 
sent through to-morrow with the luggage train; but
the Lord had not quite forsaken me, for in answer to 
my earnest prayer He so ordered affairs that I should 
not be left behind; and I now heard a man say that the 
box had come with the express, and it must be sent 
on. I was then tumbled into the car with my head
<pb id="brown56" n="56"/>
downwards again, but the car had not proceeded far 
before, more luggage having to be taken in, my box got 
shifted about and so happened to turn upon its right 
side; and in this position I remained till I got to 
Philadelphia, of our arrival in which place I was 
informed by hearing some person say, “We are in port 
and at Philadelphia.” My heart then leaped for joy,
and I wondered if any person knew that such a box 
was there.</p>
          <p>Here it may be proper to observe that the man who 
had promised to accompany my box failed to do what 
he promised; but, to prevent it remaining long at 
the station after its arrival, he sent a telegraphic 
message to his friend, and I was only twenty seven hours 
in the box, though travelling a distance of three hundred 
and fifty miles.</p>
          <p>I was now placed in the depôt amongst the other 
luggage, where I lay till seven o'clock, P.M., at which 
time a waggon drove up, and I heard a person inquire 
for such a box as that in which I was. I was then 
placed on a waggon and conveyed to the house where
my friend in Richmond had arranged I should be
received. A number of persons soon collected round
the box after it was taken in to the house, but as I did 
not know what was going on I kept myself quiet. I 
heard a man say, “let us rap upon the box and see if 
he is alive;” and immediately a rap ensued and a voice 
said, tremblingly, “Is all right within?” to which I 
replied—“all right.” The joy of the friends was very
<pb id="brown57" n="57"/>
great; when they heard that I was alive they soon 
managed to break open the box, and then came my 
resurrection from the grave of slavery. I rose a freeman, 
but I was too weak, by reason of long confinement 
in that box, to be able to stand, so I immediately swooned 
away. After my recovery from the swoon the first thing, 
which arrested my attention, was the presence of a 
number of friends, every one seeming more anxious than 
another, to have an opportunity of rendering me their 
assistance, and of bidding me a hearty welcome to the 
possession of my natural rights, I had risen as it were 
from the dead; I felt much more than I could readily
express; but as the kindness of Almighty God had 
been so conspicuously shown in my <sic corr="deliverance">delivcrance</sic>, I burst 
forth into the following him of thanksgiving,
<q type="song" direct="unspecified"><lg><l>I waited patiently, I waited patiently for the Lord,
for the Lord;</l><l>And he inclined unto me, and heard my calling:</l><l>I waited patiently, I waited patiently for the Lord, </l><l>And he inclined unto me, and heard my calling:</l><l>And he hath put a new song in my mouth, </l><l>Even a thanksgiving, even a thanksgiving, even a
thanksgiving unto our God. </l><l>Blessed, Blessed, Blessed, Blessed is the man, Blessed is
the man, </l><l>Blessed is the man that hath set his hope, his hope in 
the Lord;</l><l><gap reason="torn page" extent="1-2 words"/> my God, Great, Great, Great,</l><pb id="brown58" n="58"/><l>Great are the wondrous works which thou hast done.</l><l>Great are the wondrous works which thou hast done, 
which thou hast done:</l><l>If I should declare them and speak of them, they would 
be more, more, more than I am able to express.</l><l>I have not kept back thy loving kindness and truth from 
the great congregation.</l><l>I have not kept back thy loving kindness and truth from 
the great congregation.</l><l>Withdraw not thou thy mercy from me,</l><l>Withdraw not thou thy mercy from me, O Lord;</l><l>Let thy loving kindness and thy truth always preserve me,</l><l>Let all those that seek thee be joyful and glad,</l><l>Let all those that seek thee be joyful and glad, be joyful, 
and glad, be joyful and glad, be joyful, be joyful, 
be joyful, be joyful, be joyful and glad—be glad 
in thee.</l><l>And let such as love thy <sic corr="salvation">salvaiion</sic>,</l><l>And let such as love thy salvation, say, always,</l><l>The Lord be praised,</l><l>The Lord be praised.</l><l>Let all those that seek thee be joyful <sic corr="and">aud</sic> glad,</l><l>And let such as love thy salvation, say always,</l><l>The Lord be praised,</l><l>The Lord be praised,</l><l>The Lord be praised.</l></lg></q></p>
          <pb id="brown59" n="59"/>
          <p>I was then taken by the hand and welcomed to the
houses of the following friends:—Mr. J. Miller, Mr.
M'Kim, Mr. and Mrs. Motte, Mr. and Mrs. Davis, and
many others, by all of whom I was treated in the kindest
manner possible. But it was thought proper that I
should not remain long in Philadelphia, so arrangements
were made for me to proceed to Massachusetts, where,
by the assistance of a few Anti-slavery friends, I was
enabled shortly after to arrive. I went to New York,
where I became acquainted with Mr. H. Long, and
Mr. Eli Smith, who were very kind to me the whole
time I remained there. My next journey was to New
Bedford, where I remained some weeks under the care
of Mr. H. Ricketson, my finger being still bad from
the effects of the oil of vitriol with which I dressed it
before I left Richmond. While I was here I heard of
a great Anti-slavery meeting which was to take place in
Boston, and being anxious to identify myself with that
public movement, I proceeded there and had the pleasure
of meeting the hearty sympathy of thousands to whom
I related the story of my escape. I have since attended
large meetings in different towns in the states of Maine,
New Hampshire, Vermont, Connecticut, Rhode Island,
Pennsylvania, and New York, in all of which places I
have found many friends and have endeavoured, according 
to the best of my abilities, to advocate the cause of
the emancipation of the slave; with what success I
will not pretend to say—but with a daily increasing
confidence in the humanity and justice of my cause,
<pb id="brown60" n="60"/>
and in the assurance of the approbation of Almighty 
God.</p>
          <p>I have composed the following song in commemoration
of my fete in the box:—</p>
          <lg type="verse">
            <head><hi rend="italics">Air</hi>:—“UNCLE NED.”</head>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <head>I.</head>
              <l>Here you see a man by the name of Henry Brown, </l>
              <l>Ran away from the South to the North; </l>
              <l>Which he would not have done but they stole all his rights, </l>
              <l>But they'll never do the like again.</l>
              <lg type="chorus">
                <l><hi rend="italics">Chorus</hi>—Brown laid down the shovel and the hoe, </l>
                <l>Down in the box he did go; </l>
                <l>No more Slave work for Henry Box Brown, </l>
                <l>In the box by Express he did go.</l>
              </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <head>II.</head>
              <l>Then the orders they were given, and the cars did start
away; </l>
              <l>Roll along—roll along—roll along, </l>
              <l>Down to the landing, where the steamboat lay, </l>
              <l>To bear the baggage off to the north.</l>
              <l>CHORUS.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <head>III.</head>
              <l>When they packed the baggage on, they turned him on 
his head, </l>
              <l>There poor Brown liked to have died;</l>
              <l>There were passengers on board who wished to sit down, </l>
              <l>And they turned the box down on its side.</l>
              <l>CHORUS</l>
            </lg>
            <pb id="brown61" n="61"/>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <head>IV.</head>
              <l>When they got to the cars they threw the box off, </l>
              <l>And down upon his head he did fall, </l>
              <l>Then he heard his neck crack, and he thought it was broke, </l>
              <l>But they never threw him off any more.</l>
              <l>CHORUS.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <head>V.</head>
              <l>When they got to Philadelphia they said he was in port,</l>
              <l>And Brown then began to feel glad,</l>
              <l>He was taken on the waggon to his final destination,</l>
              <l>And left, “this side up with care.”</l>
              <l>CHORUS.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
              <head>VI<sic>,</sic></head>
              <l>The friends gathered round and asked if all was right, </l>
              <l>As down on the box they did rap, </l>
              <l>Brown answered them, saying; “yes all is right!” </l>
              <l>He was then set free from his pain.</l>
              <l>CHORUS.</l>
            </lg>
          </lg>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div1 type="appendix">
        <pb id="bappi" n="i"/>
        <head>APPENDIX.</head>
        <p>
          <hi rend="italics">The allusion in my song to the shovel and the hoe, is founded on the
following story, which forms the slave-holders version of the creation
of the human race.</hi>
        </p>
        <p>The slave-holders say that originally, there were four
persons created (instead of only two) and, perhaps, it is
owing to the christian account of the origin of man, <sic corr="in">in
in</sic> which account two persons only are mentioned, that
it is one of the doctrines of slave-holders that slaves
have no souls: however these four persons were two
whites and two blacks; and the blacks were made to
wait upon the whites. But in man's original state
when he neither required to manufacture clothes to cover 
his nakedness, or to shelter him from storm; when
he did not require to till the earth or to sow or to reap
its fruits, for his support! but when everything sprung
up spontaneously; when the shady bowers invited
him to rest, and the loaded trees dropped their <sic corr="luscious">lucious</sic>
burdens into his hands; in this state of things the
white pair were plagued with the incessant attendance
of the two colored persons, and they prayed that God
would find them something else to do; and immediately
while they stood, a black cloud seemed to gather over
their heads and to descend to the earth before them!
While they gazed on these clouds, they saw them open
<pb id="bappii" n="ii"/>
and two bags of different size drop from them. They
immediately ran to lay hold of the bags, and 
unfortunately for the black man—he being the strongest and
swiftest—he arrived first at them, and laid hold of the 
bags, and the white man, coming up afterwards, got the 
smaller one. They then proceeded to untie their 
bags, when lo! in the large one, there was a shovel and 
a hoe; and in the small one, a pen, ink, and paper; to 
write the declaration of the intention of the Almighty;
they each proceeded to employ the <sic corr="instruments">lnstruments</sic> which 
God had sent them, and ever since the colored race have 
had to labor with the shovel and the hoe, while the rich 
man works with the pen and ink!</p>
        <p>I have no apology whatever to make for what I have 
said, in regard to the pretended christianity under which 
I was trained, while a slave. I have felt it my duty to 
speak of it harshly, because I have felt its blasting 
influence, and seen it used as a cloak under which to 
conceal the most foul and wicked deeds. Indeed the 
only thing I think it necessary to say in this place is 
what seems to me, and what may really be matter of
serious doubt to persons who have the privilege of living 
in a free country, under the influence of liberal institutions; 
that there actually does exist in that land where 
men, women, and children are bought and sold, a church, 
calling itself the church of Christ; yes, my friends, it 
is true that the buyer and seller of the bodies and souls 
of his fellows; he who to day, can separate the husband 
from the wife, the parent from the child, or cut asunder
<pb id="bappiii" n="iii"/>
the strongest ties of friendship, in order to gain a few
dollars, to avert a trifling loss, or to please a whim of 
fancy, can ascend a pulpit to-morrow and preach, what 
he calls, the gospel of Christ! Yes, and in many
cases, the house, which he calls the house of God, has
been erected from the price of human beings; the very
stones of which it is composed, have actually been
dragged to their places by men with chains at their
heels, and ropes about their neck! It is not for me to
judge between those men and the God whom they
pretend to serve, if their own consciences do not condemn
them. I pray that God may give them light to see the
error of their ways, and if they know that they are
doing wrongly, that he may give them grace to renovate
their hearts!</p>
        <p>A few specimens of the laws of a slave-holding people 
may not be out of place here; not that by such means 
we can hope to convey a true idea of the actual condition 
of the people of these places, because those matters on 
which the happiness or misery of a people principally 
depend, and in general such matters as are entirely 
beyond the reach of law. Beside—the various 
circumstances, which, independent of the law, in civilised and 
free countries, constitute the principal sources of
happiness or misery—in the slave-holding states of
America, there is a strong current of public opinion
which the law is altogether incompetent to control.
In many cases there are ideas of criminality, which are
not by statute law attached to the commission of certain
<pb id="bappiv" n="iv"/>
acts, but which are frequently found to exist under the
title of “Lynch law” either augmenting the punishment 
which the law requires, or awarding punishment to 
what the law does not recognize as crime—as the following 
will be sufficient to show<corr sic="(no punctuation)">.</corr></p>
        <p>“The letter of the law would have been sufficient for 
the protection of the lives of the miserable gamblers, in
Vicksburg, and other places in Mississippi, from the 
rage of those whose money they had won; but gentlemen 
of property and standing, laughed the law to scorn<corr sic=".">,</corr> 
rushed to the gambler's houses, put ropes round their 
necks, dragged them through the streets, hanged them 
in the public square, and thus saved the money they had 
not yet paid. Thousands witnessed this wholesale 
murder, yet of the scores of legal officers present, not 
one raised a finger to prevent it. How many hundreds 
of them helped to commit the murder with their own 
hands, does not appear, but many of them has been 
indicted for it, and no one has made the least effort to 
bring them to trial. Now the laws of Mississippi were 
not in fault, when those men were murdered, nor were 
they in fault, that the murderers were not punished; the 
law demanded it, but the people of Mississippi, the 
legal officers, the grand juries, and legislature of the 
state, with one consent determine that the law shall be 
a dead letter, and thus, the whole state assumes the 
guilt of these murderers, and, in bravado, flourish their 
reeking hands in the face of the world; for the people of
Vicksburg have actually erected a monument in honor
<pb id="bappv" n="v"/>
of Dr. H. S. Bodley, who was the ring-leader of the
Lynchers in this case.”—<hi rend="italics">American Slavery as it is.</hi></p>
        <p>It may be also worthy of remark, that in all cases in
which we have strong manifestation of public opinion,
in opposition to the law, it is always exhibited in the
direction of cruelty; indeed, that such should be the
case, no person intimately acquainted with the nature
of the human mind, need be in the least surprised.
Who can consider the influence which the relationship
of master and slave  -  so extensively subsisting between
the members of slave states  -  in stimulating the passion
and in degrading the moral feelings, without being
prepared to credit all that is said of slavery? The
most perfect abstract of the laws which regulate the
duties of slaves and slave owners, must doubtless fail to
convey any proper idea of the actual state of the slave;
and the few laws which we here cite, are not given for
that purpose, but as a sample of trash, which is called
justice by slave-holders and quasi legal authorities.</p>
        <l>“All negroes, mulattoes, or mertizoes, who now are,
or shall hereafter, be in this province, and all their 
offspring, are hereby declared to be, and shall remain for
ever hereafter, absolute slaves, and shall follow the
condition of the mother.”—<hi rend="italics">Law of South Carolina.</hi></l>
        <p><corr sic="'">"</corr>The criminal offence of assault and battery, cannot,
at common law, be committed upon the person of a
slave, for, notwithstanding for some purposes, a slave is
regarded in law, as a person, yet generally he is a mere
chattel personal, and <hi>his right of personal protection</hi>
<pb id="bappvi" n="vi"/>
<hi>belongs to his master,</hi> who can maintain an action of
trespass, for the battery of his slave. There can be,
therefore, no offence against the state for a mere beating
of a slave, unaccompanied by any circumstances of
cruelly, or an attempt to kill and murder. The peace
of the state, is not thereby broken, for a slave is not
generally regarded as legally capable of being within
the pale of the State,—HE IS NOT A CITIZEN, AND IS
NOT IN THAT CHARACTER ENTITLED TO HER PROTECTION.”</p>
        <p>“Any person may lawfully kill a slave who has been
outlawed for running away and lurking in swamps, &amp;c.,”
—Law of North Carolina.</p>
        <p>“A slave endeavouring to entice another slave to run
away, if provision be prepared for the purpose of aiding
in such running away, shall be punished with <hi rend="italics">death;</hi>
and a slave who shall aid the slave so endeavouring to
run away, shall also suffer <hi rend="italics">death.</hi>”—<hi rend="italics">Law of South
Carolina.</hi></p>
        <p>“If a slave, when absent from his plantation, refuse
to be examined by any white person, no matter what
the moral character of such white person, or for what
purpose he wishes to make the examination, such white
person may chastise him, and if, in resisting his 
chastisement, he should strike the white person, by whom
he is being chastised, he may be KILLED.”—<hi rend="italics">Law of
South Carolina.</hi></p>
        <p>“If any slave shall presume to strike any white person
provided such striking be not done by the command and
in defence of the property of the owner, such slave
<pb id="bappvii" n="vii"/>
shall, upon trial and conviction, before the justice or 
justices, suffer such punishment, for the first offence, 
as they shall think fit, not extending to life or limb, and 
for the second offence, <hi rend="italics">death.</hi>”—<hi rend="italics">Law of Georgia.</hi></p>
        <p>“If any person cut any chain or collar, which any 
master of slaves has put upon his slave, to prevent such 
slave from running away, such person will be liable to a 
penalty not exceeding one thousand dollars, and 
imprisonment not exceeding two years.”—<hi rend="italics">Law of Louisiana. </hi></p>
        <p>“If any person cut out the tongue, put out the eye, 
cruelly burn, or deprive any slave of a limb, he shall be 
liable to a penalty not exceeding five hundred dollars.”</p>
        <p>“If a slave be attacked by any person not having 
sufficient cause for so doing, and be maimed or disabled
so that THE OWNER SUFFERS A LOSS FROM HIS 
INABILITY TO LABOUR, the person so doing, shall pay the 
master of such disabled slave, for the time such slave 
shall be off work, and for the medical attendance on the 
slave.”—<hi rend="italics">Law of South Carolina.</hi></p>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head>MISCELLANEOUS.</head>
          <p>If more than seven slaves be found together in any 
road without a white person, they shall be liable to 
twenty lashes each.</p>
          <p>If any slave visit a plantation, other than that of his 
master, without a written pass, he shall be liable to ten 
lashes.</p>
          <p>If a slave let loose a boat from where it has been 
made fast, he shall for the first offence be liable to a 
penalty of thirty-nine lashes, and for the second, to
<pb id="bappviii" n="viii"/>
have one ear cut from his head—for being on 
horseback, without a written permission from his master—
twenty-five lashes; for riding or going abroad at night, 
without a written permission, a slave may be cropped 
or branded in the cheek, with the letter E, or otherwise
punished, not extending to life, or so as to render him 
unfit for labour.</p>
        </div2>
        <signed>HENRY BOX BROWN.</signed>
        <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </div1>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI.2>