<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % external-entities SYSTEM "./extEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY % internal-entities SYSTEM "./intEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY hoppcv SYSTEM "hoppcv.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY hoppfp SYSTEM "hoppfp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY hopp18 SYSTEM "hopp18.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY hopp30 SYSTEM "hopp30.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY hopp32 SYSTEM "hopp32.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY hopptp SYSTEM "hopptp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>Narrative of the Life of Thomas Cooper:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Hopper, Isaac T. (Isaac Tatem), 1771 - 1852 </author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Sarah Reuning</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by</resp>
          <name>Sarah Reuning</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Fiona Mills and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1999</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca.     80K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1999.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, 
teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is 
included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note anchored="yes">Call number E444.C66 H6 (Rare Book Collection, University of 
North Carolina at Chapel Hill)</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="title page"> Narrative of the Life of Thomas Cooper.</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition/>
          </editionStmt>
          <extent>    36  p., ill.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
            <publisher>Published by Isaac T. Hopper</publisher>
            <date>1832</date>
            <authority/>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ 
and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines 
has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using 
Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Cooper, Thomas, d. ca. 1821.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Maryland -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Fugitive slaves -- Maryland -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Maryland -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- Maryland -- History -- 18th century.</item>
            <item>African American clergy -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Methodist Church -- Clergy -- Biography.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2000-04-05, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-10-12, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-10-12, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Fiona Mills</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-10-05, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Sarah Reuning</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="cover image">
        <p>
          <figure id="cover" entity="hoppcv">
            <p>[Cover Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="frontispiece image">
        <p>
          <figure id="frontis" entity="hoppfp">
            <p>The 
master mounted on his horse driving John before him. pp. 
7 8.<lb/>[Frontispiece Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="title page image">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="hopptp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">NARRATIVE
<lb/>
OF
<lb/>
THE LIFE
<lb/>OF
<lb/>
THOMAS COOPER.</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <docImprint><pubPlace>NEW-YORK:</pubPlace>
<publisher>PUBLISHED BY ISAAC T. HOPPER,</publisher>
<pubPlace>No. 386, Pearl-street.</pubPlace>
<docDate>1832.</docDate></docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="preface">
        <pb id="hopper4" n="4"/>
        <head>PREFACE.</head>
        <p>Many of the circumstances related in the following narrative,
came under the immediate notice of the writer; the others he had
from a source which he believes authentic; and however romantic
many of them may appear, he fully believes them to be correct. He
was well acquainted with Thomas Cooper, and his family, and can
testify to his sobriety and general good character, while he resided
in Philadelphia and its neighbourhood. Thomas was a man of
more than ordinary talents, and, considering his very limited
opportunities, they appear to have been well cultivated.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed>THE AUTHOR.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="preface">
        <p>Entered according to the Act of 
Congress, in the year 1832, by
ISAAC T. HOPPER, in the office of the Clerk of the Southern
District of New-York.</p>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="text">
        <pb id="hopper5" n="5"/>
        <head>NARRATIVE, &amp;c.</head>
        <p>THOMAS COOPER, the subject of the following narrative,
was of African descent, and was born a slave in the state of
Maryland, where he continued to reside until he was about
twenty-five years old. During his servitude, he experienced many
hardships, being scantily clothed and fed, and compelled to
labour very hard, and was obliged to lodge in a little hut, which
was so open, that it did not shelter him from the cold in winter; but
although his body was held in cruel bondage, his mind was free,
and he frequently put up his prayers in secret, to his merciful
Creator, for deliverance from his sufferings; believing that all are
the work of one Almighty hand,
<pb id="hopper6" n="6"/>
who hath placed them in various situations, and that he was
disposed to extend equally his care and protection to all.</p>
        <p>About the year 1800, Notly, (for this was his name while a slave,)
left his master's service, and went to Philadelphia, and hired with
M —&amp; E — , who kept a lumber yard, in which he was employed;
here he conducted with fidelity and industry, and soon gained the
confidence and esteem of his employers.</p>
        <p>After some time he married a respectable woman of his own
colour; they lived together several years in much harmony
and affection, and were esteemed,
by their neighbours and acquaintances,
as orderly and industrious people, until
a person who had gained the confidence
of John Smith, (for upon his arrival in
Philadelphia, he had assumed this name,)
<pb id="hopper7" n="7"/>
betrayed him, by informing his master where he was to be found.
This man soon after came to Philadelphia, and had poor John
arrested and carried before one of the Aldermen of that city, and
upon proof that he was a slave, an order was granted to convey
him back to Maryland.</p>
        <p>His employers were humane men, and greatly commiserating his
condition, and sympathising with his wife and children, offered to
pay a large sum of money for his freedom, that he might be
restored to them; but no entreaties would avail with his cruel
master, he was deaf to the voice of pity, and poor John was
handcuffed, and a rope fastened to each arm across his back,
to which another was tied, one end of which, the master held in
his hand; and, mounting his horse,
<pb id="hopper8" n="8"/>
rode off, driving John before him. All this took place in the
presence of his wife and children, who witnessed the horrid
transaction with the utmost distress.</p>
        <p>While they were fastening the fetters upon John, he was
engaged in talking to his wife. He counselled her to take care
of their children, whom, he said, he wished to remember their
father; expressing a hope, that by industry and frugality, she
would be able to keep them at school, until they were old
enough to be put out, when he wished them placed with
persons of good character and industrious habits; and he
cautioned her against indulging them in idleness, saying, that he
wished her to remember his advice, as it was not likely that they
would ever meet again. </p>
        <pb id="hopper9" n="9"/>
        <p>He then addressed his children, saying, “you will now have no
father to take care of you; be good children, obey your mother,
and be sure that you never do any thing to grieve her; don't play
in the street, or with naughty children—be industrious and
faithful, in whatever you are set about.”</p>
        <p>He continued his speech until his master raised his whip, when
he set out on his journey—his wife and children wept bitterly;
and, although he manifested great sensibility, he retained his
composure.</p>
        <p>John and his wife, by industry and frugality, had acquired a little
property: they lived in their own house, and had been, for several
years, enjoying as much comfort as their hearts could desire; but
in an instant, as it were, all their hopes
<pb id="hopper10" n="10"/>
seemed blasted, and they parted in the deepest anguish and
despair, not expecting ever to see each other's faces again.</p>
        <p>The writer of this was present at the examination before the
Alderman, he saw John fettered, and torn from the bosom of his
wife and children.</p>
        <p>The circumstances of the case were well calculated to awaken
feelings of sympathy and tenderness; and at this distant period,
his sensibility is excited at the recollection of the distressing
scene; it made impressions which time cannot remove, as long
as memory lasts.</p>
        <p>John's wife was now left with four small children to provide for,
and he was conveyed, in the manner above described, to the city
of Washington, and there offered for sale to persons who
bought slaves on speculation, to be transported
<pb id="hopper11" n="11"/>
to Georgia, or some other southern market. But even in
Washington, where slavery is tolerated by the laws, there were
those who could not, with indifference, behold inhumanity
like that which this poor slave was doomed to endure, and they
rebuked his master for his cruelty. This was very unexpected to
John, and inspired him with a determination to make an effort to
regain his liberty; for his feelings were acute, and his affections
warm, although his skin was black.</p>
        <p>Manacled as he was, he made out to trip up his master's heels,
and he fell to the ground. John then ran to the woods; but in a
few hours, he was pursued by his avaricious master, with a
company he had collected to assist him, and it was not long
before he was discovered
<pb id="hopper12" n="12"/>
concealed in the bushes. As soon as he found that he was seen by
his pursuers, he ran into a swamp, where he was hunted like a fox,
until the darkness of the night released him from the chase.</p>
        <p>He then made the best of his way to the house of a man of his
own colour, whose sympathy was excited on seeing an innocent
fellow-being bound with irons and cords, like the worst of
criminals. This man was an old acquaintance, and knowing
John's integrity, soon found means to rid him of his fetters, and
he once more felt himself at liberty. His friend and benefactor
hastened to set before him the best his table afforded, and after
taking a hearty meal, for he had eaten but little since he left
Philadelphia, he again set out for that city; but the journey
appeared very hazardous,
<pb id="hopper13" n="13"/>
as he had several rivers to cross, and expected persons would be
stationed at the bridges to arrest him; he, however, determined
to make the attempt.</p>
        <p>He knew it would not be safe to be
seen, and therefore hid himself in the
bushes during the day, and pursued
his journey in the night. After suffering
much with hunger and fatigue, he arrived
safely in Philadelphia, and went immediately
to see his distressed family; it was
a joyful meeting: but John well knew
that he would be again pursued, and could
not be safe to remain long under his own
roof; accordingly he left his family, and
went to the house of a respectable citizen, well
known as the black man's
friend, and whom we shall call Philo
Christian; here he was kindly entertained.</p>
        <pb id="hopper14" n="14"/>
        <p>The yellow fever was then in the city,
and the family had removed into the country, except a coloured
woman, who remained in the house to attend upon Philo, whose
engagements required that he should be mostly in the city
during the day, and not unfrequently during the night also.</p>
        <p>John was placed in an upper room, the door of which was kept
fastened. He had been in this place but a very little time,
before his master, with two constables, came in pursuit of him;
and Philo being absent, they proceeded to search the house; and,
on coming to the door of the room where John was, and finding
it fast, they demanded entrance.</p>
        <p>In a little time Philo came home, and being informed by the
coloured woman
<pb id="hopper15" n="15"/>
what was taking place, he immediately
went up stairs, and found the intruders
consulting how they should gain admittance. Philo
instantly ordered them out of his house, upon which
one of the officers replied, “this gentleman's slave is in
your house, and if you do not immediately deliver him up,
we will get a warrant from the Mayor to search it.” He again
requested them to leave his house, and added, “the Mayor
dare not grant a search-warrant for my house.” They then
withdrew, and in a few minutes the officer returned, with a
message from the Mayor, requesting to see him. Philo
promptly waited upon the Mayor who lived near by, when the
following dialogue took place.</p>
        <p><hi rend="italics">Philo.</hi>—Hast thou business with me?</p>
        <pb id="hopper16" n="16"/>
        <p><hi rend="italics">Mayor</hi>.—Yes, this gentlemen, (alluding to John's master, who
was present.) says, his slave is in your house ; is it so?</p>
        <p><hi rend="italics">Philo</hi>.—I think thou hast just informed me, that this man says
he <hi rend="italics">is</hi> dost thou not believe him?</p>
        <p><hi rend="italics">Mayor</hi>.—Well, but I wish<gap reason="damaged page"/>formed by you, whether <gap reason="damaged page"/>
house or not.</p>
        <p><hi rend="italics">Philo</hi>.—I think the Mayor, upon little reflection, will see, that
he has no authority to ask me this question, and of course, I am
not bound to answer it; if he is in my house, and this man can
make it appear, I am liable to a very heavy penalty, and no man
is bound to inform against himself; and the conduct of these
people has not been so civil that I feel myself under any
obligations of courtesy to satisfy them. Hast thou further business
with me?</p>
        <pb id="hopper17" n="17"/>
        <p><hi rend="italics">Mayor</hi>.—Did you say that I dare not
grant a warrant to search your house?</p>
        <p><hi rend="italics">Philo</hi>.—Indeed I did, and now repeat
 it, neither thou nor any
other magistrate in this city; without intending any disrespect
to those in authority; I am a man of reputation, I am not a
suspicious character.</p>
        <p><hi rend="italics">Mayor</hi>.—(Smiling) I don't know that,
 I am inclined to think,
in the present case, you are.</p>
        <p><hi rend="italics">Philo</hi>.—Hast thou any thing 
further to say to me?</p>
        <p><hi rend="italics">Mayor</hi>.—I believe not.</p>
        <p><hi rend="italics">Philo</hi>.—Farewell.</p>
        <p>The avarice of his master, together with his desire for revenge,
induced him to pursue every stratagem that he could devise to
re-capture poor John; and among others, the following was
resorted to:—one of the party procured a suit
<pb id="hopper18" n="18"/>
of clothes, such as are worn by plain Friends—a hat with a
round crown and broad brim, and a plain coat. Thus attired, he
made his way to John's house; upon entering, he saw his wife,
bathed in tears, sitting in their once peaceful and happy cottage,
with her children round her, the youngest by her side, looking its
mother in the face, and, by its gestures, seeming to inquire the
cause of her grief.</p>
        <p>But all this had no effect to soften the heart of this man, whose
object was lucre, as a reward for apprehending the unhappy
fugitive. With affected sympathy and kindness, he inquired
where John was to be found, saying, that his master was in
pursuit of him, and he wished to see him, in order to assist him,
in getting out of the way: but this artifice, although ingenious,
and must have
<pb id="hopper19" n="19"/>
<figure id="ill3" entity="hopp18"><p>Constable in quest of John. p.18</p></figure>
<pb id="hopper20" n="20"/>
been attended with some expense and trouble, proved
unsuccessful; for the woman was on her guard, and declined
giving him any information, but referred him to her friend
Philo Christian, as the most suitable person to advise with in the
case. He became greatly enraged at this disappointment, and gave
vent to his anger in profane wicked language; declaring, as he
withdrew, that he would have John, if he was to be found upon
the face of the earth.</p>
        <p>John remained under the protection of his friend about a week;
during most of this time, persons were seen lurking about the
premises watching for him, but at length they disappeared.
Supposing they had concealed themselves, a person was procured,
who, some little time after dark in the evening, suddenly
ran out of
<pb id="hopper21" n="21"/>
the house, where John was; but he had proceeded but a short
distance, before the apprehensions, which were entertained, that
the enemy was in ambush, were realized, for they suddenly rushed
from their hiding places, and seized upon the man that was
running.</p>
        <p>Finding that they were mistaken in the person, they released
him; but John's friend made application to the Mayor, had them
arrested, and compelled them to enter into bonds for their
good behaviour. The next evening, the same person went out as
before, and was not interrupted; the following evening John left
his hiding-place, and got safely into New-Jersey.</p>
        <p>Here he hired with a farmer, and, although he was within about
eight miles of his home, he was in exile from it; he
<pb id="hopper22" n="22"/>
remained in this situation several months, during which time, by
his good conduct, he gained the confidence and esteem of the
family where he resided. It was their practice on first day
afternoons, to collect together and read portions of the scriptures,
and other religious books, and John was permitted to sit with
them; which he esteemed a great <sic corr="privelege">priviledge</sic>,
 and often expressed
his gratitude for the favour; he was also permitted to take his
meals at the same table with the family. Instead of being elated
by this familiarity, it made him more humble.</p>
        <p>After it became known that John had returned to Philadelphia,
the person who had betrayed him, became greatly alarmed; and
his fears so wrought upon his imagination, that he frequently
dreamed
<pb id="hopper23" n="23"/>
that he saw John in his house, with a knife in one hand, and a
torch in the other, and that he was about to kill him and burn his
house; and he would sometimes cry out in his sleep, and start up
in his bed; so true is the saying, that, “wickedness condemned by
her own witness is very timorous, and being pressed with
conscience always forecasteth grievous things.” But he had no
cause to fear, John had no desire to revenge the wrong that had
been done him, for he had learned, that it was not right to render
evil for evil, but contrawise, blessing.</p>
        <p>His affliction was great at being obliged to live separated from his
wife and children, for whose welfare he felt a deep interest: at
length he ventured to rent a small house, in a retired situation,
<pb id="hopper24" n="24"/>
not far distant from the village of Haddonfield. He now hoped to
be permitted to enjoy the comforts of domestic life unmolested,
and yet, he was in constant fear of the man-stealers; this often
interrupted his slumbers in the night, and even when at his work,
he would startle at the rustling of the leaves; so that he passed his
days in fear, and his nights were constantly seasons of terror.</p>
        <p>After some months, the place of his retreat was again discovered,
and his master came to Philadelphia, with the intention to
proceed to New Jersey to arrest him. John's friend Philo heard
of this circumstance, and immediately apprised him of his danger.
He had already suffered much, and now finding himself again
pursued, was driven almost to despair, and determined to resist
by violence. The morning after receiving
<pb id="hopper25" n="25"/>
the information, that his master had discovered his place of
residence, and was coming to arrest him, he rose early, loaded
his gun, and, with a determined resolution, prepared to defend
himself.</p>
        <p>It was not long before he beheld his master, with two other
persons, advancing along a lane towards his house; he placed
himself in his door, and, upon their near approach, he called
out, “don't cross that fence, for the first man does, I will shoot
him.” So unexpected a salutation, coming from a man with a
gun in his hand, struck them with terror, and they soon turned
back to procure assistance.</p>
        <p>In the meantime John went to Philadelphia, which was within
about five or six miles of his home, and informed, his friend Philo
of what had transpired; his
<pb id="hopper26" n="26"/>
friend reasoned with him on the great impropriety and
inconsistency, with the christian character, of putting the life
of a human being in jeopardy. John seemed to be convinced of
the correctness of the views of his friend, and therefore resolved
again to fly for safety; and, with the advice of Philo, concluded
to remove his family to Boston, in hopes of finding an asylum
there, where he might live in peace.</p>
        <p>A vessel was then lying in the river Delaware, which was
expected to sail for that place in a few days; and the merchant
who had charge of her, pitying his distress, offered him a
passage free of expense, which he gratefully accepted; and,
although he had never been at sea before, he made himself useful,
and fully compensated the captain for his passage, by his labour.</p>
        <pb id="hopper27" n="27"/>
        <p>His friends freely gave him certificates of his good character,
which he found very useful in procuring employment among
strangers, and in a few days, after he arrived in Boston, he hired
with a lumber merchant of that place. Now finding himself in
circumstances to provide for his family, his employer at his
request, wrote to Philadelphia, desiring them to come to him;
his wife accordingly disposed of their property in that city,
and took the money she received for it, with her children to
Boston, where she again met her husband.</p>
        <p>About the time of his leaving New Jersey, he changed his name
from John Smith, to that of Thomas Cooper, and by this name he
was always afterwards known.</p>
        <p>He often noticed and greatly lamented,
<pb id="hopper28" n="28"/>
the bad conduct of the people of his own colour, as well as that of
those of a different complexion. And, with a view of making
himself more useful, he joined in religious communion with the
Methodists, and in a short time became a popular preacher
among them, and visited some of the West India Islands, as a
minister.</p>
        <p>After his return from the West Indies, he made a similar visit to
Nova Scotia. In these places it is said, he was very useful, not
only by his exhortations, but by his pious example; his religion
being that of the heart, and not of the head only, his preaching
had much effect on his hearers.</p>
        <p>Not long after his return from those visits, he concluded to go to
Africa, the birth place of his fathers, and, for this purpose took
shipping with his family,
<pb id="hopper29" n="29"/>
and safely arrived in London, the metropolis of Great Britain. He
was received with much kindness by a number of philanthropists,
who were made acquainted with him, and the object of his visit,
and his children were placed at school, at the expense of a
Friend in London, well known as a benevolent man, and a friend
of the afflicted. Thomas Cooper soon became a man of much
note, and preached to large congregations in that city. While there,
he made a selection of hymns, which were published in a large
duodecimo volume, and his friends had his likeness placed in the
book, as a frontispiece.</p>
        <p>After remaining about a year and a half in London, a passage
was procured for him and his family, to Africa, as appears by a
note in the hands of the publisher,
<pb id="hopper30" n="30"/>
of which the following is a copy
viz:—</p>
        <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1 type="letter">
                <p>J ——  
A ——  , informs his friend
Thomas Cooper, that he has this day
paid for the passage of T. C. and family
to Sierra Leone, per the Echo, Captain
Row. The vessel is not expected to sail till the third
week in this month.</p>
                <closer><dateline>34, Gracechurch-street.
<date>10<hi rend="italics">mo</hi>. 3<hi rend="italics">d</hi>, 1818.”</date></dateline><signed>THOMAS COOPER,</signed>
Borough.</closer>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <p>Thomas Cooper remained in London rather more than a month
after the date of the above note.</p>
        <p>When about to take his departure from London, for Sierra Leone,
he had a meeting, at which, it is said, there were several thousand
persons. On this occasion the following advertisement was
published in hand bills, viz:—</p>
        <pb id="hopper31" n="31"/>
        <p>
          <figure id="ill2" entity="hopp30">
            <p>Thomas Cooper's farewell address to his friends in London. p. 30.</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <pb id="hopper32" n="32"/>
        <q direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1>
                <p>
                  <figure id="ill1" entity="hopp32">
                    <p>THE<lb/>
REV. T. COOPER,<lb/>
<lb/>
THE AFRICAN,
<lb/>
Will preach his
<lb/>
FAREWELL SERMON,
<lb/>
TO HIS FRIENDS IN THIS QUARTER,
<lb/>
ON
<lb/>
TUESDAY NEXT,
<lb/>
NOVEMBER 3d, 1818.<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">At half past 6 o'clock in the Evening,</hi>
<lb/>
AT THE MEETING IN
<lb/>
BROWN'S LANE,
<lb/>
SPITALFIELDS,
<lb/>
PREVIOUS TO HIS DEPARTURE ON
<lb/>
HIS MISSION TO AFRICA
<lb/>
<lb/>Bertrand, Printer, 22, Green-street, Bethnal Green.
</p>
                  </figure>
                </p>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <pb id="hopper33" n="33"/>
        <p>Soon after this meeting, Thomas, with his wife and children,
sailed for Africa, and arrived at Sierra Leona, after enduring
many hardships on the passage, in consequence of tempestuous
weather.—They were cordially received by the inhabitants, his
fame having reached there before him.</p>
        <p>How different now were his feelings, from what they were,
when in his own country. There, in continual dread of being
torn from his family and friends, and of being reduced to the
most degrading and abject slavery; now, enjoying,
without fear of molestation, the sweets of liberty, in the bosom
of his family, and among his friends, who rejoiced in having such
an acquisition to their colony. He immediately entered upon the
object of his mission, and had
<pb id="hopper34" n="34"/>
meetings among the people—all classes flocking to hear him.</p>
        <p>But this happy state was of but short duration, for Thomas had not
been more than two or three years in Africa, before he was taken
ill with the fever, which has so often proved fatal to strangers in
that hot climate, and fell a victim to it. His wife and children, by
this afflicting, event, were again left destitute, and that too, in a
land of strangers; but with the consoling reflection, that it was a
dispensation of Providence, which had bereaved them of a
husband, a father, a protector, and a friend; and although, the
separation was painful, yet the survivors had comfort in
the reflection, that he was now gone to a state of happiness,
where the voice of the oppressor is heard no more.</p>
        <pb id="hopper35" n="35"/>
        <p>Perhaps few men have ever lived, who
experienced greater changes in their condition
in life, than the person whose
history we have been writing; we have
seen him a poor menial, suffering for the
want of food and raiment, exposed to
cold, and writhing under the lash of the
tyrannical slave driver; again, we see
a minister of religion, pleading with the
people to forsake the evil of their ways
and <sic corr="showing">shewing</sic> in his life, and by his own
example, how far superior a life of virtue
and integrity is, to that of vice and crime.
The consequences of the latter, are always
disgrace and misery; while the sure reward of
the former, is the favour and applause of the wise and good,
and in the end quietness and assurance forever.</p>
        <pb id="hopper36" n="36"/>
        <p>After the death of Thomas Cooper,
his wife and children returned to London,
and from there to Philadelphia.</p>
        <lg type="poem">
          <l>“Judge not the Lord by feeble sense,</l>
          <l>But trust him for his grace;</l>
          <l>Behind a frowning Providence,</l>
          <l>He hides a smiling face.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>“His purposes will ripen fast,</l>
          <l>Unfolding every hour;</l>
          <l>The bud may have a bitter taste,</l>
          <l>But sweet will be the flow'r.”</l>
        </lg>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>