<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY parkertp SYSTEM "parkertp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>Recollections of  Slavery Times</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Parker, Allen</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Chris Hill</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Image scanned by</resp>
          <name>Chris Hill</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Bethany Ronnberg and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>2000</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>100K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>2000.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and 
personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="title page"> Recollections of Slavery Times</title>
            <author>Allen Parker</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>96p., ill.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>Worcester, Mass.</pubPlace>
            <publisher>Chas. W. Burbank &amp; Co.</publisher>
            <date>1895</date>
            <authority/>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="yes">Call number  Bd. Pam. 326.81 Z99D
   (Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library, Duke University Libraries)</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Parker, Allen, b. ca. 1835.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- North Carolina -- Chowan County --
Biography.</item>
            <item>Fugitive slaves -- North Carolina -- Chowan County --
Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- North Carolina -- Chowan County --
Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- North Carolina -- Social life and customs -- 19th
century.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- North Carolina -- Social conditions -- 19th
century.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- North Carolina -- History -- 19th century.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- Southern States -- History -- 19th century.</item>
            <item>Plantation life -- North Carolina -- History -- 19th
centur</item>
            <item>Slaves' writings, American -- North Carolina.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2000-07-21, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2000-02-04, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2000-02-02, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Bethany Ronnberg</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2000-01-19, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Chris Hill</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="title page">
        <p>
          <figure entity="parkertp"/>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">RECOLLECTIONS
<lb/>
OF
<lb/>
SLAVERY TIMES,</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>BY
</byline>
        <docAuthor>ALLEN PARKER.</docAuthor>
        <docImprint><pubPlace>WORCESTER, MASS.:</pubPlace>
<publisher>CHAS. W. BURBANK &amp; CO., PRINTERS</publisher>
<pubPlace>34 FRONT STREET.</pubPlace>
<docDate>1895.</docDate></docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="dedication">
        <pb id="parkervs" n="5"/>
        <head>TO
<lb/>
My Mother</head>
        <p>WHOSE EYES WERE NOT PERMITTED TO SEE THE<lb/>
EMANCIPATION OF HER RACE, BUT WHO DIED A<lb/>
SLAVE AND NOW LIES BURIED IN AN UNMARKED<lb/>
AND NEGLECTED GRAVE ON THE OLD PLANTATION<lb/>
IN THE SUNNY SOUTH, NEAR<lb/>
WHERE SHE SPENT HER LIFE IN<lb/>
UNPAID TOIL FOR OTHERS,<lb/>
THIS LITTLE BOOK IS AFFECTIONATELY DEDICATED.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="introduction">
        <pb id="parker6" n="6"/>
        <head>INTRODUCTION.</head>
        <p>In presenting these pages to the public,
but little explanation need be made, for
they contain only the story of a slave, told
as nearly as possible in his own words.
One-third of a century has passed since
slavery ceased forever in our land, and to
the generation that has grown up in that
time, it hardly seems possible that such an
institution as slavery could have existed in
this free land; but he who in these pages
tells his simple story was only one of three
millions of human beings who were bought
and sold, kept in subjection and forced to
labor without pay in order that their more
fortunate white brethren and sisters might
live in ease and luxury, and though he only
saw slavery in its mildest form no one can
read his story without a feeling of indignation
that slavery should ever have been
tolerated much less sanctioned by law.</p>
        <signed>ED.</signed>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="text">
        <pb id="parker7" n="7"/>
        <head>RECOLLECTIONS
<lb/>
OF
<lb/>
SLAVERY TIMES.</head>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
          <p>I WAS born in the town of Chowan on
the Chowan River, in the northeastern
part of North Carolina, only a short distance
south of the Virginia line. My
mother, whose name was Millie, was a
slave formerly owned by one Peter Parker;
and as children born in slavery
followed the condition of their mother, I
was of course claimed as Peter Parker's
property, and have always gone by the
name of Allen Parker.</p>
          <pb id="parker8" n="8"/>
          <p>My father's name was Jeff, and being
owned by one William Ellick, he went by
the name of Jeff Ellick, but as he had
the misfortune to have been born without
ears, he was often called “no-eared
Jeff.” He did not live with my mother,
as his master's plantation was some ten
miles from the Parker plantation, but
he generally came home Saturday nights
and now and then would come to us in
the night during the week, as a slave
did not mind a walk of ten miles after
his day's work if he could have a chance
to see his loved ones.</p>
          <p>I do not know exactly when I was
born, for slaves keep no family records,
and if any records of the ages of the
slaves was kept by the Parker family I
never knew of it. I suppose however
that I must have been born sometime
between 1835 and 1840. I do not remember
my old master as his death <sic corr="occurred">occured</sic> when
I was only a few months old. While he
lived my mother was what was known as
<pb id="parker9" n="9"/>
a field hand. About two weeks after my
birth, my mistress gave birth to a little
girl whom she named Annie, and I have
been told that my mistress often nursed
me at her breast, in order that my mother
might not be kept from her work
in the field. When Mr. Parker died
both my mother and myself became the
property of the daughter Annie, in
accordance with his last will and <sic corr="testament">testement</sic>.
In his will my master provided that none
of the slaves left by him should be sold
but might be hired out, that is let to
some person by the year.</p>
          <p>Annie and her property were under
the guardianship of <sic corr="Mr.">Mr</sic> Parker's brother 
who was named James Skinner.</p>
          <p>It was customary in those days for
those having slaves to let, to take them
to some prominent place, such as a point
where two roads crossed, on the first day
of the New Year, and at a given hour
of the day the slaves would be put up at
auction, and let to the highest bidders
<pb id="parker10" n="10"/>
for one year; there was generally quite a
gathering on these occasions, both of
slaves and of white people. It was always
understood that a person hiring a
slave must furnish board and clothes in
addition to paying a certain sum of
money per year, and also agreeing not to
misuse the slave in any way that would
injure his or her value. It was also
understood that if a slave was not treated
properly the person owning or having
charge of the slave could take it away,
in which case the money paid for the
slave's hire for the year would be forfeited.</p>
          <p>In <sic corr="accordance">acordance</sic> with this custom my
mother was let out to a poor white, that
is a farmer who did not own any slaves,
and I being only a baby, went with her,
and it was upon this farm which was near
the Parker Plantation that my first
experience of slave life began.</p>
          <p>The country around Chowan was
not very thickly settled, the land being
<pb id="parker11" n="11"/>
<sic corr="divided">devided</sic> up into farms or plantations, upon
which was raised wheat, indian corn, rye,
oats, peanuts, sweet-potatoes and sometimes
rice. <sic corr="vegetables">Vegatables</sic> enough for home
use were also raised. Most of the farmers
owned hogs which were allowed to
run wild in the woods where they fed
upon acorns, nuts and roots. There were
also horses, mules and some horned cattle
all of which received full as good care
as the slaves did.</p>
          <p>The farm work was done by slaves,
women working in the field as well as
the men. Boys and girls were required
to work as soon as they were able to do
anything.</p>
          <p>The slaves lived in log cabins.
Single slaves who did not belong to slave
families, lived in common with others
and were fed from the main kitchen.
Those who had families generally lived
in small one-story log cabins. The walls
of these cabins were made of rough logs,
the spaces between the logs being filled
<pb id="parker12" n="12"/>
with clay; the roof was made of thin
strips of wood split from clear, straight
grained logs; these strips extended from
the eaves to the ridge pole, and were
laid over each other in such a manner as
to make a fairly tight roof. If the roof
did leak a little there was no danger of
spoiling any nice furniture for the very
good reason the slaves did not have any.</p>
          <p>The fireplace was made of logs and
was large enough to take in a log five or
six feet long. On the fireplace was built
a wooden chimney, made of sticks piled
up cob-house fashion, and extending out
through the roof some two or three feet.
The sides of the chimney tapered inward
as they went up, so that the hole
was somewhat smaller at the top than
at the bottom. When the woodwork of the
fireplace was done, and the chimney built
up as high as needed, the whole affair
was plastered outside and in with wet
clay, which finished the fireplace and
chimney. The heat of the fire soon hardened
<pb id="parker13" n="13"/>
the clay and a chimney of this kind
would last a long time.</p>
          <p>This kind of masonry not only has
the advantage of being cheap but it
could be repaired without difficulty at
any time, as the material cost nothing
and was always at hand.</p>
          <p>The door of the cabin was made of
rough boards nailed together and was
hung on heavy iron hinges like a barn-door.
As the slaves had little to <sic corr="lose">loose</sic>,
the door are seldom fastened on <sic>the</sic>
the inside, but was kept shut by a latch
that could be raised from the outside by
means of a string; if those inside happened
to want to fasten it they pull in the
latch string. The windows had only
wooden shutters which could be closed
when desired, but this would of course
leave the cabin in darkness.</p>
          <p>When a fire was needed a few
bricks, or stones were placed on the
hearth to take the place of firedogs, on
these was placed a huge back log, in
<pb id="parker14" n="14"/>
front of which was built a fire of small
wood. At this fire all the family cooking
was done.</p>
          <p>The cooking utensils were few and
all of the <sic corr="simplest">simplist</sic> kind. A long handled
shallow iron skillet with long legs did
duty as a spider in which to fry our salt
pork, bacon and other meat, whenever
we could get it. It was also sometimes
used to bake “hoe cake” in. These hoe
cakes, which formed a large part of the
slave's bill of fare, were made of Indian
meal, and water with a little salt and
sometimes a quantity of pork fat was
added. When the skillet was not at
hand or was wanted for some other
purpose, a “nigger hoe” that is a hoe used
by the slave in the field, was placed
handle down upon the floor, so that the
under side of the hoe would be next to
the fire. The angle that the iron part
of the hoe made with the handle was
such that when the handle was placed
upon the floor the iron part would slant
<pb id="parker15" n="15"/>
back from the fire, thereby making a
resting place for the cake. When one
side of the cake was baked the other
side was turned to the fire. From this
style of cooking, the cake came to be
called “hoe cake.”</p>
          <p>The common allowance of a slave
was four quarts of Indian meal and five
pounds of salt pork, Sometimes one quart
of molasses, per week, and all the sweet
potatoes that they wanted. Whatever
else they had, had to be earned by over
work, or by selling a part of their allowance,
or as it often happened by selling
such supplies as could be stolen from the
fields or storehouses upon the plantations.
There could always be found a
market among the poor whites, for whatever
a slave had to sell, though the price
paid was often very low, for the slave
was in a measure at the mercy of the
buyer. Generally the buyer knew or had
reasons to suspect that the goods were
stolen, and he also knew it was against
<pb id="parker16" n="16"/>
the law for him to buy goods of a slave
without knowing that everything was
all right. But he knew that the slave
could not complain of him without getting
into trouble himself, and feeling safe
along that line he had only to suggest
to the slave that he thought it would be
well to consult the master in relation to
the trade, this was of course the last
thing the slave wanted to have done;
for if his master found that he was selling
stolen goods, a severe punishment
was sure to follow, that is if the goods
were stolen from the master's plantation,
and of course the slave knew best as to
the proper owner of the goods.</p>
          <p>Men and women who were not married
lived in the common quarters as I
have said, but the men and women lived
in separate cabins. On some plantations
each slave had to do his or her own cooking,
but on the others there was a cookhouse
called the kitchen where not only
the food for the master's family was cooked, 
<pb id="parker17" n="17"/>
but also the food of such slaves as
did not live in families.</p>
          <p>The kitchen was generally under
the control of female slaves who did the
cooking with the help of one or two more
slaves and perhaps a boy to run errands.
The woman in charge would most likely
be called Aunt Dina, or Aunt somebody
else, and was quite a personage upon the
plantation, as she not only did the cooking
but also looked out for the laundry
work, and had the general charge of such
of the slave children as did not live with
their mothers, in separate cabins.</p>
          <p>These children did not have any
regular allowances but went to the
kitchen for their meals.</p>
          <p>The food being most commonly
thick sour milk and hoe cake.</p>
          <p>The milk would be poured into a
trough something like a pig's trough.
Then each child would be given a piece
of hoe cake and an iron spoon and allowed
to go to the trough and eat as much as
they wanted.</p>
          <pb id="parker18" n="18"/>
          <p>Meat was sometimes given them, but
not very often, and then it was only
what would be called waste in most families.
Good masters sometimes gave the
children meat, generally pork, three
times in a week.</p>
          <p>Fat pork was thought to improve
the looks of the children, by giving the
skin an oily look.</p>
          <p>Sometimes when the master had
company, he would have the children
all sent up to the mansion house so that
he might show them off.</p>
          <p>When this was to be done he would
send word to Aunt Dina to have the
children washed and put into clean shirts.
When this was done Aunt Dina would
take each child separately and grease its
mouth so that the child would look as if
they had been eating meat.</p>
          <p>When they were all fixed according
to Aunt Dina's idea of smartness they
would be sent to the house, and told to
stand in a row before the master, who
<pb id="parker19" n="19"/>
would point to them with about the same
kind of pride that he would have in
showing a flock of good sheep, or a lot
of good hogs.</p>
          <p>As to clothing a slave's outfit was
far from being expensive. Until I was
quite a large boy say 10 or 12 years old
my only garment was a long shirt, made
of heavy cotton cloth and reaching from
my neck to just below my knees, no
hat upon my head or shoes upon my
feet. After I was thought to be old
enough to take part in the field work, I
had a regular allowance of clothing in
common with the other slaves. This 
allowance consisted of two shirts, two pairs
of pants, two pair of shoes, one straw hat
and two blankets per year. The shirts
and pants being made of cotton ducking.
This allowance would be considered
rather small for a society young man in the
North at the present time. The outfit
of the women, like that of the men, was
very simple and inexpensive, consisting
<pb id="parker20" n="20"/>
of two sheets, two blankets, two dresses,
two pairs of shoes and now and then a
cheap hat. It must not be understood
however that slaves did not sometimes
have other clothes, for the love of dress
was just as strong with them as with
those more fortunate with funds. They
would often spend for dress the money
they earned by overwork, and sometimes
favorite slaves would have clothes
given to them. In one way or another
most of the slaves managed to have at
least one suit that was a little better
than the clothes that they wore every
day, and some of them could dress very
well when they went to meeting, or to
the gatherings upon the plantations.</p>
          <p>* * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * </p>
          <p>During the evenings in the Fall of
the year until about Christmas the
women would be required to spin cotton
yarn, which one of the hands would weave
into a <sic corr="coarse">course</sic> kind of cloth, which was
<pb id="parker21" n="21"/>
made into shirts, pants, dresses and so
forth for the slaves.</p>
          <p>When the slaves wanted to comb
their hair they did not always go to
wash as a fashionable young lady of
today does, but would get a card such as
some farmers use in carding cattle, and
would card their hair with it.</p>
          <p>It should be remembered that the
negro does not have long hair like white
people, but short curly hair commonly
called wool.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <pb id="parker22" n="22"/>
          <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
          <p>IN the locality where I lived there was
no attention paid to the ceremony of
marriage by the slaves. In fact on many
plantations many of the slaves were not
married at all but herded together very
much like cattle, living in common
quarters. On other plantations, slaves
were allowed to marry, though it often
happened that the husband lived on one
plantation and the wife and her children
upon another, but even in this case there
was seldom any marriage ceremony
performed.</p>
          <p>If a young slave took a fancy to
marry a slave girl, he first obtained the
consent of the girl herself, which, if he
was good looking and belonged to a good
family, was easily obtained, but if he
<pb id="parker23" n="23"/>
was a “no-account nigger” owned by a
failed planter or let out to a poor white
the case was different. After obtaining
the girl's consent he would go to his
master or mistress, and ask for permission
to marry, and if he stood well with
them he had no difficulty in getting
their consent. He would get permission
to go to the plantation where his
girl lived to obtain the consent of her
master. When he arrived at the plantation
where his girl lived, he would go directly
to the owner, or master as he was
called, and with whom be was most likely
acquainted, and who had perhaps been
informed by the young slave's master of
the intended visit and its object; when
a conversation something like the following
would take place:</p>
          <p>“Hello Sam! Is that you?”</p>
          <p>“Yes Massa, its me.”</p>
          <p>“How is your Master and Mistress
and the little folks?”</p>
          <pb id="parker24" n="24"/>
          <p>“Dey is all well Massa, cept Mistress
hab got a sore foot.”</p>
          <p>“Is that so Sam, how did it happen?”</p>
          <p>“D'no, spects she hurt it in de garden.”</p>
          <p>“Well Sam, when you go home give
her my compliments, and tell her that I
hope she will not be laid up long, but by
the way Sam, what message did your
Master send by you?”</p>
          <p>“Did'nt send no message, sar, I
comed myself.”</p>
          <p>“What! You don't mean to say that
you have run away Sam?”</p>
          <p>“No sar, Massa told me as how I
might come and see Massa Jones.”</p>
          <p>“Well Sam, what is it, does your
Master intend to hire you out next year
and you want me to hire you?”</p>
          <p>“No sar, Massa John don't let his
niggers, he wants me hisself. But I
comed to see you Massa cause I think
that you yellar gal Sue is a right smart,
good gal.”</p>
          <pb id="parker25" n="25"/>
          <p>“That so, Sam?”</p>
          <p>“And I thought that perhaps, maybe,
that seeing as you and Massa John was
good friends, and being as I want no bad
nigger at all, that maybe, possibly, you
might consider to consent that me and
she might be married.”</p>
          <p>At this stage of the proceedings the
“man” would look the “property” over as
carefully as a farmer would a horse or a
cow he intended to purchase, knowing as
he did so, that, if the marriage was a
desirable one, it would be for his interest
to give his consent, for would not all the
children that might be born to the couple
be his own property, and could he not
thus increase the value of his personal
estate?</p>
          <p>“Got any bad habits, Sam?”</p>
          <p>“No sar.”</p>
          <p>“Ever been whipped, Sam?”</p>
          <p>“No sar.”</p>
          <p>“Let me look at you, Sam?”</p>
          <p>“Yes sar.”</p>
          <pb id="parker26" n="26"/>
          <p>Then Sam would be carefully looked
over to see if he had any defects that
would be objectional if transmitted to his
offspring, then more questions would be
asked.</p>
          <p>“Well Sam, I like your looks, and I
will think it over. You come and see me
next week and I will tell you.”</p>
          <p>“Can I see Sue, Massa?”</p>
          <p>“Yes Sam, you can see her when she
comes from the field.”</p>
          <p>After spending some hours with his
sweetheart, Sam would go home and at
the end of the week would again get
permission to go to the Jones Plantation,
and upon arriving there he would as
before, go at once to the master.</p>
          <p>“Hello! Sam, you here again, what
do you want this time?”</p>
          <p>“Well Massa Jones, I comed to see
as to what you thought about me and
Sue getting married.”</p>
          <p>“Get out you nigger.”</p>
          <p>“But Massa told Sam to come,”</p>
          <pb id="parker27" n="27"/>
          <p>“How's that Sam?”</p>
          <p>“Massa Jones told Sam to come in
one week, and den Massa Jones tell Sam
as how he can marry Sue or not.”</p>
          <p>“O yes, I remember now, well Sam I
have talked it over with Sue's Mistress
and we have concluded to let you marry
Sue, and I will have a cabin built down
by the quarters and Sue can live there.”</p>
          <p>“Thankie Massa.”</p>
          <p>Sam would go again and find Sue and
they would spend the evening together
and from that time would be considered
as man and wife. But each would continue
a slave and must do his or her master's
bidding no matter how much it might
conflict with their own ideas of right and
wrong.</p>
          <p>In due time the cabin would be built
and would be considered as the home of
Sue, and also of Sam, whenever he could
get permission of his master to leave the
plantation or whenever he could manage
to steal away without leave.</p>
          <pb id="parker28" n="28"/>
          <p>It should be remembered that no
slave was allowed to be off the plantation
after sunset, without a written pass from
either his master or mistress.</p>
          <p>In order to prevent the slaves from
strolling about men were employed at public
expense to patrol the roads and were
instructed to whip every nigger found at
large without a written pass.</p>
          <p>A whipping of this kind meant thirty-nine
lashes on the bare back.</p>
          <p>These men were called by the slaves
“Pattie Rollers.” (Patrolmen) and were of
course hated as they deserved to be.</p>
          <p>They were generally poor whites
who did the work partly for the money
they could get out of the business, and
partly on account of the <sic corr="excitement">excitment</sic> there
was in it.</p>
          <p>They would go two, or three together
mounted on horse-back, and generally
accompanied by one or more dogs. They
were also armed with guns, and carried
great whips, made of raw-hide or leather.</p>
          <pb id="parker29" n="29"/>
          <p>If they found a slave in the road
they would at once demand his pass which
he was obliged to show when he would
be allowed to go on, but if he did not
have one he would do his best to keep
out of the way of the “Pattie Rollers,” so
that if they caught him at all it would be
after quite a chase. If the slave was a
good runner he would make straight for
the home plantation. He would of course
know the advantage, for being on foot he
could take to the woods, which he was
sure to do if hard pressed. Once in the
woods he might be obliged to hide unless
the “Pattie Rollers” had dogs with them,
but even in that case he might manage
to give them the slip, for if he came to
a stream of water he would wade or
swim across it, or he might walk in it for
a little way, in either case the dogs
would lose the scent when they got to
the water, and unless they could see or
hear him could not follow. In this way
he often managed to evade his <sic corr="pursuers">persuers</sic>.</p>
          <pb id="parker30" n="30"/>
          <p>As soon as he found that he was
not followed, he would go his way, or he
might hide a while till he thought all danger
was passed and then either go home,
or continue on his way. In any case if
he managed to get on to his master's
plantation before he was caught, the
“Pattie Rollers” were obliged to let him
go.</p>
          <p>If they caught him before he
reached the home plantation, he would
be tied to the nearest tree, what few
clothes he had on would be taken off, and
he would be given thirty-nine lashes on
his bare back.</p>
          <p>In spite of the danger of being
caught the slaves were often out nights
without passes.</p>
          <p>* * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * </p>
          <p>The slave's love for his family was as
strong as that of his white master for his,
and he would be found in his wife's cabin
as often as possible.</p>
          <pb id="parker31" n="31"/>
          <p>Of course all the children born in the
slave's cabin were slaves like their father
and mother. But there was this difference
between the children of the master
and the slave.</p>
          <p>The white child inherited his father's
name and property, but the child of the
slave mother was by law considered the
property of the mother's master even if
the father was a free negro, or as it too
often happened a free white man.</p>
          <p>The slave children were called by
the name of the master, and the father
had but very little control over them
while they were small and none at all
when they were large enough to be of
any use on the plantation.</p>
          <p>* * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * </p>
          <p>On every plantation was a place
where the slaves were buried when they
died. For the slaves were very apt to die,
as the master generally took more care
of his cattle than of his slaves.</p>
          <pb id="parker32" n="32"/>
          <p>When a slave died, the body was
placed in a rough box, carried to the
grave and buried with less form as far as
the master was concerned than would be
given the burial of a pet dog.</p>
          <p>There was not often any funeral service
at all. Sometimes in the case of the
death of a favorite the master's family
would show some interest, but generally
no more notice was taken of a slave's death
<sic corr="than">then</sic> would be given to a valuable horse
or cow. The master feeling that he had
lost so much property that was more or
less valuable.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <pb id="parker33" n="33"/>
          <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
          <p>WHEN I was a small child I lived
with my mother, in different places.
I remember that when I was about five
years old we lived with a man by the
name of Small, a name that fitted him
very well for he was a very hard, mean
man.</p>
          <p>At this time I had a little sister and
my mother would leave us in the cabin
during the day, telling me to take care of
sister.</p>
          <p>She would get up at about six
o'clock in the morning, get breakfast
for the entire family, she being the only
slave that the man Small hired.</p>
          <p>After breakfast she would put the
house in order and do all the chores and
would then work in the field till about
eleven o'clock, when she would return
<pb id="parker34" n="34"/>
and get dinner. If she happened to be
at work near the cabin she would run in
during the forenoon and feed the baby.</p>
          <p>After dinner was over and the house
again in order she would return to the
field and work till about four o'clock.
She would then return, get supper and
do the chores for the night. Everything
that she cooked was first weighed or
measured out to her and she was expected
to make it go just so far. No matter
how hungry we children were, we could
not have anything to eat till the white
folks had got all they wanted, and then
we could have what was left, and if there
was not enough left we had to wait till
mother cooked some more.</p>
          <p>One day late in the fall Small got
angry with mother and knocked her
down, then getting over her he pounded
her in the face with his fists, after which
he left her on the cabin floor and went
out. I was standing by my sister's cradle
and saw it all but of course could not do
<pb id="parker35" n="35"/>
anything to help my mother. When she
got up her face was covered with blood.
As soon as she was able she ran away to
the woods, leaving us children in the
cabin, and we did not see her again for
several weeks.</p>
          <p>When my old mistress heard of the
trouble, which she did in a very short
time, she sent and got us, and although it
was known where my mother was, she was
not required to return till Christmas time<corr>.</corr>
Small not only lost her labor during this
time but was obliged to pay for her just
the same as if she had been at work for
him.</p>
          <p>When the new year came round my
mother was let out again to another man,
but I stayed on the plantation with my
sister. The next year my sister and I
went with mother. We had a good place
and stayed there three years.</p>
          <p>The following year I was let out
alone for my board and clothes, that is
two shirts and two blankets. There was
<pb id="parker36" n="36"/>
no one in the family but the man and his
wife. I had to pick up wood for the fire,
do errands and help around the house
what I could. Sometimes I had plenty
to eat and sometimes almost nothing. I
stayed there however until the latter part
of the year, when one day the man and
his wife went away on a visit leaving me
locked up in the house with nothing to
eat. How long they intended to stay I
do not know, but it happened that my
father had got leave to visit my mother,
and on his way came to see me. When
he found out how I was situated, he got
into the house and took me out. Then
taking me upon his back he carried me
to my old mistress, who kept me with her
until my mother was let the next year.</p>
          <p>The next year I went with my
mother to live with a man by the name
of George Williams, who proved to be a
very good master.</p>
          <p>Williams had about five acres of
land and kept a small store, he also had
<pb id="parker37" n="37"/>
a horse and cow, but had no slave except
my mother. There I had a very good
time though I had to do some work.
There were several children on the place
and a part of my work was to help take
care of them.</p>
          <p>My mother did the cooking, milked
the cows and did the work on the farm.</p>
          <p>When the white children went to
school I used to carry their dinners to
them at noon. I would get there before
school was out sometimes and would hear
them singing their geography lessons,
and it was not long before I knew some
of these lessons by heart, but of course
a slave child was not supposed to need
any education.</p>
          <p>While we lived with Mr. Williams I
had many good times playing with the
other children for whatever the grown
white people might think about the colored
people, the little children did not
know any difference when they were
allowed to play with the slave children<corr>.</corr></p>
          <pb id="parker38" n="38"/>
          <p>I do not remember any game we
played that was different from those I
have seen the children in the north with
the exception of a play we used to have
with a little brown bug which we called a
“Doodle Bug”</p>
          <p>This bug as I remember it was
about three quarters of an inch long,
and spent most of its time so far as we
know at the bottom of a hole in the
ground, about half an inch in diameter
and about two inches deep. When we
wanted to play with the bug we would
hunt around till we found what we
called a Doodle Bug hole<corr>.</corr> Then one of us
would get down on all fours and put his
mouth near the hole and begin calling
“Doodle, Doodle, Doodle,” after a while
the bug would come out and play on the
ground around the top of the hole. It
would also allow itself to be taken into
the hand, when we could play with it as
long as we wished.</p>
          <p>The children believed that they
<pb id="parker39" n="39"/>
must always call it Doodle or Mr. Doodle
and that if they called it anything else it
would not come out of its hole or allow
itself to be handled. Be that as it was
we used to get a great deal of amusement
out of the Doodle Bug.</p>
          <p>Sometimes we would catch two or
three and put them together, and then
watch them play.</p>
          <p>On Sundays I used to drive the family
to church. Now it happened that
Mr. Williams had only one vehicle, and
consequently that one had to do duty
on any and all occasions. This vehicle
was a two wheeled horse cart. The body
was made of boards with stakes at the
sides, and to these were fastened rails
which ran all round the cart about three
feet above the bottom. As we stood up
in the cart the rails were very handy
to take hold of.</p>
          <p>Perhaps on Saturday I would use the
cart to carry out manure in, and on Sunday
I would brush it out and wash it a
<pb id="parker40" n="40"/>
little if it happened to be very dirty
indeed.</p>
          <p>Sunday after Sunday we all went to
church in this cart, which was drawn by
the single horse owned by Mr. Williams.</p>
          <p>In those times father often visited
us, and did what he could to make us all
happy. Though of course we saw much
less of him than most children see of
their father.</p>
          <p>At the end of our stay with Mr.
Williams, I was separated from my
mother, as it was considered that I was
then able to earn my own way living
and a little more.</p>
          <p>So on the first of the following year
I was let to a man by the name of Jacob
Parker. I remained with him for two
years, he paid five dollars the first
and ten dollars for the second year, for
my services in addition to my clothes.
Up to this time the only garment had
been the long shirt already spoken of,
but this year I had a full regular outfit
<pb id="parker41" n="41"/>
consisting, as I have said, of two shirts
two pair of pants, two jackets, two pairs
of shoes, and two blankets.</p>
          <p>At night I spread one of my blankets
upon the floor over a board about
eighteen inches wide and six feet long
and laid <sic corr="down">dawn</sic> upon it covering myself
with the other blanket using my coat for
a pillow. In the morning I got up, picked
up my blanket, put it one side and was
ready for my day's work.</p>
          <p>Mr. Parker was a common poor
white who owned or hired no slaves. I
being the only colored person on the
place, but I got along pretty well with
him, and did what I could to help.</p>
          <p>The next two years I spent on the
farm of John Cofell, another poor white<corr sic=",">.</corr></p>
          <p>He had no slaves himself but his
wife by some means became possessed
of a single female slave, who with myself
made up the list of servants. The women
did the cooking, and helped in the field;
my work was all out of doors.</p>
          <pb id="parker42" n="42"/>
          <p>Cofell was a hard man to work for
and I was glad when I got through with
him.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <pb id="parker43" n="43"/>
          <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
          <p>As I was now getting to be a good
sized boy, I began to take an interest in
the things that interested the slaves
in general and to take part in joys and
sorrows of slave life.</p>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>COON HUNTING.</head>
            <p>Although the slave's life was very far
from being pleasant it was not without
its pleasures and enjoyments, for our masters
were willing we should enjoy ourselves
after they had got all the work
they thought they could out of us.</p>
            <p>One of the diversions we had was
coon hunting.</p>
            <p>The coon is an animal a little larger
than a large house cat, His fur is gray
mixed with bluish white and brown. His
full name is raccoon, but as the colored
<pb id="parker44" n="44"/>
people of the south were pretty well
acquainted with him they generally called
him “Coon.”</p>
            <p>He lives on a mixed diet of meat,
fish, <sic corr="vegetables">vegitables</sic>, and fruit, seeming to be
equally fond of each.</p>
            <p>In the fall of the year he is often
found in the corn fields, where he feeds
upon ripening corn, and like the squirrel
not only eats it on the spot, but carries
it away to his hole, which is generally in
a hollow tree quite a distance from the
cornfield.</p>
            <p>This hole is the home of Mr. and
Mrs. Coon and two or three little coons
and they may be found there in the day-time
provided you know where the hole
is.  In the night-time both Mr. and Mrs.
Coon and the little Coons, if they are big
enough take long walks for their health,
and it is then that they visit the cornfields
and other places where they expect to find
something to eat, as they only go out on
dark nights, and they must keep a supply
<pb id="parker45" n="45"/>
of food in the hole, consequently they
carry home a great deal of food. It was
not claimed that the coons did a great
amount of damage in the cornfields.</p>
            <p>Sometimes Mr. Coon goes fishing
and he generally is able to get a dinner
of fish without much difficulty. If he
finds that fish are scarce, he will turn his
attention to his friends the frogs, of whom
he is as fond as Frenchmen.</p>
            <p>When he gets tired of fish and frogs
he eats birds, and eggs, when he can get
them, and he does not hesitate to visit
hen coops if they are near.</p>
            <p>Now it happens that the colored
people are fonder of him than he is
of them, so they go out in the night to
see him, and to catch him if they can.</p>
            <p>Two or three men or boys generally
go together on a coon hunt, taking with
them one or more dogs who are trained
for this purpose, and are known as coon
dogs.</p>
            <p>The hunters started at about nine
<pb id="parker46" n="46"/>
o'clock in the evening, taking with them
a number of pieces of fat pine. What is
called fat pine comes from those parts
of the hard pine tree that contain the
greater amount of pitch. The pine is cut
into pieces about eighteen inches long
and then split so as to be <sic corr="conveniently">conveintly</sic> handled
and is used for a torch. When the
hunt was ready to start they go to the
door of the cabin and call the dogs they
happen to have. These dogs are sent
out ahead and seem to know exactly
what is expected of them.</p>
            <p>After waiting about twenty or thirty
minutes the hunters start out themselves
and as they generally know about what
course to take to follow after the dogs,
listening for their cry. As soon as the
dogs got upon the track of the coon they
set up a peculiar cry well known to the
hunters, who then follow on as fast as
they can. Not only is the cry of the
dogs heard by the hunter but also by the
coon, who immediately begins to take
<pb id="parker47" n="47"/>
care of himself, which he does by running
in the opposite direction from which the
sound comes to him. As long as the dogs
are at a distance he takes things easy,
but as they come nearer he finds that it
will not only take all his speed, but a
large amount of cunning to keep clear of
the dogs. Up to this time he has been
running along on the ground; now he will
jump into a tree and running along from
branch to branch, and tree to tree, he
will continue his course for some time
without coming down to the ground.
Suddenly he stops and jumps so as to
strike the ground, not in the direction he
has been running but as far as possible to
one side, and in this way often reach a
place of safety before the dogs again get
upon his trail. Should he fail however
he will soon try the same trick again,
and if a stream of water be at hand he
will try and get to the other side, and
perhaps he may run in the water a little
way and then turn aside for a new trail;
<pb id="parker48" n="48"/>
but if the dogs are well trained they are
very apt to keep pretty near him, and at
last he takes to a tree as a last resort,
well knowing that the dogs cannot climb.
Up he goes to a limb near the top of the
tree. The dogs gather around the foot
of the tree and set up another sort of a
cry, which is also well understood by the
hunters who come on as fast as possible.</p>
            <p>When they get to the tree they find
the dogs, but where is the coon. After
looking into the tree for a few moments,
one of the number volunteers to go up
and find the coon. The rest stand holding
the torches. After some hard climbing,
the man in the tree gets where he
can see the light shining in the coon's
eyes, when he immediately calls out,
“Here he is, I see him,” and as well as
he can points out the location of the
coon to those below. Pretty soon he
reaches the end of the limb upon which
the coon is seated, but the coon is too
far out on the limb to be reached. But
<pb id="parker49" n="49"/>
the man wants the coon just as much
as the coon wants to keep out of
the way of the man. So a sort of
race begins; the man going as far out
on the limb as he can with safety, and
the coon going out as far as the small
limb would hold him. Then comes the
end. The man braces himself and sees
that he has a safe hold, and then begins
to shake the limb. Now, although the
the coon is almost as much at home on
a tree as a monkey or a squirrel, he
cannot hold to a very small limb a great
while. He will then go back a little way
toward the man as if to frighten him,
but finding that it is of no use, goes
back again and looks around. The shaking
of the limb is continued, and finding
that he cannot go down by the way he
came up, he jumps to the ground, not
straight down, but out at an angle from
the trunk of the tree, so as to strike the
ground at quite a distance from the foot
of the tree. If he has a good hold he
<pb id="parker50" n="50"/>
will be able to accomplish this; if not,
he may lose his hold and fall directly to
the ground. In either case he will find
that the dogs are on the lookout for him,
and he must indeed be a wise coon if he
succeeds in getting away. As soon as
the dogs come up to him a fight ensues,
in which the dogs always are the victors.
In a few minutes the coon is dead, and
the sport is over for the night.</p>
            <p>The game is carried home dressed,
the skin being carefully saved and dried
in the sun, while the coon himself
furnishes a good meal or two to his captors
and their friends.</p>
            <p>There is another animal known as the
opossum, called by the colored people
'possum. This animal is also used as
food, and is hunted in about the same
manner as the coon. The opossum has
a long tail without any hair on it, but
nevertheless, it is a very useful member.
It is used as a sort of extra hand, the
animal having full control of it, and
<pb id="parker51" n="51"/>
when pushed will use it to hang by from
a branch of a tree.</p>
            <p>The coon and opossum are very apt to
fight each other, and it is not uncommon
to see an opossum on a tree fighting a
large coon.</p>
            <p>The female has a pocket as pouch
below her breast in which she covers
her young when they are small. If an
opossum is being chased and finds that
he cannot got away, he will pretend to
be dead, and no amount of poking or
pounding will make him show any signs
of life, but just as soon as he finds his
enemy out of the way he will look
around and if he finds that the course
is clear he immediately becomes very
much alive, and takes himself out of
harm's way as soon as possible, and being
a good runner it does not take him long
to get to a safe place.</p>
            <p>Where the colored people used to
catch an opossum, one of them would
pick him up and put his tail into the
<pb id="parker52" n="52"/>
cleft of a split stick, and putting the
stick on the shoulder went carrying him
home in the same manner as a bundle
would be carried. When the opossum
is killed his skin is not taken off, but he
is put into a kettle of hot water and
scalded till the hair comes off, as do the
butchers of the hog, where he is treated
in like manner, The opossum is generally
cooked by being roasted in his skin,
and when served with roasted sweet potatoes
makes a fine dish that is much admired
by the colored people.</p>
            <p>The slaves believed that the wild
game was intended for them, for while the
master was enjoying his roast beef or
lamb, he did not think that his slaves
needed anything of the sort, but he had
no objection to the slaves' having
anything they could get to eat, provided
they got it without any expense to their
master.</p>
            <p>Black bears were to be found in the
woods, and though bear meat was
<pb id="parker53" n="53"/>
considered good eating, the slaves gave the
bears a very wide berth, for in order to
hunt him a gun was needed, and the
slaves were not allowed to have any
such weapons.</p>
            <p>Once in a while wild turkeys would
be caught in the woods. Panthers, wild
cats, and foxes were somewhat common,
but these were not meddled with by the
slaves. There were several kinds of
poisonous snakes in the woods and
swamps, but it was not often that the
slaves were bitten by them.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <pb id="parker54" n="54"/>
          <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
          <p>The slaves were unlearned, for in slavery
times it was considered a crime
to teach a slave to read, and it was not
very often that a colored person could
be found who could either read or write.
But what they lacked in book knowledge
was sometimes made up to them
in traditions. These traditions were
many of them curious and unreasonable,
but, nevertheless, were believed implicitly
by the colored people, and often-times
the white people were more or less
believers in the traditions and superstitions
of the colored people.</p>
          <p>It was very common for the white
people to have their children cared for
by colored women, whom the children
used to call mammie, and not infrequently
<pb id="parker55" n="55"/>
would these women remain in the family
year after year, caring for the children
of one generation till they grew up, and
their places filled by the children of the
second, and sometimes of the third,
generation. As these women had most
of the care of the children from their
earliest days, a very strong love always
existed between the children and the
colored mammies; and it is not strange
that the children were more or less
affected by the oft-repeated stories told
them by these mammas, sometimes to
amuse them and at other times to
frighten them into good behavior.</p>
          <p>As all the slaves believed in ghosts,
the children, both black and white,
were often told that unless they would
be good, such and such a ghost would
come and get them. One very tangible
ghost was the Bogey man, who was supposed
to have especial care of naughty
children. Nearly all the children had a
very fine belief in them until they were
<pb id="parker56" n="56"/>
grown up men and women. Sometimes
their faith was strengthened by the sight
of a frightful figure dressed in white,
with an ugly looking face, which cut up
strange capers, but it nevertheless took
good care to keep out of harm's way,
and also not to be seen at very near
distance, so as to be recognized as one of
the family slaves or field hands.</p>
          <p>Another tradition was that concerning
the owl, who the slaves considered their
especial friend and protector. Now, the
the colored man had some peculiar habits
which would hardly be tolerated in good
society. Not feeling that they were
getting all that belonged to them, or, at
least, all they wanted, they sometimes
stole corn, wheat, peas, pork, mutton, or
anything else they could eat, or that
had a market value. What they wanted
to eat was cooked in the cabin on the
sly or in the night. Sometimes they
were caught cooking the stolen food,
which, of course, was different from their
<pb id="parker57" n="57"/>
regular allowance. Then they were
questioned as to where they got it, and
if they could manage to make the
master believe that it did not come from
his plantation, nothing was said; but
those guilty were punished the next day.
So the slaves soon became aware that
the crime was not in the stealing, but in
stealing from their own masters, and
getting caught at it.</p>
          <p>But when a slave had anything to
sell, he had to be doubly careful. The
very fact that he offered anything for
sale was considered evidence that it was
stolen. It was unlawful for a white man
to buy anything of a slave unless he
could give a good account of the source
from which he got it; and as the masters
themselves generally bought what the
slaves had a right to sell, that is,
whatever they raised by working over-time
in their little yards, or, perhaps a hog
or two and a few chickens they were
allowed to keep, there was no occasion
<pb id="parker58" n="58"/>
for the slave to offer anything for sale
anywhere else. But, for all this the
slaves did have things to sell, and they
well knew where to sell them. There
was always some poor white who would
either buy the goods or sell them for the
benefit of the slaves—for a consideration.
As this man generally lived at
some distance from this plantation, the
stolen goods would have to be taken to
him secretly, and in the night, for the
night was the slaves' holiday.</p>
          <p>The slave would eat his supper and
take a nap. He would keep very quiet
until he thought that the “pattie rollers”
(patrolman)had gone home, when he
would quietly go to the place where he
had hid his stores. Taking them in a
bag, which he would throw over his
shoulders, he would start for the house
of the poor white.</p>
          <p>And now the owl plays his part. As
he sees or hears the man he is of course
disturbed, and makes much noise; but
<pb id="parker59" n="59"/>
the slave believes that if he calls from
the right side it is an omen of good luck,
and understands the owl to say, “Hoo,
hoo, hoo,” and goes about his business
without fear of being caught. But
should the owl say, “Hoo, hoo, hoo, ha,
ha,” he believes that there is danger
near, and hides himself at once, and
will keep hid as long as the owl calls in
that way. When it changes its tune to
“Hoo, hoo, hoo,” the slave moves on,
believing that the changed calls of the
owl were intended for his benefit.</p>
          <p>The slaves not only believed that the
owl was their friend, and that his language
was intended entirely for them,
but also believed that this language was
not understood by the white folks. For
example, suppose a master having no
overseers should send a number of slaves
into the field to hoe corn, they might
work well for a time, but as the day
grew warm they would get tired, and
perhaps stop to rest in the woods that
<pb id="parker60" n="60"/>
skirted the cornfield. The owl who
might happen to be near, having become
accustomed to their presence, would pay
no attention to them, but if a white man
entered the woods he would be likely to
make a different noise from that of the
slaves, and the owl would at once become
aware that something had happened
a little different from what had
been going on, and would begin to cry,
“Hoo, hoo hoo,” and the slaves would at
once take this as a warning that somebody
was near, and go to work again.
If the owl cried “Hoo, hoo, hoo, ha, ha,
ha,” they would know that somebody
was very near, and would work with all
their might, until very likely their master
would come in sight, and seeing
them doing their best, would have no
fault to find. Consequently the slave
believed that he did not know that the
owl had told them of his coming.</p>
          <p>The slaves, like some other laborers,
would work only when obliged to, and
<pb id="parker61" n="61"/>
when the horn blew for dinner or supper,
they were always ready to leave
their work. The mules that were used
to plow and cultivate, and other kinds of
farm work soon learned to know the
sound of the horn as well as the slaves,
and would want to stop when they
heard it; so that if the master came
into the field and asked the slaves why
they did not finish a certain piece of
work before they went to dinner, or
why they had left the plow in the middle
of the furrow instead of going to the
end, the slaves would reply that the
mule heard the dinner horn and would
not work any more until he had had
his dinner.</p>
          <p>There was always a kind of strife
between master and slave, the master
on the one hand trying to get all the
work he possibly could out of the slaves
at the least possible expense, and the
slaves on their part trying to get out of
all the work they could, and to take
<pb id="parker62" n="62"/>
every possible advantage of their master,
naturally feeling that all they could get
out of him was but a poor <sic corr="sustanence">sustenence</sic> for
the work they did. And whenever anything
in nature, such as the cry of an
owl, a cloud over the moon, a rainy
night, the barking of a dog, or any other
circumstance seemed to aid them in
carrying out their plans, they thought
that it was intended especially for their
benefit.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <pb id="parker63" n="63"/>
          <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
          <p>BEING out of doors a great deal of the
time, and having no books, they
learned many things from the book
of Nature, which were unknown to white
people, notwithstanding their knowledge
of books. And it often happened that
the master would be guided by the slave
as to the proper time to plant his corn,
sow his grain, or harvest his crops, and
many things of this kind, which were to
the master a source of care and anxiety,
seemed to come to the slave as it were
by instinct and not often did they made
mistake in their prophecies.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>MERRY-MAKING.</head>
            <p>Christmas was the greatest holiday
time that the slaves had; for coming as
it did at a season when there was not
as much to do as at other seasons, they
<pb id="parker64" n="64"/>
were allowed some time to enjoy themselves<corr>.</corr>
On many plantations the slaves
were allowed to have a full week to
themselves. The holiday season began
with Christmas eve, when the slaves
generally had some sort of a meeting.
Some of the people, especially the young
factor, would have a dance in one of the
cabins of the plantation.</p>
            <p>One of the slaves would plan for a
dance several weeks before the time and
word would be sent, not only to the
hands on the plantation, but also to the
other plantations near by, and when the
time came, quite a number would gather
at the appointed time, which would be
about eight o'clock as told by the <sic corr="evening">eveniug</sic>
star, for the slaves had no watches or
clocks, and consequently were obliged to
depend upon the sun, moon, and stars and
other things in nature to tell the time,
except of course, that the hours of labor
and meal times were regulated by the
watch or clock of the master.</p>
            <pb id="parker65" n="65"/>
            <p>Sometimes there would be a supper
at the gathering, in which case it would
be eaten in the first part of the evening.
This supper would consist of hominy, hoe
cakes, sweet potatoes, bacon, lamb coon
or 'possum, or any other kind of meat
that could be obtained. Sometimes the
meat would be given by the masters
who might add also flour and molasses.</p>
            <p>Sometimes the small twigs and young
needles of the hard pine tree were used
for tea. Coffee was made of corn or wheat
burnt and pounded in a mortar if one was
to be had, otherwise the corn would be
put in a cloth and pounded with an axe
or iron wedge<corr>.</corr> We also had apple
juice (cider brand), old rye whiskey,
sometimes called “old red eye,” and peach
brandy. These liquors were allowed by
the master if the slaves could buy them
themselves from the money they earned
by over work. Nearly every plantation
had its own still, so that these liquors
were both common and cheap.</p>
            <pb id="parker66" n="66"/>
            <p>After supper the room was cleared
and made ready for the dance. If some
slave could be found who had an old
fiddle and could play it at all, he was
called on to furnish music; if not, some
one would take an old tin pan and use
it like a tambourine. Two or three
others “pat Jubo,” that is, would keep
time by patting their knees with their
hands, and to this primitive music the
dance would go on hour after hour till
nearly, if not quite, broad daylight. This
would, however, be more or less singing
of words that were often made on the
spot.
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“I love my darlin', dat I do;</l><l>Don't you love Miss Susy, too?”</l></lg></q>
These words would be sung over
and over ago.</p>
            <lg type="verse">
              <l>“Sally's in de garden siftin' sand,</l>
              <l>And all she want is a honey man.</l>
              <l>De reason why I wouldn't marry,</l>
              <l>Because she was my cousin</l>
              <pb id="parker67" n="67"/>
              <l>O, row de boat ashore, hey, hey,</l>
              <l>Sally's in de garden siftin' sand.”</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Some slaves were good dancers,
especially the young girls, some of whom
could dance so steadily that if a glass of
water were placed on their heads none
of the water would be spilt. I have
often seen a girl dance for ten minutes
with a glass cup filled with water on her
head without any of it being spilt.</p>
            <p>If the next day was Sunday or was a
holiday, the dance would <sic corr="continue">contiuue</sic> all
night. The young men would dance all
night till broad daylight, and then go
home with the girls in the morning.</p>
            <p>In some other cabin, perhaps on the
same plantation, while the young people
were dancing, the old ones would be
holding a prayer “meetin'”, notice having
been sent out as in the case of the
dance. As none of the slaves could
read, there were no books at these
meetings. When the folks got together
some one would begin with a prayer, or
<pb id="parker68" n="68"/>
perhaps with a hymn, in which he or
she would be followed by all in the room,
unless it happened that they did not
know the piece, which was perhaps being
made up as the singer went along.</p>
            <p>Of course there were no musical conductors,
but the slaves in part made up
for this lack by keeping time with their
feet and hands. These meetings would
sometimes last all night, and the slaves,
ignorant as they were, always enjoyed
them.</p>
            <p>The following hymn was one of the
most popular, and was sure to be sung
at these meetings:</p>
            <lg type="hymn">
              <l>“Roll Jordan roll, roll Jordan roll,</l>
              <l>I want to be in de kingdom,</l>
              <l>To heah ole Jordan roll.</l>
              <l>You see dat falcon a-lighting,</l>
              <l>You see dat falcon a-lighting,</l>
              <l>To heah ole Jordan roll.</l>
              <pb id="parker69" n="69"/>
              <l>You see ole Massa Jesus a-coming,</l>
              <l>You see ole Massa Jesus a-coming,</l>
              <l>You see ole Massa Jesus a-coming,</l>
              <l>To heah ole Jordan roll.</l>
              <l>Roll Jordon roll, roll Jordan roll,</l>
              <l>I want to go to Heaven when I die.</l>
              <l>To heah ole Jordan roll.”</l>
            </lg>
            <p>As I have said before, slaves were
very musical in their way, which, if not
up to the modern ideas of music, was such
that they derived very much enjoyment
from it. At nearly all times one would
hear the slaves singing snatches of old
plantation songs, which for want of
space I cannot print, but the following
is a part of one of the best known
songs:</p>
            <lg type="hymn">
              <l>“When I was a little pickanninny, playin' around
de cabin door,</l>
              <l>I was de happiest little darkey in de land,</l>
              <pb id="parker70" n="70"/>
              <l>Now I'm getting ole and feeble and my hair is
turnin' gray,</l>
              <l>And I am goin' back to Georgia, if I can.</l>
              <l>Good ole Georgie, happy land!</l>
              <l>Gwine to live and die in good ole Georgie
land.”</l>
            </lg>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <pb id="parker71" n="71"/>
          <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
          <p>THE following year after I left Cofell I
went to work for Darias White who
was a step son of my old master, and I
continued to work for him three years.
His business was to get out oak and hard
pine lumber most of which was used in
ship-building.</p>
          <p>All the time I worked for White I
drove team, and had charge of the mules
and one horse. The horse was kept by
my master for his own use. The mules
were used entirely for teaming. Besides
these he had a large number of oxen that
were used for <sic corr="hauling">hawling</sic> the great logs out
of the woods.</p>
          <p>These logs were of the largest kind
and were often one hundred feet or more
in length. The but end of the log was
<pb id="parker72" n="72"/>
fastened to the axletree of an enormous
pair of wheels, from the axletree projected
a long tongue, to which was attached
a single yoke of oxen. In front of this
yoke of oxen there was sometimes as
many as fifteen yoke of oxen one ahead
of the other and all fastened by a chain
to the end of the tongue. A team of this
kind required about eight drivers. Each
driver was seated on the yoke of one
pair of oxen, and would drive that yoke
and the yoke in front.</p>
          <p>Instead of a whip such as is used in
the north, the drivers would have a long
slender birch rod, which when green
would be almost as durable as a raw-hide.</p>
          <p>The small end of the log was also
hung between a large pair of wheels. To
the tongue of which was fastened a rope
from twelve to fifteen feet long with a
<sic>a</sic> knot in the end. The end of this rope
was given into the hands of a strong
active negro, whose business it was to
steer the logs. When everything was
<pb id="parker73" n="73"/>
ready the word to start would be given
and away the logs went, the oxen pulling
with all their might and the log drivers
shouting at the top of their voices.</p>
          <p>The man with the guiding ropes of
the rear wheels sometimes on the logs
sometimes on the ground at one side,
and sometimes at the other side working
with all his strength to keep the log in
its place, and so the procession proceeded
from the woods to the river bank, where
the log would be left till enough were
got together to ship to market.</p>
          <p>Very often I had to drive oxen
myself, though my business generally
was to drive the mules, drawing grain
and fodder for the oxen. Sometimes
the mules would be hitched in front of
the ox team. I liked this sort of work
very well as it was not often hard, and
there was a good deal of excitement about
it.</p>
          <p>Mr. White was a good master and
took good care of his slaves, and was
<pb id="parker74" n="74"/>
never known to whip one. He generally
had about forty hands in all. Often at
the end of the year a slave who had done
well, would receive a present of five or
ten dollars from him.</p>
          <p>He liked to see his slaves look well
and they soon learned to keep clean and
to look as respectable as possible.</p>
          <p>Their clothes were of heavy white
cotton cloth, which would be carefully
washed each week, so that as they went
to the woods on Monday morning, they
would present quite a smart appearance.</p>
          <p>Had all masters been like Darias
White there would been far less
trouble with the slaves, as under such
masters they were generally happy and
contented.</p>
          <p>Many of the slaves camped in the
woods through the entire lumber season.</p>
          <p>A camp would be made of logs, bark
and pieces of board, which would enclose
the camp on three sides, on the fourth a
large fire would be built at night, at
<pb id="parker75" n="75"/>
which we did our cooking. Every evening
after supper had been disposed of the
slaves would spend the time till bed time
in singing and telling stories.</p>
          <p>After I got through with Mr. White
I went to live with Elisha Buck with
whom I lived one year. Buck was a
mean poor white who had a large farm,
and owned some slaves, and I made the
eighth hand on the farm. He did not
treat us at all well, and it was not often
that we had all we wanted to eat. One
day while I lived on his place I went in
company with another slave into the
woods and caught a pig, which we
knocked in the head with a large pine
knot, which we called a lighted knot, but
it so happened that the owner of the pig
was in the woods, and hearing the pig
<sic corr="squeal">squeel</sic> came to see what the matter was
We did not get away before he saw us so
he went directly to Buck and told him
that two of his niggers had been stealing
a pig. We were<sic corr="immediately"> immediatly</sic> called out
<pb id="parker76" n="76"/>
of the field by Buck, and he told the
owner of the pig that he could give us
a whipping, but that he could not strike
us on the back, so we got about thirty-nine
lashes each, and then were let go.</p>
          <p>It did not do much good to either
of us for on the following Sunday I went
into the woods again and got another pig
which I dressed in the night.</p>
          <p>As I did not have every <sic corr="advantage">atvantage</sic> of
a first-class slaughter house I was obliged
to manage as best I could. Accordingly I
built a fire and gave the pig a good singeing
and while he was warm from the
effects of the fire. I put him into water,
and then scraped him with a case-knife
and finally got him clean.</p>
          <p>When he was properly dressed I
carried him on my shoulder about three
miles, and turned him over to a “poor
white” who took him to a neighboring town
the next day, and sold him for me. I got
back to quarters before the hands were
<pb id="parker77" n="77"/>
called in the morning so that no one
knew where I had been.</p>
          <p>In due time the “poor white” gave
me my share of the money he got for the
pig. With this money I bought some
cloth, which a white woman made into a
coat and a pair of pants for me.</p>
          <p>A few days afterwards I wore my
new clothes to a “big meeting,” that is a
meeting in the woods something like a
camp meeting. Put the fact that they
were paid for with stolen goods did not
trouble me at all.</p>
          <p>The negroes at the south seemed to
think that everything that they could get
hold of belonged to them.</p>
          <p>In New England this code of morals
would appear rather out of place. But
if you consider that a strong able bodied
slave was required to work a full year for
his board and clothes. And not only this,
but that he was expected to cook his own
food after doing his day's work, and it will
be remembered that the entire cost <sic corr="of">o</sic>
<pb id="parker78" n="78"/>
food furnished him was in most cases less
than thirty dollars per year, and that the
entire outfit in the shape of clothes cost
less than twelve dollars per year, making
a grand total of less than forty two dollars
per year or three dollars and fifty cents
per month. The slave could hardly be
expected to feel the same regards for his
master's rights as he would have done had
he been a free man, properly treated and
justly paid.</p>
          <p>While I was living with this man
my mother's health began to fail, and I
frequently went to see her. As her
friends gathered around her she would tell
them that while she did not expect to live
to see it she hoped that the time would
soon come when all the slaves would be
free.</p>
          <p>The war of the rebellion had at this
time been in progress some months, and
although our masters tried to keep all
matters relating to the war from their
slaves, the slaves managed to get hold
<pb id="parker79" n="79"/>
of a good deal of news, and the idea was
fast gaining ground, that in some way
they were soon to be free. As the time
went on my mother became weak and I
obtained leave to be with her nights, and
my father got leave to be with her three
nights in a week and all day Sunday.
At this time he lived about eight miles
from my mother's cabin, and of course
had to walk both ways every time he
came to see her. Both my father and
I were with mother when she died
which took place about nine o'clock one
August night.</p>
          <p>She was buried in the same manner
that most of the slaves were. A negro
carpenter made a rough pine box, without
lining, trimming, or paint. Her only
<sic corr="shroud">shrowd</sic> was a white night-dress, yet the
tender hands of her loved ones smoothed
this out as carefully as if it had been of
the finest satin. A few of the nearest
friends and neighbors gathered round the
<pb id="parker80" n="80"/>
rough coffin to take a last look at the
dear face, then the cover was nailed on,
the coffin placed in a cart and carried
to a little sandy knoll, and beneath the
shade of a few stunted pines a shallow
grave was dug, in which without ceremony
the coffin was placed and the
sandy earth heaped above it. Not a
prayer was said nor a hymn sung for the
white folks seemed to feel that the sooner
the matter was over the more time the
slaves would have for work, and the slaves
—well they were not supposed to feel at
all, they were only cattle. Nevertheless
the form that now lies in that unmarked
grave, far in the sunny south, was that of
my mother, and my mother was just as
dear to me, kind reader, as your mother is
to you; and though she died a slave, and
lies buried where I may never visit her
grave, I hope by the grace of Him who
died that that we might live, to meet her
in that land where all shall be free, and
<pb id="parker81" n="81"/>
where there shall be no night nor any
sorrow, and where there shall be none to
oppress.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <pb id="parker82" n="82"/>
          <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
          <p>A short time after my mother died, I got
tired of living with Burk and ran
away to the woods. I would stay in the
woods in the day time, and in the night
I would go to the house of a poor white
woman who had been a friend to my
mother. After I had stayed away about
a week I got tired of that sort of life
and went back to Mr. Buck. When I
got back Buck called two of his slaves,
who helped him to tie me, and then he
gave me a whipping on the legs with a
cowhide. I did not run away again, and
for a time he treated me better than he
had done before.</p>
          <p>As the years of my service drew to a
close he grew more close, but at times
was unkind to me. He did not try to
<pb id="parker83" n="83"/>
injure me again till the end of my service,
not daring to touch me any more,
while my term of service lasted. On the
last day he came to me and said he was
going to whip me. I said he should not
and started to run. He ran after me,
but did not catch me until I got on the
old Parker Plantation. I then raised
my hand and told him that he could not
touch me<corr>.</corr>  He went to my mistress and
told her that he wanted to whip me,
but she informed him that as I had got
through my term of service, he had
nothing more to do with me, and so the
matter ended.</p>
          <p>My mistress, however, called me to
her and told me to look out for myself
for Mr. Buck, she said, would be likely
to injure me if he got a chance when I
was off that plantation.</p>
          <p>The following January I was let to a
man of the name of John Littlefield. He
was a poor white who had two women
slaves and a slave of his own. He was a
<pb id="parker84" n="84"/>
small farmer. I stayed with him some
months, and being near the old
plantation I saw my owners quite often.
One day Miss Annie said to me, “Allen,
if the war continues shall you run away
or will you stay with me?” I told her
that I did not want to leave her and
would not run off to the Yankees, I
was on good terms with Miss Annie for
there was only a few days difference in
our ages, I being the older, and we were
both still young and did not feel the
difference in our stations, it was true that
she owned me but as she had up to
this time had no care of her own property,
she did not seem to <sic corr="realize">relize</sic> that I was her
slave. And as I had <sic corr="always">slways</sic> been well <sic corr="treated">treeted</sic>
by all the Parker family I had no feelings
for any of them except love and respect.
The plantation had always been my
home when I was not out at work, either
alone or with my mother so, that I felt as
if in a measure I was one of the family<corr sic=",">.</corr></p>
          <p>However in common with all the
<pb id="parker85" n="85"/>
Negroes I had <sic corr="imbibed">inbribed</sic> very strong yearning
for freedom and was hoping that in
some way my freedom would come to me.
But up to the time of my mother's death
I had no idea of running away to stay<corr sic=",">.</corr>
But while I was with Littlefield we kept
hearing more and more about the “Yankees”
and the more we heard, the more
uneasy we became. Many of the slaves
from the plantation had been sent to
Richmond for fear they would run away, but
none of the Parker slaves had been sent
off, nor had any of them ran away.</p>
          <p>But as the summer months passed,
those of us that were left on the plantation,
felt more and more restless, for added
to our increasing desire for liberty
we could not help feeling the <sic corr="extra">xtra</sic>
restraint that was put upon all the slaves in
the vicinity to prevent them from running
away.</p>
          <p>The roads were patrolled and every
effort was made to keep the slaves on
the plantations at night, and it was very
<pb id="parker86" n="86"/>
hard to get a pass to leave home at all;
but nevertheless we did manage to get
away quite often and many conferences
were hold, in which the doings of the
“Yankees” were talked over, and ideas
in <sic corr="relation">relacion</sic> to freedom exchanged by the
slaves.</p>
          <p>During the month of August<corr sic=".">,</corr> 1862
slaves living on the adjoining plantation
together with myself began to form plans
of in some way getting to the “yankees”<corr>.</corr>
We used to get together when we could
and talk our plans over, but for a time
did nothing else. But finally finding
that lots of the slaves from the neighboring
plantation were running away we
concluded that we would take our chance,
as soon as we could get any.</p>
          <p>One day we heard a gun fire about
four o'clock in the morning and upon
gathering in the morning to see what the
matter was we saw a United States gunboat
out in the river. As this was by
no means the first we had seen of Uncle
<pb id="parker87" n="87"/>
Sam's vessels we were not at all surprised
and in fact for some days we had agreed
that the next time a vessel came up the
river we would try and get on board her.
That night after it was quiet, my three
friends, whose names were Joe, Arden
and Dick all slaves of one Robert Felton
came to see me. We talked the matter
over and concluded to start that night.
We waited till everything was quiet
for as it happened there were no “pattie
rollers” out that night; and then stole
our way down to the river bank, where
we knew there was a boat. We found
the boat all right but it was fastened to
a tree with a chain the ends being locked
together. I told the other three men to
get some sticks and march up and down
the beach like soldiers while I took
another stick with which I managed to
pull out the staple that held the chain to
the boat thereby leaving chain and lock
fast to the tree where it may be yet for
ought I know to the contrary. There
<pb id="parker88" n="88"/>
were some paddles in the boat, and we
were not long in making use of them.
Pushing out from the shore we bid goodbye
to the old plantations and slave life
forever. As we neared the boat we were
hailed with, “Who are you?” We
replied, “Friends,” and received the reply,
“Advance, friends, and come alongside.”
As we got alongside of the gunboat we
were hailed again with, “Who are you?”
and “where did you come from?” My
friends said that they were from Rob.
Felton's plantation, and I told them that
I belonged to Miss Annie Parker. They
then inquired if our owners were Union
people or not, and we replied that they
were not. The officer who had hailed
us then reported what we said to the
captain, but before he went away we
told him that all wanted to go on board
the vessel and stay. We asked him if he
could not take us on board to let us
know at once, so that we could got back
home before morning. When the officer
<pb id="parker89" n="89"/>
came back he said he had orders from
the captain to let us come aboard. We
immediately accepted the invitation, and
being very tired, were soon fast asleep
on the deck of the vessel. In the morning
we were told that we could stay on
the boat. Accordingly, we let our boat
drift, which, by the way, was only a
cypress dug out, being made of a single
log.</p>
          <p>When it was light we found that we
had been missed at home, for soon there
was quite a number of men, armed with
guns and accompanied by dogs, collected
on the shore, but there was a wide
step of water between us, and we did not
feel very much alarmed. The captain
watched them for a while, then ordered
a gun loaded with a shell to be fired in
that direction. The shell burst in the
air, but our friends did not stay to see
another fired. They seemed to remember
very suddenly that they had something
to do at home; at any rate, in a
<pb id="parker90" n="90"/>
very short time not a man or dog was to
be seen.</p>
          <p>The next night some of the sailors
taking Joe as a pilot, went to the Felton
plantation and got quite a lot of chickens,
ducks and geese. A few nights
afterward they went to the plantation
again, and finding that Mr. Fulton was
at home, they surrounded the house and
took him prisoner  He was carried on
board the vessel and kept there until
she went to New Berne. The morning
after he was taken prisoner his wife and
two little children went to the vessel and
asked to see him, which was permitted.
But it chanced that before Mrs. Felton
saw her husband she sighted Joe, to
whom she used some very hard language,
to say the least. Among other
things she told him that if the south
were successful they would kill all the
negroes that ran away. Joe quietly
informed her that as the south would not
win, he thought he was safe enough.</p>
          <pb id="parker91" n="91"/>
          <p>It happened that Joe was a son of
Mr. Felton, and his mother was one of
Col. Felton's slaves. But the tables had
turned; Joe remained on the vessel a
free man, and Felton was a prisoner of
war. A few months afterward Joe was
accidentally drowned.</p>
          <p>In a few days I embarked in the
United Suites Navy and was placed on
board a vessel that had been captured
from the rebels. I served on this vessel,
which was called “The Knockum,” and
was used as an ammunition boat, for one
year when I got my discharge. I then
went to Beaufort, where I worked in a
saw mill for some months. After that I
went to sea again as steward on a sailing
vessel, owned in Portland Me. We
loaded with timber for Brooklyn, N. Y.,
and after discharging our cargo, we
sailed to Portland, at which place I left
the vessel, and have never been South
since.</p>
          <p>After staying in Portland about a
<pb id="parker92" n="92"/>
week, I went directly to New Haven,
Conn., where I had a cousin who had
formerly been a slave in the Parker
family, but had been purchased by an
Alabama planter. When this planter
died he left it in his will that my cousin
should be free; he also left a sum of
money with which she came north. I
stayed with her for about a year, during
which time I worked for a mason as hod
carrier and general laborer. From New
Haven I went to various places, staying
but a short time in each<corr>.</corr>  I finally drifted
to Worcester, where I have lived most
of the time for the last thirty years.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div1 type="text">
        <pb id="parker93" n="93"/>
        <head>SLAVE ADVERTISEMENTS.</head>
        <p>The following advertisements were
taken word for word from different issues
of a South Carolina newspaper:</p>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>BY JACOB CHAM &amp; SON,</head>
          <p>At Probate Sale,</p>
          <p>Joe, 50, competent butler.
<lb/>
Silvia, 35, excellent cook.
<lb/>
Charles, 21, Waiting man.
<lb/>
Sophia, 14.</p>
          <p>The above family is well worth the
attention of those wishing trusty negroes.
They are to be sold to a city owner. For
further particulars apply as above at
24 BROAD STREET,
Old State Bank.</p>
          <pb id="parker94" n="94"/>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>UNDER DECREE IN EQUITY.</head>
          <p>EXECUTION OF WHITESIDES VS. WILLIAMS.
will be sold on
WEDNESDAY, 28TH OF MAY, 1860,
at 11 o'clock,
On the Mart in Chalmer Street,
the following thirteen valuable slaves, viz.,</p>
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Emanuel, aged 50, field hand and good hustler.</item>
            <item>Hager, aged 30 years, cook and washer</item>
            <item>Betty, aged 14 years.</item>
            <item>James, aged 12 years.</item>
            <item>Jack, aged 9 years.</item>
            <item>Katy, aged 25 years, cook.</item>
            <item>Anna, aged 4 years.</item>
            <item>Jenkins, aged 18 months.</item>
            <item>Mary, aged 16 years, waiting maid.</item>
            <item>George, aged 17 years, horse boy.</item>
            <item>Harriett, aged 60 years.</item>
            <item>Sam, aged 5 years.</item>
            <item>Betty, aged two years.</item>
          </list>
          <p>Terms: One-third cash; balance in
one and two years, to be secured by
bond, mortgage and two approved sureties.
Purchasers to pay for papers.</p>
          <closer><signed>JAMES TUPPER,</signed>
Master in Equity.</closer>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <pb id="parker95" n="95"/>
          <head>A REWARD OF 5 OR 20 DOLLARS.</head>
          <p>Five Dollars will be paid
for the apprehending of my
negro man named Stephen,
who, in looking out for a
master from the 29th ultimo,
has not returned to his duty, nor has he
been heard of; is about 5 feet 8 inches
high, stoutly built, well formed, speaks
good English, and is inclined to be plausible;
black complexion, small whiskers
and a few white hairs in them. He is
well-known about the city, has a free
wife at Mr. Robert Anderson's market in
King street. A reward of twenty dollars
will be paid for proof to conviction that
he is harbored by a white person or free
person of any color.</p>
          <p>A reward will also be paid for the
apprehension of old limpy negro Fortune
who for two months has been looking
for a lost turkey. For further particulars
<pb id="parker96" n="96"/>
inquire at the corner of St. Philip
and Six streets.</p>
          <closer><signed>J. JOONIS.</signed>
<dateline>Novr. 8, 1831.</dateline></closer>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI.2>