<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY alecktp SYSTEM "alecktp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY aleckvs SYSTEM "aleckvs.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY aleckcv SYSTEM "aleckcv.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>Before the War, and After the Union.  An Autobiography:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Aleckson, Sam, b. 1852</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Tom Horan and Bethany Ronnberg</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by</resp>
          <name>Chris Hill</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name rend="italics">Chris Hill and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>2000</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca. 200K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>2000.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as 
long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="title page"> Before the War, and After the Union; An Autobiography</title>
            <title type="cover"> Before the War, and After the Union</title>
            <author>Sam Aleckson</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent> 171 p., ill.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>Boston, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
            <publisher>Gold Mind Publishing Company</publisher>
            <date>[1929]</date>
            <authority/>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="yes">Call number  E185.97 .A36 1929   (Cornell University  Library)</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Aleckson, Sam, b. 1852.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- South Carolina -- Charleston --
Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- South Carolina -- Charleston -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- South Carolina -- Charleston -- History -- 19th
century.</item>
            <item>Plantation life -- South Carolina -- History -- 19th 
century.</item>
            <item>South Carolina -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.</item>
            <item>Reconstruction -- South Carolina.</item>
            <item>Slaves' writings, American -- South Carolina.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2000-12-12, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2000-03-29, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2000-03-23, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Chris Hill</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2000-03-17, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Bethany Ronnberg and Tom Horan</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="cover">
        <p>
          <figure id="cv" entity="aleckcv"/>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="title page">
        <p>
          <figure id="tp" entity="alecktp"/>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="verso">
        <p>
          <figure entity="aleckvs"/>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">Before The War,<lb/>
and<lb/>
After the Union</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="subtitle">
            <hi rend="italics">An Autobiography</hi>
          </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>By
<docAuthor>SAM ALECKSON<lb/>
1852—1914<lb/>
WINDSOR, VERMONT</docAuthor></byline>
        <docImprint><publisher>GOLD MIND PUBLISHING COMPANY</publisher>
<pubPlace>BOSTON, MASSACHUSETTS</pubPlace></docImprint>
        <pb id="aleckvs" n="verso"/>
        <docImprint><docDate>Copyrighted 1929<lb/>
SAMUEL WILLIAMS</docDate>
<pubPlace>Printed in U. S. A.</pubPlace>
<publisher>GOLD MIND PRINTERS</publisher>
<pubPlace>Boston, Mass.</pubPlace></docImprint>
        <pb id="aleck7" n="7"/>
        <epigraph>
          <q type="quote" direct="unspecified">
            <lg type="verse">
              <l>“I will a plain unvarnished tale deliver.”</l>
              <signed>Shakespeare.</signed>
            </lg>
          </q>
        </epigraph>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="contents">
        <pb id="aleck8" n="8"/>
        <head>BEFORE THE WAR</head>
        <list type="simple">
          <head>CONTENTS</head>
          <item>1 Genealogy . . . . . <ref target="aleck17" targOrder="U">17</ref></item>
          <item>2 Childhood . . . . . <ref target="aleck22" targOrder="U">22</ref></item>
          <item>3 The Fickle Maiden . . . . . <ref target="aleck35" targOrder="U">35</ref></item>
          <item>4 The Lover . . . . . <ref target="aleck61" targOrder="U">61</ref></item>
          <item>5 The Hunting Season at Pinetop . . . . . <ref target="aleck66" targOrder="U">66</ref></item>
          <item>6 The Beginning of the End . . . . . <ref target="aleck76" targOrder="U">76</ref></item>
          <item>7 In Town Again . . . . . <ref target="aleck86" targOrder="U">86</ref></item>
          <item>8 A Turkey Stew . . . . . <ref target="aleck94" targOrder="U">94</ref></item>
          <item>9 Tom Bale . . . . . <ref target="aleck98" targOrder="U">98</ref></item>
          <item>10 Silla—The Maid . . . . . <ref target="aleck108" targOrder="U">108</ref></item>
          <item>11 The Appraisement . . . . . <ref target="aleck113" targOrder="U">113</ref></item>
          <item>12 The Big Fire . . . . . <ref target="aleck117" targOrder="U">117</ref></item>
          <item>13 Mr. Ward's Return to Pinetop . . . . . <ref target="aleck119" targOrder="U">119</ref></item>
          <item>14 Roast Possum . . . . . <ref target="aleck128" targOrder="U">128</ref></item>
          <item>15 After De Union . . . . . <ref target="aleck138" targOrder="U">138</ref></item>
          <item>16 In the Land of the Puritans . . . . . <ref target="aleck147" targOrder="U">147</ref></item>
          <item>17 The Town of Springlake . . . . . <ref target="aleck155" targOrder="U">155</ref></item>
          <item>18 Wrong Impressions . . . . . <ref target="aleck165" targOrder="U">165</ref></item>
        </list>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="dedication">
        <pb id="aleck11" n="11"/>
        <p>
          <hi rend="italics">Dedicated<lb/>
to<lb/>
My Children<lb/>
and<lb/>
Grand Children<lb/>
Whose<lb/>
Kindness and Affection<lb/>
Serve in Great Measure<lb/>
to Make My Declining Years<lb/>
Peaceful and Contented.</hi>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="preface">
        <pb id="aleck14" n="14"/>
        <head>PREFACE</head>
        <p>“When I began this unpretentious narrative, I was
almost sightless. I had just recovered from a severe attack
of illness, during which for a time I became totally blind,
and after I was better my eyes seemed hopelessly affected.
This I endeavored to conceal as I had to earn my bread, but
so frequently did I pass my most intimate friends on the
street without the slightest show of recognition that I was
forced to admit I was almost blind. I was then urged to
consult an eminent physician of the town who gave special
attention to ailments of the eye, and after a complete
examination, he informed me that my eyes were in such
condition that glasses would do me no good, and with a
show of sincere sympathy said, “I am sorry for you, but
within six months you will be totally blind.”</p>
        <p>“Approaching blindness is always appalling, especially
to one who is dependent on his labor for a living. ‘What
shall I do when my sight is gone?’ This question forced
itself upon me night and day. I was then past middle life,
and the prospects of a blind and helpless old age stood out
before me. My life had not been wholly uneventful; I had
been of
<pb id="aleck15" n="15"/>
an observant turn of mind from my youth. What if I could
set down the events that had come under my observation
in some connected form? Might I not thereby be able to
earn something toward my support when I could no longer see!</p>
        <p>“I was compelled to give up some of my work on account
of failing sight, but I was still employed by day. I began to
write at night often tinder poor light, being scarcely able to
see the words as I traced them. Thus my MS. was finished.
Untoward conditions prevented publication and it has lain hidden
away all these years. The motive that first prompted me to
undertake the task no longer exists, my sight has been
providentially restored, and at the age of seventy-two I find
myself in good health and able to earn my living. There are
other considerations, however, which actuate me, even at
this late day, to present to the reader this crude story.</p>
        <p>“It is a remarkable fact that very many of the immediate
descendants of those who passed through the trying
ordeal of American slavery know nothing of the hardships
through which their fathers came. Some reason for this may
be found in the fact that
<pb id="aleck16" n="16"/>
those fathers hated to harrow the minds of their
children by the recital of their cruel experiences
of those dark days. There is, however, a deeper reason. 
It is found in the religious nature of the
Negro and the readiness with which he fell under the
influence of Christianity, and the zeal with which
he strove to follow the teaching and example of the
lowly Nazarene.</p>
        <p>“If the Negro had emerged from slavery in a sullen
and vindictive frame of mind, he would
unquestionably have shared the fate of the American 
Indian, and we would not now be witnessing the 
marvelous progress he is making, nor his surprising 
increase in numbers.</p>
        <p>“While it is sweet to forgive and forget, there 
are somethings that should never be forgotten. If 
this humble narrative will serve to cause the youth 
of my people to take a glance backward, the object 
of the writer will have been attained. As Frederick 
Douglass has said, “How can we tell the distance we 
have come except we note the point from
which we started?”</p>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="aleck17" n="17"/>
        <head>CHAPTER I</head>
        <head>GENEALOGY</head>
        <epigraph>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">“Breathes there a man with soul so dead”</hi>
          </p>
        </epigraph>
        <p>I WAS born in Charleston, South Carolina in the 
year, 1852. The place of my birth and the conditions 
under which I was born are matters over 
which, of course, I had no control. If I had, I 
should have altered the conditions, but I should not 
have changed the place; for it is a grand old city,
and I have always felt proud of my citizenship. My father
and my grandfather were born there, and there they 
died—my grandfather at the age of seventy-two, my father at
seventy-six. My great grandfather came, or rather was
brought, from Africa. It is said he bore the distinguishing
marks of royalty on his person and was a fine looking 
man—fine looking for a Negro I believe is the
<pb id="aleck18" n="18"/>
usual qualification—at least that is what an old lady once
told my own father who had inherited the good looks of his
grandsire.</p>
        <p>I do not know the name my great grandfather bore in
Africa, but when he arrived in this country he was given the
name, Clement, and when he found he needed a surname—
something he was not accustomed to in his native land—he
borrowed that of the man who bought him. It is a very good
name, and as we have held the same for more than a
hundred and fifty years, without change or alteration, I
think, therefore, we are legally entitled to it. His descendants
up to the close of the Civil War, seemed with rare good
fortune under the Providence of God, to have escaped many
of the more cruel hardships incident to American slavery.</p>
        <p>I may be permitted to add that on the arrival of my
progenitor in this country he was not allowed to enter into
negotiation with the Indians, and thereby acquire a large
tract of land. Instead, an axe was placed in his hands and he
therefore became in some sort, a pioneer of American
civilization.</p>
        <pb id="aleck19" n="19"/>
        <p>My father and my mother were both under the “yoke”,
but were held by different families. They made their home
with my father's people who were, of all slave holders, the
very best; and it was here that I spent the first years of my
life.</p>
        <p>My mother went to her work early each morning, and
came home after the day's work was done. My brother,
older than I, accompanied her, but I being too young to be
of practical service, was left to the care of my 
grandmother—and what a dear old christian she was! 
At this time her advanced age and past faithful service, 
rendered her required duties light, so that she had 
ample time to care for me. Her patient endeavor to 
impress upon my youthful mind the simple principles 
of a christian life shall never be forgotten, and 
I trust her efforts have not been altogether in
vain. She was born in the hands of the family where she
passed her entire life; and it would be a revelation to many
of the present day to know to what extent her counsel and
advice was sought and heeded by the household—white and
black.</p>
        <p>Our household was large; beside the owners, three
<pb id="aleck20" n="20"/>
maiden ladies (sisters) there were a dozen servants, some
like my father, worked out and paid wages, but all:
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“Claimed kindred here</l><l>And had their claims allowed.”</l></lg></q>
for, there never was a better ordered establishment, nor were
there ever better examples of christian womanhood than that
of the three ladies who presided over it; and it is especially
worthy of note that all the servants who were old enough,
could read, and some of them had mastered the three “R's”,
having been taught by these ladies or their predecessors.
Before the beginning of the Civil War these kind ladies
liberated all their slaves, and it is no reflection on the Negro
that many of the liberated ones refused to leave them. There
were many considerations that prompted them to decline
their proffered freedom; in some cases husband and wife
were not fellow-servants, and one was unwilling to leave the
other. All those who accepted their liberty were sent to
Liberia. I know of one who returned after the, war to visit
relatives and friends. He had been
<pb id="aleck21" n="21"/>
quite successful in his new home, and he gave good
account of those who had left Charleston with him. Some
had died, others were doing well. He found one of the good
ladies still living and had the great pleasure of relating his
story to her. When, after a brief stay in the city, he took his
departure, he carried with him many tokens of remembrance
from their kind benefactress for himself and those at home.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="aleck22" n="22"/>
        <head>CHAPTER II</head>
        <head>CHILDHOOD</head>
        <epigraph>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>
              <hi rend="italics">“How dear to my heart are the scenes of my
childhood</hi>
            </l>
            <lb/>
            <l>
              <hi rend="italics">When fond recollections present them to view.”</hi>
            </l>
          </lg>
        </epigraph>
        <p>Though fifty years of time and more than a thousand miles
of space separate me from the home of my birth and early
childhood, the old home seems more plain before me now
than places I visited but yesterday. It was a grand old
house, built of grey brick. There were three spacious
piazzas running along the west and south sides of the
house. The wide yard was paved with brick. To the west of
the paved yard was a large garden in which rarest flowers
bloomed; but dearer than all to our youthful hearts were the
“Four-o'clocks”, that grew there in great profusion and
various colors. We made festoons of them, hung them over
our heads while we
<pb id="aleck23" n="23"/>
“played house” and made mud pies beneath. We wove
garlands and twined them about the neck of dear old
“Watch.” He was our great Newfoundland. Was there ever
such a faithful dog as he? Noble animal, rough and tumble
with the boys, gentle with the girls, but kind to all. The
bulldog and the pug have taken his place now, but surely
there never was a safer or kinder friend to children than he.
Our “Watch” had never read “The Rights of the Child,” but
he put his foot, or rather his paw (no small one), down on
any of us being punished in his presence. Whenever our
parents deemed it <sic corr="incumbent">encumbent</sic> on them to give forcible and painful
evidence that they were not amendable to the charge of
“sparing the rod and spoiling the child,” it was necessary to
lock Watch up in the woodshed, and if in their haste this
precaution was neglected he would rush in, seize the slipper
or strap (they used both in those days), between his teeth
and hang on like grim death. After we had escaped to the
yard he would run out, lick our faces and seem to say, “I
told you I would not allow it. Come, let us have a romp.”</p>
        <p>There were fruit trees in our garden; peaches,
<pb id="aleck24" n="24"/>
apricots, pomegranate and figs. We loved the figs most, of
which there were several varieties. Our especial pride was
the large black fig tree. There were six of us, three girls and
three boys. Four of us were white and two were Negroes.
Did we quarrel and fight? No indeed! Our little
misunderstandings were settled long before we came to blows. 
There was more of the spirit as well as the letter of the 
little lines:
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“Let dogs delight</l><l>To bark and bite,”</l></lg></q> 
than seems generally the case now. Would there 
was more of that spirit abroad in the land today 
then would we hear less of Negro problems, 
deportations, and the like.</p>
        <p>Every morning in season would find us at our favorite
fig tree. The, boys would climb into its branches while the
girls stood below with extended aprons to catch the fruit
as we dropped them. Some times there came a voice from
above in complaining tones—“Now Jennie! I see you
eating.” “Oh,” would be the reply, “That one was all
mashed up.” “All right, now don't eat till we come down.”</p>
        <pb id="aleck25" n="25"/>
        <p>Then when we descended we took large green fig-leaves, 
placed them in a basket, laid the most perfect
fruit thereon, and one of us would run to the
house with it. . . . “Don't eat till I come back.”
“We won't.” . . . When the messenger returned
we went to our favorite nook in the garden and
after dispatching about a dozen figs apiece we
rushed to our breakfast with appetites as unappeased 
as if we had fasted for a week—And then to
school, “But not the Negroes” you say? Yes indeed!
The Negroes too.</p>
        <p>The four white children that formed a part of this little
band did not live at our house. They were niece and
nephew of our good ladies and lived a short distance from
us. They came regularly every morning and afternoon,
except Sunday, to “play in our yard.” They attended a
private school, while Jennie and myself, the two Negroes,
were taught at home by their aunts for two or three hours
each day. One of these kind ladies, usually Miss S——, strove
with our obtuseness. We had only one book each, but it
was a great book. I thought so then and I think so now.
From it, like all great men, we first
<pb id="aleck26" n="26"/>
learned our A B C's, then came A-b-âb B-a, ba and so on
to such hard words as ac-com-mo-da-tion, com-pen-sa-tion
and the like. From this wonderful book we learned to read,
write, and cipher, too. We also got an idea of grammar, of
weights and measures, etc. We had slates, for those useful
articles had not yet gone out of fashion.</p>
        <p>There were pictures in our book illustrating fables that
taught good moral lessons, such as that of the man who
prayed to Hercules to take his wagon out of the mire; of the
two men who stole a piece of meat; of the lazy maids and of
the kindhearted man who took a half frozen serpent into his
house. This book was called, “Thomas Dilworth's,” and
many a slave was severely punished for being found with a
copy of it in his hands. When one had succeeded in
mastering the contents of this book (which they frequently
did), he was considered a prodigy of learning by his fellows.
I do not know whether Mr. Dilworth has ever had a
monument erected to his memory, but if ever a man deserved
one it is he.</p>
        <p>This was a Christian household. The Sabbath
<pb id="aleck27" n="27"/>
was strictly observed. Duties were reduced to the barest
necessities, and all attended church. There was no cooking.
Cold meats, tea and bread served to satisfy our hunger on
the Lord's Day. The ladies were Congregationalists and
attended the “Circular Church.” The servants were left to
their own choice in religious matters and were divided in
their religious opinions. My grandmother was a Methodist
and attended “Old Cumberland.” It required something very
serious to prevent the dear old lady going to prayer meeting
on Sunday mornings. These meetings were held at an early
hour, but I always went with her. Each one entered the
sacred place in solemn silence. When the moment arrived
some leader would raise one of those grand
old hymns such as—
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“Early my God without delay</l><l>I haste to seek thy face.” </l></lg></q>
for, they sorely felt the need of Him who
<pb id="aleck28" n="28"/>
“Tempereth the wind to the shorn lamb!” Then at the close they
sang—
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“My friends I bid you all farewell </l><l>I leave you in God's care </l><l>And if I never more see you, </l><l>Go on, I'll meet you there.”</l></lg></q>
It not only had reference to the final dissolution, but also
to the uncertain temporal condition under which they lived,
for, in many instances before the next prayer meeting they
were sold, to serve new masters in distant parts. Often
without having time to say good-bye to relatives or friends.</p>
        <p>When meeting was over they filed out quietly. No
buzz of voices was heard until they reached the sidewalk.
Then, after a hearty handshake and a word of cheer and
hope, they hastened to their duties; many to serve hard
and impatient masters. 'Twere well for these that they had
been fortified by those few moments of prayer and meditation.</p>
        <p>The people showed commendable zeal in attending these
meetings. In those early Sunday mornings men and women
might have been seen standing within their gates. They
appeared to be listening
<pb id="aleck29" n="29"/>
intently, as if to catch some sound (for they must not be
found on the streets after “drum beat” at night or before
that hour in the morning). At the first tap they hastened out
to their respective places of worship, there to lift up their
hearts and voices in prayer and supplication to God.</p>
        <p>My mother's people too, were of the “St. Clair” type. On
Sundays after Sabbath School I was permitted to visit my
mother at their home. They were Mrs. Dane, a widow, and
three grown children—a daughter and two sons. The
daughter was married. The sons, Thomas and Edward were
unmarried. I always looked forward to these visits with
pleasure as I was sure to be regaled with lumps of sugar and
pieces of money, by the old lady and the other members of
the family. Besides, Mr. Edward (who was a lover of fine
horses, and of whom I shall have something more to say
later), would treat me to a horseback ride around the large
lot.</p>
        <p>There is nothing good to be said of American slavery. I
know it is sometimes customary to speak of its bright and
its dark sides. I am not prepared to admit that it had any
bright sides, unless it was
<pb id="aleck30" n="30"/>
the Emancipation Proclamation issued by President Abraham
Lincoln . . . There was often a strong manifestation of
sympathy, however. A sad incident which occurred in the
Dane family when I was about eight years old may serve to
illustrate this:—It was usual in those days for each member
of a family to have his or her own personal attendant. Mr.
Thomas Dane, a kind-hearted gentleman of studious habits
and quiet demeanor, had as his servant, a woman called
Beck. He did not take breakfast with the family. It was his
custom to take his morning meal in his own apartment being
waited on by her. Like all the good slaveholders the Danes
did not ruthlessly sell their slaves. I do not know how it
came about that two of Aunt Beck's children had been sold.
She had one remaining child at this time. He was a bright
fellow of about sixteen years of age. He was well-liked by all
on account of his cheerful disposition. I cannot tell the
cause of it, but the boy George was sold away from his
mother as had been his brother and sister. This was a heavy
blow to her. One morning, shortly after the sale of George,
Mr. Dane came down to
<pb id="aleck31" n="31"/>
breakfast. Noticing the dejected appearance of his servant,
and no doubt, discerning the cause he ventured some
pleasant remark, but Aunt Beck's heart was heavy. 
At last, no longer able to suppress her great
grief she began to weep. “My last chile gone now, Mas'
Thomas,” she said.</p>
        <p>“I know it Beck,” he answered, placing his hand to his
head, “But, my God! I could not help it.”</p>
        <p>He rose from the table and paced the floor. The woman
became alarmed at the agitation of her master, and forgetting
her sorrow for the moment, said, “I know you couldn't help
it Mas' Thomas. Sit down and eat your breakfast.”</p>
        <p>But, no breakfast for him that morning. Presently he went
up to his room. Soon he returned having arranged his toilet
with more than usual care. He stepped out into the yard,
entered an outer building—in a moment a pistol shot was
heard! They rushed to the step, but his life blood was
ebbing away. He never spoke again. The grief of the woman
was more than he could stand.</p>
        <p>I visited the place a few years ago. There were different
people there. They knew naught of that
<pb id="aleck32" n="32"/>
sad tragedy, nor did they know that Petigrue, Rutledge,
Horry, Pringle and Lowndes were once regular visitors here.
The old house and its surroundings are very much as they
were fifty years ago. The chimes of St. Michael can still be
distinctly heard and the hands on the dial may still be seen
from the house.</p>
        <p>It is quite different at the place where I was born. There is
not a vestige of the old house to be seen, for a great fire
since that time, swept over this district and destroyed it and
nearly every nearby dwelling house. In my childhood we had
as near neighbors Pinckney, Legare, and Prescott. There is
nothing about the locality now to show that here was once
the abode of aristocracy and wealth, for, in no instance have
the old families rebuilt their homes here. Very near our house
stood a large and quaint old dwelling built before the
Revolution. The front door was reached by high flights of
steps. I always stood in awe of that house; partly because of
the high wall that surrounded it, and partly because once a
member of the tribe of “Weary Willies,” chanced to pass
that way, He sat down on those
<pb id="aleck33" n="33"/>
steps to eat a loaf of bread that had been given him.
Whether from hunger or from some other cause, (I never
knew), he died there with the bread in his hand. As a result,
“Go die on Blank's steps” became a phrase of the day. The
wall that surrounded that old place was high—higher than
any wall appears to me now. It was ornamented on top
with glass bottles—broken bottles. The man who
broke them seemed to have had murder in his heart. He did
not follow any particular line in breaking them, nor did he
seem to strive at color effect. There were white, black and
brown bottles all broken in a way that was calculated to
inflict mortal injury on any who attempted to climb into the
inclosure.</p>
        <p>But the old house and its high wall too have disappeared. 
Cotton yards and ware-houses now occupy the site of 
many an old mansion. Houses have been built
on some of the lots, but they are far less pretentious than
their predecessors, and are occupied by different people.
For—
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“Other men our fields will till</l><l>And other men our places fill</l><l>A hundred years to come.”</l></lg></q></p>
        <pb id="aleck34" n="34"/>
        <p>There were many walls like the one I alluded to in the
quaint old city, but they have nearly all disappeared. 
All the midnight prowler has to do now is to step 
lightly over artistically trimmed hedges and meander 
through beautifully laid out walks to the rear of 
the premises to where the feathery tribe reposes in 
ornamental structures. But if the glass bottles and 
high walls are no more, the dim flickering street-lamps' 
have also been replaced by the brilliant electric light, 
thus enabling the watchful owner to place his “Mustard seed”
the more accurately where they would do the most good.
Therefore, . . . The “Knight of the feather” may well sigh for
the good old “lamp oil” times.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="aleck35" n="35"/>
        <head>CHAPTER III</head>
        <head>THE FICKLE MAIDEN</head>
        <epigraph>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>
              <hi rend="italics">"We will ring the chorus</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
              <hi rend="italics">From Atlanta to the sea."</hi>
            </l>
          </lg>
        </epigraph>
        <p>MY mother and her children fell to the lot of Edward
Dane, brother of Thomas. This young gentleman was of a
gay disposition; fond of horses and the sports of the day.
Like his brother he was kind and generous. He taught me to
ride, and when I could sit my horse well “bare-back” he had
a saddle made for me at the then famous “McKinzie's”
saddlery, sign of the “White Horse at the corner of Church
and Chalmers street. (Gentlemen had their saddles made to
order in those days). I would often accompany him “up the
road” on horseback to the Clubhouse, there to exhibit my
youthful feats of horsemanship, for the divertissement of
Mr. Dane and his friends. My horse, Agile and myself were
the best of friends. He never hesitated at a hurdle
<pb id="aleck36" n="36"/>
and we never had a mishap. Possibly Mr. Dane had
“views”, concerning me for he owned several fast horses,
but before I was old enough to be of practical service,
“Sherman came marching through Georgia.”</p>
        <p>Here I shall have to admit that I was a “Sherman
Cutloose” (this was a term applied in derision by
Some of the Negroes who were <hi rend="italics">free before</hi> the war,—
To those who were <hi rend="italics">freed by</hi> the war). I am
Persuaded however that all the Negroes in the slave belt,
And some of the white men too, were “Cutloose” by
General Sherman. But let bygones be bygones.
“We are brothers all, at least we would be if it
were not for the demagogues and the Apostles of
hate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Edward Dane was an ardent supporter of the
“Code.” He was an authority on such matters and
could arrange a meeting with all the nice attention
to details that characterized gentlemen of the “Old
School” in South Carolina. His deliberation in such
Matters would have been a keen disappointment to
“Mr. Winkle” as there was never was any danger of the 
police or anyone else interfering when he had matters
in hand. The police, however, never interfered
<pb id="aleck37" n="37"/>
with gentlemen of the “old school” in the “Palmetto” state.
The following story is told of a well-known gentleman of a
past generation:—He was a man of splendid physique and
dignified carriage. One morning he entered the Old
Charleston Market with a lit cigar between his lips. Soon he
was accosted by a policeman, a new recruit from the
Emerald Isle. “It be aginst the law to be <sic>afther schmokin</sic> in
the Market, <sic>Sor,</sic>” he said. “The law,” said Mr.——. “I am the
law. When you see me you see the law. The law was made 
for poor white men and Negroes.” And he strode on leaving
that son of Erin a wiser, if not a better man.</p>
        <p>The Danes were society people. In their well-appointed
home they kept many servants, Mrs. Dane and her daughter
Mrs. Turner were both kind ladies. The old lady had a way
of personally looking into matters about the establishment
that secured for her a pet name from the servants.
Whenever she started on her tour of inspection word would
be passed along, “de old Jay comin'. This would send
every one to their post of duty. Of course the servants were
ignorant of the fact that
<pb id="aleck38" n="38"/>
Mrs. Dane knew anything about the re-christening
she had secured at their hands. Judge of their surprise
therefore, then that lady presented herself 
before them and announced, “Yes, here comes the
‘Old Jay!’”</p>
        <p>They were all assembled in the kitchen for a little
chat, and their attitudes and the expressions of
bewilderment on their faces would have delighted the
heart of an artist. The cook was just about to 
emphasize a remark he had made by bringing a large
spoon which he held above his head down on the 
dresser, when the sudden appearance of the lady
and her words, seemed to arrest the descent. There
he stood in open-mouthed amazement. Mrs. Dane
surveyed the scene for a moment, then quietly
withdrew, a smile of amusement on her face. This
incident was long remembered by  those present, but
any reference to it in his presence was promptly
frowned down by the Cook, who felt keenly the
ludicrousness of the figure he cut with the uplifted
spoon. It was a much as their dinner was worth
for any one of them even to raise a spoon above their
heads.</p>
        <pb id="aleck39" n="39"/>
        <p>Uncle Renty, the cook, particularly disliked these
periodical intrusions in his domain. The altogether
unnecessary clatter and clashing of pans and kettles 
whenever the lady made her appearance was 
only his method of expressing his resentment. This, 
Mrs. Dane well understood, and never prolonged her 
stay in the kitchen, for the old man's ability as an 
artist in his profession was recognized and appreciated. 
It was said that when the elder Mr. Dane was alive, 
he frequently began and ended his dinner with one of 
Uncle Renty's soups. They were simply marvelous, especially 
his turtle, calf's head and okra soups. How he made 
them no one knew, nor would they have been any wiser 
if he had been questioned on the subject. He had
several dishes of his own invention to which he had given
original names. The other servants had great respect for
him; the old, because of his skill, and the young, because of
his readiness with the rolling pin. He had obtained the name
of “Old Scarlet” from his follow-servants. But those who
ventured to call him so always took pains to get out of
reach. This is how he got the name:—</p>
        <pb id="aleck40" n="40"/>
        <p>In those days personal application for work were
frequently made from door to door by the “newly arrived.”
One day an Irish woman applied to Mrs. Dane. She did not
need her particularly, but thought she might give the
woman work for a day or two as assistant to Uncle Renty,
for they were to have a large dinner party:—“Wait 
a moment,” she said. The lady knew the old man well 
enough to know that diplomacy was required. Going to the
kitchen she <sic corr="complemented">complimented</sic> him on the neat appearance of
things. “You are all in readiness for the dinner I see.”</p>
        <p>“Yes ma'am.” (Now the old man had already been
apprised of the purport of her visit. He was fully prepared.
He was by no means color blind, but was not well posted
in the nomenclature of colors.)</p>
        <p>“And do you know daddy Renty,” continued Mrs.
Dane, “I have thought that you might need some
additional help in the kitchen for a day or so.”</p>
        <p>“Everything was all right las time, ain't ee ma'am?”</p>
        <pb id="aleck41" n="41"/>
        <p>“Oh yes, certainly. Everything was just splendid,” 
she replied, “But a white woman has applied to me for work and
I thought—.”</p>
        <p>“Mis Charlotte,” interrupted Renty, “I don't <sic>car</sic> if she
white as scarlet, ma'am, I doan want um in my kitchen.”
Argument was useless and so a job had to be found for
Bridget in the laundry.</p>
        <p>But all of this was before the untimely death of Mr.
Thomas Dane, to which I referred in the preceding chapter.
That sad event seemed to have been the beginning of
trouble for the Dane family. Indeed things were becoming
serious for all. The probability of war between the states
was manifested more and more daily. There was a growing
feeling of unrest everywhere, and it was soon known that
this calamity would not be averted.</p>
        <p>The very commencement of the war seemed to have
brought disaster to the financial prosperity of many, and
the Danes were among the earliest to feel its effects. Some
of the servants were sent out to work and so it happened
that my mother went as cook for a wealthy family in the
city. They were very kind people. Mrs. Bale was a widow
with two
<pb id="aleck42" n="42"/>
children. They were both married. Mrs. Ward, the daughter,
and her husband lived with her mother. The son, Tom Bale
had establishments of his own.</p>
        <p>It was hard for me to leave our dear old home at the
Misses Jayne's, my father's people, for there was my good
old grandmother, the kind ladies, my playmates and faithful
old Watch. But the distance was too far for my mother to
walk back and forth, (there were no street cars in those
days), so we had to make our home at Mrs. Bale's house. I
found some consolation however, in our new home.
Mrs. Ward had two boys, and they and I soon 
became good friends. Besides, there were horses there, and
Uncle Ben, the coachman allowed me to
Ride them to water. There were children living next
door too, with whom I became acquainted, and this led to 
a romantic incident in my life years afterward. When 
“the Union had come in,” I married one of the little 
girls who lived next door, although I had to
go all the way to New York to find her.</p>
        <p>Our stay at Mrs. Bale's was very pleasant, circumstances
being considered. It was here, however
<pb id="aleck43" n="43"/>
that I witnessed the first instance of cruelty or
harshness of an owner to his slave that ever came
under my personal observation. Of this I shall have
more to say. I missed my weekly visits to the Danes
too, for besides the pennies, lumps of sugar and
horseback rides, I had many friends there also. Then
there was Cora, the daughter of one of the servants, 
I am still inclined to believe that she was the
most beautiful girl I have ever seen. She was 
endowed with an olive complexion, large black dreamy
eyes, raven hair, pearly white teeth and a bewitching 
smile. Her voice was one of the most unusual
voices I have ever heard. Cora used to kiss me
and call me her little sweetheart, (for though you
would not believe it now, then I was a bright-looking
little two-headed chap, and got many a kiss from
the “big girls” in the neighborhood, because they
said I was so cute.) But that was years and years
ago. Cora promised to “Wait for me.” Of course
I believed her. She was eighteen and I was about
nine years old, yet I thought that somewhere in the
race of life I would overtake her and she would be
mine. It never occurred to me that when I had
<pb id="aleck44" n="44"/>
reached eighteen she would be twenty-seven, and the
disparity in our ages would be the same. Years afterward I
met her. She was married and had several children, while I
was just entering into young manhood. How fickle some
girls are, eh?</p>
        <p>There was a large garden with fig trees and flowers in it
at Mrs. Bale's house, but the figs were not as sweet nor
were the flowers half as beautiful as those at my old home.
There were two dogs not near so clever as our Watch, and
the children—well, they had never lived at a home like our
old place on Guignard Street. In fact, there never was
another home like that, but “Grief sits light on youthful
hearts.” All my regrets were greatly modified by the
prospects of a visit to the country. Such a trip always
seems alluring to a city boy. Indeed the country seems to
hold out allurements to everyone except those who live
there. Mr. Ward owned a plantation to which the family
went every winter, and when it became known to me that
we were soon to go there, I was all impatience. I plied
Uncle Ben with a thousand questions as to how far away it
was, what kind of a place, what was to be seen,
<pb id="aleck45" n="45"/>
were there any snakes, did they bite, was there any wild
horse running about in the woods, did he think I might catch
one? Etc., etc. Now Uncle Ben was a philosopher. He was
not given over much to talking. No one but myself would have
dared to ask him so many questions. He had taken a fancy
to me. Everyone said it was a wonder. He had no children of
his own, besides he was inclined to be somewhat of a
misanthropist. I would sometime have to wait indefinitely
for an answer to a very simple question. However, by the
exercise of patience and discretion I finally got all the
information I desired, or thought I did, which amounted to
the same thing.</p>
        <p>Uncle Ben was epigrammatic as well as philosophical. 
one night after a very trying day he went to
prayer meeting. He was feeling rather blue, and
did not intend to take an active part in the exercises. Of
course the conductor of the meeting knew nothing of the
old man's frame of mind. “Will brudder Ben jine us in
prayer?” he asked, but there was no response. “I mean brudder
Ben Bale,” he said, fearing there might be some
misunderstanding. Being thus importuned the old man 
knelt down and delivered himself as follows:—
“A ha'd bone to caw. A
<pb id="aleck46" n="46"/>
bitter pill to swoller.” Bress de Lawd. Amen.</p>
        <p>But Christmas was approaching, and Santa Claus
was gleefully expected for the good old man was a
real personage in those days—not a myth. Oh,
but you say it was wrong to deceive the children, as
it had a bad effect on them? I don't know, but it
seems to me that the children who believed in Santa
Claus in those days would at least compare favorably in their 
love of truth with those of the present
day who know, “It is only father and mother.” At
all events the country was forgotten for a while. It
was sometime after holidays that we left for the
plantation. There was not a gayer boy than myself when 
we boarded the train. (This was in the year 1860).</p>
        <p>When we arrived at the station there were three
teams awaiting us; one for the family, one for the
servants, and another for the baggage. Uncle Ben
was there, having brought the horses up by road a
few days before. I rode on the baggage wagon. As
there were only the driver and myself on it I thought
I could ply the former for information without 
being requested to “Hold my tongue,” an operation
<pb id="aleck47" n="47"/>
that I had always found difficult. My companion I
found was I well grown boy whose name was Missouri. 
Why they gave him that name I do not
know. Perhaps it was in honor of the “Missouri
Compromise.” He said his name was the same as
that of a great country miles and miles away, that
he was called “Zury” for short, that his principal
work on the plantation was plowing, and that his
mule, Jack, was the best plow animal on the place.
He also informed me that there were a large number
of children on the plantation whose work was to
play, and to keep the rice birds out of the fields. 
I suppose he was thoroughly dry by the time we got
To “Pine Top,” but he was a good-natured follow.
We became firm friends. I always rode his mule
from the field to the barn. Zury is now living in
Charleston, where he is a successful mechanic known
as Mr. Ladson.</p>
        <p>Anyone visiting the old time plantation must
have been impressed by the boundless hospitality of
the people. Everybody came to see us. They
brought chickens, eggs, potatoes, pumpkins, plums
and things numerous to mention. I soon
<pb id="aleck48" n="48"/>
found many play fellows. My especial chums were Joe and
Hector, sons of the plantation driver. The boys were
somewhat older than myself. They were skilled in
woodcraft, and taught me bow to make bird traps and soon
had me out hunting. One morning early, we started out,
taking their dog, Spot along. When we reached the woods
the dog ran ahead briskly, barking as he went. Shortly he
began to bark furiously. “Spot, tree,” said Joe, and we
hastened on. When we got to the dog he was standing by
a tall stump, still barking. “Got er rabbit,” said Hector.</p>
        <p>“Where?” I inquired.</p>
        <p>“En de holler,” he replied, and thrusting his arm into it
he drew out the poor trembling creature by his hind legs.</p>
        <p>“Set him down!” I cried.</p>
        <p>“Oh no,” said he, “Ee might git 'way.”</p>
        <p>This was just what I wanted, for I pitied the little animal,
but the boys were hunters. They were not going to risk
losing their game, so they killed the frightened thing
without further ceremony, and put him in their bag. We got
three rabbits that morning. I did not enjoy the sport, nor
did I partake of the rabbit stew they had for dinner.
<pb id="aleck49" n="49"/>
I did enjoy the night hunts however, for coon and
possum were our quarry. I went with some of the young
men. While the harmless little rabbit will not even defend
himself when attacked, the possum is shy and crafty and the
coon will fight. One night the dogs tree'd a coon. Now the
wily animal usually selects a tree from which he can reach
another, but this coon did not have time to “pick and
choose.” There was no other tree within jumping distance,
so he went out on a limb as far away from the body of the
tree as possible. And there he sat. As it was a large tree, it
was decided that instead of cutting it down, someone
should go up and shake the game off of it. Sandy, one of the
party, readily volunteered to do so. Reaching the limb on
which the coon was “roosting,” he went on it so as to give
it a vigorous shaking. The limb broke and down came both
man and coon. The coon was dispatched while some of the
men went to the assistance of Sandy. We thought he was
seriously injured. He was stunned for a moment, but as
they raised him up he asked, “Did we git um, boys?” The fall
of more than twenty feet was broken by the branches
beneath him, and thus he soon was all right again.</p>
        <p>These hunts were great, but they were nothing compared
to the feasts that followed. These were
<pb id="aleck50" n="50"/>
never held on the same night as the hunt, but on the one
following. I never took kindly to either the coon or the
possum. The former is usually too fat, and the habits of the
other do not appeal to me. But the stories told at these
feasts! They would make the fortune of a writer if he could
reproduce them. They simply cannot be reproduced, that is
all. To get the real, genuine, simon pure article one must be
on the ground. And perhaps you think that you have heard
good, sound, hearty unadulterated laughter. Well, may be.</p>
        <p>You may disfranchise the Negro, you may oppress him,
you may deport him, but unless you destroy the
disposition to laugh in his nature you can do him no
permanent injury. All unconscious to himself, perhaps. It
is not solely the meaningless expression of “vacant mind,”
nor is it simply a ray—It is the beaming light of 
hope—of faith. God has blessed him thus. He sees 
light where others see only the blackness of night<corr sic="no punctuation">.</corr></p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="aleck51" n="51"/>
        <head>CHAPTER IV</head>
        <head>THE LOVER</head>
        <epigraph>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">“The tide of true love never did run smooth.”</hi>
          </p>
        </epigraph>
        <p>PINE TOP, Mr. Ward's country seat, was a beautiful
plantation about eighteen or twenty miles from Charleston.
The house, an old colonial mansion, stood on elevated
ground, well back from the main road, and commanded a
fine view of the surrounding country. From the main road
the house was reached through a wide avenue, lined on
either side by giant live oaks, while immediately in front of
the house was a large lawn circled by a wide driveway.</p>
        <p>From the front door of the house the barns, stables, 
gin-house, corn mill and Negro quarters, presented the
appearance of a thriving little village. The quarters were
regularly laid out in streets, and the cabins were all 
whitewashed. I once read in a newspaper, a letter from a Northern
<pb id="aleck52" n="52"/>
man who visited the South immediately after the
war. He took a rather unfavorable view of the
prospects of the Negro, for he said, “There was a
lamentable absence of flowers about their cabins.”
I suppose this “Oscar Wilde” thought the conditions
under which the people lived were well
calculated to foster love of the beautiful. The poor
fellow could not have visited Pine Top however, and
many other places I could name, or he would have
been delighted to see the well-kept little flower beds
near many of the cabins. And no doubt, he would
have said they were just “too, too” for words. He
might even have been tempted to enter some of those
cabins by their neat and tidy appearances which
could be seen through the open doors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ward was what was called a “good master.”
His people were well-fed, well-housed and not
over-worked. There were certain inflexible rules
however, governing his plantation of which he allowed
not the slightest infraction, for he had his place for
the Negro. Of course the Negro could not stand
erect in it, but, the Negro had no right to stand 
<pb id="aleck53" n="53"/>
erect. <hi rend="italics">His</hi> place for the Negro was in subjection
and servitude to the white man. That is, to Mr.
Ward and his class, for while he maintained that the
supremacy of all white men over the Negro was
indisputable, and must be recognized, still there was
a class of white men that he would have prevented
from ever becoming slaveholders.</p>
        <p>While I repudiate Mr. Ward's views I am bound
to believe that there is something in blood. In those
parts of the South where aristocratic influence is
dominant, opposition to the advancement and
progress of the Negro is less than where the
contrary is true. Eliminating the Negro altogether,
in some of the southern states the “bottom rail” has
gotten on top with a vengeance, and where such is
the case, it is very bad for the “enclosure.” </p>
        <p>One evening Mr. Ward sat in his library before
a blazing wood fire. He was the picture of contentment;
and why should he be otherwise? He had a
beautiful wife, two fine boys, hundreds of acres of
land and numerous slaves to work them. Furthermore,
he had just dined on wild duck. Now I would
not tax the credulity of the reader by an exact
<pb id="aleck54" n="54"/>
statement as to how long those ducks had been allowed to
hang up after being shot before they were considered
“ripe,” but, they had reached a stage that would hardly
have been appreciated by a man of less “refined” taste than
his, for Mr. Ward was a lover of “high game.” The aroma
that arose from those “birds” during their preparation for
the table would not have tempted the appetite of an
ordinary man, even if he were very hungry.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Ward had joined her husband for a little chat when
Jake, the waiting boy, entered.—(Jake was the assistant
and understudy of Uncle Sempie, the veteran butler. Uncle
Sempie always retired after dinner, leaving Jake to attend
to the later wants of his master). “Mingo, fum Mr. Hudson
place wan ter see yo, sah,” he said.</p>
        <p>“All right, let him in,” said Mr. Ward.</p>
        <p>Presently Jake returned ushering in a very young
Negro who appeared to be laboring under some 
embarrassment. As he entered he said, “Ebenin sah, 
ebenin ma'am.”</p>
        <p>“Good evening,” replied the lady and gentleman.</p>
        <pb id="aleck55" n="55"/>
        <p>“Are you Mingo from Mr. Hudson?” asked Mr. Ward.</p>
        <p>“Yees, sah.”</p>
        <p>“How are your master and mistress?”</p>
        <p>“Dey berry well, sah.”</p>
        <p>“Well, Mingo, what can I do for you?”</p>
        <p>The young fellow hesitated as if be did not know exactly
how to proceed. Both the lady and gentleman looked at him
attentively. He was becomingly attired, had a pleasant face,
and was evidently a favored servant. At last he mustered
enough courage to say, “I come sah ter ax yo p'mission ter
cum see Dolly. Dolly is the darter ob Uncle Josh and Ant
Peggy, sah,” he added.</p>
        <p>Mr. and Mrs. Ward strove hard to suppress their mirth
as they saw the poor fellow was about to collapse. “Oh,”
said the lady smiling, “So you would a-courting go, eh?”</p>
        <p>“Yees, ma'am,” recovering himself a little.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ward cleared his throat. “Well Mingo,” he asked,
“Have you got your master's consent?”</p>
        <p>“Oh yees sah.”</p>
        <pb id="aleck56" n="56"/>
        <p>“And you and Dolly understand each other?”</p>
        <p>“Yees, sah.”</p>
        <p>“Are Josh and Peggy willing to have you for a
son-in-law?”</p>
        <p>“Oh yees, sah, I don ax dem.”</p>
        <p>“I suppose you behave yourself. I am very
particular concerning this matter.”</p>
        <p>“I know dat, sah. Mas Jeem kin tell yo bout me,
sah.”</p>
        <p>“Well, I guess it is all right. Of course I shall
inquire about you. Have you got your ticket?”</p>
        <p>Here Mingo produced the desired article. Mr.
Ward read it, his brows contracting a little. “This
is all right,” he said, returning the paper, “Except
that it does not way where you are to go. Now I
never allow anyone on my place with such a ticket.
The next time you visit Dolly you must have a
different “ticket.” Ask your master to give you one
stating plainly that you are to visit my plantation.
Do you understand?”</p>
        <p>“Yes, sah.”</p>
        <p>“Well, Mingo, I wish you good luck!” said Mrs. Ward.</p>
        <pb id="aleck57" n="57"/>
        <p>“Tankee ma'am, tankee sah,” and he bowed himself off.</p>
        <p>The “ticket” referred to was simply a permit showing that
the slave had his or her master's consent to be absent from
home. In some instances their destination was mentioned; in
others it merely stated that “A— has my permission to be
absent on such a date, or between given dates.” Mr. Ward
never refused his people “leave of absence,” but in every
case their destination was clearly set forth. It would not be
safe for them to be found “off the coast.”</p>
        <p>Now I would not insinuate that Mingo was a fickle lover.
It is just possible that he wished to visit some of the other
girls in the neighborhood simply for the purpose of
convincing himself by actual comparison of the superior
charms of his own Dolly. His was a monthly “ticket,” and
under these circumstances we must excuse him for not
wishing to have it changed. In fact he determined not to do
so. He did not even acquaint Dolly with Mr. Ward's
instruction. Possibly he feared that she might have
<pb id="aleck58" n="58"/>
agreed with that gentlemen—from different motives of
course.</p>
        <p>It was the custom of the owner of “Pine Top” during his
stay on the plantation to visit the “Quarters,” ostensibly to
see how his people were getting on, and incidentally, to
note that things were as they should be on the place.
Mingo was aware of this so he thought that on his future
visits to his sweetheart all he had to do was “to lay low”
until Mr. Ward had made his rounds. In this he was
successful for a time but—
<q type="quote" direct="unspecified">“The best laid plans of mice and men, gang aft
agley.”</q>
Besides, young love is ever impatient.</p>
        <p>One night he took his stand in his usual place of
concealment. It had been raining and the weather was
decidedly cold. He had waited long after the usual time for
the gentleman's visits. “Spec de old feller ain't comin out
tonight,” he said to himself.</p>
        <p>Mingo did not know Mr. Ward. The people on Pine
Top expected their master at any hour, and were not
surprised to have him present himself at their doors when
<hi rend="italics">he</hi> thought they were not looking
<pb id="aleck59" n="59"/>
for him. He would sometimes even partake of roast possum
or coon. Unaware of these habits Mingo hastened to meet
the warm welcome that awaited him at Dolly's cabin. He was
destined to receive a warmer welcome than the one he
anticipated.</p>
        <p>Uncle Josh and Aunt Peggy sat by the fire. <hi rend="italics">Perhaps</hi> they
were asleep. Dolly and Mingo were sitting at a small table as
far away from the old folks as they possibly could get. “I
bin ober to Cedar Hill las nite,” he began, “An I see'd the
new gal dey got. I tink she is——.”</p>
        <p>“I see'd her,” interrupted Dolly, “An I tink she's just
horred.”</p>
        <p>And Mingo deeming discretion the better part of valor
said, “I tink so too.”</p>
        <p>Just then there was a loud rap on the door and Mr. Ward
entered! Sometimes the very means we use to conceal our
fears serve but to make them plain. The moment Mingo
sighted Mr. Ward he became alarmed, but he must appear
collected.</p>
        <p>“Ebenin sah. Cole nite, sah. How is Missus and de
chillun?”</p>
        <p>Immediately Mr. Ward knew “the lay of the
<pb id="aleck60" n="60"/>
land.” “Oh they are all well. How are all at Laurel Grove?”
he asked smoothly.</p>
        <p>“Berry well, sah, all berry well.”</p>
        <p>Mr. Ward turned to speak to the old people, taking good
care to place himself between Mingo and the door. When
he started to leave the house he seemed to remember
something. “Oh, by the way Mingo, did you have your
ticket changed?”</p>
        <p>“Mas Jeems, he bin gon ter town, sah, an Miss Liza say
wait til he cum back.”</p>
        <p>“Ah, then you had it changed when he came back, did
you?” Mr. Ward spoke very deliberately.</p>
        <p>“When he git back I so busy I forgot, but I hab um fix
sho fore I cum er gen, sah.”</p>
        <p>It was a cool night, but there were signs of perspiration
on Mingo's face as he spoke. “I am afraid to trust your
memory, Mingo,” he said. Then he stepped to the door
placing the silver mounted cow's horn which he always
carried about the plantation, to his lips, blowing a loud
blast.</p>
        <pb id="aleck61" n="61"/>
        <div2 type="subchapter">
          <head>THE DRIVER</head>
          <p>Uncle Joe, as he was called by the Negroes, and,
Daddy Joe as he was called by the white folks, was
Mr. Ward's driver. He was a plantation Negro,
the son of a plantation Negro, but he would not
have answered to any of the descriptions usually
given to the “plantation Negro.” He did not have
a receding forehead, a protruding jaw, nor bandy
legs. In fact, he bore a striking resemblance to a
well formed man. He had a thoughtful expression,
and although he was rarely seen to smile, he had a 
pleasant countenance. He was not harsh with those
over whom he had been placed. “Boy, doan lemme
put me han on yo,” was sufficient to bring the most
refractory into line, and this was nor a mere figure
of speech, for when his hand did drop on the shoulder
of some erring culprit it came down with a force;
the effects of which was felt for a long time after,
for he was a man of unusual strength.</p>
          <p>But Uncle Joe could laugh, and when he was
Engaged in relating some particularly ludicrous 
Adventure of Brer Rabbit and Brer Wolf, to his two boys
Joe and Hector, at night when the day's work was
<pb id="aleck62" n="62"/>
done, his sonorous voice could be heard throughout
the Quarters.</p>
          <p>This night the old man had removed the tension
from the boys' minds by completing a Jack O' Lantern
story begun on the night before. The story was
as follows:</p>
          <p>“Wonce der was er man. He lib on won plantation
en his wife an chillun dey lib on er noder, seben
mile off. Von nite de man tink he go see dem, so he
ketch a fat 'possum. He put de possum en some oder
tings een er bag en start. Wen he git good way on
de road he see er brite light. (Dem Jack O' Lantern
always lookin out fur trabblers). De lite blin
de man an he los de road. Fus ting he kno he fine
heself een a swamp. Den de Jack O' Lantern laf en
say, “Now I hab dar bag.” De lite gon out quick en
de man cudent see he han befo he face.”</p>
          <p>Here the old man pleaded weariness and sent the
boys to bed, promising to finish the story the next
night, for though Uncle Joe had never written a 
continued story he understood the art of creating a
demand for the next number. All the following day
the boys talked about the probable fate of the luckless
<pb id="aleck63" n="63"/>
traveler. “I bet,” said Joe, “Dat Jack Lantin
tak de man bag, den kill um.”</p>
          <p>“He doan hab to kill um he self. All he hab ter
do es to tak way he bag en lebe um een de dak, en
sum ob dem bad wile varmint wat be een de swomp
eat um up,” answered Hector.</p>
          <p>But to their great relief their father had skillfully
extricated the poor fellow from his perilous
position, bag and all, with no greater misfortune
than the loss of his hat which was brushed off by the
low hanging branches. His shoes came off in the
soft mud of the place. These he did not stop to hunt
for as he was glad to get out alive. The boys, thus
satisfied went willingly to bed, while Uncle Joe
settled himself for a quick no by the fire. Aunt Binah,
his wife, busied herself cleaning up supper dishes.
As she went about her work she hummed an old
Plantation hymn; the humming grew louder as she
Continued, and soon she began to sing—“I run
From Pharo, lem me go.”</p>
          <p>This seemed to arouse her husband, for he
Commenced to beat time with his foot. When she
<pb id="aleck64" n="64"/>
reached the chorus he joined in and their strong voices
blended harmoniously.</p>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>“De hebben bells er ringin, I kno de road </l>
            <l>De hebben bells er ringin, I kno de road </l>
            <l>De hebben bells er ringin, I kno de road, </l>
            <l>King Jesus sittin by de watah side.”</l>
          </lg>
          <p>“Hush,” said Aunt Binah, “Tink I yer de hon.” They
both listened attentively. Yes, there was another blast.
“Wonder wha dat debble wan wid me now,” said Uncle
Joe. He slipped on his shoes, got his hat and coat,
(meanwhile his wife had lighted his lantern), and hurried
out. As he stepped outside a third blast assailed his ears;
this to direct him, as Mr. Ward had seen the light.</p>
          <p>“Um soun like he ober to Josh house. Wonder wha da
him now?” he said to himself, hastening along.</p>
          <p>“Ah Joe,” said Mr. Ward as the driver reached Josh's
cabin, “Mingo has forgotten my orders. Take him over to
the barn and give him twenty lashes.”</p>
          <p>“Cum on boy,” said Uncle Joe, not unkindly, yet in a
tone that indicated there was to be no hanging
<pb id="aleck65" n="65"/>
back. Under these circumstances Mingo must be
excused for not having lingered to say “Good
night.” In fact, “his heart was too full for 
utterance.” And so the line of march was taken up 
in silence, Uncle Joe leading with his lantern, Mingo
next, Mr. Ward bringing up the rear. When the
humiliating performance was over, the party broke
up. Mr. Ward returned to the house whistling
softly:—
<q type="quote" direct="unspecified">“From Greenland's icy mountains.”</q>
Uncle Joe, wending his way back to his cabin, sang 
in a low voice, “There's rest for the weary.”</p>
          <p>Poor Mingo neither sang nor whistled. As he painfully
took the shortest cut for the main road he consoled 
himself with the thought that—“Faint heart never 
won fair lady.” He did not put it just in that way. 
What he really did say to himself was “Well, sum time 
Man hab ter go tru heap to git wife.”</p>
          <p>Did he win his Dolly finally? We shall see.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="aleck66" n="66"/>
        <head>CHAPTER V</head>
        <head>THE HUNTING SEASON AT PINE TOP </head>
        <epigraph>
          <p><hi rend="italics">“The Old Flag never touched the ground.”</hi><lb/>
The Color Sergeant At <sic corr="Battery">Ballery</sic> Wagener</p>
        </epigraph>
        <p>GAY hunting parties composed of friends from the city
and ladies and gentlemen from the surrounding plantations
often assembled at Pine Top. Many amusing tales were
told there of the “Stag Fright” and blunders of amateur
sportsmen on their first deer hunt. There was a Mr.
Brabham, a carpenter, who being placed at a “stand” for
the first time, and told not to let the deer pass him, waited
in breathless anxiety. Soon a magnificent buck came bounding
towards him almost within arms' reach. Throwing
<pb id="aleck67" n="67"/>
up his arms wildly, his gun held aloft, he
exclaimed, “I wish I had my hatchet!” while the
terrified animal sped on to be brought down by a more
collected hunter on the next stand.</p>
        <p>This year however, the festivities were cut short
for Mr. Ward was often called to the city as indeed
were many of the other gentlemen who were accustomed
to join the gay throng at Pine Top. It was
soon known that they were attending Mass Meetings
and Conventions. Sometimes Mr. Ward would
be absent several days. There were strange
whisperings among the Negroes. “Dat ting comin,”
they said mysteriously to each other, “Pray my brudder,
pray my sister.” I listened with wonderment,
but was taught to say nothing.</p>
        <p>Uncle August was Mrs. Ward's right hand man.
He was equally at home in the fields or in the house,
and could always be depended on in an emergency.
He was full of humor, a born mimic, and could set
those about him in gales of laughter, without seeming
to try. Mrs. Ward frequently conversed with
him when he was engaged in some task under her
directions about the house, or grounds. One day
while he was moving some pieces of furniture from
<pb id="aleck68" n="68"/>
one room to another the lady said, “Daddy August, do you
know there is going to be war?”</p>
        <p>“War! ma'am, Wey, ma'am,” Anyone who saw and heard
the old man would have been ready to affirm most
positively that this was the very first intimation he had
had of the impending conflict.</p>
        <p>His mistress certainly thought so.</p>
        <p>“Why here,” she replied.</p>
        <p>“On dis plantation, ma'am?”</p>
        <p>“Oh no, I don't mean that exactly, but you see, the
Yankees are determined to take our Negroes from us, and
we are equally determined that they shall never, never 
do so. Why Daddy August, don't we treat you all well?”</p>
        <p>“Ob cose yo does, ma'am. Wha dey bodder deyself 
bout we fer?”</p>
        <p>“That's just it; they are simply jealous to see us getting
along so well, and they want to take our Negroes and put
them at all kinds of hard work, like horses and mules. They
are sending emissaries among our Negroes, to make them dissatisfied.</p>
        <p>“Wha dem is, Miss Em'ly?” (Of course he had not the
slightest idea what an emissary was!)</p>
        <p>“Oh they are men who will try to sneak around
<pb id="aleck69" n="69"/>
and talk to the Negroes.”</p>
        <p>“Wha dey gwine say?”</p>
        <p>“Well, they will tell the Negroes that they are
their best friends, and so on, just for the purpose
of deceiving them you know.”</p>
        <p>For a second there was a twinkle in Uncle
August's eyes which Mrs. Ward did not observe.
“Mis Em'ly,” he asked with a startled expression on
his face, “Wha dem embissary look lak.”</p>
        <p>“Oh they will be in disguise, you know, but they
try to look like our own people. Why?”</p>
        <p>“Well yo kno, toder day wen I bin gon over ter
Mr. Hudsin, ma'am? When I coming back an git
mos to de big gate, I see er strange man comin' up
de road. Time as I see un I tink dem “Kidnabber”
cause you kno dey car off Mr. Hudsin Tom.”</p>
        <p>“Now Daddy August,” interrupted Mrs. Ward,
“I don't believe any kidnapper carried off that boy.
I think he just ran away.”</p>
        <p>“Wha he hab ter run away fer, Mis Em'ly? I
sho Mr. Hudsin es er good man!”</p>
        <p>The aforementioned Tom was at this very moment
on the way to freedom by means of the “Underground
<pb id="aleck70" n="70"/>
Railroad,” and this Uncle August knew very well.</p>
        <p>Enyhow I fraid dem kidnapper so I mak hase git inside de
gate. Wen he git ter de gate he call ter me “Cum yer. I wanter
tell yo somting.” </p>
        <p>I say, “Cum een, sah.”</p>
        <p>He say, “No, yo cum yer.”</p>
        <p>I say, “I see Mas Henry cummin an I ain't ga
time. (You kno Mas' Henry gon ter town dat day). 
Time as I say dat he hurry way.”</p>
        <p>“I see yo ergan,” he say. Den I say ter maself I know dat da
“kidnabber.”</p>
        <p>“Did you see him again?” asked Mrs. Ward quietly but
she did not succeed in hiding her alarm from the old man.
He knew what effect his story (and it was a great big one),
would have.</p>
        <p>“No, ma'am!” he answered, “An I doan wanter see um gan
noder.”</p>
        <p>Mrs. Ward determined to acquaint her husband with what
she had heard, as soon as possible. Therefore, when Mr.
Ward returned from the city that evening, she informed him
privately of what August had told her. He was even more
disturbed than she
<pb id="aleck71" n="71"/>
was. “And,” she added, “Daddy August is frightened 
half to death.”</p>
        <p>They both concluded that the stranger was a Yankee spy.
“It will not be good for him if I find
him prowling about here,” said Mr. Ward, “I shall question
August further about it.”</p>
        <p>He found an opportunity that evening, without
appearing to attach any importance to the incident, to
question the old man closely. However, August had
nothing to add to what he had told Mrs. Ward. He
considered it was already a sufficient “whopper.”</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ward was uneasy. He told Uncle Joe to have
two horses saddled, and they rode over to Mr. Hudson's.
He did not acquaint the driver of the object of the visit, but
that was not necessary as August and Joe had already had
a hearty laugh over the hoax. From Mr. Hudson's they went
to Mr. Benton's. To each of these gentlemen Mr. Ward
related what he had heard. Neither of them had seen or
heard of any stranger in the neighborhood. They both
promised to look out, and if such was found it would not be
their fault if he did not
<pb id="aleck72" n="72"/>
give good account of himself. But the mysterious
man was never found of course.</p>
        <p>Some days after the incident just related Mrs.
Ward was superintending some work which Uncle
August was doing in the garden; setting out plants
And the like, for it was now early spring. A team
Drove up to the house and the men proceeded to
Unload a tall pole. “Wha dey gwine do out dey, Mis
Em'ly?” asked the old man innocently.</p>
        <p>“Why they are going to set up a flagpole. You
see we are to have a government of our own so we
must have a flag of our own; the Confederate flag.
It is going to be a very pretty one, too.”</p>
        <p>“No priteer dan de old flags upstars.”</p>
        <p>“Oh yes, a great deal prettier,” but the lady was
thinking of the old flag her father and grandfather
had fought under.”</p>
        <p>The old man glanced at her. “Well,” he said, “It
hab ter be berry puty ter beat de old flag.” There
was more in his words than he meant his mistress to
understand.</p>
        <p>“Daddy August,” said Mrs. Ward, as though not
<pb id="aleck73" n="73"/>
wishing to speak any more about flags, “We will put
that right here,” (alluding to a plant the old man 
held in his hands).</p>
        <p>August did as directed, but he was not quite through
yet. Presently he said, “Mis Em'ly, wha yo gwine do wid de
old flag? Yo pa an yo granpa use ter tink er heap ob dat
one.”</p>
        <p>“Burn it up!” replied Mrs. Ward in rather a vehement tone.</p>
        <p>Uncle August knew he had said enough.</p>
        <p>It was now about the middle of April 1861. Important 
matters seemed to require Mr. Ward's attention in the 
city, and much of his time was spent there. One evening 
Mrs. Ward told Uncle Ben he must meet Mr. Ward at 
the station the following day with a pair of horses. He 
usually used a single horse and a dog cart for this purpose. 
“Sumting up,” said the old coachman to himself.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ward had not been home for near two weeks. The
Negroes on the plantation knew war was approaching,
for though they could not read the newspapers,
it is remarkable how well posted they were 
<pb id="aleck74" n="74"/>
in regard to the trend of events. They knew also
that their master's long absence was to be accounted
for in the coming conflict. His return therefore,
was anxiously awaited by them; as they hoped to
gain some information as to how matters actually
stood.</p>
        <p>The next morning Uncle Ben had his team in tip
top shape, and rigged up with his regulation 
coachman's outfit, including his shiny silk hat. He
carried Jake along to open the gates. “I kno wha he want,”
he had said, “But wait little bit.” And he drove away.</p>
        <p>As they left the station Mr. Ward said, “Save your
horses Ben,” but when they swung into the plantation
avenue he told the coachman to “let them go.”</p>
        <p>Uncle Ben pulled up his lines, drew the whip lightly
across his horses and said, “Git out.”</p>
        <p>Tom and Jerry responded and they came up the “home
stretch” in fine style. The whole family stood on the front
porch waving their handkerchiefs. Mr. Ward waved his in
return. As Uncle
<pb id="aleck75" n="75"/>
Ben drew up at the stepping stone, Mr. Ward
sprang out, ran up the steps, embraced his wife and
children, and kissed his mother-in-law, (a thing
which I believe men seldom do). “We have taken
the fort,” he said, as they entered the house.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="aleck76" n="76"/>
        <head>CHAPTER VI</head>
        <head>THE BEGINNING OF THE END</head>
        <p>THAT night conflicting emotions governed those who
lived on “Pine Top” plantation. In the big house there was
gladness and rejoicing, while at the Quarters there was
groaning and lamentation. The Negro believed that as long
as Major Anderson held Fort Sumter their prospects were
at least hopeful; but when Sumter fell, they felt that their
hopes were all in vain. Though the future looked dark,
there were two on the place who never gave up; Uncle Ben
and Aunt Lucy. You are acquainted
<pb id="aleck77" n="77"/>
with the old man already. Aunt Lucy was the plantation nurse.
Years of hard and faithful toil in the fields had gained for
her respite from active labor. It was her sole duty now to take
care of the young children of the women who had to go into
the rice and cotton fields, and those mothers were glad
indeed to have such a kind christian woman as she was
to look after their little ones while they were at
work. The old woman, though well on in years, was still
hale and hearty. “Min, wha I tell yo. De Master gwine bring
we out,” were her words of encouragement to those who were
ready to despair. Uncle Ben's words were, “Dem buckra kin
laf now, but, wait tel bime by.’</p>
        <p>Between the “big house” and the Quarters there was a
spring from which the people got their drinking water. 
Every afternoon a long line of children might
have been seen with “piggins” on their heads,
taking in the supply for the night. On the evening of Mr.
Ward's return, the children did not appear.
In their stead, and at a later hour, their parents came. It was
noticeable too, that they lingered at the spring, being 
concealed from view by the trees that grew about it. The 
reason of all this was that
<pb id="aleck78" n="78"/>
arrangement had been made with Jake that as soon as
possible after dinner, he was to run down and tell them
any news he might gather during that meal. Jake, as a
possible gatherer of news! Why that was absurd! He was
spry enough about the house and dining-room, but
otherwise he was as dense as a block of stone. At least,
that was what his master would have said of him. This
<hi rend="italics">density</hi> on the part of the Negro was, in fact, a weapon of
defense—the only one he had. Do you think Captain
Small could have run the Planter out of Charleston harbor if
it was thought he had sense enough to do so? No, indeed!
He never would have had the chance.</p>
        <p>I said Jake was to run down. That was a mistake. He was
much too wise for that. After dinner was over he
sauntered down the back steps as soon as he could. Upon
reaching the ground, he thrust his hands into his pockets,
and walked slowly toward the spring, whistling, “Way
Down Upon the Swanee River,” as though he didn't have an 
idea in his head. “He comin' now,” said Aunt Lucy, “Well 
mi son, wha he say,” as the boy drew near.</p>
        <p>“Well, ma'am, dy tak de fote. We done now”
was heard on all sides.</p>
        <pb id="aleck79" n="79"/>
        <p>“Wait, chilun, hope pray,” was the old woman's
encouraging words as she proceeded to question the boy
further. “Wha dey do wid Majer Ande'son?”</p>
        <p>“Dey le him go.”</p>
        <p>“Wha dey say bout him?”</p>
        <p>“O he say do Majer es er brave man. He mak er
speech befo he cum out. He say, (and Jake drew himself 
up to imitate the Major) ”Genlemen, if I had food 
fer my men, an ambunachun I be dam if I wed le yo 
cum on dose gates!”</p>
        <p>“Amen, bress de Lawd!” cried the old woman.</p>
        <p>“O Ant Lucy!” said Manda, the housemaid, abashed at
the old woman's endorsement of the somewhat impious 
remarks of the gallant Major.</p>
        <p>“Hole yo tong yo braze piece. Go on Jake mi son.”</p>
        <p>But the boy had little more to tell and so the people
went sadly back to their cabins. Aunt Lucy's
parting words were, “Hope chilun, pray chilun.”</p>
        <p>The next day Mr. Ward gave Uncle Sempie orders
to prepare for a large dinner party that would be given
by him in a few days. This was to be another
addition to the long list of similar functions that had
taken place at Pine Top under the supervision
<pb id="aleck80" n="80"/>
of the old butler. Among them there was one to
which the old man often referred with special pride. It was
the great dinner given by Mrs. Ward's grandfather, 
(for Pine Top had been the home of the Bale's for 
generations), in honor of the Hon. John C. Calhoun.</p>
        <p>When the day for Mr. Ward's great dinner came,
the guests began to arrive early; some on horseback,
others in carriages, the coachmen vying with each
other in the style in which they came up the avenue,
and pulled up at the stepping stone. There were
distinguished ladies and gentlemen. There were
horses that had records, and some of the coachmen
had records, too. York, Mr. Boyleston's coachman
was one of these. His horses always showed the
best of care and his stables were models of neatness
and appointment. He had three well grown stable
boys under him who were kept at rubbing and polishing 
constantly. The boys slept at the stable while York 
occupied a neat little cabin on a hill a short 
distance away. Seen early in the mornings coming 
down to look after his stock, with a cigar in his 
mouth, he might easily have been taken for Mr.
<pb id="aleck81" n="81"/>
Boyleston himself. As he neared the stable he would say,
“Ahem!” and each boy popped his head out and would say,
“Sah.” Upon entering he went through a minute inspection,
and it was for their best interest if everything was found in
perfect order. York had the record of having once knocked
his master down.</p>
        <p>The circumstances which led to this daring performance
were these: Mr. Boyleston took great pride in his horses.
His stock was always of the finest strain, and it may be
added that he appreciated his coachman's ability as a whip
and manager. His special pride was a span of dark gray trotters
of undoubted pedigree. For these he had bought an
expensive pair of blankets. “Now, York,” he had said,
“These blankets have cost me a great deal of money. Be
very careful with them. Never allow the horses to wear them
at night.”</p>
        <p>York took as much pride in those beautiful coverings for
his horses as did his master. He never permitted the boys to
touch them, but each morning after the finishing touches to
the animals, he adjusted them with his own hands. One
morning he
<pb id="aleck82" n="82"/>
led the horses out on to the floor of the barn, hitched them,
and threw the blankets lightly over them, while he took
another horse outside to water. Unfortunately he had tied
the animals too closely together. They began biting at each
other as horses are wont to do. One of them got his teeth
into the blanket of the other, pulled it down on the floor,
and together they trampled it under hoofs. The boys were
at work at a distant part of the place therefore could not see
what was going on. When York returned he was dismayed
at the sight. The once beautiful blanket now stained and
torn, lay under the feet of the horses! He picked it up, but
there was nothing he could do to repair the damage. He
placed it on the horse as best be could. To add to his
confusion be saw Mr. Boyleston coming down to the stables
for his usual morning inspection. The coachman walked to the
further end of the barn, pretending to be engaged at some
work, while his heart beat almost loud enough to be heard.</p>
        <p>“York,” called out Mr. Boyleston as soon as he entered
and his eyes fell on the damaged blanket, “Did I not tell
you never to let the horses wear
<pb id="aleck83" n="83"/>
their blankets at night?”</p>
        <p>“I dident, sah, de——.”</p>
        <p>“You are a——liar, sir——.”</p>
        <p>Out flew York's right arm before he knew it, and down
went his master. He walked out into the lot, folded his arms,
and stood facing the door. Mr. Boyleston got up. As he
came to the door York said, “Shoot me down, sah.” His
master drew his revolver. “Fire, sah, I'se ready,” and York
stood unflinchingly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boyleston put up his pistol. “Come here to me,
York,” he said.</p>
        <p>“No, sah.”</p>
        <p>“May I come to you?”</p>
        <p>“Yees, sah! I wudent ham a hair on yo head.”</p>
        <p>“York,” said Mr. Boyleston walking out to his coachman,
“How came that blanket to be in such a condition?”</p>
        <p>York gave his master a straight account of the whole
occurrence. “Here is my hand; I was wrong,” was Mr.
Boyleston's magnanimous answer, “Do not mention this
to anyone.”</p>
        <pb id="aleck84" n="84"/>
        <p>There were not many masters like this one.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ward's dinner was a grand affair, and no one
rejoiced at its success more than old Uncle Sempie. After
dinner the party went out on the lawn where a stand had
been erected. Amid cheers the new flag was raised and
many gentlemen made speeches which all seemed to be
aimed at the “White House.” I did not know where that
was, but Uncle Ben said it was where “dem buckra wud
nebah git.” Later I learned that the White House was at
Washington, and sure enough they never got there.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ward now deemed it necessary to have the
plantation carefully guarded at night. For this purpose he
chose two young Negroes, brothers, Titus and Pompey.
The confidence the southern white had in the Negro, and
the fidelity of the latter to the trust reposed in them speak
volumes. Here was this master perfectly satisfied to place
the safety of himself and family in the hands of these men,
on whom, at that moment, he was seeking to rivet the
chains of slavery forever. The men were to relieve each
other, and at stated intervals, if things were all right, they
were to come under Mr. Ward's window
<pb id="aleck85" n="85"/>
and sing out, “All is well!” If things were otherwise, they
were to pull a knob which would ring a bell in their master's
room.</p>
        <p>Titus was noted for his prodigious strength, and an
equally enormous appetite. He created great amusement one
night during his watch by standing under the window and
shouting, “All is well and I'se hungry!” Mr. Ward took the
hint and thereafter the men were each provided with a large
“hoe cake,” lined with fat bacon every night before going on
duty.</p>
        <p>The time drew near for our return to the city. We must not
remain on the plantation after the tenth of May, for those
not acclimated are liable to contract malarial fever. Soon we
bid farewell to the old place and to the many kind friends we
had met there. The kind-hearted people loaded us with
simple gifts. My stay in the country had been most pleasant.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="aleck86" n="86"/>
        <head>CHAPTER VII</head>
        <head>IN TOWN AGAIN</head>
        <epigraph>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">“Mischief, thou art afoot.”</hi>
          </p>
        </epigraph>
        <p>ON arriving in Charleston we found great excitement
there. Men were going about the streets wearing
blue cockades on the lapels of their coats. These
were the “minute men,” and the refrain was
frequently heard,
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“Blue cockade and rusty gun</l><l>We'll make those Yankees run like fun.”</l></lg></q></p>
        <p>Soldiers on parade often passed by our house,
<pb id="aleck87" n="87"/>
and we ran to see them. One day a troop of horses
went by. The ladies waved their handkerchiefs and
the officers saluted. I heard they were on their way
to the “Front.” I wanted very much to know where
that was, therefore, when Uncle Ben and I went to
the stable I asked, “Uncle Ben, where's the ‘Front?’ ”</p>
        <p>The old man made me no immediate reply. In
fact, he never did. Knowing he heard me I waited
patiently. Presently he looked up:—“De front,
boy, es de place weh dem young buckra gwine ketch
de debble,” he said, and resumed his work.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ward had received a commission in the army
with headquarters at Secessionville. It chanced
that Mr. Edward Dane was appointed on his staff,
and he took my brother, several years older than
myself, into the army with him. But the dear boy
contracted fever and soon died. Later, the command
was removed to another point in the harbor,
and for a short time I took my brother's place as
officer's boy! And here I must admit I wore the
“gray.” I have never attended any of the
Confederate reunions. I suppose they overlooked my
name on the army roll! I carried a knapsack, too.
My uniform consisted of a confederate gray jacket,
blue pants, and a Beauregard cap. My knapsack
<pb id="aleck88" n="88"/>
was somewhat smaller than the regulation article,
and was covered with glazed leather. It usually
contained clothes going to or from the washerwoman
in the city. I had a day in the city every week and
thus had ample time to do my shopping which usually
consisted of five molasses groundnut cakes, at
one dollar each! They were not quite as large as
those you get for a penny now, either. Once I went
to buy a pair of shoes and the storekeeper charged
me seventy dollars for them. I tried several other
stores and finally got a pair for sixty-five dollars.
Talk about things being high now, why then most
things were literally “out of sight”—especially
things to eat.</p>
        <p>In the early part of our day on the Island things
were reasonably plentiful. The real business of the
struggle had not yet begun, and General Ward still
had cattle at Pine Top. It was his custom to occasionally
have a lamb or a “Harry Dick” dressed on
the plantation and shipped down to the Island. On
these he regaled himself and brother officers. And,
“Hereby hangs a tale,” from which we get another
glimpse of the general's limitation for the Negro.</p>
        <p>General Ward had a boat's crew of six men. With
one exception they were detailed soldiers—up country
<pb id="aleck89" n="89"/>
men—who had little knowledge of the management
of boats. The exception was Dick Brown, a
Negro fisherman. As is well known the fishermen in
and around Charleston have no superiors in the handling
of small craft on the river, or in the open sea.
Dick pulled the stroke oar, acted as coach, and when
the wind was fair, he sailed the boat. Relying on
Dick's skill and knowledge the general had never
missed a trip on account of weather. On one occasion
he presented his crew with a side of meat and
they appointed one of their number who had had
some experience as a butcher, to cut up and share
it. The general chanced to pass by while the sharing
was in progress. “Ah boys,” said he, “Sharing
up?”</p>
        <p>“Yes sir,” replied the butcher, “There are six of
us and I am trying to divide as equally as possible.”</p>
        <p>“Oh well now, I certainly want Dick to have a
portion, but I did not expect him to share equally
with you white men; a Negro must never share
equally with a white man, you know. Where was
Dick while this was going on? He stood right
among the speakers together with Jake, the
general's boy and I, for Mr. Ward would never think
<pb id="aleck90" n="90"/>
of being so “unjust” to a Negro as to speak behind
his back.</p>
        <p>There are two of us alive today. I don't know
where General Ward is, but I do know that he is
dead. Shot did sometimes fall thick and fast on the
Island, but <hi rend="italics">then,</hi> the general, had the benefit of the
sea breeze!</p>
        <p>The command was soon ordered to Virginia, and
I, being too young to be taken along, was given an
indefinite furlough.</p>
        <p>During the latter part of my stay on the Island
things were tight. As for provisions, well, there
weren't any to speak of. Ground-seed corn and
hominy with an occasional piece of bacon, was
considered very acceptable. These advocates of
“plain food” should have been with us. Nothing could
have been more plain than our fare. I don't believe it was
unhealthy either, although I have had no desire to
try it again. “Pie” is good enough for me. For
coffee we had parched grist steeped and sweetened
with molasses, “Mule Blood” brand. I went over
from the Island in Mr. Ward's boat every Saturday.
They were steamers that ran regularly to our Island,
(“The Planter,” of heroic memory was one of
<pb id="aleck91" n="91"/>
these), but they only crossed at night so as to avoid
“salutes” from the blockading fleet. Most of the
officers of our command kept row boats in which
they could reach the city at their pleasure. Our
landing place at first was Market Dock, but when
General Gilmore began to raise the temperature in
the lower part of the city, we moved our moorings
further uptown; for it would have been rather unpleasant
to be standing on a wharf and have a shell
come whistling by taking one's head off. Furthermore,
the head might roll overboard, or else the kind
comrade who picked it up might, in his haste, be apt
to clap it on again upside down, or backside front;
and like the lady who did not receive an invitation
to the “pink tea,” one would never feel the same
again.</p>
        <p>“The Old Coffee” and “DeKalb” belonged to our
fleet. Captain Christian of the “Coffee” was one of
the most popular seamen at the port of Charleston—
“as jolly an old sea dog as ever drank grog.”
I always returned to the Island at night by steamer.
Several times, random shots fell near us but we
were never hit, and soon got used to them. When
<pb id="aleck92" n="92"/>
one came skipping toward us we simply said, “Shoo
fly.” At this time I was about ten years old, and
rather small for my age. I shall never forget the
peals of laughter that greeted my first appearance
at headquarters. I boarded the Old Coffee at “Market
Dock” and was met on the other side by Mr.
Dane who took me up to the place. Then I was
taken into a large room in which were General Ward,
Captain Parker, Lieutenant Tompson and Jenks.
“What in thunder are you going to do with that
boy!” they cried in unison.</p>
        <p>“This boy is all right Jim,” said Mr. Dane looking
at Lieutenant Tompson, “He can ride.” The
laugh was now turned on the lieutenant who, as I
afterwards learned, had been thrown from his horse
a few days before.</p>
        <p>My duties were very light. If any of the old
soldiers are now living who were on that Island at that
time, (1862-63), remember seeing an officer splendidly
mounted, followed by a mite of a Negro boy
also mounted, galloping over the Island, the boy was
myself.</p>
        <pb id="aleck93" n="93"/>
        <p>Those who remained at home in the South had
many privileges to bear, of which I got my full
share. Things that we consider common necessities
now, were luxuries then. The people who sometimes
clamor for war have no conception of what it really
is. But let us not dwell on these harrowing times
of the past. May we never see the likes again!</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="aleck94" n="94"/>
        <head>CHAPTER VIII</head>
        <head>A TURKEY STEW</head>
        <p>TURKEYS and even chickens were very scarce on
our Island. It is remarkable how quickly these creatures
disappear from the neighborhood of a soldier's
camp during war times, especially when rations
are scant. I suppose they become alarmed and
fly away. Some people may be of a contrary
opinion, but we will let that pass.</p>
        <p>Adjoining our Quarters there lived an Irishman
who owned some turkeys. Besides these there was
not so much as a turkey feather for miles around.
At this time one of these festive birds was worth his
<pb id="aleck95" n="95"/>
weight in gold. But, there was no gold in
circulation hence the amount of confederate money
it would have taken to buy one would have equalled
the turkey himself—at least in bulk. When Mr.
O'Flanagan wanted to buy a piece of real estate,
or make some similar investment, he just sold one of
his turkeys to some young officer who was willing
to part with a small fortune. For these and other
reasons you may be sure that Pat kept watchful
eyes on his flock.</p>
        <p>One afternoon one of these turkeys, without the
fear of consequences, flew over into our yard. We
had a dog that would “fetch,” therefore, Jake
quietly remarked, “Sic um, Bull.” In less than no
time Bull had that turkey by the neck, and in equally
short order, Jake had that bird in the bag.</p>
        <p>The fence between the lots was a high one. Those
on the other side would not see what was going on
in our yard, but they heard the dog chasing the
turkey. Therefore, it was not long before Mr.
O'Flanagan presented himself to the sentinel at the
gate. “I wud loike to go in an git me turkey,” he
said.</p>
        <pb id="aleck96" n="96"/>
        <p>Now the soldier had seen what was going on, and
with visions of a midnight roast before him, had
become a party to the transaction. With a view of
allowing Jake time to “cover his tracks” he resorted
to “dilatory” measures. “What kind of a turkey
was it,” he asked with an innocent look on his face,
And when he could think of no other questions to
ask he told the man he would have to see one of the
officers. “There is General Ward coming up the
street now,” he said, and Pat hastened to meet the
general.</p>
        <p>“Yr haner, one av me turkeys flyed over de
fince an oi belave some wan was afther sittin
the dorg on im.”</p>
        <p>We have already seen that General Ward was a
strict disciplinarian even in civil life. He was no less
so as a military man therefore he told the Irishman
to go in and look for his property, and if he found
that any damage had been done to it, he should have
ample satisfaction, as he never allowed any crooked
proceedings about his headquarters.</p>
        <p>In Pat went. He searched in all the out-buildings,
<pb id="aleck97" n="97"/>
high and low without success. He went to the kitchen
where Jake was busy getting the general's supper.
“The Ginral said oi cud luk fer me turkey.
De dorg——”</p>
        <p>“Dog nebbah bring no turkey een yer,” said Jake,
“Yo ken look, doe.”</p>
        <p>But the search revealed no trace of the missing
bird and Mr. Patrick O'Flanagan left muttering
“imprecations not loud but deep.”</p>
        <p>Does the devil take care of his own? I don't
know, but during the hunt in the kitchen Jake's
heart was in his mouth, for the turkey was hanging
peacefully in a bag behind the door where he might
easily have been seen if Pat had only looked there.</p>
        <p>I do not know whatever became of it. It was
never cooked in that kitchen. Jake became alarmed
and took it away under cover of night.</p>
        <p>Many a story is told about the camp fire, and
many a dainty bite goes round that never came from
the commissary.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="aleck98" n="98"/>
        <head>CHAPTER IX</head>
        <head>TOM BALE</head>
        <epigraph>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">“If thine enemy hunger, feed him.”</hi>
          </p>
        </epigraph>
        <p>IN a previous chapter I promised to say something
further about Mr. Bale. It was his habit
to spend a week or more with his mother every
year, and during our stay at Mrs. Bale's, and after
our return from Pine Top he made one of his
yearly visits, bringing his wife and child, nurse,
coachman, and three horses.</p>
        <p>It is said that no man is wholly bad. If this is
true why the young man of whom we are going to
speak must have had his redeeming qualities. But
they were never manifested in the treatment of his
slaves. He was a very young man. His father had
died when the son had barely reached his majority,
and he was left in sole control of the large plantation
on which were more than four hundred Negroes.
<pb id="aleck99" n="99"/>
It was said, he had from his youth exhibited an ugly
disposition, and this early elevation to power did
not tend to improve his character. In many
instances where the master was harsh, the mistress
was considerate; while in others the reverse was true.
In either of these cases the servants had a chance,
but where both were alike inconsiderate, the fate of
the slave was hard indeed. . . . Young Mrs. Bale
was hard to please.</p>
        <p>Some say that even the devil is not as black as he
is painted. I never could endorse that statement. I
have always thought he was as black as it was possible
to paint him, and a great deal blacker. At any
rate I am free to say there was not one, single, mitigating
feature in the treatment of those unfortunate creatures
who had to serve Tom Bale; they all
suffered. A double share seemed to fall to the lot
of “London,” the coachman. To say that this poor
fellow had a hard time would convey but a faint idea
of his condition. He was competent, faithful and
submissive, but these qualities did not secure for him
the slightest consideration. Frequently, after going
<pb id="aleck100" n="100"/>
over the cushion, etc., with her handkerchief,
his mistress would send the carriage back to the
stable as being “Absolutely too dusty to ride in.”
The slightest complaint from Mrs. Bale exasperated
his master against him and he was often severely
punished even though he had done all in his power
to have everything in perfect order. His patient
fortitude under cruel treatment was indeed wonderful.
Despite the terrible hardships he had to endure,
he managed to extract some pleasures from his
occupation. He loved his horses and often spoke
of them in terms of endearment. “Dem boys nebber
mak me shame yit,” he would say in speaking of
them, “Wen I say cum Daddy, cum Spug, de Nigger
dat pick me up got ter kno wha he bout.”</p>
        <p>London and I were best friends, and so as
to be on hand each morning when he went to the
stable I was permitted to occupy a cot in his room,
for I liked to go with him. He went much earlier
than Uncle Ben. The poor fellow was glad to have
me with him at night. It was a relief to him to have
someone to talk to. He would tell me about the fine
<pb id="aleck101" n="101"/>
horses he had handled, and others he had known: Of
Old Tar River, Bonnet so Blue and Clara Fisher.
When he was seated on his box flourishing his whip
with the easy grace of the experienced southern
coachmen, one would not think his life was the
terrible grind it really was.</p>
        <p>One morning at a very early hour I heard Tom
Bale calling from the yard, “London, London!” I
tried to rouse the sleeping man without success.
Presently I heard the heavy tread of his master coming
upstairs.—And London slept!—The balmy
air of that spring morning was seductive. The
night had been rather warm and London was not
encumbered with any superfluous clothing. Now
London was very careful with his whips. They were
not allowed to lay about carelessly, but were suspended
from a rack of polished wood, made for the
purpose, and hung against the wall in his room.
There was one gold mounted, one mounted with silver,
and one was adorned with carved ivory, one
had a dainty little red ribbon bow on it, while the
two others were decorated respectively with white
and yellow.</p>
        <pb id="aleck102" n="102"/>
        <p>Bale pushed open the door and strode into the room.
He looked at the sleeping coachmen a moment,
then, with a muttered imprecation, took down
one of those whips; I don't know which. I heard the
“swish” through the air, for by that time I had
covered my head. Blow after blow descended upon him
until the blood started. “Now,” said the tyrant
fairly exhausted, “Go down and hitch up my horse!
I told you to have my buggy ready early this morning.”
The abused and bleeding Negro hastened to
obey.</p>
        <p>Tom Bale had intended that morning to drive up
alone to one of his plantations twenty miles from the
city. He had hitched a fast young horse to a light
buggy. The mistreated London who had handled
this animal from a colt had once ventured to warn
his master about driving him with an open bridle.
In truth, he tried to prevent Bale from possibly
having his neck broken. That b— d—, the bully
had replied, “I want his head to show. He has the
finest head in South Carolina.”</p>
        <pb id="aleck103" n="103"/>
        <p>But that morning it appears retributive justice
was at his heels, for, late that afternoon the horse
reached the plantation with a part of the harness
clinging to him; clearly evident a runaway. As you
probably know this created no small stir in the
place. A searching party was sent out immediately.
“Here Caesar, you take Sancho and two or three
others. Hasten out, take lanterns with you. I will
follow with a team,” and Jim Black, the overseer,
hurried away to the barn.</p>
        <p>It was remarkable how much time Caesar managed
to consume in getting ready though apparently
using all possible expedition. At last they were off.
“Cum on boys,” he said as they got out into the
main road and he started on a brisk run in the direction
in which it was least likely to find the missing
man. They had gone nearly a quarter of a mile
before Black drove out. He yelled at them to come
back. Their confusion was so very evident that he
simply abused them roundly as a pack of blockheads,
and sent them down the road toward the city.</p>
        <pb id="aleck104" n="104"/>
        <p>They hunted some miles before any trace of Tom
Bale was discovered. At last they found a piece of
leather—some part of the harness. It was now
quite dark. Lanterns and torches were lighted. A
little further on they came to a place where the
vehicle had evidently left the road. A few hundred
yards out in the pine woods the upset buggy was
seen, and nearly lay the young man, pale and unconscious.
Even <sic corr="Caesar">Ceasar</sic> felt pity for him.</p>
        <p>He was lifted into the wagon in which the overseer
had thoughtfully placed a small mattress. He
had also dispatched a messenger on horseback who
met them on their way back. Upon a hasty examination
the physician found that Bale had one
leg broken and his shoulders severely bruised. It
was weeks before he could be removed to the city,
and months after the accident before he was able to
get about.</p>
        <p>The summary visitation of Providence, should, it
would seem, have cured this rash young man; but it
did not. At this time the war is on and Tom Bale
<pb id="aleck105" n="105"/>
is impatiently awaiting his physician's permission
to join his regiment at the front. The newspapers
are giving glowing accounts of Confederate victories.
The white people are exultingly jubilant,
and the Negroes correspondingly sad and depressed,
for though they cannot read the newspapers they
are well posted as to the news that comes in.</p>
        <p>One morning Mr. Thomas Bale was seated on his
piazza in Charleston, reading. The reports of
Confederate success pleased him. London, with his
heart bowed down was sweeping the sidewalk in
front of the house when a fellow sufferer passing by
stopped to exchange the usual morning greeting.—</p>
        <p>“Mornin' brudder Lon'on.”</p>
        <p>“Mornin' mi brudder.”</p>
        <p>“How yo gittin on?”</p>
        <p>“O mi brudder, ha'd time, an wus cumin,” was
London's sad reply.</p>
        <p>Out flew his master, and with the heavy cane he
had carried out since his accident he felled the poor
slave to the earth. “Say better times are coming,
you rascal,” he stormed, re-entering the house.</p>
        <pb id="aleck106" n="106"/>
        <p>And what did much abused Negro do? The
war being over Tome Bale returned to his home
broken in health and fortune; for despite his injured
leg he had gone into the war and remained
until the end came. At this time many of the men
who were engaged in the southern side during the
war, not knowing what would be their fate under
the new order of things, were hastening out of the
country. Bale was among these. He was forced to
leave his family inadequately provided for. However,
he was still a young man and hoped to retrieve
his fortune in a foreign land, or at least to
remain away until things were settled.</p>
        <p>It was a terrible blow to his young wife with two
children to be so suddenly reduced from affluence to
poverty. . . . But, there was a friend at hand—
London. He had secured a situation as teamster
with a wholesale house that had resumed business in
the city; and every Saturday evening found him at
the door of the house in which Mrs. Bale lived with
packages of tea, coffee, sugar, butter, etc., such as
she had been accustomed to and could no longer
afford to buy; bought with his own money, from the
<pb id="aleck107" n="107"/>
same exclusive establishment where she formerly
dealt. Occasionally when passing that way with his
truck he would leave ham at the door. This continued
until the death of the lady. Tom Bale never
returned. It was said he fell a victim to malaria and
died in a far away land.</p>
        <p>It is but a few years since London went to his
reward. He became a deacon in his church before
he died, and on many a Thursday night meeting he
would stand and sing:—
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“What troubles have we seen</l><l>What conflicts have we passed!</l><l>But out of all the Lord</l><l>Had brought us by his love.</l><l>And still he doth his grace</l><l>Afford, and hides our lives above.”</l></lg></q>
while tears of gratitude rolled down his cheeks. He
had lived to dwell “under his own vine and fig tree,
with none to molest or make him afraid.”</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="aleck108" n="108"/>
        <head>CHAPTER X</head>
        <head>SILLA—THE MAID</head>
        <epigraph>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">“As we forgive those who trespass against us.”</hi>
          </p>
        </epigraph>
        <p>IT is more pleasant to me than otherwise that I
have no other similar instance of cruelty to relate,
coming under my own observation like that of Tom Bale's.
Although the following may not be called
cruel, still it is not devoid of severity and harshness.</p>
        <p>Among our neighbors there was a family whose
servant had rather a hard time of it. The family
was very religious but not liberal minded. All their
servants had to attend the family church.</p>
        <pb id="aleck109" n="109"/>
        <p>One of the ladies had a maid whose lot was hard
indeed. She was only allowed to wear such dresses
as her mistress prescribed, and these were always
made of the coarsest material after an original design.
She was never permitted to wear a bonnet,
but must have her head tied with a bandanna. No
idea of economy prompted the mistress. There were
those mean enough to say that it was done because
Silla was very pretty and the lady was so plain.</p>
        <p>Now the maid was fond of dress. She also had
strong religious sentiments but they were different
from those of her mistress. She was also an expert
needle-woman, and her brother who “hired his time”
and “worked out,” furnished her with material which
she fashioned to suit herself—working at night and
at odd times. Sometimes on Sundays she managed
to attend the church of her choice, arrayed in such
garments as she desired, being careful however, to
leave the house after the family had gone, and to
return before their arrival. But she came to grief
at last.</p>
        <p>It was during a season of great excitement in
religious circles in the city. The Baptists were making
<pb id="aleck110" n="110"/>
heavy inroads on the Methodist Camp, and the
latter found it necessary to bring out their heavy
artillery. Many eminent Divines noted for their
piety, learning and eloquence had been invited by
the Methodist clergy to assist in calming the fears
of their flocks. Silla was a strong Methodist, therefore
when it was announced that on a certain Sunday
a Reverend Gentlemen of matchless eloquence
would preach, she determined to hear him. It was
said that this particular sermon had the effect of
sending the wavering ones back to their ranks; for,
after an impassioned appeal to his hearers to stand
firm, he closed his eloquent discourse as follows:—
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“Let others glory in the water</l><l>I glory in the blood.”</l></lg></q></p>
        <p>I need not tell you that on that Sunday Silla
appeared in a beautiful dress made in the latest style,
a rich mantilla, and a bonnet that was not inexpensive.
Altogether she presented a very enviable
appearance.</p>
        <p>When she was ready to start out Aunt Cinda, the
old nurse, said to her, “Now gal, yo luk berry nice
indeed, but doan le dem tings tun yo hed so de
buckra git home for yo.”</p>
        <pb id="aleck111" n="111"/>
        <p>“O no ma'am, Aunt Cinda, I'll be in time.”</p>
        <p>But alas! What with a word of greeting here,
and a word of congratulation there, after service,
the time slipped by. As Silla sped homeward she
became aware of the fact that she was late. She
quickened her pace, but “Time lost can never be
regained.” Miss Octavia had reached home before
she got there.</p>
        <p>On reaching the house the lady had immediately
called for her maid, and she was quite surprised to find
that she had not yet returned from church. Therefore,
she took her seat on the piazza which commanded
a full view of the servants' entrance, determined
to ascertain from Silla as soon as she came
in, the meaning of her tardiness. The lady was not
in a pleasant frame of mind either, as she was quite
thirsty and wanted a drink of water.</p>
        <p>As Silla timidly opened the gate and put her head
in she would have withdrawn it, but... “Walk
in here, madam!” came from her mistress in tones
that were not to be misunderstood, “Where have
you been?”</p>
        <pb id="aleck112" n="112"/>
        <p>“To church, ma'am.”</p>
        <p>“What church, pray?”</p>
        <p>“Methodist, ma'am.”</p>
        <p>“And who gave you those horrid things you have on?”</p>
        <p>“Bobber Jim, ma'am.”</p>
        <p>“He did, eh! Come right in here.”</p>
        <p>Silla's heart sank within her as she meekly obeyed.
Miss Octavia followed her servant into the house.
“Get me some old newspapers,” she said. “Place
them in that grate. Take off that hat and lay it on
the paper. Now get a match and set the fire.”
And the poor girl stood there and saw her beautiful
bonnet go up in smoke.</p>
        <p>“Now madam, go and take off those things and
never let me see you with them on again!”</p>
        <p>Silla served Miss Octavia for a long time after the
war. The lady is dead now, but the maid is still
living in Charleston, South Carolina.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="aleck113" n="113"/>
        <head>CHAPTER XI</head>
        <head>THE APPRAISEMENT</head>
        <epigraph>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">“He will give His angels charge concerning thee.”</hi>
          </p>
        </epigraph>
        <p>WHILE we were at Mrs. Bale's and before I went
“into camp,” I had the following sad experience:—
Up to this event it had never dawned upon me that
my condition was not as good as that of any boy in
the country. With kind parents, two sweet little
sisters, an affectionate brother, gentle companions
to play with, and every boyish wish gratified, the
improbability of my succession to the presidential
chair never once occurred to me. But now I was
made to feel that life was not all “one pleasant
dream.”</p>
        <p>One day my mother received a message calling
her down to the Dane's. When she returned she
<pb id="aleck114" n="114"/>
seemed very sad, and upon my father's arrival
home I saw them in earnest conversation. Before
I went to bed that night my mother told me that I
would have to go with her to the Dane's on the next
day. “The Old Jay wants to see you,” she said.</p>
        <p>I was greatly pleased at this for it was a long
time since I had been there. When we arrived the
next day I found all the servants arrayed as if for
some holiday occasion and I also found that they
were to be “praised.” However, I couldn't understand
why persons dressed up as they were, and who
had been bought together for commendation,
should look so sad. I did not know what I had done
deserving of special mention, but I did remember
that sometime before my horse ran away with me
through the crowded streets, and that I had managed
to keep my seat. I finally brought the animal
to a stand without any damage. Therefore, I
thought I would receive a gold medal, or perhaps
“four pence” in money. But to be certain, I would
ask Cora what it all meant.</p>
        <p>I found her seated alone on a bench in the yard
looking more beautiful than ever. “Cora,” said I,
“What is all of this about?”. . . Instead of answering
my questions she began to cry and she took
<pb id="aleck115" n="115"/>
hold of me and hugged and kissed me right there in
the yard, before all those people!! My, didn't I
blush!</p>
        <p>The fact was, kind reader, as you have already
surmised, the “Estate” was to be sold, and the people
had been brought together for “appraisement.”</p>
        <p>Several gentlemen came out into the yard. The
people stood up, and the gentlemen went among
them asking questions. One of them placed his
hand on my head. . . . “Well, my boy,” said he,
“What can you do?”</p>
        <p>“I can ride, Sir,” I answered, whereupon my mother
gave me a gentle nudge which meant, “Hush.”
She then explained to him that my brother and I
were not to be sold for she had earnestly requested
Mr. Dane not to “sell” us. She knew that we should
receive good treatment as long as we were in his
hands, and that if we went with her, the Negro
Traders would soon separate us. With many protestations
Mr. Dane had promised her that he would
not sell us even if he had to go barefoot. He kept
his word, but my mother and two little sisters went
and for four years, we neither saw nor heard of each
other. When “the cruel war was over” we were
brought together again, and you may know there
<pb id="aleck116" n="116"/>
was a happy meeting for—“He had given his angels
charge concerning us.” We were all there to
greet the gallant Major Anderson when he returned
to raise the “Old Flag” over Fort Sumter.</p>
        <lg type="verse">
          <l>“ 'Twas the star spangled banner</l>
          <l>And long may it wave,</l>
          <l>O'er the land of the free</l>
          <l>And the home of the brave.”</l>
        </lg>
        <p>The war was ended. The Union had come. Soon
the schools were thrown open, and under the leadership
of the enthusiastic Redpart, and that noble
band of pioneer men and women from the North, the
children flocked to them. Surely there must be a
future for a people so eager to learn as is the Negro,
and though we are not yet out of the woods,
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“We are coming, Father Abraham</l><l>Full many a million strong.”</l></lg></q></p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="aleck117" n="117"/>
        <head>CHAPTER XII</head>
        <head>THE BIG FIRE</head>
        <epigraph>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">“Hear the loud alarum bell.”</hi>
          </p>
        </epigraph>
        <p>ON the night of December 11th, 1861, our dear
old home on Guignard street was destroyed by fire.
This was the greatest conflagration that has happened
in Charleston during my lifetime.</p>
        <p>It broke out at, or near the corner of East Bay
and Hasel Streets, and swept in a direction across
the city to the very edge of Ashley River, at the
other side of town; licking up nearly everything in
its patch. When the alarm was given Ward 3, we
hurried out from Mrs. Bate's where we were living
<pb id="aleck118" n="118"/>
at that time. Not very far away from the old place,
looking in that direction, we saw the flames leaping
up, and hastened on. The sparks seemed to rain
down from the heavens as we ran. When we reached
there, we found the engines pouring streams of
water on the house, while there was a long line of
men reaching from the well in the yard, up the back
stairs to the roof of the house, passing buckets of
water from one to another.</p>
        <p>The devoted ladies stood by encouraging them.
“Water! More water!” they cried. But it was all
unavailing. The fire soon caught the piazzas, then
burst in the windows and doors seeming to say, “Who
would stay the ‘Fire King?’ ” Soon the old home
together with nearly all of the neighboring houses
was a mass of ruin. On swept the flames reaching
Broad Street. They raged about the Cathedral.
It was thought that owing to the material of which
that beautiful structure was built, it would have
escaped, but no—under the fierce onslaught of the
devouring element, the costly and magnificent edifice
melted away; and onward the fire sped, not stopping
until it reached the waters of the Ashley River.</p>
        <p>I do not know the casualties that attended this
distressing event, but the property loss was very
great.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="aleck119" n="119"/>
        <head>CHAPTER XIII</head>
        <head>MR. WARD'S RETURN TO PINE TOP</head>
        <epigraph>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">“Let us have peace.”</hi>
          </p>
        </epigraph>
        <p>IT was late in the Fall of 1865 that Mr. Ward
was on his way to join his family. As soon as possible
after the surrender of Richmond, he had made
a hasty visit to Charleston to assure himself of their
safety, but had returned to Richmond after a few
days stay with them to engage in some clerical work
<pb id="aleck120" n="120"/>
he had previously secured in that city; the compensation
for which he found himself sorely in need of
at that time. He was now on his way to join them
permanently. He had an irresistible impulse however
to visit the old plantation. As the train sped
on, the desire grew upon him, therefore when they
pulled up at the little station, White House, he got
off, determined to walk out to the place. It is worthy
of note that this man did not for a moment doubt
that he would be kindly received by his former slaves,
if any remained there.</p>
        <p>Fortunately he met an old friend at the station
who gladly provided him with a horse on which he
rode out to the plantation, beset by emotions better
imagined than described. As he turned from the
road into the long avenue a mass of ruins met his
eyes. The noble old house had been destroyed by
fire! With a sad heart he rode on.</p>
        <p>Uncle Joe was at work burning stubble in a nearby
field. As he raised his eyes they rested on the
lone horsemen. “Wonder who da him,” he said as
he started to meet the stranger, “Um, ee luk like
<pb id="aleck121" n="121"/>
Mass Willum, Lord bless me!”</p>
        <p>As the two men drew near each other Mr. Ward
leaped from his horse and extending his hand he
cried, “Joe!”</p>
        <p>“Mas Willum!” sobbed the old Negro.</p>
        <p>They fell on each others necks and wept like
children. Oh why did the designing stranger and the
native demagogue enter to thwart this auspicious
opening of a new era between these men?</p>
        <p>After a while they started toward Uncle Joe's
cabin. Mr. Ward refused to remount though urged
to do so by the old man. As they walked along Mr.
Ward inquired about those he had left on the place.
Some had gone away. They had sought the city.
It were well for many of these if they had remained
on the plantation, for the town held many snares
and temptations to which they were unaccustomed,
and to which they fell a prey. Old Uncle Josh and
his wife had gone to Mrs. Ward in Charleston. Uncle
Josh was not inclined to leave the plantation,
but his wife was anxious to go and see how Mrs.
Ward was faring, and if she could be of any help
<pb id="aleck122" n="122"/>
to her. Thus they went.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Ward was more than glad to see her old
friends. “I thank you very much for coming to me
at this time,” she said to Aunt ——, but I am not
able to offer you any wages, for I am without means
now.”</p>
        <p>“I a'int cum fer yo money, Chile,” the old woman
answered, “Ef yo doan need my sarbis I ken go
back.”</p>
        <p>“Oh you dear creatures, you know how much
I need you. I only meant that I cannot pay you
anything just now.”</p>
        <p>And so the old woman took charge, greatly to the
relief of Mrs. Ward, also to that of Uncle August
who had been constantly with his mistress, and was
acting in the capacity of general house servant.
The advent of Aunt Peggy allowed him a chance to
go out doing odd jobs, thereby earning a few dollars.
He steadily refused to accept any work that would
take him away permanently from Mrs. Ward. The
lady could offer comfortable quarters to Uncle Josh
and his wife. The old man soon obtained work in
the city and the three servants lived on the premises
until they died. It is doubtful if Mrs. Ward ever
<pb id="aleck123" n="123"/>
had any more faithful and truer servants than they
were.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ward was glad to find that there were still
many of his people on the plantation, all of whom
seemed glad to see him. Old Aunt Binah, Uncle
Joe's wife was dead, and his two boys, now strapping
young fellows had gone to the city to work. “Long
shore” the old man informed him, also that they
had turned out well and came up to see him often.</p>
        <p>As they neared the cabin they passed a pen in
which were six fine shoats “Dem b'long to Mingo,
sah,” said Uncle Joe.</p>
        <p>A shade passed over Mr. Ward's face. “Mingo?”
he asked.</p>
        <p>“Yessah. Mingo mar'ed Dolly, yo kno sah, an ee
com ter lib yer wid er. And den wen they gon ter
town an my old ooman dead, Dolly un him com lib
wid me sah, caise I so lonsum. Mingo is er good
christon man sah, an dey berry kine ter me.”</p>
        <p>The shade on Mr. Ward's face deepened. “Joe,”
said he, “I treated Mingo harshly once.”</p>
        <p>“I kno dat, but ee don forgit all bout it, sah.”</p>
        <pb id="aleck124" n="124"/>
        <p>Mr. Ward sighed as though he wished he could
forget also. “Is Lucy still here?” he asked.</p>
        <p>“Yee, sah. She es prime es eber.”</p>
        <p>“Let us go over and see her.”</p>
        <p>“Praise de Lawd!” cried the old woman as they
entered her cabin. Mr. Ward could not speak, but
extended his hand.</p>
        <p>“Mas Willum, I'se berry glad ter see yer. Si'
down. How yer bin all dis time?”</p>
        <p>“Well, Ma'am Lucy, I have had some hard raps,
but I am thankful to be alive, and to see you all
again. A great change has come about.”</p>
        <p>“Yee sah, God mov een er misterous way.”</p>
        <p>After a short stay at Aunt Lucy's they visited
the other cabins before returning to Uncle Joe's
abode. “Sorry de ole ooman ain't here yere, sah,” said
the old man with moistened eyes, as they went in.
Dolly, busy with the housework, had noticed Uncle
Joe and a white man going to the barn with a horse.
They had left the horse there and were next seen
<pb id="aleck125" n="125"/>
coming toward the cabin. With native shyness she
drew herself from view, and when she ventured to
peep out again, the man had passed her house going
in the direction of Aunt Lucy's. “Vonder who dat,”
she had said, and went on with her work.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile Mr. Ward and Uncle Joe had completed
their visits and returned. She did not see
them until they entered the rear door of the cabin.
She was just about to put a large dish into the cupboard
when she glanced up. . . . Down went the
dish to the floor in a hundred pieces!!! “Don't be
frightened, Dolly,” said Mr. Ward, smiling and extending
his hand. “You got your Mingo after all.”</p>
        <p>Dolly was speechless for a moment. Then she
said, “Ee this yo Mas Willum!”</p>
        <p>“Yes indeed,” replied the gentleman, “and I am
truly glad to see you. How are you and your husband?”</p>
        <p>“Ve quite well, tankee sah. How yo do?”</p>
        <p>“Oh, I feel better now, than I have for many a
day,” he replied.</p>
        <p>The men sat down before the blazing fire and
entered into a long earnest conversation concerning
<pb id="aleck126" n="126"/>
the past, the present and the future. Just before
they entered the door, Mr. Ward had noticed a fine
possum hanging outside, all cleaned and ready for
the oven. He was at the point of expressing his delight
at the sight when he was arrested by the pathetic
remarks of Uncle Joe. During a lull in the
conversation he turned to Dolly and said, “I see
you have a fine possum.”</p>
        <p>“Yees sah,” she answered, “Mingo ketch him las
night, and we gwine ter hab im for supper. Glad yo
cum jest een time.”</p>
        <p>“I am glad too,” said Mr. Ward laughingly.</p>
        <p>Mingo worked at the ferry half a mile away. He
was later than usual coming home that evening, and
had reached the house without being apprised of
Mr. Ward's arrival. When he came in and saw the
gentleman, he stood motionless with astonishment.
Mr. Ward got up. Advancing toward the bewildered
man with outstretched hand he said, “Mingo,
I treated you harshly once. I am ashamed of it,
and I wish to ask your pardon.”</p>
        <pb id="aleck127" n="127"/>
        <p>Mingo grasped his hand. “Doan say nothin bout
dat, sah. Ise glad ter see yo—berry glad ter see
yo sah. Si down.” And the two men had a long
talk.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="aleck128" n="128"/>
        <head>CHAPTER XIV</head>
        <head>ROAST POSSUM</head>
        <epigraph>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>
              <hi rend="italics">"Tun dat possum roun and roun</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
              <hi rend="italics">Tun dat possum roun."</hi>
            </l>
          </lg>
        </epigraph>
        <p>DOLLY knew the high estimate Mr. Ward had of
old Aunt Lucy's ability as a cook, therefore she
requested her to come over that evening. This the
old lady readily consented to do, and as she proceeded
with her pleasant task, she indulged in many
reminiscences of former occasions on which she had
officiated to the gastronomic delight of Mr. Ward;
and even of old Mr. Bale, Mrs. Ward's father.
When everything was ready Dolly brought out a
snowy cloth, spread it on the pine table, laid a plate,
knife and fork thereon, then she ran down to the
spring for some fresh water. Returning, she placed
a glass of this beside the plate. Meanwhile Aunt
Lucy was taking up the summer. On a large dish
she gently placed the festive possum done to a turn.
Then she carefully arranged some baked sweet
potatoes around it. Over all she poured some gravy
<pb id="aleck129" n="129"/>
that had been simmering in a saucepan by the fire.
She placed this dish in front of the plate on the
table, and flanked it on one side by a dish of rice as
white as milk, and on the other by some delicious
cornbread. She surveyed the table a moment then
announced, “Supper ready.”</p>
        <p>“Draw up, sah,” said Mingo acting as master of
ceremonies.</p>
        <p>“Surely you are all going to join me!” said Mr.
Ward rising.</p>
        <p>“No sah,” answered Uncle Joe, “It do ve mo good
ter see yo eat dan ter eat vesef, sah.”</p>
        <p>Argument was of no avail, therefore Mr. Ward
sat down and in a remarkably short space of time
that dish of possum and potatoes had very perceptively
diminished. After Mr. Ward was through,
the table was rearranged and the others sat down.</p>
        <p>The gentleman looked thoughtfully into the fire,
and when all had finished he stood up. “Joe, Lucy,
Mingo, Dolly,” said he, calling each by name, “I can
never hope to enjoy another meal such as I have
<pb id="aleck130" n="130"/>
had, as long as I live. His earnestness impressed
them all. They made no reply.</p>
        <p>Immediately after supper Mingo had excused himself,
and was absent for more than an hour. All of
those whom Mr. Ward had not seen during the day
came in after supper to shake hands with him. Mingo
was seen to whisper to two or three of the younger
men, and together they went out; seemingly on
some mysterious errand.</p>
        <p>Some of the older people tarried a while to talk.
“Chillun,” said Aunt Lucy, “Look at de vonders ob
de Master.” Then she raised her voice and sang,
“And are we yet alive?”</p>
        <p>Uncle Joe requested the old woman to pray. They
all knelt down while she uttered a prayer of
wonderful strength; full of faith and hope. Mr. Ward
was asked by the old man to read the 14th chapter
of St. John. Uncle Joe, though still vigorous, was
quite an old man; therefore, at the conclusion of the
reading he sang:—
<pb id="aleck131" n="131"/>
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“On Jordan's stormy banks I stand</l><l>And cast a wistful eye.”</l></lg></q>
They all felt that he was looking, “For a house not
made with hands, but eternal in the heavens.” And
so he was, for a few months later he passed to his
reward.</p>
        <p>They had all joined in the singing, and accustomed
as was Mr. Ward to hearing them, it seemed
as though he was never so impressed as now. Again
and again he requested them to sing, and they responded
with such old hymns as:—
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“Roll Jordan, roll</l><l>My bruder, yo aught to bin dere</l><l>To yer wen Jordan roll.”</l></lg></q></p>
        <p>When they rose to leave they sang heartily:—
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“No fearin, no doubtin</l><l>While God's on our side.</l><l>We'll all die er shoutin'</l><l>De Lawd will provide.”</l></lg></q></p>
        <p>Kind reader have you ever heard those people
<pb id="aleck132" n="132"/>
sing? If a band of these old veterans could be
brought together and travel through the country
singing their old time songs, I believe it would do
more towards settling the so called Negro problem,
and allaying the growing unrest caused thereby,
than any other single force. The particular ones of
whom I write are all, with a single exception, dead;
but there are still many of the “Old Timers” living.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ward had not expected to stay so long, but
the hours sped swiftly, and he was forced to spend
the night under the roof of old Uncle Joe. Mr.
Mingo went to work early the next morning before
Mr. Ward was up.</p>
        <p>The borrowed horse had been returned by one of
the men going to the station, as the gentleman
found his stay would be prolonged. Uncle Joe
would drive him over to take the train.</p>
        <p>After breakfast Uncle Joe went to the barn to
“hitch up.” When he drove up to the cabin door
there was a large homespun sack which seemed to
<pb id="aleck133" n="133"/>
contain something bulky, lying across the rear part
of the buggy. “Got quite a load behind you, Joe,”
remarked Mr. Ward as he stepped in.</p>
        <p>“One ob Mingo shoats, sah. Ee kill im las night.
Say ee sory ee didn't hab time to cut up de meat.
Yo kin hab dat don wen yo git home. Hang im up in
er cool space, sah.”</p>
        <p>The gentleman made no reply, but there was a
strange, far away look in his eyes. As they drove,
the old man imparted such bits of information as
he thought might be of interest. Finally both became
silent. “Joe,” at length said Mr. Ward, “You
are thoughtful as usual.”</p>
        <p>“Fine nuff ter tink bout, sah. Member once wen I
didn't tink, an ee put de wuk on de plantation bac
two days. He laughed loudly as though amused by
some recollection. Mr. Ward smilingly asked when
this happening had occurred. Then the old man related
the circumstances which were as follows:—</p>
        <p>Mr. Ward had directed him to have a piece of
work done. He had delayed in doing it because
there was something about it to which he wished to
<pb id="aleck134" n="134"/>
call his master's attention. However, before he
could do so Mr. Ward called him and demanded to
know what was the cause of the delay. “I thought
sah,” began Uncle Joe. “I don't want you to think.
Do as I tell you,” Mr. Ward had said sternly.</p>
        <p>Later the old man's reasons were discovered to be
well founded, but his master made no acknowledgment
of it. One morning some time after Mr. Ward
had said, “Joe, tomorrow morning early, take two
double teams and four men, and go over to Mr.
Bennett Ward's (a brother of his). There are
some things there; furniture, etc., that I wish to
have brought here. Make a very early start. I
will ride over after you. Wait there until I come.”</p>
        <p>Now it so happened that on this very day, after
Mr. Ward had given his instructions, he received a
letter calling him to the city on urgent business.
He went down that evening. Naturally he said nothing
to Uncle Joe, nor did he change his orders. The
old man knew he was gone, also that it was impossible
for him to return in time to ride over to his
<pb id="aleck135" n="135"/>
brother's, as it was eight miles across the country.
But he was not to think!</p>
        <p>By daylight next morning, he with teams and
men, was on the road to “Mas' Bennett.” On his
arrival he told the gentleman the orders he had
received from his master. “All right,” said he,
“Wait.” And they waited.</p>
        <p>At dinner time Mr. Ward expressed surprise that
his brother had not come. At night he felt worried
about it. “If he is not here in the morning I shall
ride over and see what the matter is,” he said.</p>
        <p>The next day, when breakfast had been completed,
he mounted his horse and rode away, telling Joe to
remain there as his brother might come at any moment.
He had expected to meet Mr. William on the
way, but after riding several miles without doing so,
he became quite alarmed and went on to Pine Top.
His brother he found, had been called to the city
unexpectedly, and had not returned as yet. Mrs.
Ward knew that her husband intended to send Joe,
but thought he had altered the arrangement when he
<pb id="aleck136" n="136"/>
found that he would be absent. She was just on the
verge of sending for Joe to come back.</p>
        <p>It was near three o'clock when Mr. Ward got
home. His brother was in the act of leaving. “I
did tell Joe to go over to your place yesterday, and
to wait until I came. I forgot all about it until a
few moments ago. When you get home, please see
that the wagons are loaded tonight, and let them
start back by daylight,” said Mr. William Ward.</p>
        <p>Not until nine o'clock in the morning of the third
day of their absence did they return to Pine Top.
Work had been terribly put back on the place. But,
Uncle Joe had done as he was told, without thinking.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ward remembered facts distinctly. He now
learned for the first time the true inwardness of
them. “Joe,” said he with a smile, “That was not
the only mistake I ever made.”</p>
        <p>They bade each other good-bye at the station.
“Remain on the plantation, Joe, and tell all the
<pb id="aleck137" n="137"/>
others to do so until we see what is to be done,”
said Mr. Ward as he boarded the train. They never
met again!</p>
        <p>Mr. Ward entered the ministry and labored for
some years on the coast among his own people, in
the vicinity where he once had his military
headquarters. Was the inspiration furnished by that
memorable visit to the old plantation? Who can
tell?</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="aleck138" n="138"/>
        <head>CHAPTER XV</head>
        <head>After De Union</head>
        <epigraph>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">“Universal Suffrage say to all, Be ye tranquil.”</hi>
          </p>
        </epigraph>
        <p>RECONSTRUCTION times were now at hand. The
ruinous conditions that followed that period have
been oft and repeatedly charged to the Negroes of
South Carolina. Is this just? Is it true? I say,
No! I was but a boy then. I remember going with
my father who was one of a delegation of men selected
for the purpose of calling on some gentlemen
of Charleston. These gentlemen, although they had
been slaveholders, were always kindly disposed
<pb id="aleck139" n="139"/>
toward the Negro. I understood the purpose of
the visits was to secure the good offices of these
gentlemen in framing new laws for the government
of the state.</p>
        <p>The first one they called on came out and stood
uncovered on the doorsteps, while the spokesmen of
the Negroes explained the object of the visit. The
venerable gentleman thanked the delegates for this
expression of their confidence, and promised to do
all in his power to bring about peace and tranquillity
to the state and people.</p>
        <p>They made other visits with like results. “Bless
be the man who ne'er consents by ill advice to walk,”
is as applicable to a state or community as to an
individual. Ill advice seemed to have ruled the first
attempt at legislation in South Carolina after the
war; for the outcome of it was the enactment of a
code of laws which rendered the condition of the
Negroes in the state worse if possible, than it was
under slavery. These laws were very appropriately
called, “The Black Code.” It is strange that we
do not hear much of that code now. Possibly somebody
<pb id="aleck140" n="140"/>
is ashamed of it.</p>
        <p>That was the entering wedge. It opened the door
to the designing stranger, and made subsequent conditions
possible. It was not the work of Negroes,
but it opened the way for, and brought about, what
is called the “Carpet Bag” era, of which nothing
good can be said. It was “Bad,” very “Bad.”</p>
        <p>But the state was finally wrested from the hands
of the despoiler. The gallant Hampton came to
the rescue. About this time men who had found
things under the corrupt Carpet Bag System, “as
sweet as a daisy in a cow's mouth,” awoke to the
discovery that the “Civilization of the Cavalier and
the Roundhead was imperiled.” That discovery it
was said, was hastened by the thought that their
own heads were no less so. In fact, in Charleston
today, a highly respected gentleman and citizen is
living, who in a public speech said in effect, “Let us
not blame the Negroes; they have been but dupes.
Let us rather ornament the lamp posts of the city
with the suspended bodies of the rascals who have
used them for their own selfish purposes.”</p>
        <pb id="aleck141" n="141"/>
        <p>At that time I was a young man in the employment
of one of the oldest business firms in Charleston.
One day one of my employers called me into
his private office. (This gentleman was one of the
most conscientious men I have ever known. He had
been very kind to me, as indeed were all the members
of the firm. In all my varied experiences I have
never met with kinder treatment than I received at
their hands). After telling me of the deplorable
condition in which the state then was, he asked me
to support General Wade Hampton for governor,
in the coming election. I told him that while I
realized the truth of what he had said, I could not
vote for Hampton! Also, that in consequence of the
chaotic conditions in the state I had determined not
to vote at all. He then asked me if I would go to
hear General Hampton, (the general was to speak
especially to the Negroes of Charleston). This I
readily consented to do.</p>
        <p>I do not remember the date of this meeting. It
was however, a short time before the election which
took place on the seventh day of November, 1876.
<pb id="aleck142" n="142"/>
At the appointed time the Academy of Music was
crowded with the Negroes of the city. I could only
get standing room. We, the Negroes, could sit in
any part of the place we desired then.</p>
        <p>General Wade Hampton rose to speak—a splendid
man, a perfect specimen of manhood and vigor.
The hardships of the war through which he had
passed seemed to have had but little effect upon
him. He was a fluent speaker. In a forceful manner
he told of the sad condition in which the affairs
of the state then stood. Our only desire he said,
was to save our dear old state from utter ruin.
Then, raising his right hand to heaven he said these
very words as near as I can recollect, “If I am
elected governor, I swear to God that not one right
or privilege that you now enjoy shall be taken from
you!”</p>
        <p>I believe, in fact I know he was sincere, and while
I did not vote for him I honored his sincerity. But
he had made pledges for his people which they failed
to keep. The immediate result of his election was
the passing of restrictive measures aimed exclusively
<pb id="aleck143" n="143"/>
at the Negro. The brave old general lived to see the
day when he, like his pledges, was laid aside—a
soldier and a gentleman. It was well for him that
he was bred in the school of the soldier; well for
him that he was truly brave, else he could not have
stood up against it.</p>
        <p><q type="quote" direct="unspecified"><lg><l>“He was a man take him in all for all”</l></lg></q>
and I fear, we in South Carolina,
<q type="quote" direct="unspecified"><lg><l>“May not look upon his like again.”</l></lg></q></p>
        <p>But the end is not yet, for we hear of other
oppressive measures, such as disfranchisement and the
like. While this is true it is equally true that the
Negro has many friends among the southern white
people. Such offensive measures as the “Jim Crow
Car,” are not the works of the better element of the
southern people. Many Negroes owe their success
in business enterprises and other efforts they have
put forward for their advancement, directly to the
aid and encouragement they have received from those
who formerly held them in bondage.</p>
        <p>If there is a Negro problem before the American
people, it is one of the greatest propositions that
has ever confronted them. If either of the measures
<pb id="aleck144" n="144"/>
yet proposed could be carried out it would not settle
the Negro question, for I hear of no plan as yet to
remove the Negro from the face of the earth.
Though, perhaps even this would find many advocates.
If there is a Negro problem, a great
principle is involved in its settlement. There is no
question of the power of the white people of America
to dispose of it in any way they may choose, but,
to “settle it,” requires the exercise of justice and
equity.</p>
        <p>To many this problem seems more imaginary than
real, and the measures thus far proposed for its
settlement seem impractical to say the least of
them. One-sided settlements are hardly ever satisfactory
or conclusive.</p>
        <p>If there is a real vital question it affects the Negro
as well as the white man, and the simple principles
of humanity and “fair play” would seem to call for
the consideration and the interest of both.</p>
        <p>Why not call the brains of the Negro into the
council for its consideration? There is plenty of it
among the men of large calibre, many whose names
<pb id="aleck145" n="145"/>
are frequently before the public, and others whose
names are seldom heard. I believe they would
convince the country, and the world that this “Great
Lion” is no formidable than those which “<sic corr="Pilgrim">Pilgram</sic>” saw.</p>
        <p>When a boy I knew a man whom I greatly disliked.
I did not know anything wrong about him,
but there was something about his looks that repulsed
me. I never cared to meet him. Some time
afterwards I learned something of his history. He
had been shipwrecked once. Together with some
others he got into a small boat. As they pulled off
from the sinking vessel a strong swimmer reached
the boat and tried to climb in. This man violently
struck the hands of the swimmer away, and the poor
fellow sank beneath the waves. He justified himself
on the ground that there was already a sufficient
number in the boat, and if the swimmer had not been
prevented from entering the boat, the lives of these
would have been endangered. Perhaps he was right,
but I was more afraid of him than ever, for I could
not think of him as other than a murderer.</p>
        <pb id="aleck146" n="146"/>
        <p>Those who would drive the Negro away from this
country for which he has fought and bled, I regard
as worse than this man; for, we are all ready in the
boat, and they seek to cast us into the sea.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="aleck147" n="147"/>
        <head>CHAPTER XVI</head>
        <head>IN THE LAND OF THE PURITANS</head>
        <epigraph>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>
              <hi rend="italics">“ 'Tis a very good land I tell you,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
              <hi rend="italics">'Tis a very fine land indeed.”</hi>
            </l>
          </lg>
        </epigraph>
        <p>FOR years I had desired to visit “away down
east.” I wanted to see more of those people from
whom sprung the liberty-loving men and women,
who did so much for the amelioration of the condition
of the race. I had all ready witnessed the practical
working of their christian charity, and the
zeal through the labor of the gallant band, who
<pb id="aleck148" n="148"/>
immediately after the war came down to the south
with the bible in one hand, and the primer in the
other; for the purpose of enlightening and elevating
a benighted people.</p>
        <p>They have nearly all passed away, for it is more
than forty years since, but there remains as monuments
to their philanthropy, the schools and colleges
they established throughout the southland.</p>
        <p>With the view therefore, of becoming better acquainted
with these people, I availed myself of the
first opportunity that presented itself. Before this
I had visited some of their large cities, but the
population of cities do not afford the opportunity of
gaining such clear insight of a people as the country
does. For, in the cities they are on “dress parade,”
but in the country they are “at home” so to speak,
therefore, I wished to visit the rural or semi-rural
parts of the country.</p>
        <p>It is a “far cry” from the land of cotton and of
rice to the land of pie and beans. Yet, within
four days after leaving my home in South Carolina,
I found myself among the hills and mountains of one
of the eastern states, and I seemed to have landed
<pb id="aleck149" n="149"/>
in the very heat of the “pie belt,” as the following
story will show.</p>
        <p>Soon after my arrival I entered the services of a
gentleman, and was assigned to duty at some distance
from his residence. It was too far away for me
to return to the house for dinner, so I was provided
with an ample “dinner pail” which the cook
arranged for me each morning before I left the
house. The first day when I opened my pail at
noon, I found some delicious bread and butter, a
generous slice of cake, a piece of pie, and a bottle
of rich milk. You may be sure I enjoyed this very
much indeed. On the second day there were cake,
bread, and pie, and on the third day pie, bread and
cake.</p>
        <p>Now, I had thought I was somewhat partial to
pie, having been accustomed to an occasional bite
of that delicacy at home, but this was “too much.”
There were more than a dozen men engaged at the
place, and I discovered that each one of them was as
abundantly supplied with pie as myself. At this
<pb id="aleck150" n="150"/>
time there was a dear relative of mine engaged with
the same family. She saw how things were going
with me, and one night when I returned from work,
she surprised me with a dish of rice and tomatoes
cooked in southern style. It was a revelation to the
cook to see rice served in this manner, but it must
have been a far greater revelation to her to see how
I devoured it. Soon my relative returned to her
home in the south, and once more I found myself
eating pie every day like a native.</p>
        <p>The country was beautiful. It was in the famed
Connecticut valley. The coloring of the landscape
was all that could be desired, but there was a
lamentable lack of color in the population. This, you
must know, was utterly unbearable to any man from
South Carolina, be he white or black, unless it be our
senior senator. Therefore, I went to my employer
and told him if the situation in this respect could
not be changed, I could not remain in that part of
the United States. “You see sir,” said I, “I have a
wife and ten children, and ——.”</p>
        <p>The gentleman leaped making a complete revolution
<pb id="aleck151" n="151"/>
in the air. “Ten children!” he exclaimed,
“Where? What in the world!”</p>
        <p>Here he seemed to recover his equilibrium. He
had four or five children himself. I then explained
to him that it was not my purpose to bring all of our
children to Spring Lake, that there were ten
children in our family, but five of them were at home,
while the other five were doing well for themselves
in another part of the States; that it was my intention
to have my wife bring the five that were at
home as far as New York, leave four of them there,
and she and the youngest join me at Spring Lake
for the present. This arrangement suited him,
and he promptly handed me a check covering the
amount of their passage.</p>
        <p>Before leaving home I had arranged with my life
that if I found my situation satisfactory, I would
send for her, and that the arrangement for the children
indicated above, would be carried out. Consequently,
it was with a light heart I wrote as follows:—
<q type="letter" direct="unspecified"><text><body><div1 type="letter"><opener><salute>“Dear H.</salute></opener><p>I enclose check for — dollars. Come on
<pb id="aleck152" n="152"/>
north. Leave Tom, Dick, Harry and Betsy
Ann with G—— in New York, and you
and Matilda Jane join me at Sorwind.</p><closer><signed>Your devoted husband.”</signed></closer></div1></body></text></q></p>
        <p>But at the last moment our plans miscarried,
and my wife found it necessary to bring all of the
children with her.</p>
        <p>The arrival of seven Afro-Americans created
some excitement in the little town. I took my family
to the Spring Lake Hotel and registered:—Mr. Sam
Aleckson, wife and children, South Carolina. The
next morning I explained the situation to my employer.
He very readily, and with great kindness,
placed at our disposal a neatly furnished cottage
which he owned. How shall we ever thank the kind
hearted Miss M—— who came personally to see
that we were comfortably situated, and not in need
of anything?</p>
        <p>We began housekeeping under very favorable conditions.
There was a large apple orchard around
the house, and the children were as happy as larks.
They had never before seen such an abundance of
this delicious fruit. But our troubles were not yet
<pb id="aleck153" n="153"/>
over, as will hereafter appear.</p>
        <p>We were quite comfortably situated. I had forgotten
all about “pie,” and we had resumed our old
bill-of-fare: hominy, meat, bread, and tea or coffee
for breakfast; meat, rice, and some vegetable for
dinner, and bread, butter and tea for supper. One
day a kind neighbor stepped in to see my wife. “I
have just finished baking,” she said, “I have made
eight pies, a big pan of doughnuts, some cookies,
and a cake. What kind of pie did you have for
dinner?”</p>
        <p>“Well er, oh, we didn't have any pie today.”</p>
        <p>“Good land, Mrs. Aleckson! No pie? What do
you give those children to eat? Why, why!”</p>
        <p>When I got home I found my wife looking
worried. “What's troubling you?” I asked.</p>
        <p>“Pie,” she replied. Then she told me about the
visit.</p>
        <p>Next day I determined to consult a friend. After
telling him my story he looked at me incredulously.
“Well, now hain't you been having at least two kinds
of pie every day right straight along?” he asked.</p>
        <p>“Well no. You see er—er, um—” I began.</p>
        <pb id="aleck154" n="154"/>
        <p>“Gosh, man!” he interrupted, “If you were going to
stay here you will have to do it.”</p>
        <p>“Don't you think I might compromise on er say,
one every other day?” I asked helplessly.</p>
        <p>“No siree! They might let you off on one each
day, but I am not sure of that.”</p>
        <p>Again, kind friends came to the rescue on the next
night. When we were about to retire, there was a
loud rap on the door. Upon opening it I saw a large
delegation of neighbors, headed by our good friend
Mrs. B——. It was a surprise party, and they
brought us material enough to make pies every day
for two months!!!!</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="aleck155" n="155"/>
        <head>CHAPTER XVII</head>
        <head>THE TOWN OF SPRINGLAKE</head>
        <epigraph>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">“Maud Miller on a Summer's Day.”</hi>
          </p>
        </epigraph>
        <p>I FOUND myself enjoying remarkable prosperity
among a kind and hospitable people, who in
industry, thrift and economy were unsurpassed.</p>
        <p>Near our house there was a large meadow very
suggestive of “Maud Miller” and the “Judge.” The
picture was heightened when I saw a buxom lass at
work in the field. However, unlike Maud, she did
not handle a rake. The raking is all done now by
horse power. Instead she was provided with a fork
which she wielded in “tumbling” with as much speed
<pb id="aleck156" n="156"/>
and dexterity as any of the men engaged in the
work. She might, too, have proven an acquisition
to the household of a judge, as I learned that she
was a teacher of the higher branches in a high
grade school, and only took this method during
vacation to develop health and muscle. I felt sure
if she had any rude boys in her class they would get
the full benefit of it during the next school term.</p>
        <p>The superiority of New England for houses
cleaning and housekeeping is well known. In
house cleaning they excel. This they go about
with absolute devotion. The spring house cleaning
is scarcely over with when that of Fall begins.
Indeed they seem to go about the house continually
with hair broom and dustpan in hand. When
any stray particle of dust is found, they swoop
down upon it like a hawk does on a chicken, and
bear it away in triumph to the furnace.</p>
        <p>Ours is a great country; great in extent as well as
in achievement. But, while many hundreds of miles
may separate one community from another, still,
through the means of the press and general literature
<pb id="aleck157" n="157"/>
we can readily obtain intelligence of our most
distant neighbors. It is remarkable though, notwithstanding
these sources of information, how our
opinions, formed from what we have read of those
at a distance from us, are apt to be altered, or completely
changed by actual contact. It is also surprising
to what extent people speaking the same language,
living under practically the same institutions,
and forms of government, may differ in forms and
customs. Here as elsewhere there are many
peculiarities noticeable to the stranger.</p>
        <p>Springlake is a historic old town. The public
school system is perfect. This is a splendid public
library which adds greatly to the educational
advantages of the place. It boasts of several churches.
All the people in Springlake go to church, but I
found in traveling through the country, the same
falling off in church attendance as is noticeable in
other parts of the United States—especially among
the men.</p>
        <p>When I was a school boy, there was a picture in
one of my books that represented a man and woman
walking through the forest. The woman held a
<pb id="aleck158" n="158"/>
book in her hand, while the man carried a gun;
presumably a safeguard against attacks of wild breasts
or savages. Indeed if I remember rightly, there did
appear the figure of an Indian peeping stealthily
from behind a tree. The picture bore the title,
“Going to Church in New England.” The date
given was sometime in the early settlement of the
country. There seemed to be deep snow on the
ground.</p>
        <p>The devotion evinced by people attending church
under such unfavorable conditions attracted my
wonder and admiration. This was, no doubt, a
faithful representation of that period. But even in
the Land of Puritans this good old custom of the
fathers seems to be, “More honored in the breach
then in the observance.”</p>
        <p>Somehow mankind seems to require the scourge
and the lash. The great religious revival in the far
north was preceded by a distressing famine in that
country. The earthquake in California set on foot
a movement for the abolition of the saloon system.
While similar distresses in other parts of this country
<pb id="aleck159" n="159"/>
have caused the “Lion and the Lamb” to lie down
together, material prosperity seems to blind men's
eyes, and they forget to “Praise God from whom
all blessings flow.”</p>
        <p>Strolling along one day I came upon a neat and
substantial edifice. “What church is that?” I asked
of an old man who lived nearby.</p>
        <p>This ancient was more than eighty years of age.
Obligingly he told me the name of the church. “You
must have a large congregation.”</p>
        <p>“No, the number of persons who attended this
church when I was young and occupied places
reserved for the choir, alone outnumbered the entire
congregation that meet here now for worship at
irregular intervals,” he answered sadly.</p>
        <p>There was to be found however, many types of the
“Village Preacher,”
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“A man he was to all the country dear,</l><l>And passing rich on forty pounds a year.”</l></lg></q>
for I fell sick, and such a person with his good wife
drove six miles, through a snowstorm to bring me
words of hope and consolation. In common with
<pb id="aleck160" n="160"/>
those in other parts of our beautiful land, there are
many who hope and pray for, and confidently look
forward to a great religious revival. To that end let
all join, at least reverently in spirit, in the old
plantation hymn:—
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“Gib me dat old time religion</l><l>For 'tis good een de time ob trouble,</l><l>'Tis good wen de doctah gib me ober</l><l>'Tis good enuf fer me.”</l></lg></q></p>
        <p>It was summer when I arrived in Springlake, but
as I remarked before, summer does not linger here.
It was soon haying-time; a very busy season of the
year. They had hardly gotten the last load from
the meadow before the snow came! The snow seemed
beautiful—nay, 'tis beautiful. To get the full
effects of its beauty you should be in a nice warm
room looking out at it through double panes of
glass. For, if you have to shovel a half mile through
snow three feet deep, you are apt, if you are not a
very temperate man, to find yourself using strong
and uncomplimentary terms in reference to the poets
who sing of its loveliness.</p>
        <pb id="aleck161" n="161"/>
        <p>It was my duty to shovel snow; I who had never
seen snow more than two or three times in my life
before, and at that only an inch or two thick. I
had to run the furnace, too. This latter was more
to my liking. One day I was sent on an errand
during a snowstorm. My way lay down grade, but
I went heedlessly on chanting gayly, “Where the
snowflakes fall thickest, nothing can freeze.”</p>
        <p>I had begun to have some misgivings though, for
while the flakes were falling thick and fast, I was
already half frozen. Some minutes later I knew nothing
at all, for down I went, striking my head against
a rock. The little Eva of the household was playing
out in the storm with the thermometer about twenty
degrees below zero, just as happy as are South
Carolinian children when they go out gathering <sic corr="jasmines">jasmins</sic>
in May. She ran to my assistance, helped me
to rise, and led me back to the house. I was stunned
and dazed.</p>
        <p>When I regained consciousness they were bathing
an ugly cut on my head, from which the blood
<pb id="aleck162" n="162"/>
poured profusely. I had relied on Mr. Holmes. I
knew he was a humorist, but I confess I had taken
him seriously. It cost me about half a gallon of
good warm southern blood to discover that he was
only joking, for frequently under a very heavy covering
of snow, there is a bed of ice as smooth as
glass. This is put there by the intelligent New Englander
to impart that glad movement to his sleigh,
which is so entrancing when he goes out driving with
his best girl.</p>
        <p>One day when it was very slippery the laundress
went out to the clothesline. She was in danger of
falling. The chivalry of South Carolina was upon
me. I rushed to her assistance, and down I went at
her feet. I was in a splendid position to propose,
but being already married I refrained. “Arise
brave knight,” said the lady, “They at the castle
doth laugh at us.”</p>
        <p>My employer was an energetic man. He had built
a house on a rock;—rather on the place where a
rock used to be. “How are you ever going to build
<pb id="aleck163" n="163"/>
a house on that rock?” he was once asked.
Napoleon like—he answered, “There shall be no rock,”
and straightaway began blasting. The result was,
a palatial mansion that towers above the surrounding
houses, as the owner does above ordinary men in
energy and determination. Such a man as he had
no time to waste on a “tenderfoot” from South
Carolina, therefore, “When the gentle springtime
came” he told me I had better return to the sunny
south; offering very kindly to arrange for my return
passage. But, like the noble Frenchman, I said,
“Here I am and here I stay.” That is, I declined
his offer with thanks.</p>
        <p>“What are you going to do?” he asked.</p>
        <p>“Work sir,” I replied.</p>
        <p>He looked at me with an incredulous smile. There
was one however, whose kindness I shall never forget.
One who had not altogether lost confidence in
me, and through whose kind intercession I obtained
another situation. By this time I had become “inoculated,”
and was able to give entire satisfaction
<pb id="aleck164" n="164"/>
to my employers, who were also very kind gentlemen.</p>
        <p>The little town of Springlake (you won't find it
on a map, for it is hidden away between high mountains),
is a most beautiful and a typical New England
settlement. Nature has done wonders to
beautify the place. Some one has said the Garden
of Eden was in the United States. If it were not for the
fact that the mercury frequently falls to forty
degrees below zero, and that the summer passes like
a “watch in the night,” I would be inclined to believe
that this is the place.</p>
        <p>The people of Springlake—well, they are New
England people; and that is all that need be said.
The women are of course, better than the men, as is
the case all over the world.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <pb id="aleck165" n="165"/>
        <head>CHAPTER XVIII</head>
        <head>WRONG IMPRESSIONS</head>
        <epigraph>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">“Twix Twiddledum and Twiddledee.”</hi>
          </p>
        </epigraph>
        <p>In many parts of New England a very erroneous
impression prevails regarding the attitude of the
white people; I mean the white people of the south
toward the Negro. The general idea seems to be
that the average southern white man sallies forth
every morning with a bowie knife between his teeth,
and the first Negro he meets, proceeds to lay him
<pb id="aleck166" n="166"/>
open in the back, broil him on a bed of hot coals
and thus whet his appetite for breakfast. I found
too, that this impression is largely the result of the
thoughtless and altogether unnecessary talk of many
southerners visiting the North, who seem to feel it
<sic corr="incumbent">encumbent</sic> on them to disavow the very friendly relations
that exist between these two races in many
parts of the South, by expressions of indifference,
and intolerance, that in many instances are never
manifested at home. The northerners do not understand
that these expressions are only meant in a
sort of “Pickwickian” sense; hence the error.</p>
        <p>There is a northern family, a branch of which
lives in Dixie, who, before the war were large owners
of slaves. Some years after the war, a member of
the southern branch visited relatives in the North.
In answer to one of the children as to how their
slaves had been treated he replied, “Oh we treated
them about the same as we did our horses and
mules.”</p>
        <pb id="aleck167" n="167"/>
        <p>Such expressions do no possible good, and are frequently
productive of harm. As a matter of fact,
the southern family was noted for the very humane
manner in which they treated their slaves, and some
of those servants as well as the descendents of
others, are in the service of the family at this very
day.</p>
        <p>Again the little girl who had asked this question
was asked by one of the servants, how she liked her
southern relative. “Not one bit,” she replied, “I
can never like any one who speaks of treating people
like cattle.”</p>
        <p>“My father once shot ten of his slaves. Yes sir,
shot them down in their tracks because he thought
they were planning to run away!” and the young
“Munchausen” from the South, looked around with
an air of superiority on the Yankee youths to whom
he was speaking.</p>
        <p>Somehow the impression has gotten abroad that
the ordinary form used by the southern white people
<pb id="aleck168" n="168"/>
in addressing a Negro is “nigger.” Now, it is
well known that this term is never used by the better
class, for, “Though I be a native here and to the
manner born,” I can truthfully say I have never, in
a lifetime of fifty years, once had the term applied
to me personality; and curiously enough, the only
time I ever was offended by it happened in the North.
(This of course, was not at Springlake). At this
time I was employed at a large store in the country
town. One day a farmer came into the store. Now
when I was a little boy a kind lady school teacher
from New England had given me a little book that
contained the picture of the Yankee Overseer on a
southern plantation, “Who down in the South became
whipper of slaves.” Upon seeking this farmer
I thought that picture must have been taken from
life, for he bore such a remarkable likeness to it.</p>
        <p>“Whar's your nigger?” he asked, speaking to one
of the clerks, “I got some pertaters I want him to
help unload.”</p>
        <pb id="aleck169" n="169"/>
        <p>I had a good place, but I made up my mind that
before I gave him any assistance, I would throw up
the job. Therefore I went on with my work, and he
got his load off without any help from me.</p>
        <p>The term “nigger” is a much controverted one.
There is not the slightest doubt that it is offensive
to all intelligent, self-respecting Negroes, and is
never used by them. This term like any other, without
regard to their significance or lack of significance,
becomes offensive when applied in derision.
And, as has been the case with many other terms,
thus applied will lose its offensiveness in proportion,
as the object it shall secure the respect of those by
whom it is applied.</p>
        <p>I can not tell of all I saw and of all I learned in
New England: of industry, of economy, of thrift,
of wealth, of charity. It is a goodly land, and yet,
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“I love the land where the cotton plant grows,</l><l>The land where there is no ice.</l><l>I love the land where the jasmine blows</l><l>I love the land of rice.”</l></lg></q>
<pb id="aleck170" n="170"/>
Both north and south, ours is a great land, and we
are justly proud of it. I say “we” and “ours” for
I know not what else to say. When I am in the
South I feel at home, and as I gaze on the high hills
and lofty mountains of New England, I feel as ready
to sing, “My country 'tis of thee—” as any man in
America, for notwithstanding the untoward conditions
surrounding my people in many parts of this
land, the heart of the Negro is loyal.</p>
        <p>“Send him away,” say some. “God forbid it!” say
I. But, if that sad day should ever come, let the
Negro fold his arms. The great fear is that this
people are looking in one direction while going in
another. The danger is that they may run against
a wall.</p>
        <p>The financial, the labor, the agricultural, and even
the “servant girl” problems have been discussed pro
and con very thoroughly. This is one problem,
however, that does not seem to receive the attention
its gravity demands.</p>
        <pb id="aleck171" n="171"/>
        <p>Divorces have reached an alarming proportion in
some parts of the United States. It is noteworthy
that they so frequently occur where the sexes appear
to possess in even measures, those qualities that
would seem to make them of mutual assistance to
each other, and where similar educational advantages
should render them mutually agreeable.</p>
        <p>The separations too, are often sought on grounds
which look ridiculously inadequate. For instance;
Because breakfast was not ready promptly at fifty-seven
minutes after six o'clock, on the one side, or
some equally grave offense on the other side. Were
I called upon to say what, in my judgement, are the
strongest forces at work to <sic corr="undermine">undermind</sic> the foundation
of this great Republic, I should name, lynching and divorce.</p>
        <p>I for one, have no fear for the ultimate fate of
the Negro. My fears are for the American nation,
for, I feel as an American, and cannot feel otherwise.</p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>