<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % external-entities SYSTEM "./extEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY % internal-entities SYSTEM "./intEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY fedriccv SYSTEM "fedriccv.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY fedrictp SYSTEM "fedrictp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY fedricvs SYSTEM "fedricvs.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph> Slave Life in Virginia and Kentucky;</emph>
<emph>or, Fifty Years of Slavery in the Southern States of America:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Fedric, Francis </author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Sarah Reuning</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by</resp>
          <name>Chris Hill</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Chris Hill and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1999</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca.     200K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1999.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note anchored="yes">Call number  (T) E444 .F29      
(Treasure Room Collection, James E. Shepard Library, North Carolina Central University)</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="title page"> Slave Life in Virginia and Kentucky; or, Fifty Years of Slavery in the Southern States of America</title>
            <title type="cover"> Slave Life in Virginia and Kentucky</title>
            <author>Francis Fedric</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>115 p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>London</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Wetheim, Macintosh, and Hunt</pubPlace>
            <date>1863</date>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>All footnotes are moved to the end of paragraphs in which the reference occurs.</p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Fedric, Francis.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Virginia -- Biography.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Kentucky -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Virginia -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Kentucky -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Fugitive slaves -- Virginia -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Fugitive slaves -- Kentucky -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Virginia -- Social conditions.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Kentucky -- Social conditions.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- Virginia -- History -- 19th century.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- Kentucky -- History -- 19th century.</item>
            <item>Plantation life -- Virginia -- History -- 19th
century.</item>
            <item>Plantation life -- Virginia -- History -- 19th
century.</item>
            <item>Slaves' writings, American -- Virginia.</item>
            <item>Slaves' writings, American -- Kentucky.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2000-03-28, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-09-13, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-08-29, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Chris Hill</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-08-09, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Sarah Reuning</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="cover image">
        <p>
          <figure id="cover" entity="fedriccv">
            <p>[Cover Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="title page image">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="fedrictp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="title page verso image">
        <p>
          <figure id="verso" entity="fedricvs">
            <p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">SLAVE LIFE
<lb/>
IN
<lb/>
VIRGINIA AND KENTUCKY;</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="main">OR,
<lb/>
Fifty Years of Slavery
<lb/>
IN THE
<lb/>
SOUTHERN STATES OF AMERICA.</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>BY</byline>
        <docAuthor>FRANCIS FEDRIC,
<lb/>
AN ESCAPED SLAVE.</docAuthor>
        <docEdition>WITH PREFACE,
<lb/>
BY THE REV. CHARLES LEE, M. A.,
<lb/>
INCUMBENT OF HOLY TRINITY, HAVERSTOCK-HILL.</docEdition>
        <docImprint><pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace>
<publisher>WERTHEIM, MACINTOSH, AND HUNT,
<lb/>
24, PATERNOSTER-ROW,
<lb/>
AND 23, HOLLES-STREET, CAVENDISH-SQUARE.</publisher>
<docDate>1863</docDate></docImprint>
        <pb id="fredverso" n="verso"/>
        <docImprint><pubPlace>LONDON:</pubPlace> <publisher>WERTHEIM, MACINTOSH, AND HUNT,<lb/>
24, PATERNOSTER-ROW,<lb/>
AND 23, HOLLES-STREET, CAVENDISH-SQUARE.</publisher></docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="preface">
        <pb id="frediii" n="iii"/>
        <head>PREFACE.</head>
        <p>THE Memoir contained in the following pages may, I
believe, be thoroughly relied on as both genuine and
authentic. The Author, Francis Fedric, came to me
well recommended; and,
since he has been in London, has been continually
under my notice. I have every reason
to regard him (as his many friends represent him)
as an honest man, and a good Christian. His
testimonials are signed, amongst others, by the well-known
names of Dr. Guthrie, Dr. Alexander, and
Dr. Johnston, of Edinburgh; by Samuel Gurney,
Esq., of London; and by the Revs. C. J. Goodhart
and Gerald Blunt, of Chelsea. His references also
to ministers of religion, and others, by whom
he was employed in Toronto, to look after escaped slaves,
are completely satisfactory.</p>
        <p>The narrative itself will sufficiently disclose the
<pb id="frediv" n="iv"/>
sad tale of bondage and brutality, to which, for
fifty years of his life, poor Fedric was an
unfortunate victim. Escaped from slavery, and
finding his way to our own country, the encouragement
and assistance of sympathizing friends
enabled him to establish a lodging-house in
Manchester. That blight of slavery, however, which
had fallen so heavily on his previous life, still
seemed to pursue him—originating the war between
the North and the South (whether directly or
indirectly need not now be discussed). This was
immediately followed by the Manchester distress,
and Fedric at once lost the scanty subsistence he had
relied on. Being paralyzed in his hands by exposure
in the swamps, he is altogether unable to follow
handiwork of any kind. He is, however, a very
effective lecturer, and is fully capable of riveting
the attention of an audience by the romantic
details of his very interesting life. To help him
a little to thus obtaining a livelihood, and hoping
that, before long, by the aid of whatever funds
he may realize, he will be able to re-establish
himself in some kind of business, I have induced
a gentleman of this neighbourhood to take
down from his lips the memoir now given to the
public. It presents no one-sided view of slavery;
<pb id="fredv" n="v"/>
but the sunny side (if bondage has any bright side), as
well as its darker and more hateful tints, are all fairly
and truthfully depicted. When we think of quadroons,
and the detestable secrets with which their career is
shockingly and shamefully associated—when we think
of the enforced separation of the poor slave from his
wife, and of children from their parents,
notwithstanding all that can possibly be said of kind
and humane masters—when we add the liability of
being sold at any time into the hands of some hard-hearted
man, it is impossible not to shudder at so
accursed a system, and to pray God, in His own good
time, and best way, to smite off every fetter and set
the captives free.</p>
        <closer><signed>CHARLES LEE, M.A.,
<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Incumbent of Holy Trinity, Haverstock-hill.</hi></signed>
<date>8, <hi rend="italics">Camden-square, London, N. W.</hi>,<lb/>
Feb. 16, 1863.</date></closer>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="contents">
        <pb id="fredvii" n="vii"/>
        <head>CONTENTS.</head>
        <list type="simple">
          <item>CHAPTER 1.
<lb/>
Birth-place—Earliest Recollections—Slave Girl Flogged
—Fear of a Slaveholder during a Thunderstorm—
Father and Mother—Piety of Grandmother, a
Native African—Systematic Degradation of Slave
Children—Grandmother the first Person I saw
Flogged—Feeding of Slaves—Grandmother's
Happy Death—Cunning of Slaves . . . . . <ref targOrder="U" target="fred1">1</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER II.
<lb/>
Scene on Leaving Virginia for Kentucky—Cross the
Alleghany Mountains—Arrive at my Master's New
Plantation in Mason County—Become a House
Slave—Difficulties of Training me—A Burglar
Encountered—Social Affections of Slaves—A Sunday at
Chapel—Christmas, how spent by the Slaves—Slave
Patrols—Brutalizing Effect of Slavery upon the Ladies—
Consequences to the Slaves of Resisting Tyranny . . . . . <ref targOrder="U" target="fred14">14</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER III.
<lb/>
Negroes' Wedding—Vanity Exposed—Love of Long Words—Death
of my old Master—Cruelly treated by my dissipated young
Master—Slaves sold to pay my Master's Gambling Debts—
Slaveholder's own Children sold to Infamy . . . . . <ref targOrder="U" target="fred32">32</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER VI.
<lb/>
Corn Songs in Harvest-time—Conversion . . . . . <ref targOrder="U" target="fred47">47</ref></item>
          <pb id="fredviii" n="viii"/>
          <item>CHAPTER V.
<lb/>
Superstition of the Slaveholders—Slaves' Party—
Reckoning-up the White Folks . . . . . <ref targOrder="U" target="fred56">56</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER VI.
<lb/>
Labour of any kind Despised—Slaves the Badge of Distinction
among White Folks—Impudence of the
Ladies . . . . . <ref targOrder="U" target="fred73">73</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER VII.
<lb/>
First Attempt to Escape—Pursued by Bloodhounds—
Reach Bear's Wallow, a dismal Swamp—Conceal
myself in a Cavern—Driven by Hunger, give myself
up to my Master—Receive 107 lashes—Brutally
treated afterwards by my Master . . . . . <ref targOrder="U" target="fred75">75</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER VIII.
<lb/>
Produce of Kentucky—Climate of Kentucky—How the
Kentuckians spend the Winter—Fevers rage in
Summer—Slaveholders frequently administer Medicine
to Slaves—Anecdote—The Domestic Animals
—The Birds—Change of Property, how it affects
the Slaves—Resignation of a Female Slave . . . . . <ref targOrder="U" target="fred87">87</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER IX.
<lb/>
Cruelty to Slaves concealed from Strangers—Slaveholders
traduce the English—Slaves' opinions of the
English—Slaves always anxious to be Free . . . . . <ref targOrder="U" n="98" target="fred98">98</ref></item>
          <item>CHAPTER X.
<lb/>
An Abolitionist Planter contrives my Escape—My Escape
by the “Underground Railway”—Land in
Canada—Employed by the Anti-Slavery Society—
Marry—Arrive in England—Conclusion . . . . . <ref targOrder="U" target="fred101">101</ref></item>
        </list>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="main ">
        <pb id="fred1" n="1"/>
        <head>SLAVE LIFE IN VIRGINIA AND
KENTUCKY.</head>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
          <argument>
            <p>Birth-place—Earliest Recollections—Slave Girl Flogged
—Fear of a Slaveholder during a Thunderstorm—
Father and Mother—Piety of Grandmother, a
Native African—Systematic Degradation of Slave
Children—Grandmother the first Person I saw
Flogged—Feeding of Slaves—Grandmother's
Happy Death—Cunning of Slaves.</p>
          </argument>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <p>I WAS born in Fauquier County, in Old Virginia. My
remembrance, as nearly as I can reckon, extends back to
my eighth or ninth year of age. Some little striking incidents
occur, now and then to my mind, which happened when I
was somewhat younger even than that. My master's house,
a frame one, as it is called in America, was situated on a
gently rising ground, skirted by a small stream, emptying
itself into a deep rivulet, named the Cedar Run. This rivulet
was from twenty to
<pb id="fred2" n="2"/>
thirty yards wide, and during the rainy season dashed along
at a headlong pace, carrying with it trees and logs, and
overflowing very often large tracts of the surrounding
country, which was mostly of a level character. But
although near so fine a body of water, unlike most slaves, I
never learned to swim, which deficiency, as you will find in
the sequel, was one of the greatest misfortunes of my life.
Almost the first circumstance which I recollect is this. A
Mrs. R——, the wife of a Colonel R——, who had a large
plantation near to my master's, possessing four or five
hundred slaves, thinking she did not receive as many eggs
as she ought to do from the girl who collected them, asked
a negro whether she ought to receive an egg from each hen
a-day. “It would be a very good hen to lay an egg every
day,” replied the negro. Mistaking the meaning of the
answer, and imagining that she had been cheated, she gave
the poor girl a flogging every time she failed to bring the
required number, notwithstanding all her protestations of
innocence, and frantic entreaties not to be whipped. At last
a lady residing near, told Mrs. R—— that it was absurd to
expect anything of the kind. Colonel R—— one day sent his
servant-man to bring some groceries from the stores; when
he returned with the groceries, the Colonel said, “Why did
you bring me such inferior sugar as this?” The slave replied
that it was the same kind as he always had. The Colonel
said it could not be so, as the price
<pb id="fred3" n="3"/>
was too low, adding, “go and tell Mr. V. at the stores to
send me some better at once.” The slave went with the
message; Mr. V. smiled, and doubled the price on a new
bill, and sent the same sugar back. The Colonel looked first
at the bill, and then at the sugar. “Aye, this is something
like; this is as it ought to be,” he said. I merely relate this
anecdote to show what kind of persons the slave-owners, in
some instances, are, and that the slaves are not always kept
in subjection by a consciousness of their master's intellectual
superiority, for the slaves often, behind their backs, laugh at
their absurdities; but by a brutal system of terrorism
practised upon them from their very birth.</p>
            <p>A circumstance of a different nature is the next I can call
to mind. The weather was warm and sultry, scarcely a
breath of air stirred, and clouds of an inky blackness
began to rise from the distant uplands. Colonel R—— had just
returned from his tobacco-fields; the rain began to
fall in large drops. “Bring in the niggers!”
shouted Colonel R——. Some fifteen or twenty soon entered
his sitting-room, and were arranged around the Colonel,
who sat on a chair in the centre of the room. A distant
thunder-clap was heard. “Come nearer,” he cried “stand
close to me.” And there sat this master of 500 niggers,
cowering and trembling during the whole of the
thunderstorm. I was told that this was his invariable custom
whenever it thundered or lightened,
<pb id="fred4" n="4"/>
imagining that the Almighty would not strike the
slaves, consequently, being surrounded by them, the Colonel
thought he should certainly escape. We slaves often talked
together about this cowardice of Colonel R——'s, and
attributed it to his fear of God, on account of his sins,
although he was not a man remarkable for cruelty. But there
is, even in the minds of those most accustomed to slavery,
and born and brought up amongst it, a secret misgiving that
all is not right; although, when no danger is near at hand,
they will not only defend it, but eulogize it and expatiate
upon its advantages, even to the negro himself. My mother
told me that the Colonel thought the negroes could drive the
lightning away. However, whether his conduct arose from
this absurd notion or fear, it only proves the weak character
of this tyrant over the souls and bodies of men. My father
and mother were slaves, and worked for different masters.
My mother had nine children, two boys and seven girls. The
children are always the property of the mother's master.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Piety of Grandmother, a Native African.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>My grandfather and grandmother were stolen from
Africa and brought to Maryland, and taken from thence to
Virginia. My grandmother was taught by her young mistress
to repeat the Prayers and Liturgy of the Protestant Church.
My grandmother
<pb id="fred5" n="5"/>
could not read, yet in spite of every disadvantage,
she was very anxious about religion, and always eager to
impart any religious knowledge she might have acquired to her
children and grandchildren, or, in fact, to any one about her.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Systematic Degradation of Slave Children.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>My grandmother showed she was actuated on every
occasion by truly Christian principles. She wished very
much to teach me the Prayers and Liturgy which she had
learnt.</p>
            <p>But the conduct of my master caused great perplexity to
me, and made me indifferent about any such thing. My
master was in the habit of sending for all the slave children
from the cabins, then standing on the verandah, he would
say, “Look! Do you see those horses?” “Yes, Sir,” all
replied together. “Do you see the cows?” “Yes, Sir.” “Do
you see the sheep?” “Yes, Sir.” “Do you see the mules?” “Yes,
Sir.” “Look, you niggers! you have no souls, you are just
like those cattle, when you die there is an end of you; there
is nothing more for you to think about than living. White
people only have souls.” My mother, when I was a boy, had
no notion of what religion is, and to my good grandmother
alone I am indebted for any instruction I at this time
received. She was ever, as I have said before, anxious to
acquire religious knowledge and to attend prayer-meetings
as often as she possibly could; for doing so on one
<pb id="fred6" n="6"/>
occasion, I witnessed the first flogging I ever saw in my life.
But before I describe the flogging, I will explain about the
overseers. Many masters possessing large plantations, and
some hundreds of slaves, being desirous to divest
themselves as much as possible of the cares of managing the
estate, hire white men, at a salary of from 1,200 to 1,400
dollars per annum, to look after the whole property. These
are the best and most humane overseers. But other slave
proprietors, in order to save the cost of an overseer, but
chiefly to exact as much work as possible out of the niggers,
make a nigger an overseer, who if he does not cruelly work
the slaves is threatened with a flogging, which the master
cannot give to a white man. In order to save his own back
the slave overseer very often behaves in the most brutal
manner to the niggers under him. My grandmother's master
was one of the hard kind. He had made her son an
overseer.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">My Grandmother Flogged.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Consequently, my grandmother having committed the
crime of attending a prayer-meeting, was ordered to be
flogged by her own son. This was done by tying her hands
before her with a rope, and then fastening the rope to a
peach tree, and laying bare the back. Her own son was then
made to give her forty lashes with a thong of a raw cow's-hide,
her master standing over her the whole time blaspheming
<pb id="fred7" n="7"/>
and threatening what he would do if her son
did not <hi rend="italics">lay it on.</hi></p>
            <p>My master had about 100 slaves, engaged chiefly in the
cultivation of tobacco, this and wheat being the staple
produce of Virginia at that time. The slaves had to work
very hard in digging the ground with what is termed a grub
hoe. The slaves leave their huts quite early in the morning,
and work until late at night, especially in the spring and fall. I
have known them very often, when my master has been
away drinking, work all night long, husking Indian corn to
put into cribs.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Feeding of Slaves.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Slaves every Monday morning have a certain quantity of
Indian corn handed out to them; this they grind with a
handmill, and boil or use the meal as they like. The adult
slaves have one salt herring allowed for breakfast, during the
winter time. The breakfast hour is usually from ten to eleven
o'clock. The dinner consists generally of black-eyed peas
soup, as it is called. About a quart of peas is boiled in a
large pan, and a small piece of meat, just to flavour the
soup, is put into the pan. The next day it would be bean
soup, and another day it would be Indian meal broth. The
dinner hour is about two or three o'clock; the soup being
served out to the men and women in bowls; but the
children feed like pigs out of troughs,
<pb id="fred8" n="8"/>
and being supplied sparingly, invariably fight and quarrel
with one another over their meals. I remember when a boy
I did not care how I was fed, all I was anxious about was to
get sufficient. This mode of living is no doubt adopted for
the express purpose of brutalizing the slaves as much as
possible, and making the utmost difference between them
and the white man. Slaves live in huts made of logs of wood
covered with wood, the men and women sleeping
indiscriminately together in the same room. But English
people would be perfectly surprised to see the natural
modesty and delicacy of the women thus huddled together;
every possible effort being exerted, under such
circumstances, to preserve appearances—an unchaste female
slave being very rarely found.</p>
            <p>As a lad, hearty, and only poorly fed, I was always
delighted, if I could get any extra food; and my memory
seems to be very tenacious of anything having reference to
eating. I remember my mother baking some short cake, and
giving a piece to me, and a piece to my cousin, who was a
lad of my own age—eight or nine. I quickly dispatched mine;
but my cousin danced about before me, with his piece,
tantalizingly crying out, “I've got bread,
and you've got none! I've got bread, and you've got none!”
as rapidly as he could. I snatched the piece out of his hand,
and ran away from him, and soon had a portion in my
mouth. He threw himself down, and shouted, “I'm dead! I'm
dead!
<pb id="fred9" n="9"/>
I'm dead!” rolling, kicking, and screaming, as rapidly as he
could, for full ten or fifteen minutes. His mother gave me a
good beating that night. I felt very proud, however, and
bragged about what I had done, for some days; but I made
a great mistake soon after, which took me down a peg. I
was wrestling with one of the children, and threw him, and
hurt him, which displeased my grandmother, who said I
should get a flogging. I made haste in the evening to get into
the straw, and to cover myself with an old rug for the night.
I began to snore away, as hard as I could, as if fast asleep;
thinking they would not wake me to whip me. When my
uncle came in, my grandmother said, she had promised me a
good flogging, and she would be as good as her word. My
uncle said, “Where is he? I'll give it to him.” One of the
women said, “There he is, in his bed, asleep.” I snored
louder and faster. Another woman said, “He is not asleep.”
“But he is asleep.” “He isn't asleep.” “But, me tell you, he
be asleep.” Thus the women disputed. I thought I would
help myself a little, and said, “Yes, I be asleep!” I forgot.
But my uncle did not forget to take me out of the straw, and
to flog me well.</p>
            <p>My good grandmother's figure and general appearance
will always be indelibly impressed upon my mind. She was
above the middle height in England, and had short black
hair, inclined to curl, but very sparse upon the head.</p>
            <pb id="fred10" n="10"/>
            <p>My grandfather was about six feet in height, a well-proportioned,
muscular man; his hair was longer than my
grandmother's, and very thick upon the head: from his
appearance, I should suppose he was not of the same tribe
in Africa as my grandmother.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Grandmother's happy Death.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I never knew any woman so religious as my grandmother;
in all her oppressions and trials, her heart was full of the love
of God. In looking back now, after so many years, I am
filled with admiration of her conduct. When any troubles had
come to her, or when she had been whipped, she would
speak of her home, far away beyond the clouds, where
there would be no whipping, and she would be at rest. This
seemed to be her greatest, indeed her sole comfort, in the
hour of trial. This would be a source of joy, when seated, on
a Sabbath evening, under the shade of the peach trees, she
talked to her fellow-slaves, or to those who came from the
neighbouring plantations to see her. I was standing by, one
Sunday, and heard a woman say to her, “Selling is worse
than flogging. My husband was sold six years ago. My heart
has bled ever since, and is not well yet. I have been flogged
many times, since he was torn from me, but my back has
healed in time.”</p>
            <pb id="fred11" n="11"/>
            <p>My grandfather never was a professing Christian; his
greatest stumbling-block was the conduct of the
slaveholders, in buying and selling slaves, and then going,
after doing so, and perhaps partaking of the Sacrament.
“How,” he would say, “can Jesus be just, if He will allow
such oppression and wrong? Don't the slaveholders justify
their conduct by the Bible itself, and say, that it tells them to
do so? How can God be just, when He not only permits,
but sanctions, such conduct?” My grandmother would
reason with him, and endeavour to show him that the
slaveholders, at the Last Day, would have to account for
their actions, and that we slaves should look to our own
conduct. However, no real, abiding change, such as had
been produced upon my grandmother, ever was effected
upon him.</p>
            <p>As the closing scenes of life approached, my
grandmother's faith became stronger and stronger. She
looked forward to the future, when all would be set right;
and delighted to talk about heaven, and to ask those about
her to be good, that they might all meet together in the next
world. Her illness was short; and ladies came to her
bedside, for her good life was a subject of conversation
even among them; and many a truthful lesson did they learn
from her. She bore everything with Christian fortitude; her
sons and daughters stood around her deathbed, receiving
her blessing, or listening to her good advice. I was not
present when she
<pb id="fred12" n="12"/>
died, but my mother said, she died gently and happily, as if
her last hours were a foretaste of what was in store for her.</p>
            <p>A badge of aristocracy among slaveholders is the number
of slaves they hold, and white people of equal fortune are
not generally allowed to visit slaveholders, who look down
upon them with a species of contempt. One remarkable fact
which I wish to impress upon my readers is this, that the
white men born in those districts in America where slaves
are held, are just as capable of bearing the heat as the
black men. And the proof is this, that in the harvest-time,
when the two are working together in the fields, the white
men can actually beat the negroes at the work, and very
often the black man has to give up, and is laughed at by the
white labourer. They say, “Only give us sufficient wages,
and we will work by the side of any nigger alive.” It is quite
shocking to hear slaveholders distorting even the Bible itself
to prove that a negro alone was made for hard work.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Cunning of Slaves.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I remember a slave, who was not treated very well with
respect to food and other things, when he had done his
work being lectured by his mistress on the duties of a slave,
she telling him that in proportion to his obedience and
servility as a slave he would be loved by God. One day, on
receiving
<pb id="fred13" n="13"/>
the Bible from his mistress, he began as follows,—
“Give your slaves plenty of bread and meat, and plenty of hot biscuit in
a morning, also be sure and give him three horns of
whiskey a-day.” “Come, come, stop that, Bob,” his
mistress cried; “none of your nonsense, Bob, there is
nothing of that kind there.” Bob, throwing down the book,
said, “There, there, take it yourself, read it; you says a
great deal more than you'll find there.” Slaves are all of
them full of this sly, artful, indirect way of conveying what
they dare not speak out, and their humour is very often the
medium of hinting wholesome truths. Is not cunning always
the natural consequence of tyranny? One of my master's
neighbours had lost two pigs. The overseer was ordered to
search the cottages to try to find any portions of the missing
pigs. An old woman, who had one of the pigs, seeing the
overseer coming to search, and having heard that the
person who had stolen them was to receive 200 lashes
when discovered, threw the pork, blood and all, into a tub
of persimum, which is a kind of beer in America. The
overseer, having searched diligently all the nooks and
corners of the cabin, even having opened the bed, said,
“Well, Molly, I am very glad to find that you have not got
the pigs. Now draw me some beer.” Molly, with trembling
hand, drew a bowl of it. “Why does your hand tremble,
Molly?” said the overseer. “Because,” said Molly, “old
woman has been sick all night.”
<pb id="fred14" n="14"/>
“Very good, this beer,” said the overseer; “draw me
another.” Molly now was frightened that the blood would
betray her. She drew another bowl.
“This is the very best beer I ever in my life tasted,”
said the overseer; “here is a shilling for you. I shall be sure and tell
your master, Molly, that you have not got the pigs.”</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
          <argument>
            <p>Scene on Leaving Virginia for Kentucky—Cross the
Alleghany Mountains—Arrive at my Master's New
Plantation in Mason County—Become a House
Slave—Difficulties of Training me—A Burglar
Encountered—Social Affections of Slaves—A Sunday at
Chapel—Christmas, how spent by the Slaves—Slave
Patrols—Brutalizing Effect of Slavery upon the Ladies—
Consequences to the Slaves of Resisting Tyranny.</p>
          </argument>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <p>I HAD arrived at about my fourteenth year of age, without
having been engaged in any definite employment,—running
errands, tending the corn-fields, looking after the cattle, in
short, doing anything and everything in turns about the
plantation. My master had determined to give up his
plantation in Virginia, and to go to another in Kentucky. I
shall never forget the heart-rending scenes which I
witnessed before we started. Men and women
<pb id="fred15" n="15"/>
down on their knees begging to be purchased to go with
their wives or husbands, who worked for my master,
children crying and imploring not to have their parents sent
away from them; but all their beseeching and tears were of
no avail. They were ruthlessly separated, most of them for
ever. Still, after so many years, their wailings and
lamentations and piercing cries sound in my ears whenever I
think of Virginia.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Cross the Alleghany Mountains.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>We had to pass over the Alleghany mountains to
Wieland, in New Virginia. Wieland lies on the banks of the
Ohio. We set out with several waggons and a sorrowful
cavalcade on our way to Kentucky. After several days'
journey, we saw at a distance the lofty range of the
Alleghany mountains. My master, by the use of his glass,
had told us two or three days before that the mountains
were near. They now became visible, looming in the
distance something like blue sky. After a while we
approached them, and began to pass over them through
what appeared to be a long, winding valley. On every side,
huge, blue-looking rocks seemed impending. I thought, if let
loose, they would fall upon us and crush us. Our journey
was, I may say, almost interrupted every now and then, by
immense droves of pigs, which are bred in Kentucky, and
were proceeding from thence to Baltimore,
<pb id="fred16" n="16"/>
and other places in Virginia. These droves contained
very often 700 or 800 pigs. When we halted for the night
we lit our fires, and baked our Indian meal on griddles;
sometimes the cakes were very much burnt, but these,
together with salt herrings, were the only food we had. Our
drink was water from the surrounding rills running down the
mountain-sides. In fact, torrents of water, arising from the
ice and melting snow, were rushing
down in hundreds of directions. The scenery was
what I may term hard and wild, the tops of the
mountains being hid by the clouds, in many places
rolling far beneath. But my thoughts in passing
over these mountains then were rather those of
amazement and wonder than those of a curious and
inquiring mind, such as now, with some enlightenment, I
might have. I only remember large flights of crows, and
what are called in America, black
birds, which make a loud screaming noise, instead
of a beautiful note, like the English bird of this
name.</p>
            <p>Two or three times during the night, when we
were encamped and fast asleep, one of the overseers
would call our names over, every one being obliged
to wake up and answer. My master was afraid of
some of us escaping, so uncertain are the owners of
the possession of their Slaves. The masters are
ever feverishly anxious about the slaves running
away, and this being always continued, necessarily
produces an irritability characteristic of the slave-holder.
<pb id="fred17" n="17"/>
The howling of the wolves, and other wild
animals, broke the solemn stillness which reigned
widely around us. Now and then my master would
fire his gun to frighten them away from us, but we
never were in any way molested. Perhaps the fires
kept them at a distance from us.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Arrive at my Master's new Plantation in Mason County.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>From <sic>Welland</sic> we took boats to Maysville, Kentucky. My
master had bought a farm in Mason County, about twenty
miles from Maysville. When we arrived there we found a
great deal of uncultivated land belonging to the farm. The first
thing the negroes did was to clear the land of bush, and then
to sow blue grass seed for the cattle to feed upon. They then
fenced in the woods for what is called woodland pasture.
The neighbouring planters came and showed my master how
to manage his new estate. They told the slaves how to tap the
sugar-tree to let the liquid out, and to boil it down so as to
get the sugar from it. The slaves built a
great many log-huts; for my master, at the next slave-market,
intended to purchase more slaves.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Become a House-slave.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I was taken into the house to learn to wait at table—a
fortunate chance for me, since I had a
<pb id="fred18" n="18"/>
better opportunity of getting food. I shall never
forget my first day in the kitchen. I was delighted to see
some bread in the pantry. I took piece after piece to skim
the fat from the top of the boiling-pot, overjoyed that I could
have sufficient.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Difficulties of Training me.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>My mistress took a fancy to me, and began to
teach me some English words and phrases, for I
only knew how to say “dis” and “dat,” “den”
and “dere,” and a few such monosyllables. It is a
saying among the masters, the bigger fool the better
nigger. Hence all knowledge, except what pertains
to work, is systematically kept from the field-slaves.
My mistress made me stand before her to learn
from her how I was to take a message. “Now,
Francis,” she said, “I want to make you quite a
ladies' man. You must always be very polite to the ladies.
You must say, ‘I will go and tell the ladies.’” I repeated
some hundreds of times, “I will go and tell the ladies.” After some days'
training, she thought she had made me sufficiently
perfect to deliver a message. “Francis!” “Yes,
marm,” I said. “Go and tell Mrs.—— that I shall
feel obliged by her calling upon me at half-past twelve o'clock
to-morrow.” “Yes, marm,” I said; and she made me repeat the message some
dozens of times. When perfect, as she thought, away I went,
repeating all the way, “Missis will
<pb id="fred19" n="19"/>
feel obliged by your calling upon her at half-past
twelve; Missis will,” &amp;c., until I met a gentleman
on the road who had seen and heard me repeating
the words over and over again before I saw him.
He called out, “Whom are you talking to?” I
jumped, and every word jumped out of me, for I
forgot it all. I ran back to my mistress and told
her I had forgotten it, but did not tell her the
reason why. “Just as I thought,” she said. The
teaching re-commenced, and, after some scores of
repetitions of the message, I started again, determined
that no one should hear me. I went whispering
the words all the way as fast as ever I could,
hastened into the lady's house, and hurriedly said
the words over two or three times to the lady, and
then ran back. Upon one occasion my mistress's
sister said that she wanted me to do some washing,
and gave me a dress to wash. I picked it up, and
put it on the wash-board, and immediately tore it
on purpose. She had left the room to fetch some
thing for me to wash it with, and, returning in a
minute, “Francis,” she said, “I hope you have not
begun to wash that dress yet?” “Oh, yes, missis,
I have,” I answered, holding up the torn dress at
the same time. “You blockhead!” she said, “I
shall never be able to teach you anything; I can
never drive anything into your thick skull. I have
a good mind to take a stick and kill you, you
worthless good-for-nothing.” But I was sufficiently
cunning by this stratagem to escape what appeared
<pb id="fred20" n="20"/>
to me the degrading womanly occupation of washing. In the
same way I acted when she attempted to teach me to milk
the cow. By no possible ingenuity could she, as she thought,
make me learn the right side of the cow to milk upon;
consequently, the cow invariably kicked when I was on the
wrong side, and upset the milk-pail. I saw one day some
cotton drying by the fire; I thought I would try whether I
could make it blaze, thinking, if it did, I could easily put it
out. I lit a stick, and set the cotton on fire. Every one in and
about the house rushed to the kitchen to extinguish the
flame; after some time they succeeded. I told my mistress
that a spark had fallen upon it and made it blaze. This story
seemed to satisfy her at the time. Some weeks afterwards
my mistress called me into her room, and gave me some
treacle and bread, and asked me if it was sweet. “Yers,
missis,” I said. “We are very good friends now, are we not?”
“Yers, missis.” She gave me two more pieces. “Now,
Francis,” she said, “don't friends always tell one another
the truth?” “Yers, missis.” “Don't friends tell each other every
thought?” “Yers, missis.” “Now, Francis,” she added, fixing
her eyes fully upon mine, “did you not set fire to the cotton?”
“Ye-ye-yers, missis,” I replied. “Now you shall have a good whipping for your lies
and for setting fire to the cotton,” she said; and sure enough
I was flogged right soundly.</p>
            <p>My mistress's sister was writing a letter one
<pb id="fred21" n="21"/>
morning; I looked over her shoulder, and thought what pretty
marks she was making. Having half finished one line, she put
her pen down and left the room to take her breakfast. I
took the pen up, and completed the line with crooks, and
commenced another line, and ended just under the part
where she had left off. I was examining what I had done,
thinking it looked better and more distinct than her's, when in
darted my mistress's sister, and began to beat me most
unmercifully. “What has he done? what has he done?”
cried my uncle, who was cook, and utterly at a loss to know
what I had been doing. “The young rascal has been spoiling
my writing,” she said, laying on all the time, until my back was
severely cut. I thought at the time it was cruel. A day or two
afterwards my mistress took me into her room and talked to
me kindly; she said it was wicked to do such things as those
for which I had been flogged. I was surprised at a good deal
of what she said, for I did not understand exactly in what the
wrong consisted.</p>
            <p>I merely mention these three or four little incidents to
show how grossly ignorant I was, and that what is known to
a child mixing in civilized society is a complete mystery and
puzzle even to men working in the fields in a state of slavery.
It was found utterly impossible to get on with me in the
house unless I was instructed in something. But the most
debasing ignorance is systematically kept up amongst the
outdoor hands,
<pb id="fred22" n="22"/>
any one manifesting superior intelligence being weeded out of
the working gang, lest he should spoil the other slaves. My
mistress was anxious to teach me to pick some wool. “You
must pick it very quickly,” she said. “Your master's brother
will watch you, and tell me if you don't.” She placed me in a
room where my master's brother's portrait hung on the wall.
“There he is,” she said, “looking at you. Now, mind, you must
pick away as fast as you can. Don't stop, or he will come and
tell me.” I thought it was my master's brother, and worked as
hard as I could until I became very thirsty. I stopped, and
looked anxiously at him, went up to him, and, putting my hand
to my head, “Please, massa,” I said, “may I go and get a
drink?” He did not answer. This occurred for several days,
until at last I thought I never saw a man who did not wink. I
went slowly and cautiously up to the picture, and, after some
hesitation, I felt it and turned it over, looked at the back, and,
whilst thus engaged, in came my mistress. “What are you
doing there,” she said, “I will teach you to mind your work;”
and she took the horsewhip and gave me a good flogging.
She was no doubt annoyed that I had found out she was
fooling me. When working within sight of the picture
afterwards, I would say, “I's not going to work. You don't
know nothing. They don't give us nothing. I's not going to
work for nothing.” And I did not half
<pb id="fred23" n="23"/>
work, only just doing a little. A remarkable
incident occurred soon after I was in our new
house, and it evidently had a great deal to do with
making me a favourite amongst them.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">A Burglar Encountered.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I was sleeping one night, when my master was from
home, on a mat near the foot of my mistress's bed. She
called out to me, “Francis, Francis!
get up! get up! come here! look!” pointing out
of the window, “there is some one trying to break
into the house.” I saw a man climbing up a ladder,
which he had placed against the wall. “Missis,
oh, missis!” I said, “I'll put de poker in de fire,”
and in an instant I thrust the poker into the fire.
We stood watching the movements of the man, my
mistress trembling and being very frightened. He
ascended the ladder, and cautiously opened the
window, and put his arm in as if feeling. I seized
the poker out of the fire and thrust it up his sleeve.
“Oh, Lord!” he cried out, and instantly threw
himself down from the top of the ladder and disappeared,
no doubt well burnt.</p>
            <p>My mistress was delighted with my quickness in
devising in a moment such a scheme, and always took great
pleasure in relating the adventure to any visitors, so that I
was looked upon as a faithful and intelligent lad.</p>
            <p>Another incident tended also to attach my mistress
<pb id="fred24" n="24"/>
to me. My grandfather had gone to the mill for some
meal. He got drunk, the bag of meal fell from the horse's back,
and the pigs devoured the meal whilst my grandfather had
gone for some one to help him. When he returned home, my
master said, “Will, where is the meal?” My grandfather said,
“Don't ask me about the meal; the pigs have eaten it up.” My
master said, “I will give you a beating.” “You had better try it
on,” said my grandfather. They both began to wrestle with one
another. My master tried to get hold of the hair of my
grandfather, but, being nearly bald, this was impossible; but
my grandfather pulled the hair out of my master's head by
handfuls. I danced about in great distraction to see them
contending with one another, and ran and got a bowl of water,
and threw it on them both, which instantly made them gasp
and desist from the struggling. My master fetched the
horsewhip, and threatened to kill me for throwing the water,
but, at the intercession of my mistress, I escaped. My mistress,
the next day, said, “Francis, what made you throw that water
on your master and your grandfather?” I said, “Missis, don't
you know?” She said, “No.” I said, “When ladies and
gemmens come to see you and the dogs come wid 'em, dey
come in de kitchen, and our dogs jump at 'em, dey get to
fighting, den my uncle he throw de cold water on dem, and
dat part 'em. Missis, I thought you always know'd dat we
parted de dogs in dat way.”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <pb id="fred25" n="25"/>
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Social Affections of Slaves.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I went about this time to see several person
baptized, all adults, both black and white, and
I shall never forget the anxiety displayed by the
black men when their wives were being dipped.
The black men protested that their wives were held
under the water longer than the white women,
although there was not a shade of difference in the
time of the immersion. The affection of the men
for their wives and children would be noticed by any
one. The men never, if possible, allow their wives
to carry the young ones, but are always delighted to have
them in their arms, and to walk by the side of the women.<ref targOrder="U" id="ref1" n="1" rend="sc" target="note1">*</ref></p>
            <note id="note1" n="1" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref1">*A slave possessing nothing, and rarely hoping
to possess anything, except a wife and children, has all his affections
concentrated upon them; hence often, when torn from them, he
pines away and dies.</note>
            <p>The social affections are so strong, that no hard usage
can weaken them. Indeed, brutality, on the part of the
master, seems to make the slave cling closer and closer;
thus intensifying his sufferings, when the “trader” comes to
tear him away.</p>
            <p>In answer to a question, which has often been put to me,
I may here state, that no slave-children
are ever christened: a name is agreed upon between the
black woman and her mistress, or her mistress's daughters.
They take a Bible in their hands, and say, let <hi rend="italics">such</hi> be the
name.</p>
            <p>When I was about fourteen years of age, my
mother whipped me, because I had hurt one of my
<pb id="fred26" n="26"/>
sisters in play. I felt very ill after it, and thought
if I feigned to be dead, she would get a whipping. I began
to groan out. The women in the spinning-room ran out,
thinking I was dying. My mistress's sister, and two young
lady visitors, ran into the room; and, feeling
I was cold, and noticing that I breathed but
slowly—which I was managing, as well as I could,
taking a good gasp every time—they turned me over.
They also were afraid that I was dying. They began
to cry, which brought my mistress into the kitchen. She began to
cry, at first; and then, looking <sic corr="steadfastly">stedfastly</sic> at me, “Stand by,”
she said, taking out a pin, unseen by me,
she thrust it right into me. I struck out with my feet,
and sent a black woman, who had been rubbing me,
sprawling on the ground. I holloed out, “Oh! oh! oh!”
until they could hear me a mile off. Some ran away instantly,
from fear; others burst into loud fits of laughter;
my mistress joining in the laugh. “Well,” she said, “I never
saw such an artful nigger in all my life.
He is always up to of his tricks.”</p>
            <p>I had a tolerably good time of it now, being
in the kitchen, helping to cook, or waiting at the table,
listening eagerly to any conversation going on; and thus
learning many things, of which the field-hands were totally
ignorant.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Sunday at Chapel.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>On Sundays we were sent to chapel; all the
<pb id="fred27" n="27"/>
slaves being seated in the galleries, apart from the white
people.</p>
            <p>Mr. Pain, the minister, was absent from chapel, one
Sabbath; but, appearing next Sunday, he explained his
absence, by informing his congregation that two of his slaves
had run away. Immediately, there was a general lamentation,
because brother Pain had lost his slaves; and many
calculations were made about their value. The following
Sunday, the minister, with a face radiant with joy, announced
to his audience, that his slaves had been brought back to
him. On hearing this, a hubbub of delight pervaded the
chapel; but, when he further informed them, that he had
administered to each eighty lashes, in order to teach them
their duty, and to deter them and others from running away in
future, the audience were overjoyed; one saying to another,
“Brother Pain has done perfectly right. He has taught them,
and all the slaves who hear, what their duty is, and how they
are to be dealt with, if they attempt to run away.”</p>
            <p>When first I came to England, I was surprised to find
every clergyman and Dissenting minister, to a man,
denouncing slavery, as contrary to Christianity. But the
reverse is the case in the Southern States of America. All
the Methodists, Baptists, and Independents—in fact, every
minister of religion—uphold slavery, and defend it by
passages from the very same Book out of which the clergy,
in this country, make quotations to condemn it.</p>
            <pb id="fred28" n="28"/>
            <p>I leave the natural inference to be drawn by themselves;
merely suggesting, that, perhaps, self-interest may, in other
cases also, cause fatal delusions and compliances.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Christmas, how spent by Slaves.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>About Christmas, my master would give four or five
days' holiday to his slaves; during which time, he supplied
them plentifully with new whiskey, which kept them in a
continual state of the most beastly intoxication. He often
absolutely forced them to drink more, when they had told
him they had had enough. He would then call them together,
and say, “Now, you slaves, don't you see what bad use
you have been making of your liberty? Don't you think you
had better have a master, to look after you, and make you
work, and keep you from such a brutal state, which is a
disgrace to you, and would ultimately be an injury to the
community at large?” Some of the slaves, in that whining,
cringing manner, which is one of the baneful effects of
slavery, would reply, “Yees, Massa; if we go on in dis
way, no good at all.”</p>
            <p>Thus, by an artfully-contrived plan, the slaves themselves
are made to put the seal upon their own servitude. The
masters, by the system, are rendered as cunning and
scheming as the slaves themselves.</p>
            <p>“Joe,” said a master, “if you will work well for me, you
shall be buried in my grave.” The slave
<pb id="fred29" n="29"/>
said nothing, in reply; but thought, Massa is a bad man,
and that he would not like to be buried near him. The slave
thought he had been too near his
master, all his life, and had rather be away from him, when he
died. Seeing the slave idling, “Joe,”  shouted his master, “have
you forgotten what I promised you, if you work well?” “No, Massa, me
bemember; but me don't want.” “What for, Joe?”
“Because de debbil might some day come, and steal me
away, in mistake for you, Massa.” His master was silent on
this subject ever afterwards.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Slave Patrols.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>On New Year's Day ten white men are chosen, who are
called patrols; they are sworn-in at the court-house, and
their special duty is to go to the
negro cabins for the purpose of searching them to see
whether any slaves are there without a pass or permit from
their masters. The head of the ten is called Captain. He
sends the men into the cabins, waiting outside himself at
some distance with the horses, the patrol being a mounted
body. If any slaves are found without a pass they are
brought out, and being made to strip are flogged, the men
receiving ten and the women five lashes each.</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="fred30" n="30"/>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Brutalizing Effect of Slavery upon the Ladies.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>This is looked upon as great fun by the patrol and the
white people, young ladies and gentlemen from the
verandahs laughing and enjoying the scene. When I have
told of my being flogged, I often hear persons in this
country say, “Oh! but he should not have whipped me in
that manner; I would have resisted, I would have done this,
that, or the other.” But, my dear reader, I will tell you a true
story, what I know and saw.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Consequences to the Slaves of Resisting Tyranny.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Two slaves, who were perhaps not so completely cowed
as the rest, said to my master, who was about to flog them,
“No, massa, we not going to be flogged so much, we won't
submit.” “What is that you say?” my master said, starting
back. They repeated, “We are not going to allow you to
beat us as you have done.” “How will you prevent it?” he
said. “You'll see, you'll see, massa,” speaking half
threateningly. He was evidently afraid of them. When they
went home at night he spoke mildly to them, and told them,
“he only wanted them to do their work, that it would be
better if they could get on in the fields without him. Don't
hurry yourselves, my boys.” For two or three days he never
went much among them,
<pb id="fred31" n="31"/>
and when he did he spoke in a very quiet, subdued manner.
But mounted negroes were sent with letters to all the
plantations around. The slaves had been sent to a species of
barn where they shell the Indian corn. Suddenly above a
hundred slaveholders, armed with revolvers, marched from
different points, and at one time, evidently agreed upon,
surrounded the place where the negroes were. All the
slaves were ordered out, and the two who had refused to
be flogged were made to strip, and my master first had one
tied up, and flogged him as hard as he could for some time,
the poor slave calling out, “Oh, pray, massa! Oh, pray,
massa!” My master, pausing to take breath, one of the
slaveholders said, “I would not flog him in that way, I would
put him on a blacksmith's fire, and have the slaves to hold
him until I blew the bellows to roast him alive.” Then my
master started again and flogged until the poor fellow was
one mass of blood and raw flesh. The other was tied up and
served in a similar manner, one of the slaveholders saying he
ought to be tied to a tree and burnt alive. And now I would
ask, How can an unarmed, an unorganized, degraded,
cowed set of negroes prevent this treatment? The
slaveholders can and do flog them to death, and nothing
more is thought of it than of a dog being killed, and not so
much.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <pb id="fred32" n="32"/>
          <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
          <argument>
            <p>Negroes' Wedding—Vanity Exposed—Love of Long Words—Death of my old Master—Cruelly treated by my dissipated young Master—Slaves sold to pay my Master's Gambling Debts—
Slaveholder's own Children sold to Infamy.</p>
          </argument>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <p>THE first wedding which I remember being at certainly
afforded a good deal of amusement to me and others who
were present. I will, therefore, endeavour to describe it as
well as I can. The black man was named Jerry, and his
intended, Fanny. Jerry went to learn from Fanny's master
and mistress whether they would allow him to take her for
his wife. Fanny's mistress said, “Jerry, do you love her?”
He said, “Yers, marm.” “How do you know?” she said.
“Because me lub ebery ting on de plantation since me lub
Fanny,—de hosses, and all de tings on de plantation seems
better dan anybody else's. It seems to me Fanny got de best
missis in de country; me give most anyting if me could fall
into dis family,” said Jerry. Mr. Ord, Fanny's master, said,
“Come, Elizabeth, you must let him have her.” She said,
“Well, Jerry, you can have her, but we don't whip Fanny,
and you must not whip her.” Jerry bowing low, said,
“No, missis, if she never get a whipping till me gives it to
her, she'll neber get one, cause me lub
<pb id="fred33" n="33"/>
her too well to whip her.” Fanny's mistress said, “Because I
know if you were to whip her, she would not deserve it, and
I should never let you come on the premises again.” Jerry
replied, “By de time me have had her one year me know
you'll give me as good name as Fanny, for Fanny's mistress
shall be my mistress, and Fanny's master shall be my
master.” “Well, Jerry,” said Fanny's mistress, “you must
bring January's Tom or Morton's Gilbert to marry you, two
weeks from this night, if your master and mistress consent,
and tell your master and mistress that we have agreed to
give Fanny a supper, and we shall be very glad to see them,
since we are going to have a great many ladies and
gentlemen come to see the wedding.” Jerry in ecstasy
answered, “Yers, marm; thank you thousand and thousand
times, missis.”</p>
            <p>On the Saturday night appointed, Jerry went with
January's Tom to Fanny's master's. Jerry had a pair of
black trousers of his master's on, a little too large in the leg,
and a coat fitting very well, except that the tails were too
long; some one had given him a white waistcoat and a white
cravat, which was only a little less stiff than its wearer, and a
pair of white gloves, contrasting very much with the coal
black of Jerry's shining face. Fanny's mistress had dressed
her in a white muslin gown and very nice light shoes, her
head being decked with white and red artificials, made from
goose's down, which accorded well with her woolly
<pb id="fred34" n="34"/>
hair. Her bridesmaid was attired somewhat similarly, only
with not quite so many artificials. The happy pair were
seated in the middle of a large kitchen; Fanny had a very
pleasant countenance, a tawny complexion, and was
admired very much by her mistress and her friends, but
most of all by Jerry. He was asked if he would have her.
“Yers, indeed me will,” he said. Fanny was very bashful, and
spoke very low, and bowed. “Come, where is the parson?”
said her mistress, “it is time for him to be marrying
them.” “Parson!” some of the ladies called out, “Parson!”
At the sound of this dignified title, bolt upright jumped
January's Tom. “Marm, yers, marm.” “It is time for you to
marry them.” “Yers, marm, yers, marm!” said Tom.</p>
            <p>Now, January's Tom not being able to read, had listened
to his master's grandson reciting the marriage service until he
had it by heart, and as luck or mischief would have it, the
Prayer-book was laid upside down. Tom now commenced,
with the book in this position, to read the service, amidst the
infinite mirth of the ladies, who every now and then glanced
over his shoulder at the inverted book. Tom, however,
thinking all the laughter was at the happy couple,
persevered in the most solemn manner. Having finished
repeating the marriage service to the satisfaction of all,
Fanny's mistress said, “Parson, make him salute his wife.”
Now, Jerry being a field hand, knew nothing about this
grammar word “salute.” “What! do what?”
<pb id="fred35" n="35"/>
he said. “Salute your bride,” said the parson. “Wh-a-t! do
what?” said Jerry, as much puzzled as if it had been a
Chinese word. Perceiving the perplexity, Fanny's mistress
said, “Parson, tell him to kiss his wife.” The parson said,
“Kiss your wife.” Jerry said, “Do you mean me to ‘bus’ her?
What for you not tell me afore?” and instantly seizing
Fanny round the neck, he made the room resound with the
smacks, amidst the roars of laughter of all, until Fanny's
mistress told him that would do, when, reluctantly, he
desisted. Fanny's master then wished Jerry to tell the
company how he got his wife. He said, “Ladies and
gemmen, me will tell you how me come to see Fanny. Me
went to see Mr. Marshall's Charlotte for two years, she
promised to hab me. Me promised to bring her a straw
bonnet, but de grubs had eaten all on my truck-patch (the
piece of ground allotted by some good masters for the
slave to cultivate for his own benefit). Me went to see
Charlotte on de Sunday, and she asked me to sit down in
de kitchen, and she say, ‘Where de bonnet?’ Me told her
de reason me didn't get it. And she said, ‘You worthless
nigger, you can't hab me,’ and she
run de fork into my arm, and me run home and say, ‘De debble
must be in dat gal.’ Me went, to see good many gals after
dat; me see good many like Charlotte, but me wouldn't
stop, me leave, till me come to see Fanny. She seem to be
good natured gal, but she hab me come to see her good
<pb id="fred36" n="36"/>
while afore she say she hab me. Me tell her dat me lub her
better dan all de people in de world. She say, ‘if she could
believe dat, she would hab me.’ Me said me would treat her
kind, and treat our chilun kind; but when me say dis about
de chilun, she ran out of de house, and me didn't see her of
three or four weeks apter dat. Me den see her, but me
didn't tink dat she would run de fork in my arm, as
Charlotte did. Fanny ask me ‘if me rebberence her.’ Me
say, ‘Fanny, don't know what you mean.’ She say, ‘Massa
rebberence Missis, and you must rebberence me.’ Me say,
‘Oh, yes, to be sure; and you be good to me?’ She say, ‘If
you be kind to me, I be kind to you.’ And dat made me feel
happy.”</p>
            <p>Thus ended Jerry's interesting account of his courtship.</p>
            <p>Then about 300 slaves, friends of the happy couple, sat
down to a good supper. Fanny being a house-servant,
presided, with considerable tact, at the head of the table,
and Jerry at the opposite end, in rather a confused and
awkward, but good-humoured manner. A bottle of whiskey
was on the table, and Jerry was called upon to give a toast.
“Me don't know what you mean by de toast,” said Jerry.
Fanny's mistress said, “We'll tell you.” He said, “Me can't
talk, but me do as well as me can. Dis is my heart dat will
be talking to you. Me hope Fanny's massa and missis neber
will come to want, and me hope all de family, when dey die,
<pb id="fred37" n="37"/>
may go to heben, and me hope dat Fanny and myself neber
will be parted from each other, nor our chilun.” At the last
word all laughed heartily.</p>
            <p>During twenty years after their wedding, I knew this
happy pair, with a dutiful family of sons and daughters
around them. A kind Providence had granted poor Jerry's
prayer; a good master and an indulgent mistress were
vouchsafed to them, on the same plantation their children
were, some of them working, and the little ones playing
about; and my sincere wish is, that no change of their
master's fortune may send the “dealer” to tear asunder those
whom affection of the purest kind had so firmly cemented
together.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Vanity Exposed.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Having been made cook, I got on for some time tolerably
well, sending up the dinners in first-rate style, exerting myself
to the utmost, for I had a favour to ask, and I knew the best
way to get at the hearts of my master and mistress was
through their stomachs. I had noticed three or four watches
hanging about the house, and one very old-fashioned, and
evidently not of much value; I thought I should like to have it
to wear on a Sunday at chapel. I asked my mistress, who
was friendly towards me, to intercede with my master for
the loan of it. “Yes, Francis,” she said; “be a good fellow;
manage the dinners well.” “Yers, missis,” I said, “I am sure
<pb id="fred38" n="38"/>
to do that.” And, sure enough, all was dished up carefully. In
the course of a short time the watch was given to me, and
off I went to the chapel, having made myself as spruce as
possible. On my way, every time I passed any one I pulled
my watch out to display it. I walked up into the gallery of the
chapel and looked down upon my fellow-negroes without
watches as ten degrees beneath me in point of dignity.
During the sermon I pulled out the watch several times,
catching the eye of the preacher. At last he paused, and,
looking at me, he said, “Ah! that must be a very good
negro, a very good negro indeed; I see he has got a watch.
Pray (looking stedfastly at me) can you tell me what o'clock it
is?” I looked hastily at my watch, and replied, “Five
o'clock.” Instantly there was a loud laugh through the chapel,
for it was only half-past twelve. My mistress ridiculed me
afterwards, and said she could teach me nothing, and all my
fellow-negroes made me a perpetual butt for their jokes.
The fact was, I knew no more about the watch than the
watch, knew about me.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Love of Long Words.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I one day overheard a young lady who was visiting at our
house say to my mistress, “My intended will be here in a
few days, I wish you would have everything put right.” I
thought, “When he comes, I'll hear what he has to say to
you, and then
<pb id="fred39" n="39"/>
I shall know how to court the black girls when I go out.”
Two or three days afterwards the young gentleman arrived,
and I was on the alert to hear what he had to say to the
young lady. I thought I heard him say, “Miss, I do admire
your beauty, I respect your ingenuity, and I adore your
virtue; I do love you, because I cannot help it.” I was
listening like a cat watching for a mouse. I repeated what I
had heard over and over again until I got it perfect, and I
then felt proud, because I thought I should have something
superior to say when I went among the girls. But the next
time I listened I made a great mistake. I heard a gentleman
who was talking to some young ladies say, “I learnt my
grammar well when I went to school.” In a few minutes
afterwards I heard him make use of the word characteristic.
I thought he said, “cutting up sticks.” I was delighted, and
went on repeating “cutting up sticks.” I thought it was a nice
grammar word to speak when I should go among the black
girls. The first time when I went among some who were
having a little spree, a black man was seated by a very nice
girl I knew; I said to her, “I can speak grammar;” she said,
“You can? what is it?” I said, “It is cutting up sticks.” She
gave the black man a blow with her elbow and said, “Go
away; I am going over to sit with our friend; he can speak
grammar; it's cutting up sticks.” It was sometime before
I found out my mistake. I knew I could not learn anything
<pb id="fred40" n="40"/>
from the slaves, and I was, therefore, constantly
listening to the gentlemen and ladies, and endeavouring
to learn as many words as possible from
them. Many times I was mistaken, but, right or
wrong, I could march into a room with full-blown
importance, and cut out a dozen men by bumptiously
repeating anything which I had overheard.
The black girls always like something which is a little better
than common conversation.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">The Death of my old Master.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I was about twenty-eight or thirty years of age when my
old master was seized with a fever. He was upwards of
seventy years of age, and, prior to this, had been a healthy
man. No change whatever of a serious nature had taken
place in his conduct or conversation; indeed, a few days
before the fever, he had been cursing and blaspheming at a
slave-woman. When he was taken ill, the family wished to
send for a doctor. “No,” he said, “I know it is of no use; I
shall die.” However, one was sent for. Some of the planters,
his neighbours, came, to be with him, and, as the fever
increased, he began to rave and cry out, “Oh, take it away!
take it away!” One of the slaveholders was very much
frightened, for he also thought that he saw something. In a
few days my master died, but he never made any sign that
he had any hope for the future. His will had been recently
made, his slaves
<pb id="fred41" n="41"/>
were apportioned to his four children, and his son said that
his father had never wished them to free the slaves.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Cruelly treated by my dissipated young Master.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>My young master now was about twenty-four or twenty-five
years of age; he did not seem to mourn much for his
lost father, but said, “You slaves have been living upon
white bread, but I will soon teach you something different
from that. You shall now have the treatment proper for
niggers. I have been wishing for some time to tan your hides
for you.” Of course his discourse was interlarded with
oaths and curses, with which I cannot pollute my page. I
soon began to wish that I was a field-hand, for day by day
he was drunk and hanging about the kitchen.</p>
            <p>I began to have a terrible life of it. A few years before his
father's death, he had led a riotous, dissipated life, losing
money by gambling, and then borrowing. All his neighbours
were astonished at the amount of his debts, for the sheriff's
officers were constantly on the premises. No doubt the
state of his circumstances made him drink more.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Slaves Sold to pay my Master's Gambling Debts.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The slaves are in general the first property parted with, a
dozen likely niggers bringing in a tolerably
<pb id="fred42" n="42"/>
round sum. Aunt Aggy was the first slave sold; she had a
little boy eight or nine years of age, and when she was
driven to the chained gang on the road he ran after her,
crying, “Mother—mother; oh my mother.” My master
ordered one of the slaves to fetch him the waggon whip. He
took it and lashed the poor little fellow, round the neck and
legs until he fell down, then he flogged him until he got up
again, and still my master cut at him until the boy shrieked
out dreadfully, writhing in agony, the blood streaming down
his little legs. His mother was driven off with the gang, and
her little boy never saw her more. In three or four weeks
after this, a “trader” was seen talking to my master. The
slaves were in a state of consternation, saying, “Is it me? Is
it me? Who'll go next?” One of the slaves said, “See, they
are selling the pigs to go to Virginia. They don't seem to
care, but we can't be like pigs, we can't help thinking about
our wives and children.”</p>
            <p>The slaves were all taking their dinners in their cabins
about two o'clock. My master, the “trader,” and three other
white men walked up to the cabins, and entered one of
them. My master pointed first to one, and then to another,
and three were immediately handcuffed, and made to stand
out in the yard. One of the slaves sold had a wife and five
children on another plantation; another slave had a wife
and three children; and the other had a wife and one
child. My master, the dealer, and
<pb id="fred43" n="43"/>
the others then went into another large cabin, where there
were eight or nine women feeding the children with Indian-meal-broth.
My master said, “Take your pick of the
women.” The poor things were ready to drop down.
The “trader” said, “I'll give you 800 dollars for that one.” My
master said, “I'll take it.” The “trader,” touching her with a
long cane he had in his hand, said, “Walk yourself out here,
and stand with those men.” She jumped up and laid her child
out of her arms in an old board-cradle, and walked to the
chained men. My master said, “Take your pick of the rest.”
The “trader” looked round and said, “I'll give you 750
dollars for that one.” “I'll not take it,” my master replied.
“What will you take?” said the “trader;” “what is the least
you'll take?” My master answered, “Not a dollar less than
I took for the other.” The “trader” paused a minute or two,
surveying her, and then said, “I'll give it.” Then, holding his
cane out, said, sternly, “Walk out of this, and stand with
those men.” She laid her child in one of the women's arms,
and speaking low, said, “Take care of my child, if you
please.” The women were so terrified that they dared not
say a word, for three or four weeks before this time this very
“trader” had given 1,000 dollars for a slave to a Mr. W., a
neighbouring planter. The slave had said it was hard for him
to be carried away from his wife and children, the “trader”
instantly beat him so unmercifully, that Mr. W. thought
<pb id="fred44" n="44"/>
the poor slave would be killed, and said, “You are not going
to throw away your money in that way, are you ?” “I don't
care,” said the “trader,” “I have bought him, he is mine, and
for one cent. I would kill him. I never allow a slave to talk
back to me after I have bought him.” He had beaten the
poor fellow so severely that he could not walk. The “trader”
said to Mr. W. he should be passing that way again in
about a month, and if they would take care of the slave and
cure him, he would pay the damage, and either call or send
for him. The three men and two women were driven out to
the gang on the highway, and chained together, two and
two. We never heard of them again. One of the wives left
behind was nearly driven mad, she took it so to heart. No
doubt those sent away were quickly used up in the sugar
plantations and rice swamps of the South. But the masters
soon replace the dead ones with others. There is an
abundant supply in the markets of the
breeding States, of all kinds, field and house hands, some
bringing long prices, so that a slaveowner finds the sale of
them the readiest mode of extricating himself from any
pecuniary difficulty.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Slaveholders' own Children Sold to Infamy.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Even his own child, by a black woman or a mulatto,
when the child is called a quadroon, and is very often as
white as any English child, is frequently
<pb id="fred45" n="45"/>
sold to degradation. I knew a —— S——, Esq., he sold his
own daughter, a quadroon, to a gentleman of New Orleans
for 1,500 dollars, who said “he only wanted her to be
housekeeper for him, and to be mistress over the other
niggers, and to do just as he wanted her, for he had no
wife.” This startled the poor girl, who said she would not
have cared if she had been going to marry him. She took it
very much to heart, and so did her unhappy mother,
especially when she heard her child say,
“Oh, mother, I hope there will come a day when those left
behind will not be forced as I shall be.” And surely that day
is being heralded in now, amidst the flaming homesteads and
the slaughter of the sons and dishonour of the daughters of
these heartless oppressors of their fellow-man, aye, of their
own flesh and blood. There are thousands upon thousands
of mulattoes and quadroons, all children of slaveholders, in
a state of slavery. Slavery is bad enough for the black, but it
is worse, if worse can be, for the mulatto or the quadroon
to be subjected to the utmost degradation and hardship, and
to know that it is their own fathers who are treating them as
brutes, especially when they contrast their usage with the
pampered luxury in which they see his lawful children revel,
who are not whiter, and very often not so good-looking as
the quadroon.</p>
            <p>I remember, one bright moonlight night, a fine young
man, a quadroon, striping his shirt off, and
<pb id="fred46" n="46"/>
showing me his lacerated back. He cried, and I cried too, to
see him in such a state. He said the next time his father
attempted to flog him, he would run a dirk-knife through
him. He produced the dirk, and said he had bought it on
purpose. I begged of him not to think of such a thing. He
swore he would; and the next time his master was going to
whip him, he pulled out the dirk, and ran through the house.
His father sold him soon after this. I saw him afterwards. He
had been sold to a hatter, and a smarter or more
gentlemanly-looking young fellow I have rarely seen. He
said, “Oh, Francis, I am so glad that you persuaded me not
to kill my master. I have got a good master now, and, if not
sold, I shall be happy.” That which in my own case weighed
most heavily upon my mind was the thought that all my work
was for another; and that even the flesh and blood, the bone
and sinew, which God had given me, I could not call my
own. I never had parted with them, but another called them
his. Heaven will, no doubt, in its own good time, redress this
shameless, cruel, infamous wrong.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <pb id="fred47" n="47"/>
          <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
          <argument>
            <p>Corn Songs in Harvest-time—Conversion.</p>
          </argument>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <p>IN harvest-time, thirty or forty years ago, it was
customary to give the slaves a good deal of grog,
the masters thinking that the slaves could not do
the hard work without the spirits. A great change
has taken place now in this respect; many of the
planters during harvest give their slaves sixpence
a-day instead of the whiskey. The consequence is
there is not a fifth of the sickness there was some
years ago. The country is intensely hot in the
harvest-time, and those who drank grog would
then want water; and, having got water, they
would want grog again; consequently, they soon
either were sick or drunk. All round where I
dwelt the sixpence was generally substituted for
the spirits; the slaves are looking better, and there
are fewer outbreaks in the fields. In the autumn,
about the 1st of November, the slaves commence
gathering the Indian-corn, pulling it off the stalk,
and throwing it into heaps. Then it is carted
home, and thrown into heaps sixty or seventy yards
long, seven or eight feet high, and about six or
seven feet wide. Some of the masters make their
slaves shuck the corn. All the slaves stand on one
side of the heap, and throw the ears over, which
<pb id="fred48" n="48"/>
are then cribbed. This is the time when the whole country
far and wide resounds with the corn-songs. When they
commence shucking the corn, the master will say, “Ain't you
going to sing any to-night?” The slaves say, “Yers, Sir.”
One slave will begin:—
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“Fare you well, Miss Lucy.</l><l>ALL. John come down de hollow.”</l></lg></q>
The next song will be:—
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“Fare you well, fare you well.</l><l>ALL. Weell ho. Weell ho.</l><l>CAPTAIN. Fare you well, young ladies all.</l><l>ALL. Weell. ho. Weell ho.</l><l>CAPTAIN. Fare you well, I'm going away.</l><l>ALL. Weell ho. Weell ho.</l><l>CAPTAIN. I'm going away to Canada.</l><l>ALL. Weell ho. Weell ho.”</l></lg></q></p>
            <p>One night Mr. Taylor, a large planter, had a corn
shucking, a Bee it is called. The corn pile was 180 yards
long. He sent his slaves on horseback with letters to the
other planters around to ask them to allow their slaves to
come and help. On a Thursday night, about 8 o'clock, the
slaves were heard coming, the corn-songs ringing through
the plantations. “Oh, they are coming, they are coming!”
exclaimed Mr. Taylor, who had been anxiously listening
some time for the songs. The slaves marched up in
companies, headed by captains, who had in the crowns of
their hats a short stick,
<pb id="fred49" n="49"/>
with feathers tied to it, like a cockade. I myself was in one of
the companies. Mr. Taylor shook hands with each captain
as the companies arrived, and said the men were to have
some brandy if they wished, a large jug of which was ready
for them. Mr. Taylor ordered the corn-pile to be divided
into two by a large pole laid across. Two men were chosen
as captains; and the men, to the number of 300 or 400,
were told off to each captain. One of the captains got Mr.
Taylor on his side, who said he should not like his party to
be beaten. “Don't throw the corn too far. Let some of it
drop just over, and we'll shingle some, and get done first. I
can make my slaves shuck what we shingle tomorrow,”
said Mr. Taylor, “for I hate to be beaten.”</p>
            <p>The corn-songs now rang out merrily; all working
willingly and gaily. Just before they had finished the heaps,
Mr. Taylor went away into the house; then the slaves, on
Mr. Taylor's side, by shingling, beat the other side; and his
Captain, and all his men, rallied around the others, and took
their hats in their hands, and cried out, “Oh, oh! fie! for
shame!”</p>
            <p>It was two o'clock in the morning now, and they
marched to Mr. Taylor's house; the Captain hollowing out,
“Oh, where's Mr. Taylor? Oh, where's Mr. Taylor?” all
the men answering, “Oh, oh, oh!”</p>
            <pb id="fred50" n="50"/>
            <p>Mr. Taylor walked, with all his family, on the verandah; and
the Captain sang,
<q type="verse" direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“I've just come to let you know.</l><l>MEN. Oh, oh, oh!</l><l>CAPTAIN. The upper end has beat.</l><l>MEN. Oh, oh, oh!</l><l>CAPTAIN. But isn't they sorry fellows?</l><l>MEN. Oh, oh, oh!</l><l>CAPTAIN. But isn't they sorry fellows?</l><l>MEN. Oh, oh, oh!</l><l>CAPTAIN.  But I'm going back again,</l><l>MEN.  Oh, oh, oh!</l><l>CAPTAIN. But I'm going back again.</l><l>MEN. Oh, oh, oh!</l><l>CAPTAIN. And where's Mr. Taylor?</l><l>MEN. Oh, oh, oh!</l><l>CAPTAIN. And where's Mr. Taylor?</l><l>MEN. Oh, oh, oh!</l><l>CAPTAIN. And where's Mrs. Taylor?</l><l>MEN. Oh, oh, oh!</l><l>CAPTAIN. I'll bid you, fare you well,</l><l>MEN. Oh, oh, oh!</l><l>CAPTAIN. For I'm going back again.</l><l>MEN. Oh, oh, oh!</l><l>CAPTAIN. I'll bid you, fare you well,</l><l>And a long fare you well.</l><l>MEN. Oh, oh, oh!</l></lg></q></p>
            <p>They marched back, and finished the pile. All then went to
enjoy a good supper, provided by Mr. Taylor; it being usual to
kill an ox, on such an occasion; Mr., Mrs., and the Misses
Taylor, waiting
<pb id="fred51" n="51"/>
upon the slaves, at supper. What I have written cannot convey
a tenth part of the spirit, humour, and mirth of the company; all
joyous—singing, coming and going. But, within one short fortnight, at least thirty
of this happy hand were sold, many of them down South, to
unutterable horrors, soon to be used up. Reuben, the merry
Captain of the band, a fine, spirited fellow, who sang, “Where's
Mr. Taylor?” was one of those, dragged from his family. My
heart is full when I think of his sad lot.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Conversion.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>One day, when I was between twenty-five and thirty years
of age, an elderly lady, who was on a visit to my mistress,
came into the kitchen, and, after speaking to me about things in
general, for a short time, she took a Bible out of her pocket,
and said, “Would you like to hear me read something about
our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ?” I said, “Please, marm.”
She said, “If your mistress should get to know that I have been
reading to you, she would be very angry, and drive me from
the house.” She then read that portion of Scripture, where it
says, “All that forget God shall be turned into hell.” There was
such an evident sincerity about the good old lady, and her
manner was so kind, that every word which she either read or
spoke to me went to my heart. Here was truth
<pb id="fred52" n="52"/>
presented to me, by one whose only possible object could be
to do me good.</p>
            <p>I listened eagerly to every word which fell from her lips.
She told me, if I believed on the Lord Jesus Christ, I should be
saved; that God was no respecter of persons; that He loved
all His people, black as well as white. She told me, if I loved
God, and showed it by my conduct, He would love me, and at
last take me to heaven, to live with Him; that the Gospel was
commanded, by our Saviour, to be preached to all people; and
that He died for the sins of all men, that they, through Him,
might be saved. And many such encouraging passages, she
either quoted, or gave me the substance of. She promised,
that, when she came again, she would give me a spelling-book.</p>
            <p>She said, “I know you are allowed to go to the chapel,
but there the preachers only preach what will be agreeable to
your masters. The real naked truth of the Gospel, the glad
tidings that were intended to comfort all hearts, you never
hear.”</p>
            <p>All this conversation was carried on in a secret manner, lest
my master or mistress should have the slightest hint of any such
thing.</p>
            <p>At night, I turned over in my mind every word which had
been said; and I resolved, from that time forward, to put my
trust in God, and get to know as much as I possibly could
about Jesus Christ.</p>
            <p>The good lady, true to her promise, brought me
<pb id="fred53" n="53"/>
the spelling-book, and told me to lay it aside, and when she
came again, she would teach me one word at a time. I put it
into the pastry-room, where my mistress's sister found it. She
asked me, what I was doing with such a book? She said, for
one cent she would break my head with it; and that she would
make my master give me one hundred lashes, if she ever knew
me to have another.</p>
            <p>When the good lady who had given me the book learnt
what had been done and said about it, she was very much
grieved, and said, she was truly sorry that the Bible should be
kept a sealed book from the poor benighted heathen.</p>
            <p>Kind readers, you who have been anxious to send your
missionaries to the East and the West, to the North and the
South, to men of every nation and race, what can be your
opinion of those who deliberately keep millions of men in the
grossest ignorance? It cannot be pretended for one moment,
truthfully, that we are not capable of understanding if we were
taught. I myself am a living witness against such an absurdity;
after fifty years of age I have learnt to read and write. No, no.
It is not our stupidity, but the slaveowners' lust of power and
gain which makes them directly oppose the precepts of our
Lord and His apostles to teach all to search the Scriptures. It is
only by keeping the poor slaves in brutish ignorance that they
can uphold slavery. Let the slaves have the same opportunity
as the freemen
<pb id="fred54" n="54"/>
to learn to read and write, and nothing could prevent their
rising, and freeing themselves. But I would have my readers
mark the effect of the accursed system even upon the gentle
nature of woman. Imagine any lady in this country threatening
100 lashes because a poor servant was found trying to read;
why the whole country would ring with the brutality of such a
thing.</p>
            <p>The kind lady who gave me the spelling-book removed to
Lexington, and I never saw her again; but her words of
sympathy and goodness will abide with me as long as life lasts.
But Providence, who had by her hands sown the good seed,
soon sent another friend to nurture it, and endeavour to bring it
to maturity. A planter, a truly Christian gentleman, a neighbour
of my master's, saw me standing by the road-side one Sunday.
“Come to my house this evening,” he said. I replied; “Yes,
Sir;” but I was not aware what he wanted me for. When it was
dark, that very evening, I went to his house. “Does your
master know that you have come?” he said. “No, Sir,” I
answered. “I am glad of that,” he said, “he would be
annoyed if he knew what I wanted with you. I wish to speak to
you about your soul.” He put several questions to me
concerning religion; but he soon discovered by my answers
that I was relying too much upon myself and upon works. He
read the words to me, “Believe on the Lord Jesus Christ, and
thou shalt be saved, thou and thy house.” What the gentleman
<pb id="fred55" n="55"/>
said to me made me very anxious about religion, and
about my salvation. I was very distressed in my mind, and the
next night I went from the house of my master down into a
valley to pray, and to think about heaven and everything which
had been read to me. Oh, how I longed for the Lord to change
my heart, and make me fit for His heavenly kingdom. I came to
a spot in the vale where the roots of the trees protruded some
distance out of the ground. I bruised my knees against these,
thinking that the Lord would the sooner convert me, out of pity
for the way in which I had hurt myself I prayed earnestly in the
best way I could to God to enlighten my mind and to save me.
I went in the course of a few days to the kind planter, and told
him all I thought and felt, and showed him how I had bruised
my knees. He told me that the Lord looked at the heart, and
wished <hi rend="italics">that</hi> to be changed, that self-mortifications and cuttings
and woundings were what the heathens did to propitiate their
false gods, but that a broken and a contrite heart was alone
acceptable to God. That I was not to put my faith in works,
but in the Lord Jesus our Saviour. Thus it was that I came to a
true knowledge of the Almighty and of religion. Through many
and many a trial, and in deep suffering and anguish, both of
body and mind, what I learnt from this good man has been a
source of comfort to me. The weary burden of slavery has
been lightened by it, my days of freedom are
<pb id="fred56" n="56"/>
rejoiced by it, and to it as to an anchor I hope to hold fast until
the closing scenes of life.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
          <argument>
            <p>Superstition of the Slaveholders—Slaves' Party—Reckoning
up the White Folks.</p>
          </argument>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <p>THE slaveholders, as a body, are very superstitious, and are
continually haunted with fears of ghosts and goblins. No one
ought, therefore, to wonder at the poor ignorant slave being
imbued with fear of what he considers supernatural; but an
anecdote, which I have omitted to relate, will best illustrate
what I mean.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Superstition of the Slaveholders.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>It was a common practice among our slave-women to say
to their children, if they shouted out, “Ole boy, I'll pully your
ears!” the old boy would answer, “Ha! ha! Ha!” you might
often, therefore, hear the children calling out these words in the
fields in their play. One day when they were returning from
the bush, crying out, “Ole boy, I'll pully your ears!” I got
behind a large hogshead, and cried out as dismally as I could,
prolonging
<pb id="fred57" n="57"/>
the sound through my hands, “Ha! ha! ha! Ha! ha! Ha!” They
instantly ran with all their might, shouting, “We didé hear
someting, we didé hear someting.” They after a few minutes, as
if to assure themselves, returned, calling the same words again,
“Ole boy, I'll pully your ears,” and I gave the same reply as
before, “Ha! Ha! ha!” They scampered off as quickly as their
legs would carry them, half frightened to death. I looked round
the hogshead, and saw them running towards my master's house,
and then observed them standing by him, as if telling him, and
then the horn gave three or four quick blasts for all hands to
return from the fields. Soon I saw the slaves hastening towards
the house, and my master motioning to the women to come from
the spinning-rooms, and calling out all his own family. He then,
with the children in front, came towards where I was, and I
heard him say to the children, “Whereabouts do you think, he
was when you heard him answer?” They said, “We no ideah yet,
its waysh, uppé yonder.” He said, “When near the place you
must holla again.” So very soon they hollowed again, “Ole boy,
I'll pully your ears.” Then I shouted as loudly as I could, &amp;Ha—a—
a,” and I heard a tremendous running and screaming, “Oh,
Lord! oh, Lord!” some tumbling over one another. In about five
minutes I heard them talking and returning, and my master asking
the slaves if they did not hear something, the slaves said they
did, and
<pb id="fred58" n="58"/>
my mistress said she was sure she did. “Well,” thought I,
“if you didn't you shall; only holla again.” He told the children
to cry out again, and this time, with all my might, like some
wild beast, I replied, “U—U—U—h!” and men, women, and
children, hand over head, scrambling in terror, ran back,
evidently nearly out of their senses. I kept quiet some time,
and then secretly hastened to the cabin. My mistress was laid
up some days from the combined effects of fear and running.
The devil was now known to be at hand.</p>
            <p>After this, I never in my life saw such a change as there was
on my master's plantation; he spoke to every one so kindly,
and went about crying, “Oh, what shall I do, what shall I do?
I heard the Old Boy, I did, I did!” and crying, “O Lord, O
Lord, don't let him take us; oh, don't, oh, don't!” He called
out to my uncle on the Saturday, about two o'clock, when the
slaves were coming out of their cabins from dinner, “My good
fellow, my good fellow!” in a most piteous tone, “come here!
come here! I hope you all have had plenty of dinner; I told the
missis to give more meat; I hope you all have had enough!”
“Yers, sir, yers, sir,” the slaves said; “we have enough to-day,
we have enough to-day.” He, in the utmost anguish of tone and
manner, said, “Because I want you all to have enough; to be
better fed and not to work so hard. Oh, Lord! oh, Lord!”
Crying, he said, “You know to-day is Saturday.” My uncle
said, “Yers, sir,
<pb id="fred59" n="59"/>
to-day is Saturday.” “Go and make all the hands
get their wood chopped for Sunday: they must not
do any work on Sunday. Let the slaves get all
their chose done, for there must be no work done
on Sunday. We heard the old boy answer the other
day. He is coming to take us all away.” And he
cried like a child, “What shall I do! what shall I do!
what shall I do! Oh dear! oh dear! oh dear!” When
my mistress was well, after the fright and the running,
I have every reason to believe, from what I had
heard said, that my master would have liberated all
his slaves; but, boy-like, I could not keep the
secret, and told one of the slaves how cleverly I had
acted the Ole Boy, behind the hogshead, and frightened
them all. The woman went and told my
mistress that it was Francis. My mistress laughed
and cried too, and said, “What will be done with
that little nigger?” She told my master about it,
and he declared he would whip me to death. He
sent for me to come to the house; he stood with the
raw cow's hide, and said, brandishing the whip,
“You little nigger, I will whip the life out of you.”
I danced about and screamed, “I won't do it
again!” Raising the lash, he said, “I'll take
good care you don't; I'll kill you, you little nigger!”
My mistress begged so hard, “Oh, don't! oh, don't! he is too
little,” and so I escaped. In two or three months' time all the
effects had vanished, and Satan's kingdom was worse than
ever through the whole plantation; it was a regular torment,
and I
<pb id="fred60" n="60"/>
was made the most wretched being imaginable, all the slaves
blaming me because they were so cruelly treated, saying I had
told the secret and brought misery again upon them all.
It was a common saying for the
slaves months after, “Massa's gone back to de begging
elements of de world.”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">The Negroes' Party.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Among the American planters there are some of a kind,
humane, and generous nature, who do everything they possibly
can to mitigate the evils of slavery. But, however strange it may
appear, these are the greatest supports to the system. Indeed,
if it were not for these bright exceptions shedding a
humanizing light upon the unspeakable evils of slavery, the
world would long ago have been so horrified by it, that it must
have been rooted out. If all were bad, and acted as the
majority do, with the greatest severity and brutality, we should
not hear persons palliating this enforced servitude by arguments
drawn from the conduct of a few. I knew a gentleman, a
planter, whose name and merits I wish to hold in
remembrance, a Mr. Franklin, having above a hundred slaves,
cultivating chiefly tobacco and hemp in Kentucky. He was a
bachelor. His overseer was Thomas, a black man, who had
some portion of his master's kindness about him in managing
the estate. His housekeeper, Thomas's wife, Sookey, looked
after
<pb id="fred61" n="61"/>
the household matters in somewhat of the same spirit. To these
two were entrusted the entire management of everything
during the absence from home of Mr. Franklin, which
frequently was for three or four months at a time. He had often
heard his neighbours say, “Why, Mr. Franklin, when you are
from home, there are pretty doings at your house. The place is
full of niggers, and Thomas and Sookey carry on a nice game,
treating all hands.” Mr. Franklin was resolved to find out for
himself exactly the state of affairs. So calling Thomas and
Sookey to him, he told them it was his intention to go from
home for three or four months, and ordered them to get his
things ready for the journey. His clothes were duly packed up
by Sookey, and his horse was brought out ready harnessed by
Thomas. But Mr. Franklin had secretly put away his clothes in
a drawer, and had adroitly substituted the oldest and most
ragged things he could lay his hands on, not forgetting a
battered old hat. On his supposed journey he started. Early in
the evening Sookey sent the slaves round to announce that her
master had gone from home, and that a party was to assemble
that evening. Not fewer than forty or fifty, when it was dark,
hastened to Mr. Franklin's house to enjoy themselves of the
best which Sookey could provide. The parlour and the
drawing-room were quickly filled with men and women eagerly
bent upon pleasure. Their conversation was of the most
animated description,—about how many lashes one
<pb id="fred62" n="62"/>
had received because the apportioned work had not
been done; how many cuts another had to spin and
reel off; how one had cunningly escaped, and another
had been lashed. About half-past eleven at
night a knock was heard at the door; an old white
beggar begged to be allowed to enter and warm
himself Sookey, with a large turban on her head,
stepped forward and asked what he wanted. “Oh
no,” she said, “you can't come in to-night, I have
got a party of friends here; certainly not.” Her
husband Thomas came at this moment to the door,
dressed in the best suit that was left at home, and, with
his fingers in the waistcoat arm-holes, and drawing
himself up, “Oh! let poor beggar come in,” he said.
“Come in and warm yourself.” In hobbled the poor benighted
beggar, and took his seat by the fire. Some of the party now
came into the kitchen, and peering at him, “Aunt Sookey,
where did that old beggar come from?” one would say. “See
here, old beggar man, where you live?” The beggar, in a low
tone, replied, “Don't live far from here.” One of the
women, taking hold of her petticoats, and gliding up to him, said,
“Old beggar man, dese de best close you got?” “Yers, marm,”
he said. “Old beggar, if we didn't give all our workey for noting, we
give you better clothes. We get noting for work, massa gets all.
Beggar man! you got any slaves?” she said. “No, I've got no
slaves.” “Would you have any if you was able to buy 'em?”
“Well,” he said, “if I had 'em I would treat 'em
<pb id="fred63" n="63"/>
well.” The woman said, “But if you get into debt, wouldn't
you sell 'em?” He said, “I'm too poor to talk about owning
anything.” The women having hold of the men's arms with one
hand, and their gowns with the other, walked past the poor old
man with all the airs of duchesses, making various remarks as
they went by.</p>
            <p>One of Mr. Franklin's slaves said to another slave, “If me
was as old as Methioseleh, me wouldn't run away, massa, be
so good.” One of the black maids had taken a dress of her
young mistress out of the drawer to show off in this night,
when, as bad luck would have it, one of the men accidentally
trod upon it, and rent it up; dire was the distress and
confusion, and the endeavouring to mend it, lest the mishap
should be discovered. “My massa,” said one of the slaves,
“aint very good massa. I's going to run away, de first chance I
get, to Canada, I tell <hi rend="italics">you;</hi> I's going to leave him.” Another said,
“What for?” “Why, because I know when he gets in debt
he go sell me, sure as you born.” The other replied, “No, he
aint going sell you.” Then all the slaves cried out together, “I
wish somebody would knock dat nigger in de head. Now,
don't you hear im say dat massa wouldn't sell im when he gets
in debt? Eberybody know better en dat.”</p>
            <p>Now, cheered by the best drink which the establishment
could afford, many were the knowing remarks which they
made concerning the qualities of the liquors. “Dis is de best
brandy dat I ever
<pb id="fred64" n="64"/>
did drink in my life.” “Well, I don't know about dat, jus give me
some of de old gin, dat is as good as anyting.” “Jus give me
some of dat ole rye whisky, and dat is jus all I want;” each
speaking according to his taste or fancy. One said, “Well, I
must go and see arter dis old beggaroowe. Come, now, ole
beggar man,” he said, “I want you to be getting out o' dis,”
reeling one step forward, and two back, having got pretty well
drunk. One of the women said, “Oh, no, now jus let dat ole
beggar man alone. He must have someting to eat and drink
afore he go away, because,” she said,
“now who knows but dat ole beggar may get up in de world
some day, and we be sold, an' he buy some of us in de slave-market,
and treat us well for dis—one good turn deserves
anoder; and so I aint going to have dat beggar man run upon
here tonight.”</p>
            <p>When the supper was all laid, the women, having hold of
the arms of the men, walked with all the consequence, and
imitating all the manners of their mistresses, into the dining-room,
and seated themselves at the tables. The supper had
been delayed for some time, because four or five of the young
women who were waiting-maids refused to enter the dining-room,
being indignant at the thought that the old beggar was to
sit along with them. However, the difficulty was got over by
the old woman who took an interest in the beggar saying there
was nothing like peace, and she would send
<pb id="fred65" n="65"/>
something into the kitchen to him, “and den,” she said, “he
should come to de table when we genfolks had done.” While
they were taking supper, Nelly said, “Me send someting into
ole beggar man, since he get hungry, we genfolks sitting chatting
so long.” One of the women seized Nelly by her arm, who
was reaching to put some pound cake on the plate for the old
beggar. “You shan't,” she said, “you make youself very busy
about dat beggar. You an im, too, will go out faster den you
come in, if you don't mine.” The grace before meat was, “Lord,
bless dat good massa of Thomas and Sookey, dat managed so
well to leave so many good tings to set before us, and hoping
dat he turn home all right;” and they all responded, “A—men,
A—men.”</p>
            <p>After they had eaten a little, the conversation began afresh.
“There ain't such a nice lady in de country as my missis,” said
one. Another disputed eagerly with her, saying that “her misses
was as good, if not better;” all who were kindly treated praising
their mistresses as unequalled. One young man protested that
his young master knew more than any young gentleman he ever
saw in his life, “because,” he said, “my young massa is going to
get married in two or three weeks. Now, how do you tink he
got his wife? Why, because a young lady was praising his
hoss, and he said, ‘How would you like its massa?’ and dat de
way de work commenced; and she might have praised all de
<pb id="fred66" n="66"/>
gemmen's hosses in de country, and none would have made de
answer; because my Massa has got more approbranchen
(apprehension) den all de gemmens in de country.” “My
Massa,” said another, “he whip me ebery time I go away from
home without asking im, and de next new moon I going to
make way to Great Britain's land, to Canada, jus as sure as
you born.” Another said, “If I had such a massa as Mr.
Franklin, uncle Thomas and aunt Sookey's massa, den I tink
myself well off.” Another said, “I see jus as good a massa in de
country as Mr. Franklin, and when he got into debt he sold all
his slaves.” And all the company; cried out to this observation,
“<hi rend="italics">True, true.</hi>” Some of them said, “We couldn't be no happier
if it wasn't for selling.” One said, “You see de hen in de
morning got twelve chickens, and before night de hawk take
dem all away but five;” and she said, “Brethren, though we be
enjoying ourselves to-night, before de end of de week some of
us may be sold down de river.” And all said, “True, true, true.
My God!” One of the women said, “My massa and missis
very kind, but my massa get into debt, and I see him dodging
away from de sheriffs dis two months, and he gone and sold all
his hemp and tobacco, and den he gone and sold all de wheat,
and so he sold all his fat pigs and three or four beeves, and I
hear my fellow-servant, de waiter, he say dat he habent half de
debt paid; so every morning I get down on my knees
<pb id="fred67" n="67"/>
and kiss all my little chilun before I go into de
fields because dey might sell me in de field, and I
mightn't come back home to see dem no more.” And many
said they had witnessed the same thing. And many a one said,
“Jus give me my freedom, and pay me for my work, and I
work for my massa from daylight till dark. I wouldn't leave my
plantation to go nowhere else if me jus had my freedom, so, I
wouldn't be sold away from my family. I lub my wife and
chilun.” And one old woman said,
“I says so too, because de worst whipping I ever had in all
my life was because I cried when dey sold my son, and dey
would have sold me, but when dey stripped my shoulders at
de market, I was whipped so bad dey said dey wouldn't hab
me.” Aunt Lucy said, “Now, uncle Harry, you say you a Christian
man.” He said, “Yers, I do, I trust I am a
Christian.” “Massa last week,” Lucy said, “whipt
my back awful because I went to a prayer-meeting.
He say, ‘Why don't you ask me?’ But when I
ask he won't let me go, and I see im since he whipt
me take de Lord's-supper. I was sitting in de
gallery looking at im. To see de oaths coming out of
his mouth when he was whipping me, and den to see him
sitting dare and taking de Lord's-supper,
I had to turn my head away and not look at im. Now, uncle
Harry, what do you tink of im?”
Uncle Harry said, “Well, Lucy, if it's true what you say, hell is
full of such Christians.”</p>
            <p>Aunt Amy came up, and began to tell about her
<pb id="fred68" n="68"/>
master whipping her because she had not done her task in
spinning. Fanny and Melvey said, “Now, uncle Harry, hear
what we have got to say. Half de times dat aunt Amy gets
whipt it be her own fault. 'Cause when her massa calls her
‘You ugly old devil,’ for all she knows dare ain't an uglier white
man in all Kentucky dan he is, she talks right back to im, and
she say, ‘I have seen cleverer gemmens dan you.’ What can
she expect when she insult im?” Several of the slaves spoke up
and said, “Amy was wrong in talking back,
dey could not expect noting else from dare massas.”
Humphery said, “Dat ole beggar will tell
what you all be talking about; I tell <hi rend="italics">you</hi>, he sits dare listening.”
Somebody said, “For Lor sake let de ole beggar alone, for
de white folks as good as de black folks, as long dey behave
demselves.” Mimey said, “Well, uncle Harry, my missis is not a
good missis; she was up in de garret to-day, and dat is as near
heben as she ever will get. I will give de debble his due, she do chain de
debble up all day Sunday, but she let im out on de Monday
morning.” Billy said, “Well, uncle Harry, what do you say
about all dese bad white folks?” Uncle Harry said, “Well, I
want you all to be good; you be talking so much about your
bad massas, and I hab been telling you all dis long time about
your duty to be good Christians.”
Billy said, “Well, if my massa was as good man as
I believe you are, I could be a good man; but he
say he be Christian, and he does such tings as I
<pb id="fred69" n="69"/>
wouldn't do. He seem to stand right before me, he seem to get
right in my way. I tink if my massa die de way he is now, de
debble would have him, he worse den de debble.” Up came
Dinah and Grace, and said, “Well, uncle Harry, I know dat we
have lost four slaveholders dat I don't tink de debble would
put em wid de rest. He must hab some place to put em by
demselves, dey so bad he wouldn't put em wid de rest.” It
was decided by two-thirds of the company that ‘the debil was
but a debil,’ but that their masters professed to be Christians,
and yet their acts made them worse than the devil. Cupid, a
smart nigger, a waiter, with his hands under his coat-tails,
strutted up to the beggar, and said, “How dare you to come
here to-night, where dere is ladies and gemmens, with such
clothes as dese on? Now, you must never be catched doing
such a ting again. Now,” said Cupid, standing before him with
one hand under his coat-tails, and motioning with the other,
“you may always know, from dis time for ever, dat de black
folks are de best folks, 'cause you see now we allow you to sit
now where dere is ladies and gemmens, and you are not taken
by de pole of your neck and throwed out of doors, as de white
people would do wid one of us if we was to come into such a
party with such rags.” Then Cupid, placing his fingers in his
waistcoat armholes, bowing to the beggar, said, “Well, you are
a very civil ole fellow, after all; won't you hab a glass of someting
<pb id="fred70" n="70"/>
to drink?” “Yes, please,” answered the beggar. Cupid
poured out a glass of brandy, and walked up to him, “Here,
take dis, you are good ole fellow, after all.” Uncle Harry said,
“I want you all to pray and ask de Lord to give us all such
massas as Thomas and Sookey's massa, dat we may
hab some more places to get such good things to eat. And
now I wish you all to rise.” And they all rose up, and he said,
“In the midst of slavery dere is something to be thankful for. To-night,
we are blessed to have good food given. Oh, Lord,
make us thankful, and bless de good massa of dis house.”
And all said, “Amen, amen.”</p>
            <p>The beggar was now called into the dining-room, and Aunt
Sookey gave him some of the good things. He then went and
sat down by the fire again. It happened that two or three years
before this Mr. Franklin, had been helping the men to chop
some firewood, and he had cut his foot very badly. Aunt
Sookey had attended to the wound. After it was well, there was
still a large sear on the foot. The old beggar by the fire began
to pull off his shoe and sock. His foot was stretched out. Aunt
Sookey, coming to the fire, said, “I wish you would be getting
ready to go away. You needn't be pulling off your shoe; you
ain't going to stop here.” She looked stedfastly at the foot for a
few moments, and then, stepping backwards and coming
forwards again, repeating these movements three or four times,
as if some dreadful thought had seized her,
<pb id="fred71" n="71"/>
she said, “Tommy, Tommy, Tommy!” “What, what?” he said.
She said, “Come here, come here! Don't you tink dat massa,
Johnny's foot?” Uncle Tommy, taking her by the shoulders
and turning her round, said, “Oh, you go away.” Then he
walked towards the beggar's foot, looking anxiously at it, and
starting affrighted back; and then stepped forward again, as if
to make himself sure of something, and then ran back again
terrified, and cried out, “It is massa Johnny's foot. It is, it is
massa Johnny's foot.” And Aunt Sookey shouted out, “Oh, oh!”
and ran away, she out of one door, and he out of the other.
Now ensued a scene of indescribable confusion. The first hat
that any one could seize he put on his head and ran off. In one
minute all had disappeared; and, what surprised me the most,
was that, although five minutes before several men were
staggering drunk, not one found the slightest difficulty in
understanding the nature of the discovery, and scampering off
as nimbly as if he had not tasted a drop.</p>
            <p>The old white beggar, changed to be Mr. Franklin, the
master of the establishment, called to his ostler, and ordered
him to go into the woodland pasture, and directed him where
he would find his horse and gig fastened up to a tree, and told
him to bring it to the house. Another slave he ordered to call
Thomas and Sookey, and tell them to come in and put
everything away and he would not disturb
<pb id="fred72" n="72"/>
them. When the servant went to call them in, and
told them what their master said, they came in, and
Mr. Franklin called Aunt Sookey, saying, “Sookey,
come here.” Sookey entered the room, and began
to beg his pardon. He said, “I only want you to
get me some clothes to put on. You shall not hear
anything more about it.” Uncle Thomas wished to
come in to beg his pardon. Aunt Sookey told Mr.
Franklin that Thomas wanted to beg his pardon,
and he said, “Tell Thomas to get on putting things
away. There will be nothing more about it.”</p>
            <p>In about five or six weeks afterwards I saw Aunt Sookey,
and asked her if Mr. Franklin had ever whipped her and Uncle
Thomas about the spree. She said, “No;” and she told me
how, when all had gone, Mr. Franklin had acted kindly. She
said she had heard her master say to a gentleman, that he had
been to a good many theatres, but he never in his life was at
one where he had so enjoyed himself as at the Niggers' Spree.
He said if some of the black women had had white faces, he
should have thought it was their mistresses, their manners and
demeanour being exact copies of the white ladies; and Sookey
told me that Mr. Franklin said, “Indeed, he never could have
believed it if he had not seen it.” He said (evidently alluding to
the kind attention he had received from Nelly) that “certainly in
woman's nature there was the milk of human kindness.” I hope
that no debt or other misfortune has compelled this good man
to
<pb id="fred73" n="73"/>
part with any of his slaves, or assuredly they will find a
difference elsewhere.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
          <argument>
            <p>Labour of any kind despised—Slaves the Badge of Distinction
among Planters—Impudence of the Ladies.</p>
          </argument>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <p>A CONTEMPT for workers characterizes every one in any way
connected with slavery. Nothing seems so degrading to them
as to do the slightest menial office, such as the making a pie, or
tart, or any little article of cooking. They talk generally about
doing such things as a person in England would talk about a
gentleman dragging a cart, or a lady carrying a basket upon
her head. Slaves do everything; and I have often heard the
ladies say, when they had been to the North, that they were
pleased they had returned home, as they hated to be waited
upon by white folks.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Slaves the Badge of Distinction among Planters.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The principal badge of distinction among the Southerners in
America is the possession of slaves. A very nice young
gentleman, whose father had no slaves, but yet was
wealthy, came to pay his
<pb id="fred74" n="74"/>
addresses to a young lady of similar fortune to his own. She
wished him to discontinue his visits, since his father, she said,
had not the toenail of a nigger in the world. She said to her
footman, “Vincent, I wish you could play some trick upon him,
so that he would not come again.” “I can do it nicely,” said
Vincent. “I shall consider you a clever fellow if you can,” she
said; “and I will make you a present if you do.” When the
gentleman came again, Vincent had ready a piece of
shoemaker's wax, flattened out thin, and, holding with his right
hand the gentleman's horse, whilst he was going to mount, he
slipped with his left the piece of wax on to the saddle. The
gentleman rode home, but when the servant came to take the
horse, he found his master could not dismount, and ran into the
house and told the family that his young master could not get
off his horse. They all came on the verandah,  and asked him
what was the matter. He said “he did not know, but he was
fast to the saddle.” After considerable difficulty, amidst a good
deal of laughter, he was separated from the saddle, his father
saying, “I would advise you to stay at home another time, since
you may see that you are not wanted where you have been.”</p>
            <p>This kind of practical jokes is very common among the
Southern young ladies. Their black footmen are prompted to
pass them off upon young gentlemen whose fathers are not
slaveholders. Hence, if a young gentleman should politely take
<pb id="fred75" n="75"/>
the reins of a horse to assist the lady to mount, the footman
would hold fast and saucily say, “I come for dis purpose.”
The gentleman, looking in the laughing face of the lady, would
perceive in an instant that he was not wanted, and walk away
directly.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
          <argument>
            <p>First Attempt to Escape—Pursued by Bloodhounds—Reach Bear's
Wallow, a Dismal Swamp—Conceal myself in a Cavern—
Driven by hunger, give myself up to my Master—Receive
107 Lashes—Brutally treated afterwards by my Master.</p>
          </argument>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <p>WORK, work, work, one day like another, only I had now been
to several  prayer-meetings, and had got a knowledge of
religion, which comforted me. I thought about the future, when
I should be free from my master, when I could join in psalms
and hymns and prayers without being afraid of the lash. Such
consolation and joy did I receive from these meetings, that I
have run the risk over and over again of being flogged for
attending them. Thus one weary day, and week, and month,
and year passed on with me, being turned out of the kitchen
sometimes, when my master was in his drunken
<pb id="fred76" n="76"/>
fits, to work in the fields. I had been flogged for
going to a prayer-meeting, and, before my back was well, my
master was going to whip me again. I determined, therefore, to
run away. It was in the morning, just after my master had got
his breakfast, I was ordered to the back of the premises to
strip. My master had got the thong of raw cow's-hide; when off
I ran, towards the swamp.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Pursued by Bloodhounds.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>He saw me running, and instantly called three bloodhounds,
kept for the purpose, and put them on my track. I saw them
coming up to me, when, turning round to them, I clapped my
hands, and called them by
name; for I had been in the habit of feeding them. I urged them
on, as if in pursuit of something else. They instantly passed me,
and flew upon the cattle. I saw my master calling them off, and
returning. No doubt, he perceived it was useless to pursue me,
with dogs which knew me so well.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Reach Bear's Wallow, a dismal Swamp.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I now hurried on further, into a dismal swamp, named the
Bear's Wallow; and, at last, wearied and exhausted, I sat
down at the foot of a tree, to rest, and think what had best be
done.</p>
            <p>I knelt down, and prayed earnestly to the
<pb id="fred77" n="77"/>
Almighty, to protect and direct me what to do. I rose from my
knees, and looked stealthily around, afraid that the dogs and
men were still in pursuit. I listened, and listened again, to the
slightest sound, made by the flapping of the wings of a bird, or
the rustling of the wild animals among the underwood; and then
proceeded further into the swamp. My path was interrupted,
every now and then, by large sheets of stagnant, putrid, green-looking
water, from which a most sickening, fetid smell arose;
the birds, in their flight, turning away from it. The snakes
crawled sluggishly across the ground, for it was autumn time,
when, it is said, they are surcharged with their deadly poison.
Their tameness frightened me, as I stood admiring their various
hues, and immense coils. A kind Providence seemed to have
made them harmless to me, for they never bit or molested me.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Conceal myself in a Cavern.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I came, at length, to an overhanging rock, forming a species
of natural cavern, into which I crept, to rest me. I was
footsore, and torn by the thorns, and parched with thirst. After
a short time, I crept out, to pluck some berries, to quench my
thirst; and then re-entered the cavern, to lie for the night; but
the barking of the wild dogs, the growling of the bears, and
sounds of wild
<pb id="fred78" n="78"/>
animals, of various kinds, made me start from my feverish
sleep.</p>
            <p>When awake in the morning, I tried to plan out some way
of escape, over the Ohio River, which I knew was about thirty
miles from where I was. But I could not swim; and I was well
aware that my master would set a watch upon every ferry or
ford, and that the whole country would be put on the alert, to
catch me; for the planters, for self-protection, take almost as
much interest in capturing another man's slaves, as they do their
own.</p>
            <p>I walked for some distance, round about the cavern; having
determined to make it my place of abode, until I could hit upon
some plan of escape. I was in continual fear, when I plucked
the berries, to eat them, lest I should be poisoned; for I had
known that slaves, especially children, had been killed by eating
some kinds of wild berries. Sometimes I vomited very much,
after eating some; at other times, those which I plucked agreed
with me better. But I am unable to describe the difference of
the berries, in other respects.</p>
            <p>I came, several times, near to dead polecats, the stench
from which was dreadful, and, in my weak state, produced
sickness. One day and night were very much like another,
except that I occasionally heard the noise of men and dogs—no
doubt, in pursuit of other negroes. My mind, whenever I heard
the barking of dogs, was distressed, beyond
<pb id="fred79" n="79"/>
all description. I felt sure, until the sounds ceased, that they
would scent me out; and strange dogs would have torn me to
pieces; the masters preferring their slaves to be devoured,
rather than to allow them to escape.</p>
            <p>At length, driven by hunger and desperation, I approached
the edge of the swamp; when I was startled by seeing a young
woman ploughing. I knew her, and called her by name. She
was frightened, and shocked at my appearance—worn,
from hunger, almost to a skeleton; and haggard, from the want
of sound sleep. I begged of her to go to get me something to
eat. She, at first, expressed her fears, and began to tell me of
the efforts which my master was making to capture me. He
had offered 500 dollars' reward—had placed a watch all
along the Ohio River—had informed all the neighbouring
planters, who had cautioned all their slaves not to give me any
food or other assistance,—and he had made it known,
that, when I should be caught, he would give me a thousand lashes.</p>
            <p>The woman went, and fetched me about two ounces of
bread, of which I eat a small portion—wishing to keep the rest to
eat in the swamp,—husbanding it, as much as possible. When
she told me that I should receive a thousand lashes, I felt
horrified, and wept bitterly. The girl wept also. I had seen a
slave, who had escaped to the Northern States, and, after an
absence of four years, had been brought back again, and
flogged, in the presence of
<pb id="fred80" n="80"/>
all the slaves, assembled from the neighbouring plantations. His
body was frightfully lacerated. I went to see him, two or three
weeks after the flogging. When they were anointing his back,
his screams were awful. He died, soon afterwards—a  tall,
fine young fellow, six feet high, in the prime of life, thus brutally
murdered.</p>
            <p>All this flashed across my mind, when I heard, from the
girl, the threat of the thousand lashes. “Oh, dear,” I said, “shall
I ever suffer one thousand lashes? Shall I ever get to free
Canada?” I went on, repeating these sentences, over and
over again, in the most distracted manner, all the way to my
place of retreat.</p>
            <p>Driven, in a day or two after this, to seek some food, I
ventured across the country again, about two or three miles,
when I came to a log-house. I approached slowly, looking
anxiously around, lest any one should be about. It was a fine
moonlight night, and, I think, a little after twelve o'clock. I
listened, and, not hearing any one stirring, I looked through the
window, and saw a white man and woman in bed. At first, I
thought I would make my wants known to them; and then—
remembering that white people had given up slaves, and had
received rewards, and had threatened, if the slaves attempted
to run away, to shoot them—I hesitated, and, looking around, I
saw a piece of wood, with which I gently raised the window. I
first cautiously put one leg in; and then, listening, I heard them
<pb id="fred81" n="81"/>
snoring. I drew my other leg in, and passed the bed gently, and
went, into what, from the pots and pans about, I guessed was
the kitchen. I looked and felt about, for something to eat; not
finding anything, I was coming out, when my elbow knocked
against a cupboard-door. I felt in, and found a ham-bone, with
about an ounce of meat on it. I hastened out of the window, as
quickly as possible, and closed it. I soon picked every morsel
from the bone. In my cavern, I sucked the bone, until I went
to sleep, and when I awoke in the morning, I sucked it again,
until it was completely polished. Whenever I now see a dog
picking a bone, I remember the luxury it was to me.</p>
            <p>A few nights afterwards, driven by hunger, I ventured out
again, and, about four miles from the swamp, I came up to
where I saw a house. I noticed, on the ground, what I thought
was a goose, and, going gently up, I caught hold of it, when
instantly it barked, for it was a dog. Having been caught in its
sleep, it was evidently frightened, and howled fearfully. I ran
back, towards the bush, but had not proceeded many yards,
before a shot whistled past me, and I heard the report of a
gun. I was running in a stooping position, or I think the shot
would have penetrated my head. I regained my hiding-place—
faint, wearied, and disheartened.</p>
            <p>Driven almost to desperation, the next night I went again in
search of food. I had wandered
<pb id="fred82" n="82"/>
about for some hours, without finding anything,
when I saw a number of stumps of trees, two or
three feet high; and about a hundred and fifty
yards away from them, I noticed a log hut. I approached
it, by degrees, hiding first behind one
stump, and then another. I waited for a short
time, looking round to spy out something to eat.
I observed a white woman, with an Indian basket,
come out of the house and walk towards a brick
oven at some distance from the house, which is
usual in that country; she opened the oven-door
and took some loaves out, until she had filled her
basket, and then taking it in her arms she carried
it into the house. As soon as she had entered the
house I ran to the oven, hoping to pick up a few
crumbs, when to my utter surprise I found a loaf
(surely the Lord had so ordained it); I hastily bit
two or three pieces from it, and ran back to a
stump. The woman came out of the house again,
this time without the basket, and went to the
oven, looked into it, and then, as if the devil
himself were after her, she ran, as I never saw a
woman run before or since, to the house.</p>
            <p>I made all the haste I could to the cavern in the swamp.
Oh! what a luxury that loaf was! I was afraid to let the
mouthsful go down my throat, it was so pleasant to taste the
bread, and I was afraid it would soon be all gone. Never shall
I forget that heaven-sent loaf and the prayers of gratitude I
offered up to the Giver of all good things for it.</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="fred83" n="83"/>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Driven by Hunger, give myself up to my Master.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>My loaf was soon gone, and I was in the same state of
hunger and desperation as before, when driven almost to my
wits' end, and seeing no possible mode of escape (not being
able to swim, I could not cross the Ohio River), I resolved to
go to a Methodist preacher of the name of Brush, whom I
knew, and entreat him to intercede with my master for me. I
went towards his house, hesitating and pausing every now and
then, hoping something would suggest itself to my mind even
now by which I might escape. At length I knocked at the door,
he came and looked at me, I spoke a few words to him, when
he asked me who I was. I told him; he said he only knew me by
my voice. His wife came to me, and wanted to give me some
food, for she seemed  shocked at my appearance. Her husband
insisted that she should not, since, he said, I was hungred, and
the food would perhaps kill me, and he should be blamed.
However, she gave me one cup of tea and a slice of bread. Mr.
Brush had promised to ask forgiveness for me, but he did not
speak kindly to me. He put his hat on to go, and I followed him
across the street, when a crowd of thoughts rushed across my
mind,—the 1,000 lashes, the poor man whom I had seen
flogged to death, the threats the woman ploughing in the
fields had told me my master had made. I felt
<pb id="fred84" n="84"/>
my strength gone, I stood, my brain swimming round, I thought I
should fall; when Mr. Brush, turning suddenly round, in a sharp
tone said, “Come on! Come on! Quick!” I followed him; we
had ten or twelve miles to walk; he said but very little, and that
not kindly, all the way. He seemed sullen. He said I should not
have run away. At length, wearied and ready to drop, we got to
my master's house. Mr. Brush entered, and I heard him say, “I
have brought your slave Francis.” My master exclaimed, “What!
you have! Well, I will do for him.” I heard his footsteps, he
came and looked at me, but said nothing. My mistress came,
and said, “Francis! is that you?” I said, “Yes, missis, I have
been longing to see you.” “Come in,” she said, “you are very
bad for running away; now you must promise me only to eat just
what I shall give you.” I was weak, and sat down in the kitchen.
A black woman was doing my work. Small portions of food
were given me at a time each day. A little tea and dry toast, then
a little milk, then a little bread and butter. I remained in the
kitchen assisting, as my strength returned, the black woman. In
about three weeks I found my former strength returning. During
the three weeks, I had from time to time begged of my mistress
not to have me whipped. She said she would do all she could if
I would be a good slave in future. She spoke and treated me
kindly.</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="fred85" n="85"/>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Receive 107 Lashes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>At the end of about a month my master, one morning, came
into the kitchen; he had a rope and a cow-hide whip in his
hands. “Francis!” he said.
“Yers, massa,” I answered. “Come this way, I will now settle
with you; you have been away nine weeks, and I will now
reckon with you.” I dropped on my knees, and begged hard
for mercy. But all in vain. He produced a revolver, and said,
“Look here, if you attempt to run away, I will shoot you
as sure as you are alive. Strip instantly.” I took my clothes off,
and he fastened me to an apple-tree behind the house, and
flogged me until he was tired. I could not cry any more. The
slaves who were watching me told me afterwards that I had
received 107 Lashes. He untied me, I could scarcely walk.
For one cent he swore he would shoot me. He threatened, if
ever I attempted to do so again, he
would certainly do for me. I crawled into the kitchen. I thought
I should die. After dinner was over in the parlour, the
servants looked at my back, which was frightfully lacerated,
and rubbed it with something. Generally before this, after I
had had a whipping, my master had ordered my
back to be attended to, and salt to be applied, but
this time he did not seem to care whether I recovered or
not. In the evening my mistress came into the kitchen, and
said, “Francis, you have had
<pb id="fred86" n="86"/>
a very severe flogging. I could not prevent it. I hope you will
never attempt to run away again. I thought your master would
have killed you (she had been watching the flogging from a
window); you must not be sullen or sulky to him in any way, or
he will flog you again. I shall send you something into the
kitchen to rub your back with,” and after some more advice
and cautions she went away.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Brutally Treated by my Master.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Slowly I began to recover; but now, after about
fourteen years, I feel the effects of it, especially in
bad weather. I was dreadfully frightened of my
master ever after this flogging. Whenever he had
been whipping any of the slaves in the fields, and
came into the kitchen, he would cut at me, or when
drunk would make me stand with my hands down,
and strike me in the face and ribs, and threaten, if
I got out of his way, to shoot me with his revolver,
which he always carried with him. “Blast the lot
of them,” he used to say; “when I begin, if I had
strength, I would flog the whole plantation round.”
When he had been in the fields flogging the slaves
for anything or nothing, and was returning home,
he would stop to scratch his pet pig, which would
stretch itself out, evidently enjoying life. He would
call it master's pig, master's pig. He would then
pat his favourite dog, which had run to meet him,
<pb id="fred87" n="87"/>
and was gambolling about him, calling it master's dog,
master's dog. Then coming into the kitchen he would make a
dash at me, striking and lashing me several times, not caring
whether he hit me on the head or elsewhere. The girl would
rush out of the kitchen, but calling her back, he would curse
her, and ask her “what the h—— she was screaming for,” and
threaten to give her a whipping. After having lashed her two or
three times he would then pass upstairs. Oh, how often have I
looked at that pig and dog and wished I was either rather than
a black man!</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
          <argument>
            <p>Produce of Kentucky—Climate of Kentucky—How the
Kentuckians Spend the Winter—Fevers Rage in
Summer—Slaveholders frequently administer
Medicine to Slaves—Anecdote—The Domestic Animals—
The Birds—Change of Property, how it affects the
Slaves—Resignation of a Female Slave.</p>
          </argument>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <p>I STILL had to work on, now hopeless of ever getting
my liberty. I was now very busy in the kitchen
preserving various kinds of fruits. The fruit trees
are generally in bloom in March. There are large
orchards containing apple, peach, plum, pear, and
damson trees, also gooseberries, currants, and raspberries.
<pb id="fred88" n="88"/>
What we termed the sweet grape grows abundantly in
the gardens; in the bush a vine grows wild bearing a very large
grape, but it is sour. There are also great quantities of
mulberries grown. There is a very nice fruit in the bush called
the black and red haugh. In the beginning of June there are
plenty of ripe apples, indeed, there are apples of different
kinds becoming ripe until December; large quantities of them
are preserved. The apples are peeled and cut from the core,
then stewed down in a pan containing cider, and put into jars;
this is called apple butter, and is very nice and sweet to put
upon bread in the winter time. There are enormous quantities of
preserved fruits of all kinds put away in jars in the cellars. The
slaves gather the apples and peaches when ripe, and take them
to the distillery, and there beat
them up in large troughs. This is put into tubs and ferments.
Apple brandy, which is very strong, is made from it. Peach
brandy, made in a similar
manner, is mild. The spouse (pulp) is thrown out into the
distillery-yard for the pigs; hence there are
drunken pigs as well as teetotal pigs. The pigs, after eating
some spouse, will get up and grunt, grunt, grunt, and then
down they will fall, to the infinite delight of the children. Some
of the pigs, after being drunk two or three times, will not touch
the spouse afterwards, thus teaching a very good lesson to us.</p>
            <p>The principal produce of Kentucky is flax, hemp,
<pb id="fred89" n="89"/>
tobacco, and excellent crops of wheat, except when the weevil
and other insects, owing to the shortness of the winter and want
of frost, destroy, in some measure, the crops. Large tracts of
land are cultivated with Indian corn, which is the chief article of
food for the negroes, and it is cooked for the use of the planters
in a variety of ways, and is very much liked by strangers at the
tables of the planters. I myself can cook it in ten different ways.
Lately, prior to the war, the slaveholders of Kentucky had large
patches of cotton. I must not forget to mention the excellent
crops of sweet potatoes. Many of the slaves are allowed to
keep the small potatoes for seed; and as the white people do
not save the seed, the negroes sell them in the spring, and thus
have a little money with which to purchase a few things for
themselves. There is a very pleasant drink made from cherries,
called cherry bounce, by mixing two-thirds of the juice with
one-third of whiskey. Although such great quantities of fruit are
grown, the slaves dare not, generally, touch any except it is
given to them, which is very seldom; the Almighty not having
sent the fruits of the earth for the slaves, but for their masters.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Climate of Kentucky.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The weather in Kentucky is very hot from the beginning of
June to the middle of October. Europeans at first with
difficulty can bear the
<pb id="fred90" n="90"/>
heat in July and August. The cause of the intense heat is the
absence of rain for some time. The heat from the sun in these
months is very often such that it dazzles the eyes so that
persons can only see distinctly at short distances. I remember
at two large Camp Meetings in Fleming County, water was
sold at fourpence per cup. The heat having dried up all the
streams around, the water had to be brought three or four
miles. The winters generally commence a little after Christmas,
the cold, sharp winds beginning then to blow. It freezes for a
day or two, when the ground becomes as hard as a brick, and
then a thaw sets in, and in a day or two more it freezes again.
The winters vary very much; one winter the ice will come
floating down the river Ohio, in large pieces, the next winter
perhaps the Ohio will be frozen so hard that hundreds of teams
are crossing and recrossing it in all directions. The ice generally
breaks up about the end of February. </p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">How the Kentuckians Spend the Winter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>From Christmas to March the planters keep up a perpetual
succession of evening parties; there is nothing but fiddling and
dancing, and “ladies-chain,” and “cross half over.” Many
ladies dance so long that often they are carried in a fainting
state out of the room. Balls and visiting continue the whole
winter through; they seem to live for
<pb id="fred91" n="91"/>
nothing else. The weather is so changeable that often when
parties have gone over the snow on a sledge, the next day
there is not a vestige of ice or snow left, and they are
compelled to return on wheels. Generally winter is
the easiest time for the slaves, who
if they can get out for a dance do so, at least as many as are
inclined. The slaves in Kentucky are better clothed and fed, far
better, than in Virginia.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Fevers Rage in Summer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Fevers are very prevalent in Kentucky, many of
the planters losing during the summer months large numbers of
slaves. I have seen the planters, who have lost their slaves by
fever, walking about with
clenched fists distracted, and saying, “I shall have to take the
money I put away to buy more slaves,” and almost cursing the
Almighty for depriving
them of their property. My master was one of this stamp.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Slaveholders Frequently Administer Medicine to Slaves.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The planters are in the habit of giving all their slaves
medicine at the commencement of spring, that it may go easier
with them in case of fever.
In fact, they constantly resort to medicine in case of the
slightest indisposition.</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="fred92" n="92"/>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Anecdote.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I had a cousin who was fond of drink. One night he went to
a distillery, where a black man was distilling, and got some
whiskey, which made him drunk. Next morning he was crying,
“Oh! oh! oh! me can't work to-day. Jee-e-ry,” he said,
“can't you go to de house and tell Massa I's sick to-day? I's so
sick, me couldn't live to get out into de fields if me was to
start.” Jerry went to the house and told my master that Reuben
was very sick. My master took some calomel with him, and
went to the cabin. “Well, Reuben,” he said, “are you sick to-day?”
Reuben putting his hand to the side of his head, said,
“Yes, Massa, I's very sick indeed, Massa.” “Where is the
pain?” said my master. “All over me, in my head and back,
all over me, Sir,” said Reuben. “What time did your illness
commence?” said my master. “Me tinks, as well as me can
bemember, two clock dis morning,” answered Reuben. “I have
got something which will suit all your complaints,—calomel and
jalap,” said my master. Reuben's eyes flew wide open,
“Massa, Massa,” he said, “don't you tink if me was to walk
bout in de air it might help me widout takin dat?” “No, no,”
said my master, “I want you to take this and stay in to-day,
and if you feel better you can go out to-morrow.” He ordered
Aunty, who takes care of the children, to give him
<pb id="fred93" n="93"/>
some blood-warm water in a cup. “Now, Reuben,” he said,
“you drink this physic down, and then take a little water after
it, and rinse your mouth with some more.” Reuben swallowed
the physic, and pulled such a face as I never saw in all my life.
My master left the cabin saying, “Now, if you feel better you
can go out to-morrow.” Reuben got drunk again, another night
about three months afterwards. Next morning he was holloing
out, “Oh! oh! oh! me know me die afore night, me does feel
so bad.” “Reuben,” said Jerry. “Wh-a-at deyah want?”
answered Reuben. “Can me go to de house and tell Massa dat
you sick gen?” replied Jerry. “No, no, M—Massa,—M— Massa
will come down 'ere an bring some more of dat calomer and
jolloper,” stammered out Reuben. But to return from this little
digression to my account of the produce of Kentucky.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">The Domestic Animals.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>They pride themselves very much on the breed of their
horses, mules, bullocks, sheep, and pigs. The winter destroys
a great many sheep, because they are housed without
sufficient ventilation. They are compelled to house the sheep
on account of the great number of wolves roaming about in
winter.</p>
            <p>The Kentuckians do not in general begin to break in their
horses until they are four or five years old, consequently many
accidents happen to the riders,
<pb id="fred94" n="94"/>
their horses being often very restive. The houses of the planters
are built of brick and stone, and generally a verandah runs right
round them; the kitchens are situated at a short distance from
the house, so that the cooking may not be smelt.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">The Birds.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The woods are full of birds, with plumage of almost every
colour, black, blue, green, &amp;c.—the mocking bird, whip-poor-will,
and many others whose names I do not know, and birds
with most melodious notes. There is a large bird called the
Turkey buzzard, which lives upon dead animals. It is wonderful
to see them perched in the trees by hundreds when a dead
animal is near. They watch until the bald-eagle comes and takes
the eyes out of the carcase, apparently being afraid as long as
the eyes are there; but they are no sooner out than down the
buzzards fly and swarm about it, picking every morsel of flesh
from the bones. The quill of the buzzard is valued to make pens
of, being much better than the goose quill. They are a very
harmless bird, and not easily frightened by the presence of man,
since he rarely disturbs them, on account of their being such
excellent scavengers to clear the ground of dead animal matter.
There is a fowl living in the water as large as a wild duck, called
the waterwitch, which is as black as jet. It can be approached
within a yard, and any one would suppose
<pb id="fred95" n="95"/>
that, being so near, he could easily strike it. But in a
twinkling, when aimed at, it darts down, appears again at some
distance, and will allow you to approach near again, seemingly
thinking that it can avoid the intended blow. Although I have
struck at many, and seen others strike, I never once saw one
hit. Hence, I should suppose its name. There are the
woodcock and woodpecker, and a variety of squirrels, some
of them, especially the fox-squirrel, being very large, which
destroy great quantities of corn. In short, Kentucky is a very
beautiful country; and, as I heard a gentleman remark, “All but
the spirit of man is divine.”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Change of Property.—How it affects the Slaves.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>And so, my reader, you would think if I could bring before
your mind's eye the lovely landscape, and then open out to
you the interior of that fine house, with a splendid lawn in the
front, looking upon as magnificent scenery as you perhaps
ever saw. I will tell you something about its owner. His name is
O—— B——, the nephew of a kindhearted planter, Mr. P——  , recently
dead, and who had left a fine tobacco plantation and 150
slaves to Mr. B——, of Virginia, a slave-breeding State. Being a
house-slave myself, I became acquainted with the housemaids,
waiting-maids, and other slaves about Mr. P——'s house. And I
am sure I never saw more modest and better-behaved
<pb id="fred96" n="96"/>
girls in my life than they were. Perfect models of propriety.
Their neatness, good conduct, and virtuous conversation were
praised by all. Mr. P—— left this property in Kentucky to his
sister's eldest son, the present proprietor.</p>
            <p>But, oh, what a sad change! My heart is full when I recall to
mind the forced pollution of one after another of these good
girls. Satiated with one, he would force another to submit to his
lusts, in spite of all their entreaties. Soul and body they were
bound to him. Louisa was the first who was taken, and in
secret, among her friends, the sorrowful conversation about her
degradation I well remember. Aunt Celia, poor Louisa's
mother, went one day to the house to ask that her daughter
might spend a night at her cabin. “Come in, come this way,”
said Mr. B——, quite mildly. Aunt Celia followed him. He took
her into a spinning-room, tied her to a loom, tore the clothes
from her back and said, “How dare you insult me by asking
such a thing?” and flogged her within an inch of her life, her
wretched son and daughter, who heard her shrieks for mercy,
not daring to intercede. Imagine the feelings and thoughts of the
unhappy girl spending that night by the side of her mother's
torturer and her tyrant polluter.</p>
            <p>Surely ungoverned lust makes man a fiend. Poor Jane made
an attempt to resist, but he presented a loaded revolver at her
head, and threatened to send all its contents into her. She
shared
<pb id="fred97" n="97"/>
the same fate as Louisa. Two or three more were served in a
similar manner. But why need I dwell upon the sickening
details. Good reader, you can imagine them; and the worst you
can imagine will not be a tenth part so bad as the reality. Such
is the ever-impending fate of the slave. To-day kindly treated,
virtuous, timorous of the future, yet comparatively happy. A
death, a debt, or any change of property, plunges them, in
spite of themselves, into unspeakable horrors, brutality, shame,
and woe. Surely the Lord of all will soon blot out such
things from the face of His fair creation.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Resignation of a Female Slave.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I can scarcely convey by any description the spirit of
complete resignation and hope for the future manifested by
religious slaves when suffering as no one but slaves could
suffer. The following anecdote will illustrate what I mean. My
master had a slave, by name Milly, who used to sing when she
was milking the cow (for Milly was constantly singing psalms
and hymns); when she stopped singing, the cow gave no milk,
but as soon as the cow heard the song again, she gave her
milk. My mistress has often taken visitors to see this. Poor
Milly was one day being flogged for some trifling fault, and my
master threatening to kill her because she did not say what
slaves being whipped generally do cry out, “Oh, pray
massa; oh, pray massa,” she
<pb id="fred98" n="98"/>
looked round at him so innocently and pitifully, and said, “De
sooner you kill me de sooner me go home to Jesus; He be
better massa dan you.” At last he did not whip her for any little
error, and the slaves said he was afraid of killing her, lest she
should be happy.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER IX.</head>
          <argument>
            <p>Cruelty to Slaves Concealed from Strangers—Slaveholders traduce
the English—Slaves' Opinions of the English—Slaves always
anxious to be Free.</p>
          </argument>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <p>TRAVELLERS and strangers passing through the Southern States
have no conception of the cruelty practised around them; it is
kept in the <sic>back ground.</sic> My master was ordering two slaves
to strip, for the purpose of flogging them, for having been out
without leave during the night. Two gentlemen rode up to the
house, and called to my master, and asked him, in a nasal tone,
if he had 1,000 cattle for sale, a boasting way, characteristic
of the Yankees. My master, perceiving instantly that they were
Northerners, said to the two slaves, “Put your things on
quickly. Make haste, boys;” and, addressing the gentleman,
said, “I have got nine or ten;” and turning to
<pb id="fred99" n="99"/>
the two slaves, “Now, my boys, fetch up the cattle for the
gentlemen; be as quick as you possibly can, that's good
fellows,” speaking in the kindest and blandest tones possible.
The cattle broke away, and got into the field again; my master,
not appearing in the least irritated, encouraged the two slaves, in
a very kind way, to bring them up again, which, after some time,
they succeeded in doing. The cattle were sold and driven
northwards, by some men belonging to the two gentlemen.
Some slaves heard one of the gentlemen call to the drivers, and
say, “Did you ever hear a northern gentleman speak more
kindly to his men than that slaveowner did to his slaves?”
“Never, never in all our lives,” the drivers replied. “Well, then,”
said the gentleman, “I will never, as long as I live, believe one
word about the cruelty of the slaveowners; it is all a foul libel;
they are only a great deal too kind.”</p>
            <p>As soon as the two gentlemen who had purchased the
cattle had departed, my master took the money which he had
received and put it away in the house, and then called the two
slaves to him and said, “Now, you scoundrels, come and
have your rations.” Each one was stript, and received a most
cruel whipping, their backs being cut in the most horrible
manner, the pour slaves calling and shrieking out for mercy,
but calling in vain; their cries ascending to heaven at the very
time when the two northern gentlemen were protesting that
every word about the cruelty of the southern planter was
false.</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="fred100" n="100"/>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Opinions of Slaves concerning the English.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Is it to be wondered at that slaves are almost always, when
they have a chance, talking privately about escaping, and
getting away to Great Britain's land, as Canada is called?
“You had better be a slave here than live in any of the British
Islands,” said a gentleman, a neighbour of my master, one day
to his slave. “If you were in any of the British possessions, and
were to speak against the Government, they would take you,
put your head upon a block, and chop it off. It would then
dance up and down apart from the body, which would be
wriggling about.” “Massa, is dat de way dey do?” said the
slave, laughing. “Yes; and if you were to speak against the
Queen, they would make a great fire and burn you alive.”
“Massa, is dat de way dey do?” said the slave, still laughing;
“will Massa let me go see?” “No; go along to your work,”
answered the irritated master. The negroes, although kept in
the grossest ignorance, cannot but be aware of the systematic
means adopted to debase them, and, in spite of all the masters
can do, the slaves see through their shallow pretended reasons
for oppressing them. However sedulously the slaveholders
may shut their slaves up from the outer world, and may distort
anything and everything which is contrary to their interests, yet
the power of truth is too great for them. Wonderfully
<pb id="fred101" n="101"/>
subtle is the atmosphere of opinion, penetrating where it is least
wanted. Every slave to a man has the most exalted idea of Great
Britain and her possessions. Whenever we slaves have been together
talking, we have always wished to be among the 
“Britainers.” We looked upon them as something very much
superior to Americans. There was a charm about the word
British which I cannot convey to any one. It meant, associated as
it was in our minds with the abolition of slavery, everything which
was noble and good.<ref targOrder="U" id="ref2" n="2" rend="sc" target="note2">*</ref> I never in my life knew a slave who did
not wish to escape. Several I have known who were well-treated,
and, if liberated, would willingly and gladly have remained
with their masters, but the fear of the “trader” constantly made
them uneasy.</p>
            <note id="note2" n="2" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref2">* I remember anxiously asking, when I escaped into Canada,
to be shown a Britainer, and a fine portly specimen was pointed out
to me, who, to my infinite delight, shook me by the hand, and congratulated me upon my escape.</note>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER X.</head>
          <argument>
            <p>An Abolitionist Planter contrives my Escape—My Escape by the
“Underground Railway”—Land in Canada—Employed by
the Anti-Slavery Society—Marry—Arrive in England—
Conclusion.</p>
          </argument>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <p>SINCE My first attempt to escape I was so uniformly treated
badly, that my life would have been
<pb id="fred102" n="102"/>
insupportable if I had not been soothed by the kind words of
the good abolitionist planter who had first conveyed to me a
true knowledge of religion. I had been flogged, and went one
day to show him the state in which I was. He asked me what I
wanted him to do. I said, “To get me away to Canada.” Oh,
what a delightful word to us poor slaves! It was like speaking
of some heavenly country. There was music in its sound to our
ears. Never did tempest-tossed sailor long so much for a
haven as we did for that land of the free. When I mentioned
Canada to the gentleman, he sat for full twenty minutes
thoughtfully, and at last said, “Now, if I promise to take you
away out of all this, you must not mention a word to any one.
Don't breathe a syllable to your mother or sisters, or it will be
betrayed.” Oh, how my heart jumped for joy at this promise. I
felt new life come into me. Visions of happiness flitted before
my mind. And then I thought before the next day he might
change his mind, and I was miserable again. I solemnly assured
him I would say nothing to any one. “Come to me,” he said,
“on the Friday night about ten or eleven o'clock; I will wait till
you come. Don't bring any clothes with you except those you
have on. But bring any money you can get.” I said I would
obey him in every respect. I went home and passed an
anxious day. I walked
<pb id="fred103" n="103"/>
out to my poor old mother's hut, and saw her and my sisters.
How I longed to tell them, and bid them farewell. I hesitated
several times when I thought I should never see them more. I
turned back again and again to look at my mother. I knew she
would be flogged, old as she was, for my escaping. I could
foresee how my master would stand over her with the lash to
extort from her my hiding-place. I was her only son left. How
she would suffer torture on my account, and be distressed
that I had left her for ever until we should meet hereafter in
heaven I hoped. At length I walked rapidly away, as if to leave
my thoughts behind me, and arrived at my kind benefactor's
house a little after eleven o'clock. He said but little, and
seemed restless. He took some rugs and laid them at the
bottom of the waggon, and covered me with some more.
Soon we were on our way to Maysville, which was about
twenty miles from his house. The horses trotted on rapidly, and
I lay overjoyed at my chance of escape. When we stopped
at Maysville, I remained for some time perfectly quiet, listening
to every sound. At last I heard a gentleman's voice, saying,
“Where is he? where is he?” and then he put in his hand and
felt me. I started, but my benefactor told me it was all right, it
was a friend. “This gentleman,” he added, “will take care of
you; you must go to his house.” I got out of the waggon and
shook my deliverer by the hand with a very, very grateful
<pb id="fred104" n="104"/>
heart, you may be sure; for I knew the risk he had run on my
account. He wished me every success, and committed me to
his friend, whom I accompanied to his house, and was
received with the utmost kindness by his wife, who asked me if
I was a Christian man. I answered yes. She took me up into a
garret and brought me some food. Her little daughters shook
hands with me. She spoke of the curse of slavery to the land. “I
am an abolitionist,” she said, “although in a slaveholding
country. The work of the Lord will not go on as
long as slavery is carried on here.” Every possible attention was
paid to me to soothe my troubled mind. The following night the
gentleman and his son left the house about ten o'clock, and
had not returned at twelve. I was crying, being afraid they
could not manage it. The lady assured me her husband would
get a skiff, if even he had to break the lock (skiffs are chained
and locked to the shore). However, a little after twelve o'clock
the gentleman returned, and said he had got a boat and I was
to go with him. His lady bid me farewell, and told me to put
my trust in the Lord, in whose hands my friends were, and
asked me to remember them in my prayers, since they had
hazarded everything for me, and, if discovered, they would be
cruelly treated. I was soon rowed across the river, which is
about a mile wide in that place. The son remained with me in
the skiff whilst his father went to a neighbouring village
<pb id="fred105" n="105"/>
to bring some one to take charge of me. After some time, he
brought a friend, who told me never to mention the name of
any one who had helped me; and that when I got to Canada I
might write and tell my master of my escape, but never to
allude to those who had in any way assisted me, and to ask the
blessing of the Lord for them. He took me to his house outside
the town, where I had some refreshment, and remained about
half-an-hour. A waggon came up, and I was stowed away,
and driven about twenty miles that night, being well guarded by
eight or ten young men with revolvers. It would do any real
Christian man good to see the enthusiasm and determination of
these young Abolitionists. Their whole heart and soul are in the
work. A dozen such men would have defied a hundred
slaveholders. From having seen over and over again slaves
dragged back chained through their country, and having heard
the tales of horrible treatment of the poor hopeless
captives, some having been flogged to death, others burnt alive,
with their heads downwards, over a slow fire, others covered
with tar and set on fire,—these noble, courageous, self-sacrificing
men have been so wrought upon, that they are
heroes of the highest stamp, and I verily believe they would
willingly lay down their lives rather than allow one fugitive slave
to be taken from them.</p>
            <p>On I went, from one station to another, everywhere
<pb id="fred106" n="106"/>
where being received and lodged as if I were a chosen guest. If
it was after midnight, all in the house, even to the old
grandmother and little children, would get up and crowd round
me, listening to my sorrows, and shedding alternately tears of
joy and grief for my escape and the bitter pangs I had had to
endure. How shall I, who, to the age of fifty, was a poor
illiterate slave, find adequate language to express my eternal
gratitude to them! He who is above, and is the Lord and
Master of us all, I know will reward them for their goodness.
To Him I pray as I pass on in the day, and as I lie awake in the
silent hours of the night, to pour blessings upon them.</p>
            <p>I came at last to a large station of what is called the
Underground Railway, about 160 miles from the banks of the
Ohio river. But think not, you who read this, that my mind was
at rest. Two or three nights in succession I dreamt that I was
taken by my master, and all the details of the capture were so
vividly depicted in my dreams, that I could scarcely, when
awake, believe it was all a vision of the night. I should have
been pleased to have entered more fully into particulars
concerning these journeys from station to station, but my
Quaker friends tell me it would be very injudicious to do so,
since one or two fugitive slaves, having described things too
minutely, had put the slaveholders upon the right track, and the
Underground
<pb id="fred107" n="107"/>
Railway had been torn up, to the injury of my
brethren in bondage, who might otherwise have
escaped.</p>
            <p>At this large station I remained over the winter, from
November to the middle of May. I had now got pretty well
assured of my safety, and had the range of a large house.
There was a family of eleven or twelve children, some grown-up
young men and women. The younger portion of the children
soon became very much attached to me, following me from
room to room, and asking me to learn to read. I told them I
was fifty years of age, and too old. Oh, no, they said; I could
learn, and they would soon teach me. One day little Johnny, a
fine fellow about twelve years of age, and his sister Charlotte,
about ten, stood by my side with a book with the A, B, C, in
large letters. “Can you see that?” said Johnny, pointing at the
first letter. “Yes,” I replied. “Well, then,” they rejoined,
laughing, “you <hi rend="italics">can</hi> learn, for you can see. Now, that is A.”
Pointing to the next, “That is B. Oh, I see you can know
them,” said Johnny; and I felt I could tell the difference.
Regularly did they teach me, often laughing at my mistakes, but
still delighted whenever I, stupid enough, no doubt, made an
effort. I soon found I had conquered the letters. My little
master and mistress were as proud of this victory as if it had
been some noble achievement. Yes, and so it was, for it
opened the gates of ignorance, and displayed to me a new
world,
<pb id="fred108" n="108"/>
part of which I could make permanently my own. Day by day
I said to my little instructors my spelling, first of one syllable,
and then of two, dozens of times over. It would have tired the
patience of man or woman, but my little teachers were never
out of temper, but persevered until I finally could read the first
chapter of John.</p>
            <p>Bless all the children in the world! I should have remained in
ignorance if I had not been taught by them. When I see them
gambolling about in their sports, how delighted I am. Often and
often have I stood among them in the Sunday-school, and
when the teacher has said “Boys,” I have straightened myself
up, and thought I was one of them. Where-ever I go, I find they
feel the influence of this kindly disposition towards them. They
hang about me, take me by the hand, and never am I so happy
as when I am surrounded by them. I can truly say, reverently,
in the words of my sacred Master, “Suffer little children to
come unto me, for of such is the kingdom of heaven.”</p>
            <p>About the middle of May, I was sent to Sindusky city, on
the borders of Lake Erie. But I shall never forget the prayers
offered up for my welfare by the master, and the pain it gave
me to part from my dear young friends. They would have
willingly kept me always, they said; but I knew, although there
was not much danger, yet there was risk, and I longed to be
on British soil. I heard my friends bargain with the captain of a
<pb id="fred109" n="109"/>
steamer to take me across the lake. He said, “Have you only
one? I wish you had a hundred. I would gladly take them
over.” A noble, generous-hearted man he was!</p>
            <p>I was landed at some town in Michigan, but I forget the
name of the town. The mate took me to an Abolitionist's
house, who said he would forward me on to Canada. From
this town I went to another place in Pennsylvania, and from thence
to a minister's house in York State, who said jocosely
that he had the strongest fort, next to Gibraltar, in the world.
He said, for fifteen miles round they were all Abolitionists, and
I was perfectly safe; that, although he was acting contrary to
the Fugitive Slave Law, he did it with pleasure, since he
believed that law to be contrary to the law of God, and he
willingly trampled it under his feet; that he had had at least
thirty fugitive slaves before me.</p>
            <p>After a few months, the Abolitionist gentlemen held a
Meeting, and I told them some of my sufferings in slavery.
They prayed with me; and I remember an old Quaker lady,
shaking me by the hand, and speaking kindly, said, “Thee must
not, when thee gets to Canada, say, ‘I have done it 'cute; I
have been Smart.’ Thee must remember, that it is the Lord
who has been thy friend. Ask Him to give thee a portion of
His Spirit; and give Him the glory and honour.”</p>
            <p>I was passed on to Louistown, on Lake Ontario, to be
sent across to Toronto.</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="fred110" n="110"/>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Land in Canada.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>On Lake Ontario—unlike when I was on Lake Erie—although
it was rough, I was not sick or ill; for my mind seemed so much
on the stretch, and so elated with the thought that Canada was
at hand, I felt nerved for anything, and could almost bound
out of the steamer.</p>
            <p>I gazed upon the people on shore, until I thought they
would think I was wild; and, at last—thank the Lord for ever!—
placed my foot on free British soil, in Toronto.</p>
            <p>But now, when I was in Toronto, under the British flag and
the British ride, I found there was still the Yankee prejudice
existing against my race, and a distinction, and badge of inferiority, still clinging to me. Going into a barber's shop, one day, to be shaved, the master
said, “What do you want?” I replied, “To be shaved.” “Oh, we
don't shave black men here,” he said. I went towards the door,
when, following me, the barber said, “If I were to shave you, I
should lose all my customers; but you will find a shop down the
street where they shave black men exclusively.”</p>
            <p>Now, when I came to Liverpool, and went into a shop, to be
shaved, when it came to my turn, I declined, saying, the other
gentlemen, who had come in after me, had better be shaved
first; but, after three or four more had been operated upon they
<pb id="fred111" n="111"/>
insisted that I should take the next turn. No one can possibly
understand my delight and mingled feelings of pleasure and
gratitude, that I was, at last, placed on an equality with the
white man; and, rising up, I could not refrain from ejaculating,
loudly and sincerely, “God save the Queen!” to the
astonishment and merriment of those in the place. Aye, true
liberty is surely a pearl of great price. I felt, at last, completely
disenthralled in mind and body.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Employed by the Anti-Slavery Society.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>But, to return to Toronto, I was soon employed by the Anti-Slavery
Society there, to look after the fugitive slaves. And I
can assure my readers that this was to me, who could truly
sympathize with them, a most heart-rending occupation.
Haggard and emaciated, from anxiety and want of rest, men
and women presented a most deplorable picture. Some of
them were mulattoes and quadroons, and, being employed
generally in household duties, they were very intelligent, and,
in many cases, except to a practised eye, they could scarcely
be distinguished from the pure white. Others were of coal-black
colour, and, having been degraded to the uttermost, by
abuse hardship, on the plantations, seemed but little removed
from an animal; but a short
<pb id="fred112" n="112"/>
period of kindness and attention, and freedom, seemed to
work wonders in the development of their minds.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Marry.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I soon found that, at least in the minds of the English, there
was not such a repugnance to, and prejudice against, my race;
for I formed an attachment—I suppose, at my age, I must not
call it love—to a Devonshire female, who was residing in
Toronto, and I have the best of all reasons to suppose it was
reciprocated, for I was accepted by her, and married her; and
it was owing to her wishing to come among her friends, that
has brought me to this grand old land of liberty.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Arrive in England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Armed with recommendations from the Rev. J. S. Ellerby,
minister of the First Congregational Church, Toronto, to the
Rev. Dr. Raffles, of Liverpool, I bid farewell to that land of
many sorrows, and, in the last few months, some joys and
regrets to part from my kind benefactors.</p>
            <p>I was kindly received, on my presenting my credentials, by
that gentleman. Since then, to the best of my humble ability,
and as much as my
<pb id="fred113" n="113"/>
enfeebled health would permit, I have been engaged in various
parts of the country, speaking concerning my own experience
and escape from slavery, and lecturing, as well as I could,
about slavery generally; thus doing my best for many who are
still enduring what a merciful Providence has rescued me from.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>
              <hi rend="italics">Conclusion.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I am not competent to enter into learned arguments about
the natural rights of man, and the consequent wrongs inflicted
by slavery on the African race. I have but little acquaintance
with literature; but there is one Book, which I read as much as
I can, and what it says I believe, and all the arguments of all
the learned in the world are nothing to me, if they are opposed
to what it says and teaches.</p>
            <p>I was reading, the other day, the eighth chapter of the Acts
of the Apostles, and I found a passage there so interesting to
me, that I cannot refrain from transcribing it,<ref targOrder="U" id="ref3" n="3" rend="sc" target="note3">*</ref> and asking you,
candid reader,
<note id="note3" n="3" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref3">* “And the angel of the Lord spake unto Philip, saying, Arise,
and go toward the south unto the way that goeth down from
Jerusalem unto Gaza, which is desert. And he arose and went:
and, behold, a man of Ethiopia, an eunuch of great authority
under Candace queen of the Ethiopians, who had the charge of
all her treasure, and had come to Jerusalem for to worship, was
returning, and sitting in his chariot read Esaias the prophet.
 Then the Spirit said unto Philip,
Go near, and join thyself to this chariot. And Philip ran thither to
him, and heard him read the prophet Esaias, and said,
Understandest thou what thou readest? And he said, How can
I, except some man should guide me? And he desired Philip
that he would come up and sit with him. The place of the
scripture which he read was this, He was led as a sheep to the
slaughter; and like a lamb dumb before his shearer, so opened he
not his mouth: in his humiliation his judgment was taken away:
and who shall declare his generation? for his life is taken from
the earth. And the eunuch answered Philip, and said, I pray thee,
of whom speaketh the prophet this? of himself, or of some other
man? Then Philip opened his mouth, and began at the same
scripture, and preached unto him Jesus. And as they went on
their way, they came unto a certain water: and the eunuch said,
See, here is water; what doth hinder me to be baptized? And
Philip said, If thou believest with all thine heart, thou mayest.
And he answered and said, I believe that Jesus Christ is the Son
of God. And he commanded the chariot to stand still: and they
went down both into the water, both Philip and the eunuch; and
he baptized him. And when they were come up out of the
water, the Spirit of the Lord caught away Philip, that the eunuch
saw him no more: and he went on his way rejoicing. But Philip
was found at Azotus: and passing through he preached in all the
cities, till he came to Cesarea.”—ACTS, viii. 26—40.</note>
<pb id="fred114" n="114"/>
to see whether Philip—who is a greater authority, I have no
doubt, with you, than all the slaveholders, and their clerical
supporters, put together—objected to the Ethiopian, that his skin
was black, and that he was of the African race?</p>
            <p>No. No such things were suggested. The one
<pb id="fred115" n="115"/>
thing required by Philip was, belief in the Lord Jesus Christ;
and, in order to induce that belief, the Apostle himself
preached, that is, explained, to the Ethiopian, the wondrous
prophecy concerning our Lord contained in the fifty-third
chapter of the Prophet Isaiah.</p>
            <p>Thus, I find, long before the Gospel was known to the
ancestors of the slaveholders, the Lord had sent His heavenly
messenger, with the glad tidings to my countrymen in Africa.
There can be no true controversy about this. It is so plain that
he that runs may read; and, although my race may, by an
inscrutable Providence, have been permitted to be oppressed
for generations, yet, as they were among the first to receive
His Spirit, I believe there is a good time at hand, when a fresh
outpouring of it will be felt amongst them; the barriers being
now breaking down, amidst the horrors of civil war.</p>
            <p>Depend upon it, when the Gospel shall be preached to
them, in its purity, the negro race will receive it, in its simplicity,
and will show a higher Christian capacity than the world has
given them credit for. The Gospel is just suited to their simple,
forgiving, humane nature. May God hasten that time! is my
sincere prayer.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <trailer>LONDON: WERTHEIM, MACINTOSH, and HUNT,
24, Paternoster-row, and 23, Holles-street, Cavendish-square.</trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>