<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY white78 SYSTEM "white78.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY whitetp SYSTEM "whitetp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY whitevs SYSTEM "whitevs.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>The African Preacher. An Authentic Narrative:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>White, William S. (William Spotswood)  1800-1873</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Laura Button and LeeAnn Morawski</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by</resp>
          <name>Laura Button and LeeAnn Morawski</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Aletha Andrew  and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1999</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca.     200K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1999.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching 
and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note anchored="yes">Call number         
PS3179.W48A4  (Davis Library, UNC-CH)</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>The African Preacher. An Authentic Narrative.</title>
          <author>Rev. William S. White</author>
          <imprint>
            <pubPlace>Philadelphia:</pubPlace>
            <publisher>Presbyterian 
Board of Publication</publisher>
            <date>1849</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>All footnotes are moved to the end of a paragraph in which the reference occurs.</p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ 
respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not
 been preserved.</p>
        <p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor 
(SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st 
edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="spa">Spanish</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Jack, Uncle, 1746?-1843.</item>
            <item>African American clergy -- Virginia -- Nottoway County --
Biography.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Virginia -- Nottoway County --
Religion.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Virginia -- Nottoway County --
Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Virginia -- Nottoway County -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Religious life -- Virginia -- Nottoway
County.</item>
            <item>Jones, James, 1772-1848.</item>
            <item>Slaveholders -- Virginia -- Nottoway County --
Biography.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2000-06-05, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-07-21, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-07-20, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Aletha Andrew</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-07-13, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Laura Button and LeeAnn Morawski</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="titlepage">
        <p>
          <figure id="tp" entity="whitetp"/>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="verso">
        <p>
          <figure id="vs" entity="whitevs"/>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">THE<lb/>
AFRICAN PREACHER.<lb/>
AN AUTHENTIC NARRATIVE.</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>BY THE</byline>
        <docAuthor>REV. WILLIAM S. WHITE,<lb/>
Pastor of the Presbyterian Church, Lexington, Virginia.</docAuthor>
        <docImprint><pubPlace>PHILADELPHIA:</pubPlace>
<publisher>PRESBYTERIAN BOARD OF PUBLICATION,</publisher>
<pubPlace>No. 265 CHESTNUT STREET.</pubPlace></docImprint>
        <pb id="whitevs" n="verso"/>
        <docImprint><docDate>Entered according to the Act of Congress in the year 1849, by<lb/>
A. W. MITCHELL, M.D.,<lb/>
In the Office of the Clerk of the District Court for the Eastern District<lb/>
of Pennsylvania.</docDate>
<publisher>Stereotyped by Wm. S. SLOTE, No. 19 St. James Street,<lb/>
Philadelphia.</publisher></docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="dedication">
        <pb id="white3" n="3"/>
        <opener><salute>To the Rev. BENJAMIN H. RICE, D. D.,</salute><lb/>
<dateline>Pastor of Hampden Sidney Church, Va.:</dateline></opener>
        <p>REV. AND DEAR BROTHER—BY your counsel, my
humble labours as a Domestic Missionary were
commenced in the county of Nottoway; and to your
sympathy and co-operation is to be ascribed a large
portion of the little good which may have resulted
from those labours. It is, therefore, most reasonable
that a narrative resulting, as this does, from that
mission, should be inscribed to you.</p>
        <p>Accept it, then, as an humble expression of the
respect, the gratitude, and the love of</p>
        <closer><salute>Your Friend and Brother,</salute>
<signed>WILLIAM S. WHITE. </signed>THE MANSE, <hi rend="italics">Lexington, Va., March</hi> 10, 1849.</closer>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="narrative">
        <pb id="white5" n="5"/>
        <head>THE AFRICAN PREACHER.</head>
        <p>THE prominence given in the Scriptures
to the characters and lives of such persons as
Ruth, Esther, and Nehemiah, proves, that
“God hath chosen the poor of this world,
rich in faith, and heirs of the kingdom which
he hath promised to them that love him”—
that he hath moreover “chosen the foolish
things of the world, to confound the wise,
and the weak things of the world, to
confound the things that are mighty.” Since
the days of inspiration ended, the dealings
of God's providence and the dispensations
of his grace, have beautifully harmonized
with the revelations of his word. Hence, in
all ages of the world, down to
the present hour, many of the loveliest
<pb id="white6" n="6"/>
specimens of true piety, have been found in
the humblest walks of life. Here, God's
wisdom, love, and mercy shine with a lustre
all their own; and here, religion displays its
richest fruits.</p>
        <p>The narrative now to be given is
designed to illustrate these remarks. The
subject of it was a native of Africa. When
about seven years of age, he was
kidnapped, brought to this country, and
enslaved. He was supposed to belong to
one of the last <hi rend="italics">cargoes</hi> of this sort, ever
landed on the shores of Virginia. He was
purchased at Osborne's, on James' river, by
a Mr. Stewart, and was subsequently taken
to the county of Nottoway, Virginia, where
the whole of his long and interesting life
was spent.</p>
        <p>He grew to manhood, ignorant of letters,
and a stranger to God; engaged in the
occupations common to those in a state of
bondage. The region of
<pb id="white7" n="7"/>
country in which he lived, was, at this
period, deplorably destitute of the means of
grace. The gospel was seldom preached,
the Sabbath scarcely known as a “day of
sacred rest,” and few were found willing to
incur the odium of a public profession of
religion.</p>
        <p>Before we proceed further with our
narrative it is important to state, that
“Uncle Jack,” for so he was universally
called, possessed great acuteness of mind,
and understood and spoke the English
language far better than any
native of Africa we have ever known. His
pronunciation was not only distinct and
accurate, but his style was chaste and
forcible. His great superiority in this respect
must be ascribed to the following causes:—
First, to his having left his native land at so
early an age. Next, to the freedom with
which he was permitted and encouraged to
mingle in the best society the country afforded;
<pb id="white8" n="8"/>
and above all, to the familiar
acquaintance he soon formed with the
language of the Bible. The reader must not
be surprised, therefore, that nothing occurs
in what we quote from his own lips, of the
jargon peculiar to the African race. Nobody
ever heard the good old preacher say <hi rend="italics">massa</hi>
for <hi rend="italics">master</hi> or <hi rend="italics">me</hi> for<hi rend="italics"> I.</hi></p>
        <p>It was during the period of intellectual
and moral darkness already referred to, and
when he had probably reached the fortieth
year of his age, that he became anxious on
the subject of religion. The account he gave
of his early religious impressions, was very
simple. He said nothing of dreams and
visions, as is so common with persons of his
colour. His attention was first arrested, and
his fears excited, by hearing from a white
man that the world would probably be
destroyed in a few days. On hearing this, he
<pb id="white9" n="9"/>
asked his informant what he must do
to prepare for an event so awful. He was told
to pray. “This,” he said, “I knew nothing
about. I could not pray.” At length he was
enabled to recall some portions of the Lord's
prayer, which he continued to repeat for a
considerable time. But these efforts brought
him no relief.</p>
        <p>That which thus commenced in mere
alarm, soon led to a deep and thorough
conviction of his guilt, helplessness, and
misery, in the sight of God. He now exerted
himself in various ways, and with untiring
zeal, to obtain a knowledge of the truth as it
is in Jesus. There were literally none in his
vicinity, either in the ministry, or among the
private members of the church, qualified to
teach and to guide an inquiring mind like his.
The Presbyterian church, then recently
established in Prince Edward, was within
<pb id="white10" n="10"/>
thirty miles of his residence. The ministers
of the gospel from that county, made
occasional excursions into Nottoway.
From these he soon obtained the help he
needed. His own statement on this subject
is as follows: “I had a very wicked heart,
and every thing I did, to make it better,
seemed to make it worse. At length a
preacher passed along; they called him Mr.
President Smith.<ref id="ref1" n="1" rend="sc" target="note1" targOrder="U">*</ref>He turned my
heart inside out. The preacher talked
so directly <hi rend="italics">to</hi> me, and <hi rend="italics">about</hi> me, that I
thought the whole sermon was meant
for me. I wondered much, who could
have told him what a sinner I was.
But after a while there came along a young 
man they called Mr. Hill;<ref id="ref2" n="2" rend="sc" target="note2" targOrder="U">**</ref> and about the same
time another, with a sweet voice, they called Mr.
<note id="note1" n="1" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref1">* The Rev. John Blair Smith, D. D., then President of
Hampden Sidney College.</note>
<note id="note2" n="2" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref2">** (The Rev. Wm. Hill, D. D., of Winchester, Va.</note>
<pb id="white11" n="11"/>
Alexander.<ref id="ref3" n="3" rend="sc" target="note3" targOrder="U">*</ref> These were powerful preachers too,
and told me all about my troubles; and
brought me to see, that there was nothing
for a poor, helpless sinner to do, but to go
to the Lord Jesus Christ, and trust in him
alone for salvation. Since that time, I have
had many ups and downs; but hitherto the
Lord has helped me, and I hope he will
help me to the end.”</p>
        <note id="note3" n="3" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref3">* The Rev. Archibald Alexander, D. D., afterwards
Professor of Theology, Princeton, New Jersey.</note>
        <p>He now became deeply interested in
hearing the Scriptures read. As his
knowledge of the Bible increased, he
found, to use his own language, “that it
knew all that was in his heart.” He
wondered how “a book should know so
much.”</p>
        <p>He was still unable to read, but now
determined to learn. To this end he
applied to his master's children for
assistance; promising to reward them for
<pb id="white12" n="12"/>
their pains with nuts and other fruits, as
tuition fees. By the aid of his youthful
instructors, his object was soon attained, and
he read the word of God with ease. The
sacred volume now became the constant
companion of his leisure hours. So rapid
was his progress in divine knowledge, and
such his prudence, good sense, and zeal,
that many of the most intelligent and pious
people of his neighbourhood expressed the
desire to have him duly authorized to preach
the gospel. The Baptist church, of which he
had become a member, took this matter into
serious consideration; and after subjecting
him to the trials usually imposed by that
denomination, licensed him to labour as a
herald of the cross.</p>
        <p>Upon the duties of his new and
responsible office, he entered with a truly
apostolic spirit. He commenced his ministry
in a neighbourhood where there
<pb id="white13" n="13"/>
were literally none to break statedly to the
people the bread of life. His labours were
abundant and faithful. He was often called
to preach at a distance of more than thirty
miles from his home. He was still a slave,
and never seemed to think of any better
state, until his attention was called to it by
others. He belonged to the undivided estate
of his original purchaser, who was now
dead. Some of the legatees of this estate
were willing to emancipate him, but others
were not. This, however, constituted no
serious obstacle. He had rendered himself
so useful, and had gained the confidence
and good will of the community to so great
an extent, that a sum of money was soon
raised by subscription, quite sufficient to
satisfy the demands of those who were
unwilling to liberate him. Some idea may be
formed of the estimation in which he was
held, when it is known that many
<pb id="white14" n="14"/>
contributed liberally to the fund thus
created, who were not professors of
religion. Having thus secured his freedom,
he settled on a small tract of land, of which
he became the proprietor, chiefly through
the munificence of others, and lived in a
way which satisfied his humble wishes.
Here he literally earned his bread with the
sweat of his brow, while he faithfully
dispensed to others the bread of life, with
scarcely any compensation, except the
consciousness of doing good.</p>
        <p>The late Rev. John H. Rice, D. D., had
a brief interview with our preacher, in
which he was deeply interested. This
occurred during the summer of 1826, when
the old man had nearly reached the 80th
year of his age, and one year before our
acquaintance with him commenced.</p>
        <p>Referring to this interview afterwards,
Dr. Rice said, “The acquaintance
<pb id="white15" n="15"/>
of this African preacher with the
Scriptures is wonderful. Many of his
interpretations of obscure passages are
singularly just and striking. In many
respects, indeed, he is one of the most
remarkable men I have ever known.”</p>
        <p>At this period, Dr. Rice was editor of
the Virginia Literary and Evangelical
Magazine; and entertaining the views
expressed above, it is not surprising that
the pages of this valuable
periodical should contain a brief but
interesting memoir of “Uncle Jack.” It may
be found in the first number of Vol. 10. In
this memoir, Dr. Rice expresses himself
thus: “There lives in a neighbouring county,
an old African, named Jack, whose history is
more worthy of record than that of many a man
whose name has held a conspicuous place
in the annals of the world. There is a book
which, I have no doubt, contains the name
of <hi rend="italics">Old Jack,</hi> but not those,
<pb id="white16" n="16"/>
I fear, of many great men and nobles
of this world. It is ‘the Lamb's book of life.’</p>
        <p>“Jack possesses the entire confidence of
the whole neighbourhood in which he
lives. No man doubts his integrity or the
sincerity of his piety. All classes treat him
with marked respect. Everybody gives
unequivocal testimony to the excellence of
his character.</p>
        <p>“He possesses a strong mind, and,
for a man in his situation, has acquired
considerable religious knowledge. His
influence among people of his own
colour is very extensive and beneficial.</p>
        <p>“Old Jack is as entirely free from all
bigotry and party spirit, as any Christian
I have ever seen. He acknowledges
every man to be a brother, whom he
believes to be a Christian. A very
striking proof of his humble, teachable,
catholic spirit, is given in his conduct
towards two Presbyterian missionaries,
<pb id="white17" n="17"/>
who were successively sent to the part of
the country where he resides. On their
arrival, he seemed very cautiously to
investigate their character. The result was a
conviction that they were pious and
devoted men; and a hearty recognition of
them as ambassadors of Christ. He found,
too, that they knew a great deal more than
he did, and resolved to employ his influence
in bringing the black people in his
neighbourhood under their instruction. He
also frequently consulted them in regard to
matters of difficulty with himself, and used
their attainments for the increase of his own
knowledge, and for enabling him the
better to instruct the numerous blacks who
looked up to him as their only teacher.</p>
        <p>“It has before been said, that the
conduct of this old Christian had secured
the respect and confidence of the white
people. As evidence of this, some
<pb id="white18" n="18"/>
time ago a lawless white man
attempted to deprive him of his land, under a
plea that his title was not good. As soon as
the design was known, a number of the first
men in the neighbourhood volunteered to
assist him in maintaining his right, and a
lawyer of some distinction, not then a
believer, rendered gratuitous service on the
occasion, because everybody said, Uncle
Jack was a good man.</p>
        <p>“But while the white people respect, the
blacks love, fear, and obey him. His
influence among them is unbounded. His
authority over the members of his own
church is greater than that of the master, or
the overseer. And if one of them commits
an offence of any magnitude, he never
ceases dealing with him, until the offender is
brought to repentance, or excluded from the
society. The gentlemen of the vicinity freely
acknowledge, that this influence is highly
<pb id="white19" n="19"/>
beneficial. Accordingly, he has permission to
hold meetings on the neighbouring plantations
whenever he thinks proper. He often visits
the sick of his own colour, and preaches at
all the funerals of the blacks who die any
where within his reach.”</p>
        <p>The high source from whence this
extract is taken, and the extent to which it
must sustain and enforce the
subsequent portion of our narrative, is
a sufficient excuse for its introduction.</p>
        <p>One of the most gifted and honoured sons of old
Virginia,<ref id="ref4" n="4" rend="sc" target="note4" targOrder="U">*</ref> who resided for more than forty
years within one mile of the subject of this
narrative, who was thoroughly acquainted
with his public and private life, and who even
acknowledged himself under obligations
to this humble preacher of righteousness as
a spiritual instructor, furnished
<note id="note4" n="4" rend="SC" place="FOOT" anchored="yes" target="ref4">* Dr. James Jones, of Mountain Hall.—See Appendix.</note>
<pb id="white20" n="20"/>
the following just and beautiful delineation
of his character.</p>
        <p>“I regard this old African as a burning
and shining light, raised up by
Christian principles alone, to a degree
of moral purity seldom equalled, and never
exceeded in any country. Think of him as
an African boy, kidnapped at seven years
of age, torn away from his heathen parents,
thrust into a slave-ship among hundreds of
the most degraded beings, transported
across the Atlantic, landed on our coast,
bought by a very obscure planter in what
was then the back-woods of Virginia, here
kept in bondage at the usual occupation of
slaves, under circumstances but little
calculated to improve the mind, or mend
the heart; without letters, without
instruction, until a glimpse of divine truth,
caught by hearing the Bible read, arrested
his attention. Seizing on the truth thus
<pb id="white21" n="21"/>
obtained, and appreciating its excellence,
almost without assistance, he soon learns
to read the sacred volume. His researches
are now pursued with growing zeal, and
signal success, until he is enabled to
penetrate into some of its most sublime
mysteries, to feel the force of its
obligations, to enjoy its consolations, and
to become an able and successful
expounder of its doctrines to others.</p>
        <p>“As a preacher of the gospel, he gained
the good will and secured the confidence
of all who were capable of appreciating
true excellence of character, gained
admittance into the best families, and was
there permitted to enjoy a freedom of
intercourse that I never witnessed in any
other similar case.</p>
        <p>“All these views of this old man's
character, have excited in my mind
somewhat of an enthusiastic admiration
<pb id="white22" n="22"/>
seldom felt by me for any member of the
human family, of any rank or station. Such
effects under all the circumstances of the
case, must be traced up to a cause
altogether superhuman, and set the seal to
the superlative excellence, the divine
authenticity of the Christian system.”</p>
        <p>A lady, whose rank, intelligence and
piety, place her among the first of her sex,
and who still lives to bear testimony to the
literal truth of this narrative, has kindly
furnished the following statement written
more than ten years ago.</p>
        <p>“My acquaintance with the old man
commenced about thirty years since,
when there was scarcely a vestige of
piety, especially among the higher classes
in this community. The Baptist church
to which he belonged was in this region
nearly extinct. The few members who
remained, he regularly visited and 
<pb id="white23" n="23"/>
instructed. His first visit at our
house was intended for a Baptist lady who
was spending some time with us. In his
conversation with this lady, I was surprised
at the readiness and propriety with which
he quoted the Scriptures; and especially at
the sound sense which characterized his
practical reflections on the passages
quoted. This induced me to seek a more
intimate acquaintance with him; and as he
found I was interested in his conversation,
he often called on me.</p>
        <p>“He has been eminently useful to many
persons of my acquaintance. When under
spiritual concern, they would apply to no
other teacher. During the period of dreadful
darkness, to which I have already alluded,
he went from house to house, doing good.
About this time, he became signally
instrumental in the conversion of his former
master's youngest son. This youth gave
<pb id="white24" n="24"/>
abundant evidence of vital piety, both in
his life and his death.</p>
        <p>“I think the most prominent traits in his
character, are meekness, humility and rigid
integrity. He possesses naturally a strong
mind, a very retentive memory, with the
happiest talent for illustrating important
truth, by the objects of sense, and the
ordinary employments of life. I trust, dear
sir, you will be able to furnish the public
with an instructive account of this humble
and obscure, but interesting and useful old
man.”</p>
        <p>This communication was designed to aid
in the preparation of a series of biographical
sketches of “The African Preacher,” which
appeared in the columns of the Watchman
of the South in 1839; and was so used. The
writer still lives, and would doubtless
acknowledge that in her transition from
darkness to light, and from the power of
<pb id="white25" n="25"/>
Satan unto God, she was mainly indebted,
through divine grace, to the visits and the
conversations of the good old African,
referred to in her letter.</p>
        <p>Uncle Jack's views of the fundamental
doctrines of the Bible, were thoroughly
evangelical. He was particularly fond, to
use his own words, of “that preaching
which makes God everything, and man
nothing.” The total depravity of man—the
absolute sovereignty of God in electing him
to salvation through the imputed
righteousness of Christ—the necessity of
regeneration by the Spirit, through the belief
of the truth—the growth in grace and final
salvation of all who truly repent and believe
the gospel; these were his favourite themes,
both in his sermons and conversation. And
these, with all their kindred topics, he could
illustrate by allusions to nature and art, with
a clearness which left no obscurity
<pb id="white26" n="26"/>
about his real sentiments. He was
particularly fond of the Epistle to the
Romans, and often spoke of it, as
containing “the very marrow of the
gospel.” He often bestowed much time on
a single passage. On one occasion, he
called our attention to the third verse of the
eighth chapter of Romans, saying, “Master C.
and I have been studying a great deal over
that verse for the last three weeks, and we do not
fully understand it yet. Do tell me all about it.”</p>
        <p>Anxious to know what his own construction
was, we insisted that he should give us his
opinion, promising to give him ours when he had
concluded. With this proposition he was very
reluctant to comply, but finally consenting, he
proceeded as follows. We give the exposition
in his own order, and almost <hi rend="italics">verbatim</hi> as he
gave it to us. “Well,” said he, “I will do
<pb id="white27" n="27"/>
the best I can. The verse begins thus: ‘For
what the law could not do.’ And what is it
the law can't do? Why, it can't justify us in
the sight of God. Why not? Because ‘it was
weak through the flesh.’ There is no
weakness in the law. <hi rend="italics">That</hi> is as strong as
its Author. But the weakness is in man's
flesh. Observe, this is a weakness <hi rend="italics">‘through
the flesh.’</hi> That is, the weakness is in man's
corrupt nature. Now, what is to be done
for man in his helplessness and guilt? The
text tells us plainly, ‘God sending his own
Son’—for what? Why, to do for ruined man
what the law could not do on account of
his sinfully weak nature. And when God
sent his Son, <hi rend="italics">how</hi> did he come? ‘In the
likeness of sinful flesh.’ I suppose that
means, he came as a man, though not a sinful
man; for he knew no sin. And <hi rend="italics">why</hi> did he come?
The text answers, ‘and for sin, condemned
<pb id="white28" n="28"/>
sin in the flesh.’ That is, on account of sin
in man, he suffered the condemnation due
to <hi rend="italics">that</hi> sin in his own person. So,” says the
old African—his dark visage brightening with
the emotions within—“what God's law cannot
do, his own Son can do. Thanks be to God
for his unspeakable gift!”</p>
        <p>We could only join in his closing
exclamation, assuring him that, according to
our best judgment, he had adopted the true
interpretation of the passage, and we left
him, blessing God, as we shook his hand,
for bestowing such grace and knowledge
upon one so humble and so unpretending.
His knowledge of human nature was
profound, because it was derived wholly
from the Bible, confirmed by his own
observation. Hence his extensive
usefulness, not only among those of his
own colour, but also in a large circle of
whites, embracing many of the most
<pb id="white29" n="29"/>
intelligent, wealthy, and refined people of
the county.</p>
        <p>In the familiar intercourse to which he was
admitted by the latter class, he was never
known to offend by any thing like
forwardness. Says one who knew
him well: “His humility has always
been of the most rational kind—entirely
removed from all cant and grimace. Before
he became superannuated, the great field of
his operations as a preacher was the funeral
sermons called for by the owners of
deceased slaves. He was universally
employed in this way, with the hearty
consent of persons of all descriptions in this
community. I have known him to be sent for
to a distance of more than thirty miles to
attend to a service of this kind. In every
instance he would receive the most polite and
friendly attentions of the white portion of the
family and even by the irreligious, was frequently
<pb id="white30" n="30"/>
remunerated in money for his services.”</p>
        <p>Through life, he manifested a surprising
thirst for knowledge. He embraced with
avidity every opportunity of getting
instruction, both in public and in private.
Nothing pleased him more than the
opportunity of conversing, with ministers of
the gospel. Mountain Hall, the delightful
residence of the late Dr. Jones, was a home
for Christ's ministering servants as they journeyed
through that part of the country. The African
Preacher lived at the distance of a mile from
this place. He seemed to know, almost by
intuition, when a minister called to spend the
night with the good doctor and his lady. And
however dark or even stormy the night might
be, when the bell rang for evening family
worship, the good old African would be seen
with tremulous steps slowly entering,
<pb id="white31" n="31"/>
and with deep solemnity, seating himself in
a retired part of the room to attend upon the
service. A stranger would not be likely to
observe him, unless indeed the person
conducting the worship should happen to
sing Windham, or Mear, or Old Hundred, to
some appropriate psalm or hymn. Then his
attention would very probably be arrested
by a voice, not remarkable for its melody,
nor yet remarkable for its strength—but a
voice so solemn, so tremulous with the
emotions which seemed to accompany it
from the depths of a heart all alive to God's
praise, that he could no longer remain
unobserved.</p>
        <p>When the service closed, he resumed his
seat—so modest as never presuming to
seek an introduction to the reverend
visitor. The polished, but pious inmates
of that mansion, were his special patrons
and friends, and had given him
<pb id="white32" n="32"/>
a prescriptive right to that corner and to that
chair. But he was never permitted to remain
unnoticed. The visitor was invariably taken
to the place where the old man sat, and told,
“this is our friend and neighbour, Uncle
Jack, who has come to-night expressly to
join in our worship, and to make your
acquaintance, with a view to his
improvement in divine knowledge.” Then
followed an interview, in which the teacher
rarely failed to learn as much as the scholar.</p>
        <p>He greatly delighted in hearing the gospel
preached by those who were well
educated, as well as pious; and never
seemed to enjoy a sermon which consisted
mainly in empty declamation. We have
often heard him say, “I don't like to hear
more <hi rend="italics">sound</hi> than <hi rend="italics">sense</hi> in the pulpit.”</p>
        <p>He uniformly opposed, both in public
and private, every thing like noise and
<pb id="white33" n="33"/>
disorder in the house of God. His
coloured auditors were very prone to err in
this way. But whenever they did, he
suspended the exercises until they became
silent. On one of these occasions, he
rebuked his hearers substantially as follows:
“You noisy Christians remind me of the
little branches (streams) after a heavy rain.
They are soon full, then noisy, and as soon
empty. I would much rather see you like
the broad, deep river, which is quiet,
because it is broad and deep.”</p>
        <p>On another occasion, when a very
large assembly had convened, and when
he had reason to suppose there might
be a good deal of mere animal excitement,
before he sung or prayed, addressing
himself to one of his audience by
name, he said, “Suppose your master
had directed you to go to Petersburg
<sic corr="tomorrow">to-morrow</sic>; and suppose, on your telling
him you knew nothing of the road,
<pb id="white34" n="34"/>
and therefore could not go, he should
repeat the command, and say, “You shall go,
whether, you know the way or not, and shall
be severely punished if you fail to go.” Now
you are in great trouble, and going to look
for some one who can tell you the way, you
happen to find a good many people together,
all of whom say they know the way
perfectly. You tell them the trouble you are
in, and beg them to tell you the way to
Petersburg. Now, there happens to be one
in that crowd, older than the rest, and who
is thought to know the way rather better
than they. So, all wait for him to talk. Now,
suppose that, just as this old man begins to
tell you about the road—where this fork, and
where that is—when you must turn this way,
and when that, all his companions
commence clapping their hands, groaning
and shouting so, that <hi rend="italics">you can't hear</hi>
<pb id="white35" n="35"/>
<hi rend="italics">distinctly a word the old man says.</hi> Could
he possibly teach you the road to
Petersburg, unless they would keep still?
Now, here are a great many sinners, who
must find the road to heaven or perish for
ever. I am about to tell them, as well as I
can, how they may find that road, and
escape that destruction, and don't <hi rend="italics">you
Christians bother me, and hinder their
learning by your noise.</hi> Let every mouth
be stopped, and let all keep quiet until I am
done.”</p>
        <p>His sentiments and his practice on this
subject seem the more remarkable, when it
is remembered, that at this time nothing was
more common, not only among the blacks,
but also among whites, than noise and
confusion during public worship. Indeed,
they were thought the best Christians who
shouted the oftenest and prayed the
loudest. This sentiment he literally abhorred,
and did his utmost to exterminate.
<pb id="white36" n="36"/>
He was particularly fond of a tract
published by the American Tract Society,
entitled, “The importance of distinguishing
between true and false conversions.” He
often applied for this tract, that he might
take it to some white neighbour, who had
recently professed conversion; expressing
the fear, that the individual for whose
benefit he wanted it, was in danger of
resting in a groundless hope. With those of
his own colour, he talked thus on this
subject: “You who can read the Bible,
should read it much; and you who cannot,
should embrace every opportunity of
hearing it read. If you do not, how will you
ever know that your religion is such as God
will approve? God alone knows, and he
alone can tell us, what will satisfy him, and
this he has done in his word. Why, persons
fond of smoking, can't tell whether their pipe
is lighted, if they smoke in the dark;
<pb id="white37" n="37"/>
much less can you tell whether your heart is
right in the sight of God, unless the light of
his word is poured upon your experience.”</p>
        <p>The reader will be interested also in
knowing something of his sentiments
in regard to revivals of religion. More
mistaken views on this subject could hardly
prevail any where, or at any time, than
prevailed in the region of country in which
the African Preacher lived, and during the
time of his ministry. His sentiments may be
fairly and fully learned from the following
incident.</p>
        <p>On a certain occasion, he attended a
protracted meeting, conducted by some of
the best white preachers in that part of the
country; at which “the new measures” were
used, and at which there was a great deal
of excitement and no little noise. On his return,
he called to see me, and, during his visit,
<pb id="white38" n="38"/>
gave me the following account of the
meeting. “There were a great many
people, and a great deal of talking, and
singing, and praying. They call it a revival;
and if by a revival, they mean a great
increase of confusion and noise, they are
right. But so it is, I had no enjoyment at the
meeting. I heard very little of what I call
<hi rend="italics">real preaching.</hi> I was constantly thinking,
and it may be, this was a temptation of the
devil—any how, I was constantly thinking Of
what I have sometimes noticed in <hi rend="italics">new
grounds.</hi> If a man <hi rend="italics">clears up</hi> a piece of land
in the summer, and has not time to cut down
and take away all the trees, but <hi rend="italics">belts</hi> a good
many, and leaves them standing about in the
field, the leaves die, but don't fall. Now,
when winter comes, and the wind blows
hard, I always noticed that one of these
<hi rend="italics">belted</hi> trees made more noise in the wind,
than a half dozen green, living trees.
<pb id="white39" n="39"/>
These noisy Christians look to me so much
like <hi rend="italics">belted</hi> trees with the leaves on, in a
windy day, that I could not enjoy the
meeting at all. And yet the fault might have
been in me.”</p>
        <p>Few things delighted him more than to be
made acquainted with the views of standard
evangelical authors on doctrinal subjects.
He was at all times particularly interested in
clear and sound expositions of such
passages of Scripture as are hard to be
understood. A friend says, “After I had
read to him, at some length, the opinions of
one of our ablest divines on a disputed point
in theology, he said, ‘Well, I have
long wanted to have that matter explained,
but all I could gather about it, was like
picking up a few scanty crumbs and dry
pieces of crust, which could not satisfy my
hunger; but now, you have given me a great
loaf, that I may eat and be full at once.’ ”</p>
        <pb id="white40" n="40"/>
        <p>At another time, on having a very
difficult text explained to him, he said,
“Whenever I came to that text, I was like a
little child two or three years old, trying to
go from one room of his father's house into
another. After trying again and again to
reach and raise the latch, but all in vain, his
father comes along, and does, without the
least difficulty, what the child could not
possibly do. Just so with me. You have
opened the door, and now I can go on in.”</p>
        <p>He was a close observer of passing events—
an accurate discerner of the signs of the times.
He looked at every thing in its bearing on the
cause of Christ. He said to us on one occasion,
“Real Christians are the salt of the earth; and I do
believe that this world would have been destroyed
long ago, but for them. Does not the word of
<pb id="white41" n="41"/>
God say, that for the elect's sake those days
shall be shortened?”</p>
        <p>There were two individuals in the circle
of his acquaintance, remarkable, not only
for their own destitution of religious
principle, but also for doing all they could to
suppress it in the large families of which
they were the heads. During their lives, no
member of either household made any
advance towards forming a connection with
the church. Soon after their deaths, which
happened nearly about the same time,
the widow and several of the children of
each, became pious, active members of the
church. When his attention was called to
this fact, he said, “I have often seen a large,
spreading oak, standing alone in a field, with
nothing growing under it—but only cut that
tree down and take it away, and a little culture
will make the land very productive.”</p>
        <p>We have already learned that he was
<pb id="white42" n="42"/>
admitted to terms of great familiarity with
persons of every grade in society; and yet
his deportment never savoured of arrogance
or presumption. There was but one class of
persons with whom he ever used a freedom
which the most fastidious could censure.
These were such as scoff at sacred and divine
subjects. Persons of this sort would sometimes
jeer him about his religion; and endeavour to
make Christ and his precious cause
subjects of buffoonery and ridicule. The old
African was far more jealous of his
Master's glory than of his own ease or
reputation. On such occasions, his usual
diffidence and reserve would give place to
a firm but dignified defence of the truth; and
most happily could he “answer a fool
according to his folly.” Nor did one of this
fraternity ever encounter him without being
seriously worsted.</p>
        <p>A man addicted to horse-racing and
<pb id="white43" n="43"/>
card-playing, stopped him in the road
one day, and addressed him as follows:
“Old man, you Christians say a great
deal about the way to heaven being
very narrow. Now, if this be so, a
great many who profess to be travelling
it, will not find it half wide enough.”
“That's very true,” said the good African,
“of all who merely have a name to live,
<hi rend="italics">and of all like you.”</hi> “Why refer to <hi rend="italics">me?”</hi>
asked the man; “if the road is wide enough
for any, it is for me.” “By no means,”
was the pertinent reply; “when you set out,
you will wish to take along a race-horse or
two, and a card-table. Now there's no room
along this way for such things, and what
would you do, even in heaven, without them?”</p>
        <p>Another individual of large fortune, who
was accustomed to treat the subject of
religion rather sportively, and
who at the same time prided himself
<pb id="white44" n="44"/>
on his morality, said to him, “I think, old
man, I am as good as need be. I can't help
thinking so, because God blesses me as
much as he does you Christians, and I don't
know what more I want than he gives me;
and yet I never disturb myself about
preaching or praying.” To this the old
preacher replied with great seriousness,
“Just so with the hogs. I have often seen
them rooting among the leaves in the
woods, and finding just as many acorns as
they needed, and yet I never saw one of
them look up to the tree from which the
acorns fell.”</p>
        <p>He was fond of considering piety, both
internal and external, as progressive in its
developments. He opposed with the utmost
firmness and faithfulness, the idea of one's
<hi rend="italics">getting religion,</hi> as the phrase is, and then
folding his hands in utter idleness. He was
fully aware that this error prevailed to a
<pb id="white45" n="45"/>
deplorable extent, among those of his own
colour, and he spared no pains to resist and
eradicate it. He was accustomed to say, “I
have no notion of that religion which is
better at first than it ever is afterwards.
When Christians hear a sermon on the text,
“Turn ye, turn ye, for why will ye die?” they
are apt to conclude that it don't suit them,
because they <hi rend="italics">have turned</hi> long ago. Now,
the truth is, to be the real children of God,
we must continue to turn as long as we live.
For my own part, I often feel as if I <hi rend="italics">had as
much turning to do</hi> now, as I had when I
first set out.”</p>
        <p>His views on this subject were unusually
enlarged and scriptural. They reached into
eternity. Nothing less than the expectation
of an eternal progression, in knowledge,
holiness, and usefulness satisfied his desires.
Of this, we are furnished with a striking
<pb id="white46" n="46"/>
illustration, in the following incident. A pious
young man, of considerable intelligence,
conversing with him on growth in grace,
said, “We should strive to grow until we
die.” “Yes,” replied our preacher, “and
hope to grow after we die. I trust in God I
shall grow for ever.”</p>
        <p>Standing one day in sight of a field of
tobacco, he said to me, “Some fifty years
ago, I expected the time would come, when
I should be of some account in the Lord's
vineyard. But now, I am very old, and have
given up this hope.” Then pointing to the
tobacco, which grew near us, he said, “That
is very <hi rend="italics">promising</hi> tobacco, but it must be
<hi rend="italics">cut and cured,</hi> before it will be of any
service to its owner. And so it is with me.
All that now comforts me on this subject, is
the hope that God will make some good use
of me in another and better world. The
<pb id="white47" n="47"/>
redeemed of the Lord are said to serve him
in heaven. What a service that must be!
How unlike any thing seen or known on
earth!”</p>
        <p>Here let the reader pause and consider,
that this old African could barely read, and
never learned to write. He was taught in the
school of Christ, and only there. We never
knew him read, nor do we think he cared to
read, any book except the Bible, or
something of a kindred character. He was
literally taught of God, and thus became
wise unto salvation. With the jet black
colour, and all the features of the African
race fully developed, such were the
beauties of his mind and heart, as to render
him an object worthy of the highest 
respect—the most profound 
veneration. Often have
we rejoiced to sit at his feet and learn, and
with no little delight do we anticipate the
day when we shall walk, side by side,
<pb id="white48" n="48"/>
along the banks of the river of life, and
partake together of the fruits of that tree,
whose leaves are for the healing of the
nations.</p>
        <p>Another very striking characteristic
of the African Preacher was solicitude
for the prevalence of pure and undefiled
religion He sought, in every legitimate
way, the advancement of Christ's cause.
Most truly could he say, “If I forget thee,
0 Jerusalem, let my right hand forget
her cunning.” Perhaps few, if any, have ever
lived, who entered more fully into the spirit
of the 80th Psalm—or who, with reference
to the interests of Zion, could with greater
sincerity or deeper earnestness, adopt the
beautiful language of one of our hymns:</p>
        <lg type="verse">
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>“If e'er my heart forget</l>
            <l>Her welfare or her woe;</l>
            <l>Let every joy this heart forsake,</l>
            <l>And every grief o'erflow.</l>
          </lg>
          <pb id="white49" n="49"/>
          <lg type="verse">
            <l>“For her my tears shall fall</l>
            <l>For her, my prayers ascend;</l>
            <l>To her my toils and cares be given,</l>
            <l>‘Till toils and cares shall end.”</l>
          </lg>
        </lg>
        <p>All who visited him might expect
to be questioned on this subject, as closely
as good manners would warrant. No one,
who made the attempt, ever failed to
interest him deeply on the subject of
missions. We have often seen the tear roll
down his dark and furrowed cheek, as he
listened to some thrilling statement
respecting the spread of the gospel among
the heathen. He fully believed, that “the
field is the world”—that the great commission
of the ascending Saviour binds the Church
to preach the gospel to every creature,
and make disciples of all nations. Here his
faith and zeal were such as to put to shame
many who, with advantages far superior to
his, are still strangers to the missionary spirit,
<pb id="white50" n="50"/>
which is but another name for the spirit of
the Gospel—the spirit of Christ.</p>
        <p>When he prayed, as we know he did
with unusual faith and fervour, “Thy
kingdom come, thy will be done on
earth, as it is in heaven,” his far reaching
mind and heart extended to every
nation and kindred and tribe, upon the whole
earth. He had known what it was to live
amidst the darkness of heathenism, and
what it is to enjoy the genial light of the Sun
of righteousness.</p>
        <p>On one occasion, after listening with
fixed attention and deep feeling to a
statement of a discouraging character
respecting the state of religion in a
neighbouring county, he said, “There seems
to be great coldness and deadness on the
subject of religion every where. The fire has
almost gone out, and nothing is left, but a <hi rend="italics">few
smoking chunks lying about in places.”</hi>
How striking is the thought of one's having
<pb id="white51" n="51"/>
just religion enough <hi rend="italics">“to smoke,”</hi> but not
enough to burn. No light, no beat—only a little
smoke. Who that has the fire of divine love
in his heart, can be content to lead such a
life? Indeed it is extremely doubtful,
whether a principle of such potency can
exist, and yet exert no more influence. Let
the inactive, useless member of the church,
ponder the homely but expressive language
of the good old African, and hang his head
for shame, that he should hold no higher
place, and act no better part in the vineyard
of his Master, than that of a <hi rend="italics">“smoking
chunk”</hi> lying by the <sic corr="wayside">way-side</sic>.</p>
        <p>Speaking of the causes of a low state of
piety, he said, “Christians don't love each
other enough. They don't <hi rend="italics">keep
close enough together.</hi> They are too
much like fire-coals, scattered over a
large hearth. Coals in that condition,
you know, soon die out. Only gather
<pb id="white52" n="52"/>
them up, and bring them close together, and
they soon become bright and warm again.
So it is with Christians. They must be often
and close together—in the church—at the
prayer meeting, and thus help one another
along.”</p>
        <p>His attention was frequently called to the
purposes and plans of the American
Colonization Society. He always said it
would succeed if the natives were duly
restrained. Young as he was when taken
from that country, he seems to have formed
a just estimate of the African character.
Comparing their superstitious practices and
degraded condition, with the privileges
enjoyed under the Christian system, he was
often heard to thank God that he had been
brought to America. “For,” he would say,
“coming to the white man's country as a
slave, was the means of making me free in
Christ Jesus.” He remembered very
distinctly having often been forced
<pb id="white53" n="53"/>
to participate in the idolatrous rites and
ceremonies practised by his parents; and he
seldom exhibited deeper emotion than when
referring to these things. From this subject
he seldom passed, without adding, “If I
were only young enough, I should rejoice to
go back and preach the gospel to my poor
countrymen. But,” he would say, “it would
be a great trial to live where there are no
white people.”</p>
        <p>In every situation, whether of freedom or
of bondage, he had found in the white man
a friend and a brother. And we scruple not
to say, that the black man has no better
friend on all this earth, than he finds in the
educated, pious son of the good old
commonwealth, in which the African
Preacher lived, preached and 
died—respected while he lived, 
and lamented
when he died.</p>
        <p>Perhaps no Christian grace shone
more brightly in his character, than
<pb id="white54" n="54"/>
humility. The attentions bestowed upon him
by persons of the highest standing, were
remarkable. He was invited into their
houses—sat with their families—took part in
their social worship, sometimes leading in
prayer at the family altar. Many of the most
intelligent people attended upon his ministry,
and listened to his sermons with great delight.
Indeed, previous to the year 1825, he
was considered by the best judges the best
preacher in that county. His opinions were
respected, his advice followed, and yet he
never betrayed the least symptom of arrogance
or self-conceit. When in the presence of white
people, he seldom introduced conversation, and
when he did, it was invariably done by
modestly asking some very pertinent
question on some very important
subject. He was perpetually employed
either in seeking or communicating
information, and when no opportunity
<pb id="white55" n="55"/>
presented itself of doing either, he was
habitually silent.</p>
        <p>His dwelling was a rude log cabin;
his apparel of the plainest and even
coarsest materials, and yet no one ever
heard him utter one “murmuring word.”
Like the shepherd of Salisbury Plain, his
gratitude for what he had, precluded all
anxiety for what he had not.</p>
        <p>The tones of his voice, the expression of
his countenance, together with every word,
and every action, proclaimed that, in true
lowliness of mind, he esteemed others
better than himself.</p>
        <p>An illustration of his meekness and humility
is furnished by the fact, that when asked
his opinion respecting the law, then recently
enacted by the State Legislature, prohibiting
coloured men from preaching, he very promptly
expressed his approbation of the law; adding,
“It is altogether wrong for such as
<pb id="white56" n="56"/>
have not been taught themselves, to
undertake to teach others. As to <hi rend="italics">my</hi>
preaching, I have long thought it was no
better than the ringing of an old cowbell,
and ought to be stopped.” He accordingly
bowed to the authority of this law; and
although often told, that the penalty for its
violation would not be inflicted on him, he
never preached afterwards; but became a
constant and devout worshipper in a
neighbouring Presbyterian congregation,
which had been recently organized, and
over which the first pastor of that
denomination ever settled in the county of
Nottoway, had been recently installed.</p>
        <p>Another incident, illustrating his humble and
contented disposition, must not be omitted
Previous to the cessation of his public
ministry, a pious and wealthy lady, feeling
grieved to see him so rudely clad, presented
him with a well made suit of black cloth. This
<pb id="white57" n="57"/>
suit, he wore but once, and then returned it
to his kind friend, begging that she would not
be displeased at his doing so, and justified
his conduct thus: “These clothes are a great
deal better than are generally worn by
people of my colour. And besides, if I wear
them, I find I shall be obliged <hi rend="italics">to think about
them even at meeting.”</hi></p>
        <p>We have already spoken of the polite
attentions he received at the hands of white
people. In truth, Uncle Jack was always a
welcome guest. In warm weather, he
always insisted on sitting in the portico, or
on the steps leading into the house, as a
place better suited to his rank and character,
than the parlour. Whenever he took this
humble position, the whole family would
soon gather around him, and hang upon his
words, as long as he could be induced to
remain. We have known the whole of a
large and fashionable dining party,
<pb id="white58" n="58"/>
leave the gay attractions of the parlour, and
repair to the porch, or to the shade of some
venerable tree, under which he had taken
his position, each saying as they went,
“Uncle Jack has come, let's go and hear
him.” On such occasions, he displayed great
prudence and wisdom in the topics
introduced. He seemed fully to realize the
importance of not repelling or disgusting the
young and irreligious, by pressing religious
truth upon their consideration, any further
than they were disposed to give him their
serious attention. The skill with which he
could “rightly divide the word of truth, and
give to each his portion in due season,”
might well rebuke some far better educated,
and more distinguished ministers than he.</p>
        <p>He never seemed to suppose for a
moment, that the attentions shown him,
were the result of any personal merit of his
own. He considered them all as
<pb id="white59" n="59"/>
flowing directly from a regard to his
Master, and his Master's cause. Nor was
he led by such attentions to consider
himself above those of his own colour.
Most meekly and humbly did he
“condescend to men of low estate.” Most
tenderly did he love, fervently did he pray,
and faithfully did he labour, for his
“brethren, his kinsmen according to the
flesh.” He sought their society, and mingled
with them in their cabins, with the utmost
familiarity. The respect shown him by the
whites, united with the vast superiority of
his intellectual and moral attainments over
theirs, rendered him the object of suspicion
and jealousy with the more ignorant, and
vicious of this class. He was, moreover, a
rigid disciplinarian. He was the relentless
enemy of all pretended sanctity. Every
departure from what he deemed an orthodox
creed, or a consistently pious life, was sure to
<pb id="white60" n="60"/>
meet with his most decided opposition.
Hence, all feared, and some really hated
him. He was no stranger to persecution for
righteousness' sake.</p>
        <p>A gentleman of our acquaintance
detected one of his servants, who belonged
to Uncle Jack's pastoral charge, in some
petty theft. The master merely admonished
the offender, and dismissed him, saying, “I
shall content myself with laying this matter
before your preacher.” He retired, but soon
returned, and with the deepest concern
depicted in his countenance, said, “Master,
I have come back to say to you,
that if you think I deserve punishment for
what I have done, I would much rather you
would punish me at once, as you think I
deserve, than to tell Uncle Jack about it.”
The gentleman very wisely concluded not to
comply With this strange request, and the
servant was commended to the <hi rend="italics">moral</hi> discipline
<pb id="white61" n="61"/>
of the good old pastor, which
resulted very favourably.</p>
        <p>It is somewhat remarkable, that just
about the time that Alexander Campbell,
of Bethany, commenced the propagation
of his peculiar sentiments, which so
seriously disturbed and divided the
Baptist churches in the west, a coloured
preacher whose name was Campbell,
entered upon the work of “reformation”
among the Baptists of his own colour
in <sic corr="southeastern">south-eastern</sic> Virginia. This
man, however, struck out a course of
his own—in some respects the reverse
of the system adopted by his more
learned namesake, but possessing equal,
if not superior claims to originality. It
will be quite sufficient for our present
purpose, to mention two articles in the
new creed of this sable reformer. One
of these may be expressed thus: Inasmuch
as very few of the blacks are able
read, they should no longer rely
<pb id="white62" n="62"/>
upon, or be directed in their faith or
practice by, the written word of God, but
depend entirely upon the teachings of the
Holy Spirit. The other was, that the old
Jewish law, forbidding the use of swine's
flesh, was still in force, and hence it was a
great sin to eat pork or bacon.</p>
        <p>Our Mr. Campbell could read, but, he
said, God had shown to him in a dream the
great impropriety of his doing so, as so many
of his people were deprived of this privilege.
He accordingly called a number of his
congregation together, told them his dream,
and gave them the interpretation thereof—said
it was very wrong for the preacher to be
above the people, and then, with great
affected solemnity, threw his Bible into the
fire and burned it to ashes. The success of
this fanatic was considerable; so much so,
as to awaken no little alarm among the
owners of slaves in that section
<pb id="white63" n="63"/>
of the country. As soon as tidings of
these things reached our old African, true to
his principles, and faithful to the cause of
truth and righteousness, he determined to
make an effort to check the evil.
Accordingly, he set out on a visit to the
“reformer,” and on reaching the
neighbourhood in which he lived, called on
several gentlemen whose servants had
become <hi rend="italics">his</hi> “disciples”—stated the object of
his visit, and desired that a meeting might
be held for the purpose of checking, if
possible, these new and strange doctrines.
His approach was hailed by these
gentlemen, as if he bad been a second
Luther, come to withstand another Tetzel.
The meeting was held.</p>
        <p>Mr. Campbell commenced, with all the
self-importance so common to
self-constituted, and self-styled
reformers—pouring forth torrents of “great
swelling words of vanity.” The people
<pb id="white64" n="64"/>
sympathized with their leader, and joined warmly
in the clamour. The African Preacher
maintained the utmost silence for a
considerable time, but at length arose
with great solemnity and said, “My
Bible teaches me, in all my ways to
acknowledge God, and never to lean to my
own understanding. Hence, I can go no
further in this business until we have prayed
for God's guidance and blessing.” This
proposition was evidently unexpected, and
to many very unacceptable. But the
dignified and solemn manner in which it
was made, awed them into momentary
silence, and kneeling, he prayed with strong
faith and deep feeling, that God would be
pleased to direct and bless them in their
efforts to learn and do his will. The
impression made by this prayer was
eminently salutary. Finding that the
people had become silent and more
respectful, our good preacher proposed to
<pb id="white65" n="65"/>
this “setter forth of strange” doctrines, to
state and prove his creed. He commenced
with an attempt to sustain his positions by
quotations from the Bible. To this, Uncle
Jack objected, on the ground, that he had
burned his Bible, and accordingly had no
right to the use of any thing it contained.
This was extremely embarrassing. But the
prohibition was very properly enforced with
the utmost firmness. An appeal to the
audience as to the propriety of this course,
met with so much favour, that Campbell,
finding the current beginning to turn against
him, became very angry, and resorted to
personal abuse of the good old African.
Upon this, the latter arose and with a
good deal of biting sarcasm—a weapon
he knew quite well when and how to use,
said to the people My friends, you all
see that what this man says about doing
without the Bible, and depending on
<pb id="white66" n="66"/>
the Spirit, cannot be true; for he was not
able to talk at all, when I told him he had no
right to quote a book he had burned. And
you can all see, by his getting so angry, that
if any spirit came to his help, it was not the
Holy Spirit. And as to that notion of his
about the sin of eating <hi rend="italics">hog-meat,</hi> if the half
of what I hear about him and a great many
of his members be true, the white people
ought to do all they call to encourage that
belief, as it will make the raising of hogs
down this way, much easier and more
certain than it is now.” With this he took
his leave., and with this, <hi rend="italics">coloured Campbellism</hi>
died entirely.</p>
        <p>The life of the African Preacher was
one of no little toil and suffering.
Perhaps the most imprudent step he
ever took, was marrying a woman
who was in no respect “a help meet for
him.” Without mental culture, without
religion, encumbered with a large family
<pb id="white67" n="67"/>
of children, the fruits of a former marriage,
and surrounded by an extensive circle of
other relatives, she only served to burden
him with domestic cares, sufficient to have
crushed the spirit of any ordinary man.
These people were idle and profligate; he,
industrious and economical. They hung,
around and imposed upon him in the most
shameful manner. Often would they filch
from him the products of his own daily
labour, and then add insult to injury, by the
grossest personal unkindness, and even
cruelty. But all this only served to give
additional brightness and purity to his piety.
Some metals become the more brilliant on
being rubbed, and some flowers are all the
more fragrant when trodden upon. So with
pure and undefiled religion, and so it was
with this good old African Preacher.</p>
        <p>His thoughts, his affections, his aims,
were all lifted so far above the din of
<pb id="white68" n="68"/>
domestic strife, that it seldom or never
disturbed his equanimity even for a
moment. The dreariness of his home on
earth only served to make him sigh more
deeply for “that house not made with hands,
eternal in the heavens.” He rarely alluded to
these things, and whenever he did, he never
failed to say all he could in extenuation of
the guilt of those who had injured him. To
the writer, he never alluded to these trials
but once, and then he said, “I am such a
<hi rend="italics"><sic corr="hardheaded">hard-headed</sic>,</hi> disobedient child, that I need
a whipping every day.” At another time,
referring to his poverty, and also to the fact
that he had no descendants, he said, “I left
nothing in Africa, and I brought nothing to
this country. When I die, I shall leave
nothing behind me, and shall carry nothing
with me, but the merits of my Saviour's
obedience and death.”</p>
        <p>The simplicity of faith, and the self-application
<pb id="white69" n="69"/>
with which our good preacher was
accustomed to attend upon the ministrations
of the sanctuary, were truly remarkable.
“A day in thy courts is better than a
thousand,” was not only the language of his
lips, but of his heart and of his life. When
more than ninety years of age, we have
known him to walk two, and sometimes
four miles to reach the house of God. And
this he would sometimes do in very
inclement weather. Nor was he a forgetful
hearer, but a doer of the word. We have
often been surprised at the accuracy with
which he could give the outlines of a
sermon many days, and even weeks, after
he had heard it. Under faithful and pungent
exhibitions of the truth, he was often very
deeply affected. After hearing a very lucid
and impressive sermon on the resurrection
of the dead, we found him, when the service
had ended, in the rear of the church,
<pb id="white70" n="70"/>
leaning against the side of the house, bathed
in tears. On asking him why he wept, he
replied, “I am afraid, sir, that after all, I shall
never realize what that young preacher
talked about today. The glories of the
resurrection unto life are too high for me.”
He was reminded of what the preacher had
said about the changes which annually occur
in nature, as to some extent illustrative of the
resurrection. He was told to recollect the
astonishing difference in the appearance of
the trees in winter and spring; and was then
asked, if the God who caused this difference,
who, in the spring thus adorned the forest,
could not, with perfect ease, beautify and
adorn his body in an infinitely higher degree.
To this he said, “I do not doubt the power or
the love of God; but that which troubles me
is this. If the tree has not a good root, God
will never make it bloom. And so it is with
<pb id="white71" n="71"/>
me. If I have not the root of the matter in
me, I shall never know any thing
of the resurrection unto life.”</p>
        <p>On another occasion, we found him in no
little distress of mind; and on asking the
cause, were answered substantially as
follows: “About a week ago, I heard a
sermon on the text, “Turn ye, turn ye, for
why will ye die?” The preacher, who came
from the school up here in Prince Edward,
took more pains than common to tell us
what was meant by <hi rend="italics">turning.</hi> He made the
gate appear so strait, and the way so
narrow, that he soon made me fear I had
never turned at all. He certainly convinced
me that I had still a great deal of turning to
do, and that this turning must be the great
business of the Christian's whole life.” This
was a very favourite thought with him. In
strict conformity with his views on this
<pb id="white72" n="72"/>
subject, he preferred the term <hi rend="italics">converting</hi>
to converted.</p>
        <p>In the course of a sermon on
regeneration, he once introduced the
following illustration to enforce the duty of
growing in grace: “If a farmer,” said he, “in
clearing and preparing a piece of ground for
cultivation, should do no more than to cut
down the trees, and remove the bodies and
branches of those trees, whilst all the
stumps were left undisturbed, he would very
soon find that around every one of those
stumps, a considerable number of sprouts, of
the very nature of the old tree, had <hi rend="italics">put up,</hi>
and he would have even more clearing to do
than he had at first. Now, to get his land in a
proper condition, he must not only cut down
the trees, but he must <hi rend="italics">grub up</hi> the stumps.
Yes, he must continue to grub as long as
any part of the root is left. Just so
<pb id="white73" n="73"/>
with sin in man's heart and life. He
must not only forsake open sin, he must
look to the heart, where the roots of this
open sin are, and these roots must be
grubbed up. And this grubbing he must keep
at, as long as life lasts, or he will never
bring forth the peaceable fruits of
righteousness to the praise of God's free
grace.”</p>
        <p>Our good preacher was much opposed to
the hasty admission of members into the
Church. He was accustomed to say, “It is
much easier and safer, to keep unworthy
persons out of the Church, than <hi rend="italics">to get them
out, </hi>after they have been once received.”
And again he would say, “The Church will
not suffer half as much, by keeping a dozen
worthy members out, a little too long, as she
will by admitting one individual too soon. If you
adopt this method of admitting members you must
see to it, that <hi rend="italics">your back door is as wide as the</hi>
<pb id="white74" n="74"/>
<hi rend="italics">front. </hi>You must prepare for <hi rend="italics">dropping
them,</hi> as readily as you<hi rend="italics"> took them up.”</hi></p>
        <p>It should be remembered, that these
views were entertained and expressed, by a
native of Africa, at different periods,
between the years 1828 and 1836. Every
one, at all acquainted with the history of the
Presbyterian Church during those eight
years, will be struck with the difference
between the sentiments of this sable son of
a Pagan continent, and some who stood
high, as learned doctors of divinity, and even
professors in Theological Seminaries, in
these enlightened ends of the earth. And we
presume there are few or none now in our
communion, who would hesitate to say, that
the Church would have fared much better,
had she asked counsel of the African
Preacher, instead of following the advice of
some of her “most enlightened and pious
divines.” Had this been done, our motto would
<pb id="white75" n="75"/>
have been, <hi rend="italics">a pure church, or no church.</hi>
It is true, the course recommended by the
African, would not have emblazoned our
church registers with so long and imposing
an array of names; but the purity, and by
consequence the moral power of the
Church, would have been far greater. The
efficiency of an army depends upon the
patriotism, the courage, and the activity of
each soldier, more than it does upon the
gorgeous uniform, the graceful movements,
or even the imposing numbers of those who
fill its ranks. So every one destitute of the
essential qualities of “the good soldier of
Jesus Christ,” hinders the progress, and
detracts from the efficiency, of “the
sacramental host of God's elect.” Such
views as these led the good African
Preacher to make the Saviour's rule his, and
they should lead us to make it ours. It is the
only reliable rule: “By their fruits ye shall
<pb id="white76" n="76"/>
know them.” And the application of this rule
in any given case, requires more than a day,
a week, or a month.</p>
        <p>The next thing deserving of consideration
in the character of this excellent old man,
was his method of dealing with persons
awakened to a sense of their sinfulness in
the sight of God. He was very often
consulted by persons in this state of mind, of
every grade in society; as also by those
who, having hope in Christ, were asking
what step they should take next, to honour
Christ and do good. Here, as in other
matters, his course was characterized by
good sense and discretion.</p>
        <p>On one occasion, a lady of great
respectability told him that she
considered herself a Christian, but at
the same time avowed the purpose of
not making a profession of religion
by connecting herself with the Church.
At this he expressed great surprise—
<pb id="white77" n="77"/>
reminded her of what our Saviour said of
those who “confessed,” and of those who
“denied” him, and then added,
“Mistress, if you should suddenly come
in possession of a large sum of money,
would you lock it up in your house, and try
to keep it a great secret? It would neither do
you nor any body else much good, to take
that course with it.”</p>
        <p>At another time, one gave him a long
account of a remarkable dream she had
had, and desired his opinion on the subject.
To this he replied, “The Scriptures do tell us
something about dreams, but no where that
I remember, of any one converted by a
dream or converted when he was asleep. I
can understand people a great deal better
when they tell me of what they say and do
when they are awake, and when they talk
about a work of grace in their hearts.”</p>
        <pb id="white78" n="78"/>
        <p>There lived in his immediate vicinity, a
very respectable man who had become
interested on the subject of religion, and
who, with some earnestness, had begun to
“search the Scriptures.” He had been thus
employed but a short time when he became
greatly perplexed with some of those
passages which even an inspired apostle has
said, are “hard to be understood.” In this
state of mind he repaired to our preacher for
instruction, and found him at noon, on a
sultry day in summer, occupied in his field,
hoeing corn. As the man approached, the
preacher saluted him with his accustomed
politeness; and then with patriarchal
simplicity, leaning upon the handle of his
hoe, listened to his story. “Uncle Jack,”
said he, “I have discovered lately that I
am a great sinner, and I have commenced
reading the Bible that I may learn
<figure id="ill2" entity="white78"><p>“I have discovered lately that I am a 
great sinner.”—Page 78.</p></figure>
<pb id="white79" n="79"/>
what I must do to be saved. But I
have met with a passage here,” holding up
his Bible, “which I cannot understand, and
which greatly perplexes me. It is this, ‘God,
will have mercy on whom he will have
mercy, and whom he will he hardeneth;’
what does this mean?” A short pause
intervened, and the old African answered as
follows: “Master, if I have been rightly
informed, it has only been a short time since
you commenced reading the Bible, and I
think the passage you have just
read is in the Epistle to the Romans. Long
before you get to that, at the very beginning
of the gospel it is said, ‘Repent, for the
kingdom of heaven is at hand.<hi rend="italics">’ Now, have
you done with that?</hi> The truth is, <hi rend="italics">you read
entirely too fast.</hi> You must begin again,
and learn the lesson as God has been pleased
to give it to you. When you have <hi rend="italics">done</hi> what
you are told to do in Matthew, come to
<pb id="white80" n="80"/>
see me, and we will talk about that passage
in Romans.” Having thus answered, he
resumed his work, and left the visitor to his
own reflections.</p>
        <p>Who does not admire the simplicity and
good sense displayed in thus dealing with a
person of this description ? Could the most
learned polemic more effectually have met
and disposed of such a difficulty? The
gentleman particularly interested in this
incident gave the foregoing account of it to
the writer, and, if he still lives, will joyfully
say now, as he did when he first spoke of it,
“It convinced me fully of the mistake into
which I had fallen. I took the old man's
advice, soon saw its propriety and wisdom,
and hope to bless God for ever for sending
me to him.” The consequence was, that he
soon became an intelligent, consistent
Christian, connected himself with the
Church, and contributed in no small degree to
<pb id="white81" n="81"/>
the promotion of a cause he had once
hated and opposed.</p>
        <p>Our preacher was not only skilful in
imparting instruction, but patient and
submissive in the endurance of evil. We
have already seen with what meekness he
bore the domestic trials which befell him.
He sometimes suffered abroad as well as at
home. But his Christian submission was
every where and at all times conspicuous.
When reviled, he reviled not again. He
rejoiced in being counted worthy to suffer
shame for the name of Christ. We know of
but one instance in which he was threatened
with personal violence. A party of such as
the Apostle Paul denominates “lewd
fellows of the baser sort,” on one occasion
interrupted him while preaching, and took
him into custody. After reviling him a good
deal, they avowed the horrid purpose of
punishing, him with stripes, and asked him,
<pb id="white82" n="82"/>
tauntingly, what he had to say in his own
defence. “I wish to know,” said the good old
man, “why you intend to punish me. If it is
for preaching the gospel, I have not a word
to say.” “Why,” asked one of the party, “you
are not willing to be whipped, are you?”
“Perfectly willing,” was the emphatic
answer, “perfectly willing ; and I will
tell you why I am. I can read the Bible <hi rend="italics">a
little;</hi> and in reading it, hardly any thing
surprises and grieves me more than to find
that such a man as the Apostle Paul, ‘five
times received forty stripes save one,’ for
preaching this same gospel. Now, when I
remember this, and then remember that an
old sinner, such as I am, should have been
preaching, or trying to preach this gospel for
more than forty years, and never yet had
<hi rend="italics">one lick</hi> for it, I am perfectly willing to be
whipped.”</p>
        <p>This reply wholly disarmed his
<pb id="white83" n="83"/>
adversaries. They were literally silenced. With
a moral courage which was fully equal to
his humility, he resolved to improve the
advantage he had thus gained. The whole of
his audience, frightened by the brutal assault
of these wicked men, “forsook him and
fled.” He stood alone, in the midst of his
enemies, with no eye to pity, and no hand to
help. But He who said, “I will never leave thee nor
forsake thee,” fulfilled his gracious promise.
Thus sustained, thus cheered, he addressed
his persecutors in language so pungent, and
yet so tender, that one by one, they walked quietly
away, leaving him in the undisturbed
possession of the ground. The leader of this
party, who gave us this story, and who
subsequently became a pious man, was
often heard to say, “the impression made
on my mind and heart by that incident, was
never effaced.”</p>
        <p>Knowing that the African Preacher
<pb id="white84" n="84"/>
was now very old, and evidently near
the end of his earthly pilgrimage and
our personal intercourse with him having
for several years ceased, we addressed
a letter, early in the winter of 1838, to <hi rend="italics">our</hi>
best earthly friend and <hi rend="italics">his,</hi> Dr. James Jones,
asking for information of his state, now that
the shadows were lengthening, and his end
supposed to be near. To this letter, the good
Doctor promptly sent us the following reply:</p>
        <q type="letter" direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1 type="letter">
                <opener>“MOUNTAIN HALL, <hi rend="italics">Nottoway, Dec.</hi> 31,1838.</opener>
                <p><hi rend="italics">“My Dear Sir</hi>—There are very few
persons either among the living or the dead,
with whom I have had so long personal
intercourse, as with <hi rend="italics">Uncle Jack.</hi> I found
him among my nearest neighbours, when I
first settled at my present residence. His
deportment, under all circumstances, has
never varied; always modest, unassuming
and humble. His serene and placid countenance
is seldom without a smile, if engaged in
<pb id="white85" n="85"/>
conversation, or great gravity, if disengaged.
Ever prone to enter into conversation, where
he thinks it not disagreeable, he scarcely
ever fails to make religion the topic before it
ends. He visits my family with the utmost
freedom, on all sorts of business and
occasions which are legitimate, and I think I
cannot be mistaken in the assertion just
made. His visits are now, perhaps, more
frequent than ever; and seem to be made
almost exclusively for the purpose of getting
information on some text or parable or
narrative in the Bible. When this is his
object, he announces it immediately on his
arrival, asks to have it read from the Bible,
and frequently inquires what our
commentators say on the subject.</p>
                <p>“It is proper here to state, that while
his memory is greatly impaired on all
matters of secular concern, it is
retentive and ready on every thing relating
<pb id="white86" n="86"/>
to the Scriptures, in connection with
his own experience of the influence of
divine truth. On propounding his
questions for information, he invariably
quotes, most accurately, the chapter
and verse; not unfrequently, the words
themselves. Very frequently he will
refer to the occasion on which he first
heard it read or spoken of; perhaps
thirty or forty years ago, in some sermon
or private conversation.</p>
                <p>“Both his physical and mental powers
are evidently on the wane. He exhibits no
little debility by his unsteady gait, his head
inclining forwards, so that his chin almost
rests upon his breast; and he complains much
of rheumatism. Still, he manifests great
reluctance to confinement, so long as he can
use the organs of motion. He gives his
personal attention to every branch of business
on his little establishment, and is, at this time,
<pb id="white87" n="87"/>
in a most comfortable situation, as respects
his supplies of the necessaries of life. I
perceive no alteration at all in the temper
and disposition of his mind The same
equanimity which has so long distinguished
him, still prevails; and so remarkable has his
character been, in this respect, that I have
never yet seen an individual who has known
him to be put out of temper, or to show any
thing like petulance, or irritation, or
resentment, on any occasion whatever,
throughout his whole life.</p>
                <p>“Weak and feeble as he is at this time, he
seems to have been most highly excited,
both in mind and body, by the revival of
religion which has been for some time past
in progress in the churches around him. He
is unable to attend distant meetings, but
frequently walks to those near at hand.
He takes special care, however, to get to
very many of the families in which
<pb id="white88" n="88"/>
conversions have been reported, let them be
far or near. I am often surprised to hear
from him an account of what passed
between him and certain families, in recent
conversations. Upon inquiry, I find he has
walked all the way expressly to see them.
He would say, ‘I could not resist. I was
obliged to try and get to them, that I might
tell them all I knew to help them on their
way.’</p>
                <p>“I can only add the assurance of the
undiminished esteem and affection of</p>
                <closer><salute>Yours truly,</salute>
<signed>JAMES JONES.”</signed></closer>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <p>It must not be forgotten, that the subject
of this narrative was supposed to be nearly
eighty years of age when the writer first
made his acquaintance. Both in mind and
body he was already on the wane. Little or
nothing, is remembered of what he was in
the vigour of mature age. There were none at
<pb id="white89" n="89"/>
that period, whose feelings and habits
prompted them to preserve for future use
the incidents of a life so unpretending and
so humble. They who have rendered us so
much assistance, were not then professors
of religion; and few, if any, of those who
were, could be considered capable of
appreciating the old man's real worth. We
have therefore only called the attention of
the reader to the rays of a luminary near the
horizon. For any adequate, conceptions of
his <sic corr="noonday">noon-day</sic> brilliancy, we are left wholly to
conjecture. We have, moreover, sketched
the lineaments of a mind almost entirely
destitute of cultivation. With thorough
training, may we not reasonably suppose
that our African Preacher would have
attained to the intellectual stature of an
Augustine or a Cyprian—those distinguished
sons of his <sic corr="fatherland">father-land</sic>?</p>
        <p>But we must resume our narrative.
<pb id="white90" n="90"/>
Shortly after the foregoing letter was
written, he became extremely ill. He
thought the time of his departure had
arrived, and so thought all his friends. Dr.
Jones, who attended him as his physician,
during this illness, has kindly furnished us
with the following account of the old man's
views and feelings at this trying time.</p>
        <p>“During his illness, I often listened with
intense interest to the views and feelings he
expressed, as he lay upon what he supposed
to be his <sic corr="deathbed">death-bed</sic>. And views more
rational and scriptural I never heard from
any one. The most perfect calmness, as to
his future destiny, pervaded his bosom.
Gratitude to God for all his merciful dealings
towards him, was the prominent exercise of his
mind. The neighbours vied with each other in
acts of kindness in that crisis. In view of this
he said to me, ‘What have I done to deserve all
<pb id="white91" n="91"/>
this? I came, a stranger to all, thousands of
miles across the great water, and as long as
I have lived, I have never wanted a friend.
And now, when I am about to die, I am loaded
with kindness beyond any thing that I deserve.’ ”
The Doctor closes his statement thus:
“Whenever this venerable African departs
hence, it may be truly said, that a purer
spirit than his never escaped its clay
tenement on earth, to its house not made
with hands, eternal in the heavens.”</p>
        <p>From this attack, however, he recovered,
and lived about four years longer. During
this period, his hearing, sight, and speech
were all impaired. Still he enjoyed surprising
health for one of his advanced age. Nor did
his interest in the cause of Christ suffer the
least abatement. His path was emphatically
that of the just, “which shineth more and
more to the perfect day.” The truth
<pb id="white92" n="92"/>
is, when every thing else failed to arrest
his attention and excite his feelings, the
bare mention of that name which “is
above every name,” imparted, in no
small degree, the lustre of youth to his
almost sightless eyes, and the animation
and vigour of mature age to his emaciated
frame.</p>
        <p>In July, 1842, we saw him for the last
time. On reaching Mountain Hall, we soon
learned from the family that Uncle Jack
was then with them. He had recently come
on one of his accustomed visits, and was
taken suddenly so ill that be could not return
to his own cottage. This was very
favourable to his comfort. For here he was
supplied with every thing necessary to
check his disease or to cheer his spirit. On
proposing to go to his room, we were told
that he had been for some days in a stupor;
that he could scarcely be induced to say any
thing, or to notice any body; and
<pb id="white93" n="93"/>
that it would be painful to see him. But we
determined to go, not doubting that he could
be roused. He had no fever, and suffered no
pain. The candle had sunk in the socket, and
only needed <hi rend="italics">raising,</hi> to make it shine as
brilliantly as ever. And there was a way by
which this might be done. Accordingly, we
went to his room, accompanied by the good
friend, whose guests both Uncle Jack and
we were, as we had often been before.
We found him, on entering his apartment,
surrounded with as many conveniences and
comforts as any one could reasonably have
desired. He lay calm and tranquil, with his
eyes fixed on the ceiling. Approaching his
bedside, we took his black and bony hand in
ours, but he spoke not, nor moved his eyes.
We then saluted him in the usual style of
ordinary civility, inquiring, in a very distinct
voice, after his health. Perceiving that he scarcely
<pb id="white94" n="94"/>
noticed what we said to him, Dr. Jones
advanced and said, “Old man, don't you
know who this is?” He replied, “My
hearing is better than my <sic corr="eyesight">eye-sight</sic>. I don't
know the face, but I am sure I have heard
the voice before. I think I have heard that
voice in the pulpit,” We then determined to
try the experiment of rousing him, by
merely quoting passage after passage of
Scripture in his hearing; and soon succeeded,
far beyond our most sanguine expectations.
When the passage, commencing, “For God so
loved the world, that he gave his only begotten
Son,” was mentioned, he responded with
great animation, “<hi rend="italics">That he did—that he did;</hi>
and there rests all my hope.”</p>
        <p>He now expressed great pleasure in
recognizing an old acquaintance, and
said, “Sometimes I hear of you in one
place, and sometimes in another; but
<pb id="white95" n="95"/>
go where you may, the Lord takes care of
you.”</p>
        <p>On being asked how he felt in prospect
of death, he replied: “Every thing I call my
own will soon be dissolved and pass away.
Without Christ, I am but as sounding brass
and a tinkling cymbal.” After a short
pause, he proceeded to speak, substantially
as follows: “Some years ago I heard you
preach a sermon on the text, ‘Behold, I
stand at the door and knock!’ That text, I
think, is in Revelations. I have thought of
that day and that sermon a great many
times since. You seemed to be much
in earnest, but I was sorry to see how
little interest the people took in it. They
seemed to go away unconcerned. Then I
thought, what will all our knocking come to,
unless the Lord adds his blessing?” After
another pause, during which he seemed to be
asleep, he opened his eyes and said, “We have
<pb id="white96" n="96"/>
had a revival here lately. Some call it a
revival, and some say <hi rend="italics">it is all trash.</hi> Any
how, the Lord can take <hi rend="italics">even trash,</hi> and
make <hi rend="italics">a real fire,</hi> if he chooses.”</p>
        <p>Having joined with him in prayer and
praise, we left him for the night, greatly
revived both in body and spirit. We had
seen and heard <hi rend="italics">that</hi> over which the soul of
man might well rejoice, and we could but
utter in silent ejaculation, thanksgiving to
Him who not only came into our world “to
seek and to save” the rich publican,
Zaccheus, but also to provide that the poor
should have the gospel preached to them.</p>
        <p>On the ensuing morning we found him
improved in health, but depressed in spirit.
“I have lived a long time,” he said, “but all to
no purpose. I do not see the least fruit of
any thing I ever did; and I suppose it would
be no better if I should live as long again.
For a long time I have tried to get a
<pb id="white97" n="97"/>
new heart and a right spirit, but fear I never
succeeded. Such thoughts and feelings as
trouble me, would never disturb a real
Christian.” Here he was reminded of the
Christian warfare, and particularly of what
the Apostle says about “wrestling.” He
replied, “That is all true. I have many a time
gone into the woods and wrestled in prayer,
until my enemies would all flee, and I would
think they were gone for ever; but they
soon came back and worried me worse
than ever.”</p>
        <p>His attention was next called to our
Saviour's interview with the woman of
Samaria; and particularly to this expression:
“If thou knewest the gift of God, and who it
is that saith to thee, Give me to drink, thou
wouldest have asked of him and he would
have given thee living water.” In this
he was deeply interested, and made many
pertinent remarks about the water of
<pb id="white98" n="98"/>
life, and concluded as follows: “This water
<hi rend="italics">springeth up:</hi> it don't <hi rend="italics">run down</hi> like
common water. It is very pleasant and
refreshing water. Sometimes we suffer <hi rend="italics">the
trash</hi> of this world to get into it, and then it
is not so good. But it is our own fault. The
fountain is in heaven, but there are streams
of this water now running about almost
every where. I am nearly done with the
stream, and hope soon to be at the
fountain.”</p>
        <p>Speaking of prayer he said, “Wherever
there is a praying heart, there is the throne
of grace.”</p>
        <p>He was next told that a missionary had
recently returned from Africa, his native
land, and brought the pleasing intelligence
that many of his countrymen had received
the gospel. At this announcement he clasped
his withered hands, and with much emotion
said, “Every word that cometh out of the
<pb id="white99" n="99"/>
mouth of the Lord is true. He said that his
word should be a witness among all nations—
that it should have free course, run and be
glorified—and so the gospel has gone across
the great sea all the way to Africa. When
the Lord works, none can hinder. Then, I
suppose, I shall meet some of my
countrymen in heaven. Bless the Lord! As
we shall all sing one song, I suppose we
shall all speak one language.”</p>
        <p>When we rose to leave him, he said,
smiling, “You have given me <hi rend="italics">a snack</hi> upon
which I can feed for some time; such talk
is meat and drink to me. You must not go
away <sic corr="today">to-day</sic>. I wish you to say and do all
you can before you leave, to keep me from
wandering away any more. It is no wonder
that God's child, when he leaves his father's
side, should get crippled; and when he
does, he has nobody to blame but himself.”
Shortly after we had left his
<pb id="white100" n="100"/>
apartment, one of his attendants came 
to me, saying, “Uncle Jack has sent me 
to tell you that his doubts and fears 
and difficulties are all gone; that he is 
now very peaceful and happy, and has 
nothing more to do but to die and be at 
rest.”</p>
        <p>To the surprise of every one, he 
lingered for several months, but never 
fully regained his health. We left him, 
never expecting to see his face in the 
flesh again. Nor did we. All that we 
subsequently learned of his state was, 
that he so far recovered as to be carried 
to his own humble home, where he
lingered a little longer, and then rested 
from his labours, and now his works 
follow him.</p>
        <p>In the Watchman of the South, of May
4th, 1843, the following announcement
occurs:</p>
        <q type="obituary" direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1 type="obituary">
                <head>THE AFRICAN PREACHER— HE IS GONE.</head>
                <p>The following obituary, written by
<pb id="white101" n="101"/>
one who had some knowledge of the
deceased through the last fifty years of his
life, will be read with lively interest by 
many of God's people.</p>
                <p>“The African Preacher, alias Uncle
Jack, departed to his rest on the 6th 
of April, full of years, and full of the 
hopes of the gospel. A perfect calm 
marked his last moments. ‘I am ready 
and waiting to go,’ were his last 
words.</p>
                <p>“Since the publication of a series of
biographical sketches of this extraordinary 
man, in the columns of the
Watchman of the South, between four
and five years ago, there has occurred
nothing in his subsequent life, different
from the uniform tenor of it, as 
depicted in those sketches. Both body
and mind gradually sunk, and gave
way to the pressure of nearly one hundred 
years, which he had numbered on
earth.  J. J.”</p>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <pb id="white102" n="102"/>
        <p>About the time the foregoing obituary 
appeared, we received the following
communication from another, but a 
kindred pen.</p>
        <q type="obituary" direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1 type="obituary">
                <opener>“NOTTOWAY, 
<hi rend="italics">April</hi> 12, 1843.</opener>
                <p>“Uncle Jack is no more. He sunk 
gently down to the grave on the 6th 
instant, under the pressure of nearly one 
hundred years. His last days, like his 
whole life, were calm and peaceful. But 
little could be gathered of the exercises 
of his mind, except from the attitude of 
prayer, which was indicated by the 
frequent raising of his hands and eyes
upwards. A few hours before he died, he
revived a little, and said, “I am ready 
and waiting for the Saviour;’ then gently 
breathed his last.</p>
                <closer>
                  <signed>C. J.”</signed>
                </closer>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <p>It is pleasing to review such a life,
terminating in such a death. It might
be profitable to detain the reader with
<pb id="white103" n="103"/>
the reflections which very obviously 
arise from this unpretending narrative 
of so humble and obscure a man. But 
the writer is conscious that the moral 
of these simple annals, will at once
occur to every serious reader. Let him 
only remember, that this old man's 
pilgrimage commenced on the dark shores 
of Africa: that when a heathen boy,
he was captured and brought to this 
land; for a time enslaved, but soon 
emancipated: that he was indebted 
for his freedom, under God, to the 
liberality of benevolent and Christian 
masters, whose sole object was to confer on 
him the merited reward of an upright 
life, and to enlarge his sphere of
usefulness to others. Visited by “the daystar
from on high,” he was numbered 
among those whom the Son makes free. 
And having led a very long life of 
humble, consistent, and devoted piety; 
a life which won for him the kind
<pb id="white104" n="104"/>
attentions and affectionate confidence 
of the best people of the country in 
which Providence had placed him, he 
died, cheered by the bright prospect of 
a blessed immortality. And through 
all that country, his memory is cherished, 
and his influence felt to this day. 
True, to use his own striking language, 
“having done with the stream, he is 
now beside the fountain,” but still he 
lives, and will live, as the wise, the 
good, the useful always do, to the end 
of time.</p>
        <p>We conclude with the prayer, that 
he who writes, and they who read, may 
only live the life, and share at last, the 
heavenly inheritance of the African 
Preacher.</p>
      </div1>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div1 type="appendix">
        <pb id="white105" n="105"/>
        <head>APPENDIX I.</head>
        <head>BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH OF DR. JAMES JONES.</head>
        <p>THERE occurs, very frequently, in the
foregoing narrative, the name of one with 
whom the reader may wish to become better
acquainted. Such a wish is reasonable, and
should be gratified. But a higher purpose 
may be answered by the brief sketch we now
propose to give. In thus associating two
individuals, in many respects so different, it
must be gratifying to the pious, and may be
useful to all, to see how the religion of the 
Bible reaches <hi rend="italics">up</hi> to the highest, then <hi rend="italics">down</hi> 
to the lowest; and disdaining the distinctions 
which birth, education, rank and 
<pb id="white106" n="106"/>
fortune create, can make companions and 
friends of both. Thus it was with the African 
Preacher and the late Dr. James Jones, 
of Mountain Hall. During the last twenty 
years of their lives, it was difficult to know 
one, without knowing the other. They 
resided for almost fifty years within one mile 
of each other. The former was poor, the
latter rich; the former almost wholly 
destitute of the knowledge of letters, the 
latter educated in the best schools on 
two continents. The one humble in his 
circumstances, unpretending, and unknown; 
the other occupying several of the highest 
civil stations ever held in this country,
besides shining as one of the brightest
ornaments of the medical profession. What but
the gospel of the Son of God, could have
brought together two individuals, so diverse
from each other, and called forth so much
condescending kindness in the one, so much
<pb id="white107" n="107"/>
reverential regard in the other, and so much
fraternal sympathy in both?</p>
        <p>Dr. James Jones, was born in the county 
of Nottoway, Virginia, December 11th, 1772. 
His parents were among the most reputable 
and wealthy citizens of the county in which 
they lived. They wisely determined to spare 
neither care nor money in the education of 
their son. He was accordingly sent to the 
best schools, and as early as 1788, he matriculated 
at Hampden Sidney College, during 
the presidency of the celebrated Dr. John 
Blair Smith. Here his mind became deeply 
imbued with religious principles, during one 
of the most remarkable revivals of religion 
ever known in this, or any other country,
since the great revival on the day of Pentecost,
recorded in the Acts of the Apostles. 
He left College, however, without making a 
profession of religion, and mainly to gratify 
his desire for religious knowledge, he became
<pb id="white108" n="108"/>
a temporary resident in the family of the
celebrated Devereux Jarret, an Episcopal
clergyman of Dinwiddie. Here his religious
impressions were fostered; and although he
sometimes thought of the gospel ministry as 
his profession, he seems not to have been 
really converted. He remained but a short 
time in the family of his friend Mr. Jarret, 
and at the earnest solicitation of his father, 
repaired to Philadelphia, where he prosecuted 
the study of medicine with great 
success, under the celebrated Dr. Benjamin
Rush. Thence he was transferred to the
University of Edinburgh, where be graduated
with signal honour, and returned to his 
native State, and native county, a physician, 
whose talents and education soon placed him 
at the head of his profession.</p>
        <p>Shortly after his return from Europe, he
married Miss Catherine Harris, of Surry; a 
lady, whose mind, manners and education
<pb id="white109" n="109"/>
were such as to enable her, in a very high
degree, to promote his happiness and 
contribute to his success. Her dignified and 
gentle manners, her polished mind, her 
amiable disposition, her <sic corr="warmhearted">warm-hearted</sic> 
hospitality, are extensively known and highly 
appreciated through Virginia and elsewhere, 
especially by travelling ministers of 
the gospel, who so often found in her a sister, 
and in her house a home. She survives her 
husband; and now, at an advanced age, in 
all the loneliness of a childless widowhood, 
she awaits, with Christian meekness, the 
summons, which must ere long call her to 
that land, where</p>
        <lg type="verse">
          <l>“Everlasting spring abides, </l>
          <l>And never withering flowers.”</l>
        </lg>
        <p>Dr. Jones was not permitted to continue 
long in private life. He was frequently 
called to represent his county in the State
<pb id="white110" n="110"/>
Legislature. He served as Privy Counsellor
under the elder John Tyler; represented his
district in Congress during the administration 
of Mr. Madison, and was chosen to act 
as a member of the Electoral College in the 
election of four successive Presidents. In all 
these important stations, he discharged his 
duty with signal faithfulness and ability.</p>
        <p>His extreme modesty, and nothing but 
this, prevented his becoming distinguished as 
a debater in our national councils. But he 
was a politician whose prudence, whose accurate 
and varied knowledge, sound judgment, 
purity of purpose, and practical wisdom, 
rendered him eminently useful.</p>
        <p>His residence, as a student of medicine, in
Philadelphia, and still more, his subsequent
residence in Europe, was by no means
favourable to the development of the religious
feelings and principles which had been
awakened at Hampden Sidney. Indeed, an
<pb id="white111" n="111"/>
opposite and a disastrous influence was 
exerted. He returned to his native land very 
decidedly skeptical in his views. Unfortunately, 
such views had, at this time, become 
very popular in Virginia, and particularly so 
in the region of country in which our friend 
commenced the practice of medicine. Here 
a number of the wealthiest and most intelligent 
gentlemen, had united in the formation 
of an “infidel club,” the place of whose 
meetings is known to this day as
<hi rend="italics">“Paineville”</hi>—thus named in honour of <hi rend="italics">Tom Paine. </hi>
The high intellectual character of these
gentlemen was such, as to give them great
influence over our young physician; and he was
accordingly led to think, and feel, and act as
they did. Thus he lived for many years, 
and thus, to use his own language, he “did 
much to embitter the latter portion of his life 
with wormwood and gall.”</p>
        <p>His domestic relations were eminently
<pb id="white112" n="112"/>
happy, and perhaps no man was ever better
fitted, by high social qualities, to impart and 
to enjoy happiness as a husband and father. 
In the wise but inscrutable providence of 
God, the sources of our purest and most 
elevated enjoyments often become the occasions 
of our deepest grief. It was thus with 
these fond parents. God had given them 
two lovely daughters, the only children He 
ever gave them. One of these died in 
infancy. The other had nearly attained maturity, 
and gave abundant promise of the rarest 
excellences. A lovely person, a sprightly 
and well cultivated mind, a tender and amiable 
heart, made her almost the idol of her 
doting parents. She seemed to them as a 
source of light and comfort, by which their
footsteps were to be directed, and their 
hearts cheered, amidst the darkness of old 
age. But, in all this, they were sadly 
disappointed. Death came again, and laid this
<pb id="white113" n="113"/>
lovely form by the side of her who had been
buried in infancy, and bore her spirit to Him
who is the resurrection and the life.</p>
        <p>The death of two such children, with none 
to supply their place, was an affliction almost 
too heavy to be borne, and threatened to 
crush those upon whom it fell.</p>
        <p>The following extract is taken from a 
paper found in his desk after his death, and 
written at the time of his sad loss. It is 
here presented, as furnishing proof of the 
strength of his parental feelings, an illustration 
of the greatness of his grief, and as a 
specimen of the efforts made by a vigorous 
mind and tender heart—as yet, unenlightened 
and unrenewed by divine grace—to 
find consolation in sorrow. The extract is 
as follows:</p>
        <lg type="verse">
          <l>“She was her parents' sole delight;</l>
          <l>They had but one—one only child.”</l>
        </lg>
        <p>“The loss of this fair bud of being, just 
<pb id="white114" n="114"/>
beginning to bloom and spread all its sweets
abroad to our enraptured senses, nipped by an
untimely frost, has left me to wail in gloomy
silence. Ever dear, ever sacred shall be the
recollection of her! Yes, an <sic corr="all wise">all-wise</sic> Providence
permitted her to shed on this benighted 
world, the effulgent beams of her brilliant 
soul, for a short time only, and then took her 
back to himself, in order to attract more 
forcibly the earnest longings, the ardent 
aspirations of her afflicted parents towards 
himself. Never can I again plunge into the 
gay scenes, the flattering, beguiling pleasures 
of this troubled ocean of time. Whilst 
I possessed such a treasure as she was, far 
short of its intrinsic value was my estimate 
of it. Now that I am bereft of it, my fond,
my mortified recollection goes back to scenes, 
which, could I return to them again, would 
afford me the most exquisite delight—the 
antepast of heaven. To cultivate such a
<pb id="white115" n="115"/>
mind; to cherish all its virtuous emotions; 
to guard it against the attacks of vice; to 
direct its expansive operations in the fields 
of fancy and of science! O God! what 
exquisite enjoyments didst thou put within my 
reach, and what shameful indifference did I 
betray! Pardon, O pardon, my gross 
ingratitude! Give me resignation to thy 
heavenly will, believing that all things shall 
work together for good to those who, through 
faith and patience in well doing, seek for 
immortality of bliss in thy favour only.”</p>
        <p>Here the manuscript ends abruptly. About
this time, whether before or after writing the
above we are not informed, the <sic corr="deeply distressed">deeply-distressed</sic> 
father addressed a letter to a 
distinguished gentleman, whose acquaintance he
had made in Congress, asking for consolation. 
His friend, who was an utter stranger
to the Bible, if not an avowed unbeliever,
replied with promptitude and kindness, saying
<pb id="white116" n="116"/>
all that the light of nature, and all that 
reason, unassisted by revelation, could say, to 
cheer the heart, when well nigh crushed with 
grief. Having read this letter again and 
again, he exclaimed, “Is this all? Can 
nothing more be said or done to cheer me in 
my sorrow? There must be a God. This
I have always believed. It is equally
obvious, that this God is benevolent; and if so,
he has somewhere made provision for support
and comfort at a time like this. But where 
is this provision to be found? The letter of 
my friend shows plainly that this world has 
it not. Had it been discoverable by reason, 
the writer would have known it. But, 
instead of giving comfort, his communication 
adds poignancy to my grief. It must be in 
the Bible. <hi rend="italics">I will look.”</hi> Thus he reasoned. 
Then opening the inspired volume, he turned 
its leaves somewhat at random, when his
eyes fell on this passage, “For our light
<pb id="white117" n="117"/>
affliction which is but for a moment, worketh 
for us a far more exceeding and eternal 
weight of glory; while we look not at the 
things which are seen, but at the things 
which are not seen: for the things which are 
seen, are temporal, but the things which are 
not seen, are eternal.” 2 Cor. iv. 17, 18.</p>
        <p>This arrested his attention. This touched 
his heart, and he exclaimed, “I have found 
it. This meets my case.” Thus encouraged, 
he read on, and in process of time, became a 
true believer in Christ, and a consistent and 
useful member of his church.</p>
        <p>He now sought to promote the spiritual 
good of his friends and of the world, with 
great liberality and zeal. Upon thorough 
investigation, he became a Presbyterian, and 
sought and obtained from the Presbytery a 
missionary, who found in his house a home, 
and at his hands a support, which enabled 
him to prosecute his work with some success;
<pb id="white118" n="118"/>
and thus, through the instrumentality of 
this distinguished physician and statesman—
now an humble Christian—were the foundations 
of a church laid, which has increased 
in numbers and efficiency, until it has 
become one of the largest and strongest country 
churches in the Synod of Virginia.</p>
        <p>At an early period of his Christian life, 
he became a ruling elder in the church which 
he had so materially aided in organizing; 
and for many years served with great fidelity 
in all our church courts, from the Session to 
the General Assembly.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jones had mingled freely, until about 
the fiftieth year of his age, in the gayest, 
most fashionable, and the least religious 
circles of society. His manners and his 
habits were accordingly such, as strongly 
incline those who make a profession of 
religion, from the higher walks of life, to 
content themselves with the shadow, rather than
<pb id="white119" n="119"/>
the substance. As an illustration of the 
mighty power of divine truth in remodeling 
the character; and as a proof of the sincerity 
and depth of his piety, it should be stated, 
that on connecting himself with the Church, 
he engaged promptly and zealously in the 
active duties of the Christian life. He 
erected an altar, around which his family 
were regularly called to offer their morning 
and evening devotions. He took the deepest 
interest in the religious instruction of his 
large family of servants; and few have
succeeded so well in inducing this class of
persons to attend regularly and seriously on
divine worship, both social and public. From 
his earliest connection with the Church, to 
the end of his earthly pilgrimage, he had a 
neat apartment kept as a private chapel, 
where divine service was regularly performed 
on the Sabbath, for the benefit of his own 
servants, and such of his neighbours' servants
<pb id="white120" n="120"/>
as might choose to attend. For several 
years, the writer was accustomed to officiate 
in this place, and to this people, on the 
Sabbath afternoon; and never can he forget the 
dignified, yet subdued and chastened manner, 
with which this excellent man regularly seated 
himself in the midst of this humble audience, 
to hear with them the words of life eternal. 
There, too, sat the good old African Preacher, 
with his dark visage, but brilliant mind and 
pious heart, who never failed, when the service 
was over, to remain, that he might 
propound questions, and make remarks suggested 
by the sermon just delivered.</p>
        <p>Our lamented friend became the early and
zealous champion of the temperance reformation. 
As early as the year 1828, he attended 
and addressed the first temperance meeting 
ever held in that part of the country. He was 
one of only eight persons who could be
induced to favour the holding of this meeting;
<pb id="white121" n="121"/>
and shared largely, but cheerfully, in the 
public odium which this movement elicited. 
In this war—and war it was of a truth—he 
enlisted for life, and lived and died its wise 
and prudent, but firm and fearless friend and 
promoter. It was his happiness, too, to see 
this cause, as well as that of his church, both 
of which had so feeble a beginning, surmount 
every obstacle, and attain a high degree of 
prosperity and usefulness.</p>
        <p>All the benevolent enterprises of the 
Church, enjoyed his confidence, and shared 
in his benefactions. We have rarely known 
a man, whose judgment more promptly 
approved, and whose heart more warmly 
embraced, whatever tended to elevate and bless 
his race. Thoroughly educated himself, he 
was the firm friend of the education of 
others. An alumnus of Hampden Sidney 
College, and subsequently a trustee, he was 
the warm friend and liberal supporter of that
<pb id="white122" n="122"/>
venerable and useful institution. He saw, 
too, the obvious difference in rank and 
importance, between the College and the 
University; and hence his zeal for the former 
did not make him the blind opponent of the 
latter. His private letters abound with 
expressions of the highest admiration for the 
University of Virginia. He, more than once, 
visited this seat of learning, and informed 
himself thoroughly respecting its course of 
instruction and system of discipline by 
personal inspection; the result of which was,
an abiding conviction, that, without an
institution planned, endowed, and conducted 
as that is, the literary and scientific 
wants of the commonwealth could not be 
supplied.</p>
        <p>From the period of Dr. Jones's conversion 
no subject more constantly occupied his 
thoughts, or more deeply enlisted his 
feelings, than the condition and future prospects 
<pb id="white123" n="123"/>
of his servants. We have already seen the
measures he adopted for their religious
instruction. But when taught, he wished 
them to enjoy the benefits of that instruction 
to the fullest attainable extent. In a word, 
he desired and he purposed to emancipate 
them.</p>
        <p>He fully believed that the only wise and
benevolent method of doing this, was to send
them to Liberia, under the auspices of the
American Colonization Society. Accordingly,
after corresponding with Mr. Elliot 
Cresson, and other distinguished friends of 
this cause, in reference to this matter, he 
and Mrs. Jones, whose sentiments and feelings 
were identical, commenced a course of 
instruction designed to enlighten their minds, 
and to form their characters with a view to 
emigration.</p>
        <p>But the condition of these servants was
rendered so extremely comfortable, by the
<pb id="white124" n="124"/>
<hi rend="italics">parental</hi> treatment received at the hands of
their excellent master and mistress, that not 
one of them could be induced to go, until 
that master and mistress should be taken 
from them by death.</p>
        <p>In 1837 he made his will, in which he 
provides amply for the emancipation and 
emigration to Liberia of as many as could be 
induced to go, leaving the whole to be 
executed at the death of his widow. This will 
contains the following clause: “The whole 
subject is to be fully and intelligibly 
presented to their minds, so that they may have 
the option of going to the Colony, or remaining 
in bondage. And I particularly desire 
that any of them who may be willing to go, 
shall <hi rend="italics">at any time</hi> be emancipated by due 
form of law, by my executors, and transferred 
to such agents of said Colony as may 
be willing to receive them. I would prefer 
that point known as Bassa Cove, under the
<pb id="white125" n="125"/>
direction of the New York and Pennsylvania
Colonization Societies.”</p>
        <p>The will of 1846, which is his last will 
does not differ materially from the former<corr>.</corr> 
Knowing how tenderly his loved wife felt on 
this subject, he only leaves the whole matter 
more fully in her hands.</p>
        <p>She has accordingly commenced the work,
both of colonization and emancipation; having
tendered to some of them the privilege 
of going this spring to Liberia, and having 
actually emancipated others, in the best and 
only way permitted by the laws of Virginia, 
with the privilege of remaining in the 
commonwealth.</p>
        <p>Were it expedient, we might easily and
greatly extend this sketch. We should like 
to speak, as truth would warrant, of his 
purity and patriotism; his unshaken 
constancy as a friend; and particularly of his 
almost excessive tenderness, faithfulness and
<pb id="white126" n="126"/>
affection as a husband. But we can only 
glance at his last moments.</p>
        <p>He had lived the life of the enlightened
patriot, the hospitable and polished gentleman,
the consistent, useful Christian. Such 
a life might be expected to terminate in a 
calm and peaceful death. His last illness 
was protracted and severe; but borne with 
Christian fortitude and Christian submission. 
He was among the first to discover, that his 
sickness would be unto death. With the
utmost composure, he proceeded to give such
directions respecting his temporal concerns, 
as he deemed necessary; not neglecting a 
full expression of his wishes as to his burial. 
Having done this, he said to a friend, who 
had travelled many miles to visit him, “I am 
glad to see you. I have endeavoured, from 
the first, to cast myself upon a gracious God, 
through a Redeemer. This I now do. The 
violence of my disease interrupts thought,
<pb id="white127" n="127"/>
and hinders devotion. <hi rend="italics">I can only trust.”</hi> 
Shortly after this, he seemed to have drawn 
his last breath. All perceptible signs of life 
were gone. His fond wife bent over him in 
agony, exclaiming, “It is all over.” To the 
surprise of all around him, he opened his 
eyes, and looked tenderly upon her who 
was dearer to him than his own life, and 
said, “Be still and wait. I am waiting
quietly.”</p>
        <p>On another occasion he said, “When I do 
go, I hope to go straight to a better world.” 
He was now unable to carry on a connected
conversation, but as he lay, struggling for
breath, and expecting every moment to be 
his last, he was heard, from time to time, 
indulging in such expressions as these: 
“<hi rend="italics">Bluntly</hi> prepared. Yes, ready, and sometimes 
very anxious, to go.”—“There is still 
a great deal of evil in the world. Satan is 
still permitted to have much power. But
<pb id="white128" n="128"/>
the Lord reigns, and will do all things well.”
To the friend before referred to, who was, at 
this critical moment, very reluctantly forced 
to leave him, and whom, with much difficulty, 
he was made to recognize, he said, “Farewell! 
God bless you! It is all that I can 
say.”</p>
        <p>These were among the last expressions 
which fell from that tongue which had so 
often, and with so much eloquence, edified 
and delighted the intelligent and pious 
visitors, who were accustomed to frequent his 
delightful residence. That tongue is now 
silent in death, but the spirit which animated 
it, lives in a purer and brighter world. That 
body which, with so much dignity and grace, 
was accustomed to move through the
apartments, and over the fields and gardens of
Mountain Hall, now lies beside the remains 
of the loved ones lost in childhood; but his
character and his example still live, to teach
<pb id="white129" n="129"/>
surviving friends and relatives how to be 
useful in life and happy in death.</p>
        <p>Thus lived and thus died, the African
Preacher and his distinguished friend and
patron. The former ended his days on the 
6th of April, 1843, supposed to be nearly 
one hundred years old. The other followed 
on the 25th of April, 1848, in the 77th year 
of his age.</p>
        <p>We bless the God and Father of our Lord
Jesus Christ for that gospel which can thus
influence all classes in society; revealing, as 
it does, a Saviour, who could thus lay one 
hand on the kidnapped African, and the 
other on the polished graduate of a European 
University; then mould and fashion their 
habits and tastes so much alike, that it is 
hard to say, whether the power and grace of 
that Saviour are most conspicuous, in 
elevating the former, or in humbling the latter.
As unlike by nature as the two continents
<pb id="white130" n="130"/>
which gave them birth, by grace they 
became one in Christ Jesus, and, beyond a 
doubt, are now together before the throne, 
singing, as with one voice and one heart, 
“the song of Moses and the Lamb.”</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="appendix">
        <pb id="white131" n="131"/>
        <head>APPENDIX II.</head>
        <p>IT is stated at page 29, that Uncle Jack 
was very often called upon to officiate at the
funerals of the coloured people. Such occasions
on the plantations often exhibit scenes 
of much solemn interest, both on the part of 
the planters and the slaves. The following 
extract from a popular journal, gives a 
graphic sketch of such a scene.—[EDITOR OF 
PRESB. BOARD OF PUBLICATION.]</p>
        <q type="article" direct="unspecified">
          <text>
            <body>
              <div1>
                <head>THE NIGHT FUNERAL OF A SLAVE.</head>
                <p>Travelling recently on business, in the
interior of Georgia, I reached, just at sunset, 
the mansion of the proprietor through whose
<pb id="white132" n="132"/>
estate, for the last half hour of my journey, 
I had pursued my way. My tired companion 
pricked his ears, and with a low whinny 
indicated his pleasure, as I turned up the 
broad avenue leading to the house. Calling 
to a black boy in view, I made him inquire 
of his owner if I could be accommodated 
with lodgings for the night.</p>
                <p>My request brought the proprietor himself 
to the door, and from thence to the gate, 
when, after a scrutinizing glance at my person 
and equipments, he inquired my name, 
business, and destination. I promptly 
responded to his questions, and he invited me 
to alight and enter the house, in the true 
spirit of Southern hospitality.</p>
                <p>He was apparently thirty years of age, 
and evidently a man of education and refinement. 
I soon observed an air of gloomy 
abstraction about him. He said but little, 
and even that little seemed the result of an
<pb id="white133" n="133"/>
effort to obviate the seeming want of civility 
to a stranger. At supper, the mistress of 
the mansion appeared, and did the honours 
of the table, in her particular department. 
She was exceedingly <sic corr="ladylike">lady-like</sic> and beautiful. 
She retired immediately after supper, and a 
servant handing some splendid <foreign lang="spa"><hi rend="italics">habanas</hi></foreign> on 
a small silver tray, we had seated ourselves 
comfortably before the enormous fire of oak 
wood, when a servant appeared at the end 
door near my host, hat in hand, and uttered,
in subdued but distinct tones, the, to me, 
startling words:</p>
                <p>“Master, de coffin hab come.”</p>
                <p>“Very well,” was the only reply, and the
servant disappeared.</p>
                <p>My host remarked my gaze of inquisitive
wonder, and replied to it—</p>
                <p>“I have been sad, sad,” said he, “<sic corr="today">to-day</sic>. 
I have had a greater misfortune than I have
experienced since my father's death. I lost
<pb id="white134" n="134"/>
this morning the truest and most reliable 
friend I had in the world—one whom I have 
been accustomed to honour and respect since 
my earliest recollection. He was the playmate 
of my father's youth, and the mentor 
of mine; a faithful servant, an honest man, 
and sincere Christian. I stood by his bedside 
<sic corr="today">to-day</sic>, and with his hands clasped in 
mine, I heard the last words he uttered; 
they were, ‘Master, meet me in heaven.’ ”</p>
                <p>His voice faltered a moment, and he
continued, after a pause, with increased
excitement:</p>
                <p>“His loss is a melancholy one to me. If 
I left my home, I said to him, ‘John, see that 
all things are taken care of,’ and I knew 
that my wife and child, property and all, 
were as safe as though they were guarded by 
a hundred soldiers. I never spoke a harsh 
word to him in all my life, for he never 
merited it. I have a hundred others, many
<pb id="white135" n="135"/>
of them faithful and true, but his loss is
irreparable.”</p>
                <p>I came from a section of the Union where
slavery does not exist; and I brought with 
me all the prejudices which so generally 
prevail in the free States in regard to this 
“institution.” I had already seen much to 
soften these, but the observation of years 
would have failed to give me so clear an 
insight into the relation between master and 
servant as this simple incident. It was not 
the haughty planter, the lordly tyrant,
talking of his dead slave as of his dead horse,
but the <sic corr="kindhearted">kind-hearted</sic> gentleman, lamenting 
the loss and eulogizing the virtues of his 
good old <hi rend="italics">friend.</hi></p>
                <p>After an interval of silence, my host 
resumed:</p>
                <p>“There are,” said he, “many of the old 
man's relatives and friends who would wish 
to attend his funeral. To afford them opportunity,
<pb id="white136" n="136"/>
several plantations have been notified
that he will be buried <sic corr="tonight">to-night</sic>. Some, I 
presume, have already arrived; and desiring to 
see that all things are properly prepared for 
his interment, I trust you will excuse my 
absence a few moments.”</p>
                <p>“Most certainly, sir; but,” I added, “if 
there is no impropriety, I would be pleased 
to accompany you.”</p>
                <p>“There is none,” he replied; and I 
followed him to one of a long row of cabins, 
situated at the distance of some three 
hundred yards from the mansion. The house 
was crowded with negroes. All arose on our 
entrance, and many of them exchanged 
greeting with my host, in tones that 
convinced me that they felt that he was an
object of sympathy from them! The corpse 
was deposited in the coffin, attired in a 
shroud of the finest cotton materials, and the 
coffin itself painted black.</p>
                <pb id="white137" n="137"/>
                <p>The master stopped at its head, and laying
his hand upon the cold brow of his faithful
bondsman, gazed long and intently upon
features with which he had been so long
familiar, and which he now looked upon for the
last time on earth. Raising his eyes at length,
and glancing at the serious countenances 
now bent upon his, he said solemnly, and 
with much feeling—</p>
                <p>“He was a faithful servant and true Christian.
If you follow his example, and live as 
he lived, none of you need fear when the 
time comes for you to lie here.”</p>
                <p>A patriarch, with the snow of eighty winters
on his head, answered,</p>
                <p>“Master, it is true, and we will try to live 
like him.”</p>
                <p>There was a murmur of general assent, 
and after giving some instructions relative 
to the burial, we returned to the building.</p>
                <p>About nine o'clock a servant appeared
<pb id="white138" n="138"/>
with the notice that they were ready to move,
and to know if further instructions were
necessary. My host remarked to me that, 
by stepping into the piazza, I would probably
behold, to me, a novel scene. The 
procession had moved, and its route led within 
a few yards of the mansion. There were 
one hundred and fifty negroes, arranged 
four deep, and following a wagon in which 
was placed the coffin. Down the entire 
length of the line, at intervals of a few feet 
on each side, were carried torches of the
resinous pine, here called <sic corr="lightwood">light-wood</sic>. About 
the centre was stationed the black preacher, 
a man of gigantic frame and stentorian lungs, 
who gave out from memory the words of a 
hymn suitable to the occasion. The Southern 
negroes are proverbial for the melody and 
compass of their voices, and I thought that 
hymn, mellowed by distance, the most 
solemn, and yet the sweetest music that had
<pb id="white139" n="139"/>
ever fallen upon my ear. The stillness of 
the night, and strength of their voices, 
enabled me to distinguish the air at the 
distance of half a mile.</p>
                <p>It was to me a strange and solemn scene, 
and no incident of my life has impressed me 
with more powerful emotions than the night 
funeral of the poor negro. For this reason 
I have hastily and most imperfectly sketched 
its leading features.</p>
              </div1>
            </body>
          </text>
        </q>
        <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </div1>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI.2>