<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>Life, Last Words and Dying Speech of Stephen Smith, a Black Man, Who Was Executed at Boston This Day Being Thursday, October 12, 1797 for Burglary :</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Smith, Stephen, 1769 or 70-1797.</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text  transcribed  by</resp>
          <name>Elizabeth Wright </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Elizabeth S. Wright  and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>2001</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca.   16K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>2001.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="caption"> Life, Last Words and Dying Speech of Stephen Smith, A Black Man, who was executed at Boston this Day being Thursday, October 12, 1797 for Burglary</title>
            <author>Stephen Smith</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>Broadside, 1  p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
            <publisher>The Author.</publisher>
            <date>1797</date>
            <authority/>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="yes">This electronic edition has been transcribed from a microfiche printout.</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Original grammar, punctuation, and spelling have been preserved.  Encountered
typographical errors have been preserved, and appear in red type.</p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>African American criminals -- Biography.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Burglary -- Massachusetts -- History -- 18th century.</item>
            <item>Crime -- Massachusetts -- History -- 18th century.</item>
            <item>Fugitive slaves -- Massachusetts -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Last words.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- Early works to 1800.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Virginia -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves' writings, American -- Massachusetts.</item>
            <item>Smith, Stephen, 1769 or 70-1797.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2001-10-25, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2001-05-02, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2001-04-26, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Elizabeth S. Wright</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2001-04-26, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Elizabeth S. Wright</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished transcribing  and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div1 type="statement">
        <head><hi rend="italics">Life, Last Words and Dying Speech of Stephen Smith</hi><lb/>A BLACK MAN, who was EXECUTED at BOSTON this Day<lb/> being Thursday, October 12, 1797 for BURGLARY</head>
        <p>I <hi rend="italics">Stephen Smith</hi>, was born in <hi rend="italics">Virginia</hi>, in the County of Sussex, belonging to Mr. WILLIAM ALLEN. My Father was a religious
Man, and gave good Advice, which if I had followed would have prevented my DISGRACEFUL END. But my Mother
encouraged me to <hi rend="italics">Steal</hi>. My name was <hi rend="italics">Stephen</hi>, the name of <hi rend="italics">Allen</hi> I took from my Master, but changed it to that of <hi rend="italics">Smith</hi>, that I
might escape from my Master. </p>
        <p>In my Youth I was guilty of many small Thefts. The first great Crime I committed was breaking up my Master's Tan Fats, and
taking some Leather; for which he sent me to the West-Indias to be Sold. I concealed myself and returned to Virginia, by the
same Vessel, and determined not to be carried to my Master by the Captain. I stole the Boat clothes and went on Shore
unperceived, landed on an Island and hid myself in the Woods till I was almost starved. I then broke into a House, got something
to Eat, and Stole the Man's Shoes and Shirts, and returned to the Woods again, tarried two days, and then went to a Man's
House to get some Victuals, but they tried to take me: I <sic corr="ran">run</sic> to the Woods, and they shot at me and wounded me in the Leg. A
few days after, they took me and carried me to my Master again, who gave me to his Son, but quarrelling with his Overseer, he
sent me again to the West-Indies. From thence I went to St. John's in Nova Scotia, then to St. Ann's, where I was tried on four <hi rend="italics">Indictments</hi>; <hi rend="italics">one</hi> for striking a Lawyer; a <hi rend="italics">second</hi> for striking the
<sic corr="Gaol">Goal</sic> Keeper; to these I plead Guilty, and was pardoned by the Governor, on condition that I should leave the Kingdom.</p>
        <p>The <hi rend="italics">third Indictment</hi> was for Shop-breaking; the <hi rend="italics">fourth</hi> for breaking into a House; to these I pleaded not Guilty, and was
cleared! though I confess I was Guilty of breaking into the House, but not the Shop. </p>
        <p>I then came to Boston, where I lived seven Months, at which time I was taken and committed to Prison on <hi rend="italics">four Indictments</hi>:
<hi rend="italics">two</hi> for House-breaking, and two for burning Houses; to which <hi rend="italics">(though I was guilty of the whole)</hi> I pleaded not Guilty, but
was cast on my <hi rend="italics">Trial</hi> and CONDEMNED. </p>
        <p>I set <hi rend="italics">FIRE</hi> to the Houses of Mr. Turner, and Mr. Goldsbury, and robbed them; but I had no accomplice in these crimes, nor
was I hired or asked by any one to commit them, nor had I any Malice against any Body; my only Object was to obtain Money
for wicked Purposes. For this <hi rend="italics">Lie</hi> of pleading <hi rend="italics">not</hi> Guilty, I am ashamed before GOD, whom I have offended, and before Man. I
<hi rend="italics">took</hi> some Goods out a shop in Boston, in the Day Time; from Mr. Cushing a Bottle of Wine, and from Mr. Thomas Brewer a
Bottle of Porter, with both whom I lived. With bad Women I have been much connected, who have been a great cause of my
<hi rend="italics">shameful End</hi>. The Sabbath I broke, and neglected publick Worship. Such has been my wicked Life. I ask forgiveness of all
whom I have injured: Although I have been such a great <hi rend="italics">Sinner</hi> I hope God will forgive <hi rend="italics">me</hi> for the sake of JESUS CHRIST: I
trust in him for my Salvation. When I think how I have sinned against the great <hi rend="italics">GOD</hi>, my <hi rend="italics">heart</hi> breaks, and <hi rend="italics">tears</hi> <sic corr="run">runs</sic> from <hi rend="italics">my
Eyes</hi>. To the Ministers who visited, and instructed <hi rend="italics">me</hi> about my <hi rend="italics">poor Soul</hi>, and the <hi rend="italics">way</hi> of being <hi rend="italics">saved</hi>, and who have often
<hi rend="italics">prayed</hi> with me, I give my sincere <hi rend="italics">thanks</hi>. I forgive <hi rend="italics">every Body</hi>, and hope that <hi rend="italics">GOD</hi> will have <hi rend="italics">mercy</hi> on me. </p>
        <p>Now in the 28th Year of my Age I commit my <hi rend="italics">spirit</hi> into the Hands of <hi rend="italics">merciful</hi> and <hi rend="italics">just</hi> <hi rend="italics">GOD</hi> and hope <hi rend="italics">he</hi> will receive me for
<hi rend="italics">his</hi> great <hi rend="italics">mercy's</hi> <hi rend="italics">sake. I die</hi> in <hi rend="italics">peace</hi> with all <hi rend="italics">mankind</hi>, and <hi rend="italics">beg</hi> that <hi rend="italics">all people</hi> will take <hi rend="italics">warning</hi> by <hi rend="italics">my Awful END. </hi></p>
        <closer>
          <signed>
            <name>STEPHEN SMITH</name>
          </signed>
        </closer>
      </div1>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div1 type="note">
        <p><hi rend="italics">The Prisoner</hi> about 15 minutes before two o'clock, left the <hi rend="italics">Jail</hi> and for the place of <hi rend="italics">Execution.</hi> He was proceeded by Sheriff
ALLEN, and his Deputies Messrs. HARTSHORN, SYMES, and BELL, on Horseback; and accompanied by the Rev. Doctors STILLMAN
and THATCHER, on foot. At 2 o'clock the procession reached the place of execution, which was at the bottom of the common.
The Sheriff read the warrant which authorised the <hi rend="italics">Prisoner's Execution</hi>. Doctor THATCHER then addressed the <hi rend="italics">fountain</hi> of <hi rend="italics">mercy</hi>
in a pertinent pathetic <hi rend="italics">prayer</hi>. After a short conversation between the Rev. Gentlemen and Culprit, Dr. THATCHER, at his
request, addressed the numerous croud which the <hi rend="italics">awful</hi> occasion had collected, desired them to be warned by the <hi rend="italics">fate</hi> of the
<hi rend="italics">Criminal</hi>, assured them that <hi rend="italics">he</hi> received <hi rend="italics">his Trial fair</hi>, forgave all who have ever injured him, and <hi rend="italics">died</hi> in peace with the <hi rend="italics">family of
Mankind</hi>. After a lengthy pause, the Gentlemen of the Clergy having retired, SMITH, addressed himself to Sheriff ALLEN, Mr.
HARTSHORN (as jailer) and Mr. LEWIS a Constable, and thanked them for their particular attention and kindness to <hi rend="italics">him</hi>. The <hi rend="italics">last
moment</hi> drew near, the <hi rend="italics">HALTER</hi> was put round the <hi rend="italics">Culprit's neck</hi>, the <hi rend="italics">white CAP</hi> drawn over his eyes, and, after an <hi rend="italics">instant's</hi>
pause which <hi rend="italics">HE</hi> appeared to devote to <hi rend="italics">fervent</hi> though <hi rend="italics">silent prayer</hi>, <hi rend="italics">HE</hi> was led to the <hi rend="italics">scaffold</hi>, the <hi rend="italics">supporting</hi> line unfastened and the <hi rend="italics">malefactor launched</hi> into <hi rend="italics">ETERNITY</hi>. After
HANGING about half an hour, <hi rend="italics">HE</hi> was <hi rend="italics">cut</hi> down, <hi rend="italics">and put into his COFFIN.</hi></p>
      </div1>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI.2>