<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % external-entities SYSTEM "./extEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY % internal-entities SYSTEM "./intEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY cugoantp SYSTEM "cugoantp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY cugoanvs SYSTEM "cugoanvs.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>Narrative of the Enslavement of Ottobah Cugoano, a
Native of Africa; Published by Himself, in the Year  1787:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Cugoano, Ottobah</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Bethany Ronnberg</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by</resp>
          <name>Bethany Ronnberg</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns"> Sarah Reuning and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1999</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca.     50K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1999.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, 
teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="text"> Narrative of the Enslavement of Ottobah Cugoano, a
Native of Africa; published by himself, in the Year  1787</title>
            <title type="title page"> The Negro's Memorial, or, Abolitionist's 
Catechism</title>
            <author>by an Abolitionist</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent>8      p.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
            <publisher>Hatchard and Co., and J. and A. Arch</publisher>
            <date>1825</date>
            <authority/>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="yes">Electronic edition has been transcribed from pages 120-127 of the Appendix to 
"The Negro's Memorial; or, Abolitionist's catechism; by an Abolitionist" </note>
            <note anchored="yes">Call number  DOSS 326.4 F536N  (Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special 
Collections Library, Duke University Libraries)</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Electronic edition has been transcribed from pages 120-127 of the Appendix to 
"The Negro's Memorial; or, Abolitionist's catechism; by an Abolitionist" </p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor 
(SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Cugoano, Ottobah.</item>
            <item>Blacks -- Africa -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slavery.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- Grenada.</item>
            <item>Slave-trade -- Africa.</item>
            <item>Slaves' writings.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>1999-12-02, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-11-29, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-11-22, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Sarah Reuning</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-11-20, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Bethany Ronnberg</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="title page">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="cugoantp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="verso">
        <p>
          <figure id="verso" entity="cugoanvs">
            <p>[Title Page Verso Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <pb id="fish120" n="120"/>
    <body>
      <div1 type="text">
        <head>
          <hi>APPENDIX.</hi>
        </head>
        <head>NARRATIVE <hi rend="italics">of the Enslavement of</hi> OTTOBAH CUGOANO, <hi rend="italics"> a
Native of Africa; published by himself, in the Year </hi>1787.</head>
        <argument>
          <p>[<hi rend="italics">The following artless narrative, as given to the public by the
subject of it, in </hi>1787,<hi rend="italics">fell into the hands of the author 
of the foregoing pages when they were nearly 
completed, and after that portion of his work to which it more particularly belonged 
had been printed off. It is, nevertheless, a narrative of such high interest, and 
exhibits the Slave-trade and Slavery in such striking colors, throwing light upon 
not a few of the most important facts which form the argument of this work, 
that he could not resist the temptation to give it in an appendix, leaving 
it to operate unassisted upon the minds of his readers, and to inspire them, 
according to their respective mental constitutions, either with admiration or 
detestation of the</hi> SLAVE-TRADE <hi rend="italics">and</hi> NEGRO SLAVERY.]</p>
        </argument>
        <p>I WAS early snatched away from my native country, with
about eighteen or twenty more boys and girls, as we were
playing in a field. We lived but a few days' journey from the
coast where we were kidnapped, and as we were decoyed and
drove along, we were soon conducted to a factory, and from
thence, in the fashionable way of traffic,
<pb id="fish121" n="121"/>
consigned to Grenada. Perhaps it may not be amiss to give a
few remarks, as some account of myself, in this
transposition of captivity.</p>
        <p>I was born in the city of Agimaque, on the coast of
Fantyn; my father was a companion to the chief in that part
of the country of Fantee, and when the old king died I was
left in his house with his family; soon after I was sent for by
his nephew, Ambro Accasa, who succeeded the old king in
the chiefdom of that part of Fantee, known by the name of
Agimaque and Assince. I lived with his children, enjoying
peace and tranquillity, about twenty moons, which,
according to their way of reckoning time, is two years. I was
sent for to visit an uncle, who lived at a considerable
distance from Agimaque. The first day after we set out we
arrived at Assinee, and the third day at my uncle's habitation,
where I lived about three months, and was then thinking of
returning to my father and young companion at Agimaque;
but by this time I had got well acquainted with some of the
children of my uncle's hundreds of relations, and we were
some days too venturesome in going into the woods to gather
fruit and catch birds, and such amusements as pleased us.
One day I refused to go with the rest, being rather
apprehensive that something might happen to us; till one of
my playfellows said to me, “Because you belong to the great men,
you are afraid to <sic>“</sic>venture your carcase, or else of the <hi rend="italics">bounsam</hi>,” 
which is the devil. This enraged me so much, that I set a resolution to
join the rest, and we went into the woods, as usual but we
had not been above two hours, before our troubles began,
when several great ruffians came upon us suddenly, and said
we had committed a fault against their lord, and we must go
and answer for it ourselves before him.</p>
        <p>Some of us attempted, in vain, to run away, but pistols
and cutlasses were soon introduced, threatening, that if we
<pb id="fish122" n="122"/>
offered to stir, we should all lie dead on the spot. One of them
pretended to be more friendly than the rest, and said that he
would speak to their lord to get us clear, and desired that we
should follow him; we were then immediately divided into
different parties, and drove after him. We were soon led out of
the way which we knew, and towards evening, as we came in
sight of a town, they told us that this great man of theirs lived
there, but pretended it was too late to go and see him that
night. Next morning there came three other men, whose
language differed from ours, and spoke to some of those who
watched us all the night; but he that pretended to be our friend
with the great man, and some others, were gone away. We
asked our keeper what these men had been saying to them, and
they answered, that they had been asking them and us together
to go and feast with them that day, and that we must put off
seeing the great man till after, little thinking that our doom was
so nigh, or that these villains meant to feast on us as their
prey. We went with them again about half a day's journey, and
came to a great multitude of people, having different music
playing; and all the day after we got there, we were very
merry with the music, dancing, and singing. Towards the
evening, we were again persuaded that we could not get back
to where the great man lived till next day; and when bed-time 
came, we were separated into different houses with different 
people. When the next morning came, I asked for the men 
that brought me there, and for the rest of my companions; and 
I was told that they were gone to the sea-side, to bring 
home some rum, guns, and powder, and that some of my companions 
were gone with them, and that some were gone to the fields to do
something or other. This gave me strong suspicion that there
was some treachery in the case, and I began to think that my
hopes of returning home
<pb id="fish123" n="123"/>
again were all over. I soon became very uneasy, not knowing
what to do, and refused to eat or drink, for whole days
together, till the man of the house told me that he would do all
in his power to get me back to my uncle; then I eat a little
fruit with him, and had some thoughts that I should be sought
after, as I would be then missing at home about five or six
days. I inquired every day if the men had come back, and for
the rest of my companions, but could get no answer of any
satisfaction. I was kept about six days at this man's house,
and in the evening there was another man came, and talked
with him a good while and I heard the one say to the other he
must go, and the other said, the sooner the better; that man
came out and told me that he knew my relations at Agimaque,
and that we must set out to-morrow morning, and he would
convey me there. Accordingly we set out next day, and
travelled till dark, when we came to a place where we had
some supper and slept. He carried a large bag, with some gold
dust, which he said he had to buy some goods at the sea-side
to take with him to Agimaque. Next day we travelled on, and
in the evening came to a town, where I saw several white
people, which made me afraid that they would eat me,
according to our notion, as children, in the inland parts of the
country. This made me rest very uneasy all the night, and
next morning I had some victuals brought, desiring me to eat
and make haste, as my guide and kidnapper told me that he
had to go to the castle with some company that were going
there, as he had told me before, to get some goods. After I
was ordered out, the horrors I soon saw and felt, cannot be
well described; I saw many of my miserable countrymen
chained two and two, some handcuffed, and some with their
hands tied behind. We were conducted along by a guard, and
when we arrived at the castle, I asked my
<pb id="fish124" n="124"/>
guide what I was brought there for, he told me to learn the
ways of the <hi>browfow</hi>, that is, the white-faced people. I saw
him take a gun, a piece of cloth, and some lead for me, and then
he told me that he must now leave me there, and went off. This
made me cry bitterly, but I was soon conducted to a prison, for
three days, where I heard the groans and cries of many, and saw
some of my fellow-captives. But when a vessel arrived to
conduct us away to the ship, it was a most horrible scene; there
was nothing to be heard but the rattling of chains, smacking of
whips, and the groans and cries of our fellow-men. Some would
not stir from the ground, when they were lashed and beat in the
most horrible manner. I have forgot the name of this infernal
fort; but we were taken in the ship that came for us, to another
that was ready to sail from Cape Coast. When we were put into
the ship, we saw several black merchants coming on board, but
we were all drove into our holes, and not suffered to speak to
any of them. In this situation we continued several days in
sight of our native land; but I could find no good person to give
any information of my situation to Accasa at Agimaque. And
when we found ourselves at last taken away, death was more
preferable than life; and a plan was concerted amongst us, that
we might burn and blow up the ship, and to perish all together
in the flames: but we were betrayed by one of our own
countrywomen, who slept with some of the headmen of the
ship, for it was common for the dirty filthy sailors to take the
African women and lie upon their bodies; but the men were
chained and pent up in holes. It was the women and boys which
were to burn the ship, with the approbation and groans of the
rest; though that was prevented, the discovery was likewise a
cruel bloody scene.</p>
        <p>But it would be needless to give a description of all the
<pb id="fish125" n="125"/>
horrible scenes which we saw, and the base treatment
which we met with in this dreadful captive situation, as
the similar cases of thousands, which suffer by this infernal
traffic, are well known. Let it suffice to say that I was
thus lost to my dear indulgent parents and relations, and
they to me. All my help was cries and tears, and these
could not avail, nor suffered long, till one succeeding woe
and dread swelled up another. Brought from a state of
innocence and freedom, and, in a barbarous and cruel 
manner, conveyed to a state of horror and slavery, this 
abandoned situation may be easier conceived than described.
From the time that I was kidnapped, and conducted to a
factory, and from thence in the brutish, base, but fashionable 
way of traffic, consigned to Grenada, the grievous
thoughts which I then felt, still pant in my heart; though
my fears and tears have long since subsided. And yet it
is still grievous to think that thousands more have suffered
in similar and greater distress, Under the hands of 
barbarous robbers, and merciless task-masters; and that many,
even now, are suffering in all the extreme bitterness of
grief and woe, that no language can describe. The cries
of some, and the sight of their misery, may be seen and
heard afar; but the deep-sounding groans of thousands,
and the great sadness of their misery and woe, under the
heavy load of oppressions and calamities inflicted upon
them, are such as can only be distinctly known to the ears
of Jehovah Sabaoth.</p>
        <p>This Lord of Hosts, in his great providence, and in great
mercy to me, made a way for my deliverance from Grenada.
Being in this dreadful captivity and horrible slavery, without
any hope of deliverance, for about eight or nine months,
beholding the most dreadful scenes of misery and cruelty, and
seeing my miserable companions often cruelly lashed, and, 
as it were, cut to pieces, for the most trifling
<pb id="fish126" n="126"/>
faults; this made me often tremble and weep, but I escaped
better than many of them. For eating a piece of sugar-cane,
some were cruelly lashed, or struck over the face, to knock their
teeth out. Some of the stouter ones, I suppose, often reproved,
and grown hardened and stupid with many cruel beatings and
lashings, or perhaps faint and pressed with hunger and hard
labour, were often committing trespasses of this kind, and
when detected, they met with exemplary punishment. Some
told me they had their teeth pulled out, to deter others, 
and to prevent them from eating any cane in future. Thus 
seeing my miserable companions and countrymen in this pitiful, 
distressed, and horrible situation, with all the brutish baseness
and barbarity attending it, could not but fill my little mind
horror and indignation. But I must own, to the shame of my own 
countrymen, that I was first kidnapped and betrayed by some
of my own complexion, who were the first cause of my exile,
and slavery; but if there were no buyers there would be no
sellers. So far as I can remember, some of the Africans in my
country keep slaves, which they take in war, or for debt; but
those which they keep are well fed, and good care taken of
them, and treated well; and as to their clothing, they differ
according to the custom of the country. But I may safely say,
that all the poverty and misery that any of the inhabitants of
Africa meet with among themselves, is far inferior to those 
inhospitable regions of misery which they meet with in the 
West-Indies, where their hard-hearted overseers have neither
Regard to the laws of God, nor the life of their fellow-men.</p>
        <p>Thanks be to God, I was delivered from Grenada, and that
horrid brutal slavery. A gentleman coming to England took me
for his servant, and brought me away, where I soon found my
situation become more agreeable.  After coming to England,
and seeing others write and read, I
<pb id="fish127" n="127"/>
had a strong desire to learn, and getting what assistance I
could, I applied myself to learn reading and writing, which
soon became my recreation, pleasure, and delight; and when
my master perceived that I could write some, he sent me to a
proper school for that purpose to learn. Since, I have
endeavoured to improve my mind in reading, and have sought
to get all the intelligence I could, in my situation of life,
towards the state of my brethren and countrymen in
complexion, and of the miserable situation of those who are
barbarously sold into captivity, and unlawfully held in
slavery</p>
      </div1>
      <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      <trailer>PRINTED BY JAMES BULLOCK, WHITEFRIARS, FLEET-STREET.</trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>