<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % external-entities SYSTEM "./extEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY % internal-entities SYSTEM "./intEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY hughes165 SYSTEM "hughes165.gif" NDATA gif>
<!ENTITY hughes168 SYSTEM "hughes168.gif" NDATA gif>
<!ENTITY hughes190 SYSTEM "hughes190.gif" NDATA gif>
<!ENTITY hughescv SYSTEM "hughescv.gif" NDATA gif>
<!ENTITY hughesfp SYSTEM "hughesport.gif" NDATA gif>
<!ENTITY hughes25 SYSTEM "hughes25.gif" NDATA gif>
<!ENTITY hughes59 SYSTEM "hughes59.gif" NDATA gif>
<!ENTITY hughes108 SYSTEM "hughes108.gif" NDATA gif>
<!ENTITY hughestp SYSTEM "hughestp.gif" NDATA gif>
<!ENTITY hughes111 SYSTEM "hughes111.gif" NDATA gif>
<!ENTITY hughes136 SYSTEM "hughes136.gif" NDATA gif>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Thirty Years a Slave. From Bondage to Freedom. The Institution       
           of Slavery as Seen on the Plantation and in the Home of the Planter:
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Hughes, Louis, b. 1832</author>
        <funder>Funding from the Library of Congress/Ameritech National Digital
Library Competition  supported the electronic publication of this
title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Claire LaForce</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by</resp>
          <name id="ns">Teresa Church and Natalia
Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition,
<date>1997.</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca. 400K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill,</pubPlace>
        <date>1997.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of
North
Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note anchored="yes">Call number E444 .H89 1897 (Davis Library,
UNC-CH)</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>Thirty Years a Slave. From Bondage to Freedom. The Institution       
           of Slavery as Seen on the Plantation and in the Home of the
Planter</title>
          <author>Louis Hughes, b. 1832</author>
          <imprint>
            <pubPlace>Milwaukee:</pubPlace>
            <publisher>South Side Printing
Company</publisher>
            <date>1897</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the
UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American
South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been removed,
and the trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using
Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell checkers.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl>
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings,</title>
            <edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Hughes, Louis, b. 1832.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- United States -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- United States -- Social conditions.</item>
            <item>Freedmen -- United States -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Freedmen -- United States -- Social conditions.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- United States.</item>
            <item>Plantation life -- United States -- History -- 19th
century.</item>
            <item>Slaves' writings, American.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>1997-08-19, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith,</name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished
TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1997-08-02, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Teresa Church</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1997-05-20, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Claire LaForce </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="cover image">
        <p>
          <figure id="cover" entity="hughescv">
            <p>[Cover Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="frontispiece image">
        <p>
          <figure id="frontis" entity="hughesfp">
            <p>[Frontispiece Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="title image">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="hughestp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">
            <emph rend="bold">THIRTY YEARS A SLAVE</emph>
          </titlePart>
          <titlePart type="subtitle">From Bondage to Freedom</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="subtitle">THE INSTITUTION OF SLAVERY
    AS SEEN ON THE PLANTATION AND
    IN THE HOME OF THE PLANTER</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <docAuthor>AUTOBIOGRAPHY OF LOUIS HUGHES</docAuthor>
        <docImprint><pubPlace>MILWAUKEE:</pubPlace>
    <publisher>SOUTH SIDE PRINTING COMPANY</publisher>
    <docDate>1897</docDate></docImprint>
        <titlePart type="verso"> COPYRIGHT,
    1896.</titlePart>
      </titlePage>
      <pb id="hughes3" n="3"/>
      <div1 type="preface">
        <head>PREFACE.</head>
        <p>The institution of human slavery, as it existed in 
this country, has long been dead; and, happily for all 
the sacred interests which it assailed, there is for it 
no resurrection. It may, therefore, be asked to what 
purpose is the story which follows, of the experiences 
of one person under that dead and accursed institution? 
To such question, if it be asked, it may be answered 
that the narrator presents his story in compliance 
with the suggestion of friends, and in the hope that 
it may add something of accurate information regarding 
the character and influence of an institution 
which for two hundred years dominated the country  -   
exercising a potent but baneful influence in the 
formation of its social, civil and industrial structures, 
and which finally plunged it into the most stupendous 
civil war which the world has ever known. As the 
enlightenment of each generation depends upon the 
thoughtful study of the history of those that have 
gone before, everything which tends to fullness and 
accuracy in that history is of value, even though it be 
not presented with the adjuncts of literary adornment, 
or thrilling scenic effects.</p>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <pb id="hughes5" n="5"/>
    <body>
      <div1 type="chapter">
        <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
        <head>LIFE ON A COTTON PLANTATION.</head>
        <div2 type="subchapter">
          <head>BIRTH  -  SOLD IN A RICHMOND SLAVE PEN.</head>
          <p>I was born in Virginia, in 1832, near Charlottesville, 
in the beautiful valley of the Rivanna river. 
My father was a white man and my mother a negress, 
the slave of one John Martin. I was a mere child, 
probably not more than six years of age, as I remember, 
when my mother, two brothers and myself were 
sold to Dr. Louis, a practicing physician in the village 
of Scottsville. We remained with him about five 
years, when he died, and, in the settlement of his 
estate, I was sold to one Washington Fitzpatrick, a 
merchant of the village. He kept me a short time 
when he took me to Richmond, by way of canal-boat, 
expecting to sell me; but as the market was dull, he 
brought me back and kept me some three months 
longer, when he told me he had hired me out to work 
on a canal-boat running to Richmond, and to go to 
my mother and get my clothes ready to start on the 
trip. I went to her as directed, and, when she had
   <pb id="hughes6" n="6"/>
made ready my bundle, she bade me good-by wit 
tears in her eyes, saying: “My son, be a good boy; 
be polite to every one, and always behave yourself 
properly.” It was sad to her to part with me, though 
she did not know that she was never to see me again, 
for my master had said nothing to her regarding his 
purpose and she only thought, as I did, that I was 
hired to work on the canal-boat, and that she should 
see me occasionally. But alas! We never met again. 
I can see her form still as when she bade me good-bye. 
That parting I can never forget. I ran off from her 
as quickly as I could after her parting words, for I did 
not want her to see me crying. I went to my master 
at the store, and he again told me that he had hired 
me to work on the canal-boat, and to go aboard immediately. 
Of the boat and the trip and the scenes 
along the route I remember little  -  I only thought of 
my mother and my leaving her.</p>
          <p>When we arrived at Richmond, George Pullan, a 
“nigger-trader,” as he was called, came to the boat 
and began to question me, asking me first if I could 
remember having had the chickenpox, measles or 
whooping-cough. I answered, yes. Then he asked 
me if I did not want to take a little walk with him.
<pb id="hughes7" n="7"/>
I said, no. “Well,” said he, “you have got to go. 
Your master sent you down here to be sold, and told 
me to come and get you and take you to the trader's 
yard, ready to be sold.” I saw that to hesitate was 
useless; so I at once obeyed him and went.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>A SLAVE MARKET.</head>
          <p>The trader's establishment consisted of an office, a 
large show-room and a yard in the rear enclosed with 
a wall of brick fifteen feet high. The principal men 
of the establishment were the proprietor and the foreman. 
When slaves were to be exhibited for sale, the 
foreman was called to the office by means of a bell, 
and an order given him to bring into the show-room 
work of but a few minutes, and the women were 
placed in a row on one side of the room and the men 
on the other. Persons desirous of purchasing them 
passed up and down between the lines looking the 
poor creatures over, and questioning them in about 
the following manner: “What can you do?” “Are 
you a good cook? seamstress? dairymaid?”  -  this to 
the women, while the men would be questioned as to 
their line of work: “Can you plow? Are you a blacksmith? 
Have you ever cared for horses? Can 
<pb id="hughes8" n="8"/>
you pick cotton rapidly?” Sometimes the slave would 
be required to open his mouth that the purchaser 
might examine the teeth and form some opinion as to 
his age and physical soundness; and if it was suspected 
that a slave had been beaten a good deal he 
would be required to step into another room and undress. 
If the person desiring to buy found the slave 
badly scarred by the common usage of whipping, he 
would say at once to the foreman: “Why! this slave 
is not worth much, he is all scarred up. No, I don't 
want him; bring me in another to look at.” Slaves 
without scars from whipping and looking well physisally 
always sold readily. They were never left long 
in the yard. It was expected that all the slaves in the 
yard for sale would be neatly dressed and clean before 
being brought into the show-room. It was the foreman's 
business to see that each one was presentable.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>SLAVE WHIPPING AS A BUSINESS.</head>
          <p>Whipping was done at these markets, or trader's 
yards, all the time. People who lived in the city of 
Richmond would send their slaves here for punishment. 
When any one wanted a slave whipped he 
would send a note to that effect with the servant to 
the trader. Any petty offense on the part of a slave 
<pb id="hughes9" n="9"/>
was sufficient to subject the offender to this brutal 
treatment. Owners who affected culture and refinement 
preferred to send a servant to the yard for 
punishment to inflicting it themselves.  It saved them 
trouble, they said, and possibly a slight wear and tear 
of feeling. For this service the owner was charged a 
certain sum for each slave, and the earnings of the 
traders from this source formed a very large part of 
the profits of his business. The yard I was in had a 
regular whipping post to which they tied the slave, 
and gave him “nine-and-thirty,” as it was called, 
meaning thirty-nine lashes as hard as they could lay 
it on. Men were stripped of their shirts in preparation 
for the whipping, and women had to take off 
their dresses from the shoulders to the waist. These 
whippings were not so severe as when the slaves were 
stripped entirely of their clothes, as was generally the 
case on the plantations where slaves were owned by 
the dozen. I saw many cases of whipping while I 
was in the yard. Sometimes I was so frightened that 
I trembled violently, for I had never seen anything 
like it before.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>SOLD IN THE MARKET.</head>
          <p>I was only in the yard a short time before I was
    <pb id="hughes10" n="10"/>
bought by one George Reid who lived in Richmond. 
He had no wife, but an old lady kept house for him 
and his three sons. At this time he had a place in the 
postoffice, but soon after I came there he lost it.   He 
then moved into the country upon a farm of about one 
thousand acres, enclosed by a cedar hedge. The house 
was a plain frame structure upon a stone basement 
and contained four rooms. It was surrounded with 
shrubbery, and was a pleasant country seat. But I 
did not like it here. I grieved continually about my 
mother. It came to me, more and more plainly, that 
I would never see her again. Young and lonely as I 
was, I could not help crying, oftentimes for hours 
together. It was hard to get used to being away from 
my mother. I remember well “Aunt Sylvia,” who 
was the cook in the Reid household. She was very 
kind to me and always spoke consolingly to me, 
especially if I had been blue, and had had one of 
my fits of crying. At these times she would always 
bake me an ash cake for supper, saying to me: “My 
child, don't cry; ‘Aunt Sylvia’ will look after you.” This 
ash cake was made of corn meal and water, a 
little salt to make it palatable, and was baked by putting 
it between cabbage leaves and covering it with
<pb id="hughes11" n="11"/>
hot ashes. A sweeter or more delicious cake one could 
not desire, and it was common upon the tables of all 
the Virginia farmers. I always considered it a great 
treat to get one of these cakes from “Aunt Sylvia.”</p>
          <p>The appellations of “aunt” and “uncle” for the 
older slaves were not only common among the blacks, 
but the whites also addressed them in the same way.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>ON THE AUCTION BLOCK</head>
          <p> I was sick a great deal  -  in fact, I had suffered with 
chills and fever ever since Mr. Reid bought me. He, 
therefore, concluded to sell me, and, in November, 
1844, he took me back to Richmond, placing me in the 
Exchange building, or auction rooms, for the sale of 
slaves. The sales were carried on in a large hall 
where those interested in the business sat around a 
large block or stand, upon which the slave to be sold 
was placed, the auctioneer standing beside him. 
When I was placed upon the block, a Mr. McGee came 
up and felt of me and asked me what I could do. 
“You look like a right smart nigger,” said he, “Virginia 
always produces good darkies.” Virginia was 
the mother of slavery, and it was held by many that 
she had the best slaves. So when Mr. McGee found 
I was born and bred in that state he seemed satisfied. 
<pb id="hughes12" n="12"/>
The bidding commenced, and I remember well when 
the auctioneer said: “Three hundred eighty dollars  
-  once, twice and sold to Mr. Edward McGee.”  He 
was a rich cotton planter of Pontotoc, Miss. As near 
as I can recollect, I was not more than twelve years of 
age, so did not sell for very much.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>PRICE OF SLAVES.</head>
          <p> Servant women sold for $500 to $700, and sometimes 
as high as $800 when possessing extra qualifications. 
A house maid, bright in looks, strong and 
well formed, would sell for $1,000 to $1,200. Bright 
mulatto girls, well versed in sewing and knitting, 
would sometimes bring as high as $1,800, especially 
if a Virginian or a Kentuckian. Good blacksmiths 
sold for $1, 600 to $1, 800. When the slaves were put 
upon the block they were always sold to the highest 
bidder. Mr. McGee, or “Boss,” as I soon learned to 
call him, bought sixty other slaves before he bought 
me, and they were started in a herd for Atlanta, Ga., 
on foot.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>STARTED FOR A COTTON PLANTATION.</head>
          <p> Boss, myself and ten others met them there. We 
then started for Pontotoc, Miss. On our way we 
stopped at Edenton, Ga., where Boss sold twenty-one
<pb id="hughes13" n="13"/>
of the sixty slaves. We then proceeded on our way, 
Boss by rail and we on foot, or in the wagon. We 
went about twenty miles a day. I remember, as we 
passed along, every white man we met was yelling, 
“Hurrah for Polk and Dallas!” They were feeling 
good, for election had given them the men that they 
wanted. The man who had us in charge joined with 
those we met in the hurrahing. We were afraid to 
ask them the reason for their yelling, as that would 
have been regarded as an impertinence, and probably 
would have caused us all to be whipped.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>MY MISSISSIPPI HOME.</head>
          <p>At length, after a long and wearisome journey, we 
reached Pontotoc, McGee's home, on Christmas eve. 
Boss took me into the house and into the sitting room, 
where all the family were assembled, and presented 
me as a Christmas gift to the madam, his wife. </p>
          <p>My boss, as I remember him, was a tall, rawboned 
man, but rather distinguished in looks, with a 
fine carriage, brilliant in intellect, and considered 
one of the wealthiest and most successful planters of 
his time. Mrs. McGee was a handsome, stately lady, 
about thirty years of age, brunette in complexion, 
faultless in figure and imperious in manner. I think
<pb id="hughes14" n="14"/>
that they were of Scotch descent. There were four 
children, Emma, Willie, Johnnie and Jimmie. All  
looked at me, and thought I was “a spry little fellow.” 
I was very shy and did not say much, as everything 
was strange to me. I was put to sleep that night on 
a pallet on the floor in the dining room, using an old 
quilt as a covering. The next morning was Christmas, 
and it seemed to be a custom to have egg-nog 
before breakfast. The process of making this was 
new and interesting to me. I saw them whip the 
whites of eggs, on a platter, to a stiff froth; the yolks 
were thoroughly beaten in a large bowl, sugar and 
plenty of good brandy were added, and the whites of 
the eggs and cream were then stirred in, a little nutmeg 
grated on top of each glass when filled for serving.  
This was a delicious drink, and the best of all 
was, there was plenty of it. I served this to all the 
family, and, as there were also visiting relatives 
present, many glasses were required, and I found the 
tray so heavy I could hardly carry it. I helped myself, 
after the service was finished, and I was delighted, 
for I had never tasted anything so fine before.</p>
          <p>My boss told me I was to wait on the madam, do any 
errand necessary, attend to the dining room  -  in
<pb id="hughes15" n="15"/>
fact I was installed as general utility boy. It was 
different from the quiet manner of life I had seen before 
coming here  -  it kept my spirits up for some time. 
I thought of my mother often, but I was gradually 
growing to the idea that it was useless to cry, and I 
tried hard to overcome my feelings.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head> PLANTATION LIFE.</head>
          <p>As already stated, it was Christmas morning, and, 
after breakfast, I saw the cook hurrying, and when I 
went out into the yard, everywhere I looked slaves 
met my view. I never saw so many slaves at one 
time before. In Virginia we did not have such large 
farms. There were no extensive cotton plantations, 
as in Mississippi. I shall never forget the dinner 
that day  -  it was a feast fit for a king, so varied and 
lavish was the bill of fare. The next attraction for 
me was the farm hands getting their Christmas rations. 
Each was given a pint of flour of which they 
made biscuit, which were called “Billy Seldom,” 
because biscuit were very rare with them. Their 
daily food was corn bread, which they called “Johnny 
Constant,” as they had it constantly. In addition to 
the flour each received a piece of bacon or fat meat, 
from which they got the shortening for their biscuit. 
<pb id="hughes16" n="16"/>
The cracklings from the rendering of lard were also 
used by the slaves for shortening. The hands were 
allowed four days off at Christmas, and if they worked 
on these days, as some of them did, they got fifty 
cents a day for chopping. It was not common to have 
chopping done during the holidays; some planters, 
however, found it convenient thus to get it out of the 
way for the work which came after Christmas.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>THE GREAT HOUSE.</head>
          <p>I soon became familiar with my work in the house 
and with the neighborhood, as I often had to carry 
notes for Boss to neighboring farmers, as well as to 
carry the mail to and from the postoffice. The “great 
house,” as the dwelling of the master was called, was 
two stories high, built of huge logs, chinked and 
daubed and whitewashed. It was divided, from front 
to rear, by a hall twenty-five feet long and twelve 
feet wide, and on each side of the hall, in each story, 
was one large room with a large fire-place. There 
were but four rooms in all, yet these were so large 
that they were equal to at least six of our modern 
rooms. The kitchen was not attached to the main 
building, but was about thirty feet to the rear. This 
was the common mode of building in the south in
<pb id="hughes17" n="17"/>
those days. The two bedrooms upstairs were very 
plain in furnishings, but neat and comfortable, judged 
by the standard of the times. A wing was added to 
the main building for dining room. In rear of the 
kitchen was the milk or dairy house, and beyond this 
the smoke house for curing the meat. In line with 
these buildings, and still further to the rear, was the 
overseer's house. Near the milk house was a large 
tree, and attached to the trunk was a lever; and here 
was where the churning was done, in which I had 
always to assist. This establishment will serve as a 
sample of many of those on the large plantations in 
the south. The main road from Pontotoc to Holly 
Springs, one of the great thoroughfares of the state 
and a stage route, passed near the house, and through 
the center of the farm. On each side of this road was 
a fence, and in the corners of both fences, extending 
for a mile, were planted peach trees, which bore excellent 
fruit in great profusion.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>HOUSE SERVANT AND ERRAND BOY.</head>
          <p>My first work in the morning was to dust the parlor 
and hall and arrange the dining room. It came 
awkward to me at first, but, after the madam told me 
how, I soon learned to do it satisfactorily. Then I
<pb id="hughes18" n="18"/>
had to wait on the table; sweep the large yard every 
morning with a brush broom and go for the mail once 
a week. I used to get very tired, for I was young 
and consequently not strong. Aside from these 
things which came regularly, I had to help the 
madam in warping the cloth. I dreaded this work, 
for I always got my ears boxed if I did not or could 
not do the work to suit her. She always made the 
warp herself and put it in, and I had to hand her the 
thread as she put it through the harness. I would 
get very tired at this work and, like any child, wanted 
to be at play, but I could not remember that the 
madam ever gave me that privilege. Saddling the 
horse at first was troublesome to me, but Boss was 
constant in his efforts to teach me, and, after many 
trials, I learned the task satisfactorily to the master 
and to bring the horse to the door when he wished to 
go out for business or pleasure. Riding horseback was 
common for both ladies and gentlemen, and sometimes 
I would have to saddle three or more horses 
when Boss, the madam, a friend or friends desired a 
ride. Bird hunting parties were common and were 
greatly enjoyed, by the young people especially. Boss 
always invited some of the young people of the 
<pb id="hughes19" n="19"/>
neighborhood to these parties and they never failed to 
put in an appearance. Williams, Bradford and Freeman 
were the sons of rich planters, and were always 
participants in this sport, and their young lady friends 
joined in it as on-lookers. The young men singing and 
whistling to the birds, I in the meantime setting the 
net. As soon as I had got the net in order they would 
approach the birds slowly, driving them into it. 
There was great laughter and excitement if they were 
successful in catching a fine flock.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>CRUEL TREATMENT.</head>
          <p>I was but a lad, yet I can remember well the cruel 
treatment I received. Some weeks it seemed I was 
whipped for nothing, just to please my mistress' 
fancy. Once, when I was sent to town for the mail 
and had started back, it was so dark and rainy my 
horse got away from me and I had to stay all night in 
town. The next morning when I got back home I 
had a severe whipping, because the master was expecting 
a letter containing money and was disappointed 
in not receiving it that night, as he was going 
to Panola to spend Christmas. However, the day 
came and all the family went except me. During the 
time they were gone the overseer whipped a man so 
<pb id="huhhes20" n="20"/>
terribly with the “bull whip” that I had to go for 
the doctor, and when Dr. Heningford, the regular 
family physician, came, he said it was awful  -  such 
cruel treatment, and he complained about it. It was 
common for a slave to get an “over-threshing,” that 
is, to be whipped too much. The poor man was cut 
up so badly all over that the doctor made a bran poultice 
and wrapped his entire body in it. This was done 
to draw out the inflammation. It seems the slave 
had been sick, and had killed a little pig when he became 
well enough to go to work, as his appetite 
craved hearty food, and he needed it to give him 
strength for his tasks. For this one act, comparatively 
trivial, he was almost killed. The idea never seemed 
to occur to the slave holders that these slaves were 
getting no wages for their work and, therefore, had 
nothing with which to procure what, at times, was 
necessary for their health and strength  -  palatable 
and nourishing food. When the slaves took anything 
the masters called it stealing, yet they were stealing 
the slaves' time year after year. When Boss came 
home he was called on by the town officials, for the 
case had been reported to them. Boss, however, got 
out of it by saying that he was not at home when the
<pb id="hughes21" n="21"/>
trouble occurred. The poor slave was sick from his 
ill treatment some four or five months, and when he 
recovered there was a running sore left on his body, 
from the deep cuts of the whip, which never healed. 
I can not forget how he looked, the sore was a sickening 
sight; yet, when he was able to walk he had to 
return to work in the field.</p>
          <p>I had not been at Pontotoc very long when I saw 
the hounds run a slave, by name Ben Lyon. “Old 
Ben,” as he was called, ran away and had been gone 
a week when he was seen by a woman who “told on 
him,” and then I was sent to get the man who had 
trained dogs, or hounds as they were called. The 
dogs ran the slave about ten miles when they lost 
track at a creek, but he was caught that night in a 
farmer's house getting something to eat.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>INSTRUCTIONS IN MEDICINE.</head>
          <p>After some time, Boss began to tell me the names 
of medicines and their properties. I liked this and 
seemed to grasp the idea very well. After giving me 
a number of names he would make me repeat them. 
Then he would tell me the properties of each medicine 
named, how it was used and for what purpose 
and how much constituted a dose. He would drill me 
<pb id="hughes22" n="22"/>
in all this until I knew it and, in a short time, he 
would add other names to the list. He always showed 
me each medicine named and had me smell and carefully 
examine it that I might know it when seen 
again. I liked this, and used to wish that I was as 
wise as my master. He was very precise, steady and 
gentle in any case of sickness, and, although he had 
long retired from the medical world, all recognized 
his merit wherever he went. I used to go to the 
woods and gather slippery elm, alum root and the 
roots of wild cherry and poplar, for we used all these 
in compounding medicines for the servants.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>THE OVERSEER  -  WHIPPINGS AND OTHER CRUELTIES.</head>
          <p>The overseer was a man hired to look after the 
farm and whip the slaves. Very often they were not 
only cruel, but barbarous. Every farmer or planter 
considered an overseer a necessity. As a rule, there 
was also on each plantation, a foreman  -  one of the 
brighter slaves, who was held responsible for the 
slaves under him, and whipped if they did not come 
up to the required task. There was, too, a forewoman, 
who, in like manner, had charge of the female slaves, 
and also the boys and girls from twelve to sixteen 
years of age, and all the old people that were feeble. 
<pb id="hughes23" n="23"/>
This was called the trash gang. Ah! it would make 
one's heart ache to see those children and how they 
were worked. Cold, frosty mornings, the little ones 
would be crying from cold; but they had to keep on. 
Aunt Polly, our forewoman, was afraid to allow them 
to run to get warm, for fear the overseer would see 
them. Then she would be whipped, and he would 
make her whip all of the gang. At length, I became 
used to severe treatment of the slaves; but, every 
little while something would happen to make me 
wish I were dead. Everything was in a bustle  -  always 
there was slashing and whipping. I remember when 
Boss made a change in our overseer. It was the beginning 
of the year. Riley, one of the slaves, who 
was a principal plower, was not on hand for work one 
Monday morning, having been delayed in fixing the 
bridle of his mule, which the animal, for lack of 
something better, perhaps, had been vigorously chewing 
and rendered nearly useless. He was, therefore, 
considerably behind time, when he reached the field. 
Without waiting to learn what was the reason for the 
delay, the overseer sprang upon him with his bull 
whip, which was about seven feet long, lashing him 
with all his strength, every stroke leaving its mark 
<pb id="hughes24" n="24"/>
upon the poor man's body, and finally the knot at the 
end of the whip buried itself in the fleshy part of the 
arm, and there came around it a festering sore. He 
suffered greatly with it, until one night his brother 
took out the knot, when the poor fellow was asleep, 
for he could not bear any one to touch it when he was 
awake. It was awful to hear the cracking of that 
whip as it was laid about Riley  -  one would have 
thought that an ox team had gotten into the mire, 
and was being whipped out, so loud and sharp was
the noise!</p>
          <p>I usually slept in the dining room on the floor. 
Early one morning an old slave, by name of “Uncle 
Jim,” came and knocked at the window, and upon my 
 jumping up and going to him, he told me to tell Boss 
that Uncle Jim was there. He had run away, some 
time before, and, for some reason, had returned. Boss, 
upon hearing the news, got up and sent me to tell the 
overseer to come at once. He came, and, taking the 
bull whip, a cowhide and a lot of peach-tree switches, 
he and Boss led Uncle Jim back into the cow lot, on 
the side of the hill, where they drove four stakes in 
the ground, and, laying him flat on his face, tied 
his hands and feet to these stakes. After whipping him, 
<pb id="hughes24a" n="24a"/>
<figure id="ill1" entity="hughes25"><p>[Image of Confederate Currency]</p></figure>
<pb id="hughes25" n="25"/>
in this position, all they wanted to, a pail of strong 
salt and water was brought, and the poor fellow was 
“washed down.” This washing was customary, after 
whippings, as the planters claimed it drew out all the 
soreness, and healed the lacerated flesh. </p>
          <p>Upon one occasion, the family being away, I was 
left extra work to do, being set to help three fellow 
slaves lay off the rows for planting corn. We did not 
get them quite straight. The deviation we made 
from the line was very little, and could scarcely be 
seen, even by an expert; but the least thing wrong 
about the work would cause any slave to be whipped, 
and so all four of us were flogged.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>THE SLAVE CABIN.</head>
          <p>There was a section of the plantation known as 
“the quarters,” where were situated the cabins of the 
slaves. These cabins were built of rough logs, and 
daubed with the red clay or mud of the region. No 
attempt was made to give them a neat appearance  -  
they were not even whitewashed. Each cabin was 
about fourteen feet square; containing but one room, 
and was covered with oak boards, three feet in length, 
split out of logs by hand. These boards were not 
nailed on, but held in their places by what were
<pb id="hughes26" n="26"/>
termed weight-poles laid across them at right angles. 
There were in each room two windows, a door and a 
large, rude fire-place. The door and window frames, 
or facings, were held in their places by wooden pins, 
nails being used only in putting the doors together. 
The interior of the cabins had nothing more attractive 
than the outside  -  there was no plastering and 
only a dirt floor. The furniture consisted of one bed, 
a plain board table and some benches made by the 
slaves themselves. Sometimes a cabin was occupied 
by two or more families, in which case the number of 
beds was increased proportionately. For light a 
grease lamp was used, which was made of iron, bowl 
shaped, by a blacksmith. The bowl was filled with 
grease and a rag or wick placed in it, one end resting 
on the edge for lighting. These lamps gave a good 
light, and were in general use among the slaves. 
Tallow candles were a luxury, never seen in 
the “great houses” of the planters. The only light 
for outdoors used by the slaves was a torch made by 
binding together a bundle of small sticks or splinters.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>COTTON RAISING.</head>
          <p>After the selection of the soil most suitable for 
cotton, the preparation of it was of vital importance. 
<pb id="hughes27" n="27"/>
The land was deeply plowed, long enough before the 
time for planting to allow the spring rains to settle it. 
Then it was thrown into beds or ridges by turning 
furrows both ways toward a given center. The seed 
was planted at the rate of one hundred pounds per 
acre. The plant made its appearance in about ten 
days after planting, if the weather was favorable. 
Early planting, however, followed by cold, stormy 
weather frequently caused the seed to rot. As soon 
as the third leaf appeared the process of scraping 
commenced, which consisted of cleaning the ridge 
with hoes of all superflous plants and all weeds and 
grass. After this a narrow plow known as a “bull 
tongue,” was used to turn the loose earth around the 
plant and cover up any grass not totally destroyed by 
the hoes. If the surface was very rough the hoes 
followed, instead of preceding, the plow to unearth 
those plants that may have been partially covered. 
The slaves often acquired great skill in these operations, 
running plows within two inches of the stalks, 
and striking down weeds within half an inch with 
their hoes, rarely touching a leaf of the cotton. 
Subsequent plowing, alternating with hoeing, 
usually occurred once in twenty days. There was 
<pb id="hughes28" n="28"/>
danger in deep plowing of injuring the roots, and this 
was avoided, except in the middle of rows in wet seasons 
when it was necessary to bury and more effectually 
kill the grass. The implements used in the culture of 
cotton were shovels, hoes, sweeps, cultivators, harrows 
and two kinds of plows. It required four 
months, under the most favorable circumstances, for 
cotton to attain its full growth. It was usually 
planted about the 1st of April, or from March 20th to 
April 10th, bloomed about the 1st of June and the 
first balls opened about August 15th, when picking 
commenced. The blooms come out in the morning 
and are fully developed by noon, when they are a pure 
white. Soon after meridian they begin to exhibit 
reddish streaks, and next morning are a clear pink. 
They fall off by noon of the second day.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>THE COTTON WORM.</head>
          <p>A cut worm was troublesome sometimes; but the 
plants were watched very carefully, and as soon as 
any signs of worms were seen work for their destruction 
was commenced. The majority of the eggs were 
laid upon the calyx and involucre. The worm, after 
gnawing through its enclosed shell, makes its first 
meal upon the part of the plant upon which the egg 
<pb id="hughes29" n="29"/>
was laid, be it leaf, stem or involucre. If it were laid 
upon the leaf, as was usually the case, it might be 
three days before the worm reached the boll; but were 
the eggs laid upon the involucre the worm pierced 
through within twenty-four hours after hatching. 
The newly hatched boll worm walks like a geometrical 
larva or looper, a measuring worm as it was called. 
This is easily explained by the fact that while in the 
full grown worm the abdominal legs, or pro legs, are 
nearly equal in length, in the newly hatched worm 
the second pair are slightly shorter than the third, 
and the first pair are shorter and slenderer than the 
second  -  a state of things approaching that in the full 
grown cotton worm, though the difference in size in 
the former case is not nearly so marked as in the latter. 
This method of walking is lost with the first or 
second molt. There is nothing remarkable about 
these young larvae. They seem to be thicker in proportion 
to their length than the young cotton worms, 
and they have not so delicate and transparent an appearance. 
Their heads are black and their bodies 
seem already to have begun to vary in color. The 
body above is furnished with sparse, stiff hairs, each 
arising from a tubercle. I have often watched the 
<pb id="hughes30" n="30"/>
newly hatched boll while in the cotton fields. When 
hatched from an egg which had been deposited upon 
a leaf, they invariably made their first meal on the 
substance of the leaf, and then wandered about for 
a longer or shorter space of time, evidently seeking a 
boll or flower bud. It was always interesting to 
watch this seemingly aimless search of the young 
worm, crawling first down the leaf stem and then 
back, then dropping a few inches by a silken thread 
and then painfully working its way back again, until, 
at last, it found the object of its search, or fell to the 
ground where it was destroyed by ants. As the boll 
worms increase in size a most wonderful diversity of 
color and marking becomes apparent. In color different
worms will vary from a brilliant green to a deep 
pink or dark brown, exhibiting almost every conceivable 
intermediate stage from an immaculate, unstriped 
specimen to one with regular spots and many stripes. 
The green worms were more common than those of 
any other color  -  a common variety was a very light 
green. When these worms put in an appearance it 
raised a great excitement among the planters. We 
did not use any poison to destroy them, as I learn is 
the method now employed. </p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="hughes31" n="31"/>
        <div2>
          <head>THE COTTON HARVEST.</head>
          <p>The cotton harvest, or picking season, began 
about the latter part of August or first of September, 
and lasted till Christmas or after, but in the latter 
part of July picking commenced for “the first bale” 
to go into the market at Memphis. This picking was 
done by children from nine to twelve years of age and 
by women who were known as “sucklers,” that is, 
women with infants. The pickers would pass through 
the rows getting very little, as the cotton was not yet 
in full bloom. From the lower part of the stalk 
where it opened first is where they got the first pickings. 
The season of first picking was always a great 
time, for the planter who brought the first bale of 
cotton into market at Memphis was presented with a 
basket of champagne by the commission merchants. 
This was a custom established throughout Mississippi. 
After the first pickings were secured the cotton developed 
very fast, continuing to bud and bloom all over 
the stalk until the frost falls. The season of picking 
was exciting to all planters, every one was zealous in 
pushing his slaves in order that he might reap the 
greatest possible harvest. The planters talked about 
their prospects, discussed the cotton markets, just as 
 <pb id="hughes32" n="32"/>
the farmers of the north discuss the markets for their 
products. I often saw Boss so excited and nervous 
during the season he scarcely ate. The daily task of 
each able-bodied slave during the cotton picking 
season war 250 pounds or more, and all those who did 
not come up to the required amount would get a 
whipping. When the planter wanted more cotton 
picked than usual, the overseer would arrange a race. 
The slaves would be divided into two parties, with a 
leader for each party. The first leader would choose a 
slave for his side, then the second leader one for his, 
and so on alternately until all were chosen. Each 
leader tried to get the best on his side. They would 
all work like good fellows for the prize, which was a 
tin cup of sugar for each slave on the winning side. 
The contest was kept up for three days whenever the 
planter desired an extra amount picked. The slaves 
were just as interested in the races as if they were 
going to get a five dollar bill.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>PREPARING COTTON FOR MARKET.</head>
          <p>The gin-house was situated about four hundred 
yards from “the great house” on the main road. It 
was a large shed built upon square timbers, and was  
similar to a barn, only it stood some six feet from the  
<pb id="hughes33" n="33"/>
ground, and underneath was located the machinery 
for running the gin. The cotton was put into the 
loft after it was dried, ready for ginning. In this 
process the cotton was dropped from the loft to the 
man who fed the machine. As it was ginned the lint 
would go into the lint room, and the seed would drop 
at the feeder's feet. The baskets used for holding 
lint were twice as large as those used in the picking 
process, and they were never taken from the gin house. 
These lint baskets were used in removing the lint 
from the lint room to the place where the cotton was 
baled. A bale contained 250 pounds, and the man 
who did the treading of the cotton into the bales 
would not vary ten pounds in the bale, so accustomed 
was he to the packing. Generally from fourteen to fifteen 
bales of cotton were in the lint room at a time.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>OTHER FARM PRODUCTS.</head>
          <p>Cotton was the chief product of the Mississippi 
farms and nothing else was raised to sell. Wheat, 
oats and rye were raised in limited quantities, but 
only for the slaves and the stock. All the fine flour 
for the master's family was bought in St. Louis. 
Corn was raised in abundance, as it was a staple 
article of food for the slaves. It was planted about 
<pb id="hughes34" n="34"/>
the 1st of March, or about a month earlier than the 
cotton. It was, therefore, up and partially worked 
before the cotton was planted and fully tilled before 
the cotton was ready for cultivation. Peas were 
planted between the rows of corn, and hundreds of 
bushels were raised. These peas after being harvested, 
dried and beaten out of the shell, were of a reddish 
brown tint, not like those raised for the master's 
family, but they were considered a wholesome and 
nutritious food for the slaves. Cabbage and yams, a 
large sweet potato, coarser than the kind generally 
used by the whites and not so delicate in flavor, were 
also raised for the servants in liberal quantities. No 
hay was raised, but the leaves of the corn, stripped 
from the stalks while yet green, cured and bound in 
bundles, were used as a substitute for it in feeding 
horses.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>FARM IMPLEMENTS.</head>
          <p>Almost all the implements used on the plantation 
were made by the slaves. Very few things were 
bought. Boss had a skilled blacksmith, uncle Ben,
for whom he paid $1,800, and there were slaves who 
were carpenters and workers in wood who could turn
their hands to almost anything. Wagons, plows, 
<pb id="hughes35" n="35"/>
harrows, grubbing hoes, hames, collars, baskets, 
bridle bits and hoe handles were all made on the farm 
and from the material which it produced, except the 
iron. The timber used in these implements was 
generally white or red oak, and was cut and thoroughly 
seasoned long before it was nedeed. The articles 
thus manufactured were not fine in form or finish, but 
they were durable, and answered the purposes of a 
rude method of agriculture. Horse collars were made 
from corn husks and from poplar bark which was 
stripped from the tree, in the spring, when the sap was 
up and it was soft and pliable, and separated into narrow 
strips which were plaited together. These collars 
were easy for the horse, and served the purpose of 
the more costly leather collar. Every season at least 
200 cotton baskets were made. One man usually 
worked at this all the year round, but in the spring he 
had three assistants. The baskets were made from 
oak timber grown in the home forests and prepared 
by the slaves. It was no small part of the work of 
the blacksmith and his assistant to keep the farm implements 
in good repair, and much of this work was 
done at night. All the plank used was sawed by 
hand from timber grown on the master's land, as there 
<pb id="hughes36" n="36"/>
were no saw mills in that region. Almost the only 
things not made on the farm which were in general 
use there were axes, trace chains and the hoes used in 
cultivating the cotton.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>THE CLEARING OF NEW LAND.</head>
          <p>When additional land was required for cultivation  
the first step was to go into the forest in summer and 
“deaden” or girdle the trees on a given tract. This 
was cutting through the bark all around the trunk 
about thirty inches from the ground. The trees so 
treated soon died and in a year or two were in condition 
to be removed. The season selected for clearing 
the land was winter, beginning with January. The 
trees, except the larger ones, were cut down, cut into 
lengths convenient for handling and piled into 
great heaps, called “log heaps,” and burned. The undergrowth 
was grubbed out and also piled and burned. 
The burning was done at night and the sight was 
often weird and grand. The chopping was done by 
the men slaves and the grubbing by women. All the 
trees that blew down during the summer were left as 
they fell till winter when they were removed. This  
went on, year after year, until all the trees were  
cleared out. The first year after the new land was  
<pb id="hughes37" n="37"/>
cleared corn was put in, the next season cotton. As a 
rule corn and cotton were planted alternately, especially 
if the land was poor, if not, cotton would be continued 
year after year on the same land. Old corn 
stalks were always plowed under for the next year's 
crop and they served as an excellent fertilizer. Cotton 
was seldom planted on newly cleared land, as the 
roots and stumps rendered it difficult to cultivate the 
land without injury to the growing plant.</p>
          <p>I never saw women put to the hard work of grubbing 
until I went to McGee's and I greatly wondered 
at it. Such work was not done by women slaves in 
Virginia. Children were required to do some work, 
it mattered not how many grown people were working. 
There were always tasks set for the boys and girls 
ranging in age from nine to thirteen years, beyond 
these ages they worked with the older slaves. After 
I had been in Pontotoc two years I had to help plant 
and hoe, and work in the cotton during the seasons,  
and soon learned to do everything pertaining to the  
farm.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>COOKING FOR THE SLAVES.</head>
          <p>In summer time the cooking for the slaves was 
done out of doors. A large fire was built under a 
<pb id="hughes38" n="38"/>
tree, two wooden forks were driven into the ground on 
opposite sides of the fire, a pole laid on the forks and 
on this kettles were hung over the fire for the preparation 
of the food. Cabbage and meat, boiled, alternated 
with meat and peas, were the staple for summer. 
Bread was furnished with the meals and corn meal 
dumplings, that is, little balls made of meal and 
grease from the boiled bacon and dropped into boiling 
water, were also provided and considered quite palatable, 
especially if cooked in the water in which the 
bacon was boiled. In winter the cooking was done in 
a cabin, and sweet potatoes, dried peas and meat were 
the principal diet. This bill of fare was for dinner or 
the mid-day meal. For supper each slave received two 
pieces of meat and two slices of bread, but these 
slices were very large, as the loaves were about six 
inches thick and baked in an old fashioned oven. 
This bread was made from corn meal for, as I have 
said, only on holidays and special occasions did the 
slaves have white bread of any kind. Part of the 
meat and bread received at supper time was saved for 
the “ morning bite.” The slaves never had any 
breakfast, but went to the field at daylight and after  
working till the sun was well up, all would stop for
<pb id="hughes39" n="39"/>
their morning bite. Very often some young fellow 
ate his morning bite the evening before at supper and 
would have nothing for the morning, going without 
eating until noon. The stop for morning bite was 
very short; then all would plunge into work until 
mid-day, when all hands were summoned to their 
principal meal.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>CARDING AND SPINNING.</head>
          <p>Through the winter and on rainy days in summer, 
the women of the field had to card the wool and spin 
it into yarn. They generally worked in pairs, a spinning 
wheel and cards being assigned to each pair, and 
while one carded the wool into rolls, the other spun it 
into yarn suitable for weaving into cloth, or a coarse, 
heavy thread used in making bridles and lines for the 
mules that were used in the fields. This work was 
done in the cabins, and the women working together 
alternated in the carding and spinning. Four cuts 
were considered a task or day's work, and if any one 
failed to complete her task she received a whipping 
from the madam. At night when the spinners brought 
their work to the big house I would have it to reel. 
The reel was a contrivance consisting of a sort of 
wheel, turned on an axis, used to transfer the yarn 
<pb id="hughes40" n="40"/>
from the spools or spindles of the spinning wheels 
into cuts or hunks. It was turned by hand and when 
enough yarn had been reeled to make a cut the reel 
signaled it with a snap. This process was continued 
until four cuts were reeled which made a hunk, and 
this this taken off and was ready for use. So the 
work went on until all was reeled. I often got very 
weary of this work and would almost fall asleep at it, 
as it was generally done at night after I had had a 
long day's toil at something else.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>WEAVING  -  CLOTHES OF THE SLAVES.</head>
          <p>One woman did the weaving and it was her task to 
weave from nine to ten yards a day. Aunt Liza was 
our weaver and she was taught the work by the 
madam. At first she did not get on so well with it 
and many times I have seen the madam jump at her, 
pinch and choke her because she was dull in understanding 
how to do it. The madam made the unreasonable 
demand that she should do the full task at 
first, and because she failed she was punished, as was 
the custom in all cases of failure, no matter how unreasonable 
the demand. Liza finally became equal to 
her task and accomplished it each day. But the 
trouble and worry to me was when I had to assist the
<pb id="hughes41" n="41"/>
madam in warping  -  getting the work ready for the 
weaver. She would warp the thread herself and place 
it in the loom, then I would have to hand her the 
threads, as she put them through the hames. For 
any failure in quickly comprehending or doing my 
work, I did not fail to receive the customary blow, or 
blows, from her hand.</p>
          <p>Each piece of cloth contained forty yards, and this 
cloth was used in making clothes for the servants. 
About half of the whole amount required was thus 
made at home; the remainder was bought, and as it 
was heavier it was used for winter clothing. Each 
man was allowed for summer two pairs of pants and 
two shirts, but no coat. The women had two dresses 
and two chemises each for summer. For winter the 
men had each two pairs of pants, one coat, one 
hat and one pair of coarse shoes. These shoes before 
being worn had to be greased with tallow, with a 
little tar in it. It was always a happy time when the 
men got these winter goods  -  it brought many a smile 
to their faces, though the supply was meager and the 
articles of the cheapest. The women's dresses for 
winter were made of the heavier wool-cloth used for 
the men. They also had one pair of shoes each and 
<pb id="hughes42" n="42"/>
a turban. The women who could utilize old clothes, 
made for themselves what were called pantalets. 
They had no stockings or undergarments to protect 
their limbs  -  these were never given them. The 
pantalets were made like a pant-leg, came just above 
the knee, and were caught and tied. Sometimes they 
looked well and comfortable. The men's old pant-legs 
were sometimes used.</p>
          <p>I remember once when Boss went to Memphis and 
brought back a bolt of gingham for turbans for the 
female slaves. It was a red and yellow check, and the 
turbans made from it were only to be worn on Sunday. 
The old women were so glad that they sang and 
prayed. A little gift from the master was greatly appreciated 
by them. I always came in for my share 
each year, but my clothes were somewhat different. 
I wore pants made of Bosse's old ones, and all his old 
coats were utilized for me. They rounded them off at 
the tail just a little and called them jackets. My 
shoes were not brogans, but made of lighter leather, 
and made suitable for in the house. I only worked on 
the farm in busy seasons, and did not have the regular 
wear of the farm hands. On Monday morning it 
was a great sight to see all the hands marching to
<pb id="hughes43" n="43"/>
the field. The cotton clothes worn by both men and 
women, and the turbans of the latter, were snowy 
white, as were the wool hats of the men  -  all contrasted 
with the dark faces of the wearers in a strange 
and striking manner.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>SLAVE MOTHERS  -  CARE OF THE CHILDREN.</head>
          <p>The women who had young babies were assigned 
to what was considered “light work,” such as hoeing 
potatoes, cutting weeds from the fence corners, and 
any other work of like character. About nine o'clock 
in the forenoon, at noon, and three o'clock in the afternoon, 
these women, known on the farms as “the 
sucklers,” could be seen going from work to nurse 
their babies. Many were the heart-sighs of these 
sorrowing mothers as they went to minister to their 
infants. Sometimes the little things would seem 
starved, for the mothers could only stop their toil 
three times a day to care for them. When old enough 
to receive it, the babies had milk, the liquor from 
boiled cabbage, and bread and milk together. A 
woman who was too old to do much of anything was 
assigned to the charge of these babies in the absence 
of their mothers. It was rare that she had any on 
to help her. The cries of these little ones, who were 
<pb id="hughes44" n="44"/>
cut off almost entirely from motherly care and protection, 
were heart-rending.</p>
          <p>The cabin used for the infants during the day was 
a double one, that is, double the usual size, and was 
located near the great house. The cradles used were 
made of boards, and were not more than two by three 
feet in size. The women carried their babies in the 
cradles to the baby cabin in the morning, taking them 
to their own cabins at night. The children ranging 
in age from one to seven years were numerous, and the 
old woman had them to look after as well as the babies. 
This was indeed a task, and might well have taxed 
the strength of a younger woman. They were 
always from eight to a dozen infants in the cabin. 
The summer season was trying on the babies and 
young children. Often they would drink too much 
liquor from cabbage, or too much buttermilk, and 
would be taken with a severe colic. I was always 
called on these occasions to go with Boss to administer 
medicine. I remember on one occasion a little boy 
had eaten too much cabbage, and was taken with 
cramp colic. In a few minutes his stomach was  
swolen as tight and hard as a baloon, and his teeth 
clenched. He was given an emetic, put in a mustard 
<pb id="hughes45" n="45"/>
bath and was soon relieved. The food was too heavy 
for these children, and they were nearly always in 
need of some medical attendance. Excessive heat, 
with improper food, often brought on cholera infantum, 
from which the infants sometimes died rapidly 
and in considerable numbers.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>METHODS OF PUNISHMENT.</head>
          <p>The methods of punishment were barbarous in the 
extreme, and so numerous that I will not attempt to 
describe them all. One method was to tie the slave 
to a tree, strip off his clothes, and then whip him 
with a rawhide, or long, limber switches, or the 
terrible bull whip. Another was to put the slave in 
stocks, or to buck him, that is, fasten his feet together, 
draw up his knees to his chin, tie his hands together, 
draw them down over the knees, and put a stick under 
the latter and over the arms. In either of these ways 
the slave was entirely at the mercy of his tormentors, 
and the whipping could proceed at their pleasure. 
After these whippings the slave was often left helpless 
and bleeding upon the ground, until the master, 
or overseer, saw fit to let him up. The most common 
method of punishment was to have the servants form 
a ring, called the “bull ring,” into which the one to 
<pb id="hughes46" n="46"/>
be punished was led naked. The slaves were then 
each given a switch, rawhide, strap or whip, and each 
one was compelled to cut at the poor victim as he ran 
around the ring. The ring was composed of men, 
women and children; and, as they numbered from 
forty to fifty, each circuit of the ring would result in that 
number of lashes, and by the time the victim had 
made two or three rounds his condition can be readily 
imagined. The overseer was always one of the ring, 
vigorously using the whip, and seeing that all the 
slaves did the same. Some of the victims fainted 
before they had passed once around the ring. Women 
slaves were punished in the same manner as the men. 
The salt water bath was given after each punishment. 
Runaway slaves were usually caught by means of 
hounds, trained for the purpose by men who made it a 
business and a source of revenue, notwithstanding its 
brutal features and degrading influence.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>FOURTH OF JULY BARBECUE.</head>
          <p>Barbecue originally meant to dress and roast a 
hog whole, but has come to mean the cooking of a 
food animal in this manner for the feeding of a great 
company. A feast of this kind was always given to 
us, by Boss, on the 4th of July. The anticipation of it 
<pb id="hughes47" n="47"/>
acted as a stimulant through the entire year. Each 
one looked forward to this great day of recreation 
with pleasure. Even the older slaves would join in 
the discussion of the coming event. It mattered not 
what trouble or hardship the year had brought, this 
feast and its attendant pleasure would dissipate all 
gloom. Some, probably, would be punished on the 
morning of the 4th, but this did not matter; the men 
thought of the good things in store for them, and 
that made them forget that they had been punished. 
All the week previous to the great day, the slaves 
were in high spirits, the young girls and boys, each 
evening, congregating, in front of the cabins, to talk 
of the feast, while others would sing and dance. 
The older slaves were not less happy, but would only 
say: “Ah! God has blessed us in permitting us to 
see another feast day.” The day before the 4th was 
a busy one. The slaves worked with all their might. 
The children who were large enough were engaged 
in bringing wood and bark to the spot where the 
barbecue was to take place. They worked eagerly, 
all day long; and, by the time the sun was setting, 
a huge pile of fuel was beside the trench, ready for 
use in the morning. At an early hour of the great
<pb id="hughes48" n="48"/>
day, the servants were up, and the men whom Boss 
had appointed to look after the killing of the hogs 
and sheep were quickly at their work, and, by the 
time they had the meat dressed and ready, most of 
the slaves had arrived at the center of attraction. 
They gathered in groups, talking, laughing, telling 
tales that they had from their grandfather, or 
relating practical jokes that they had played or seen 
played by others. These tales were received with 
peals of laughter. But however much they seemed to 
enjoy these stories and social interchanges, they  
never lost sight of the trench or the spot where the 
sweetmeats were to be cooked.</p>
          <p>The method of cooking the meat was to dig 
a trench in the ground about six feet long and eighteen 
inches deep. This trench was filled with wood and 
bark which was set on fire, and, when it was burned 
to a great bed of coals, the hog was split through the 
back bone, and laid on poles which had been placed 
across the trench. The sheep were treated in the 
same way, and both were turned from side to side as 
they cooked. During the process of roasting the 
cooks basted the carcasses with a preparation furnished 
from the great house, consisting of butter
<pb id="hughes49" n="49"/>
pepper, salt and vinegar, and this was continued 
until the meat was ready to serve. Not far from this 
trench were the iron ovens, where the sweetmeats 
were cooked. Three or four women were assigned to 
this work. Peach cobbler and apple dumpling were 
the two dishes that made old slaves smile for joy and 
the young fairly dance. The crust or pastry of the 
cobbler was prepared in large earthen bowls, then 
rolled out like any pie crust, only it was almost twice 
as thick. A layer of this crust was laid in the oven, 
then a half peck of peaches poured in, followed by a 
layer of sugar; then a covering of pastry was laid 
over all and smoothed around with a knife. The 
oven was then put over a bed of coals, the cover put on 
and coals thrown on it, and the process of baking 
began. Four of these ovens were usually in use at 
these feasts, so that enough of the pastry might be 
baked to supply all. The ovens were filled and 
refilled until there was no doubt about the quantity. 
The apple dumplings were made in the usual way, 
only larger, and served with sauce made from brown 
sugar. It lacked flavoring, such as cinnamon or 
lemon, yet it was a dish highly relished by all the 
slaves. I know that these feasts made me so excited, 
<pb id="hughes50" n="50"/>
I could scarcely do my house duties, and I would never 
fail to stop and look out of the window from the 
dining room down into the quarters. I was eager to 
get through with my work and be with the feasters. 
About noon everything was ready to serve. The 
table was set in a grove near the quarters, a place set 
aside for these occasions. The tableware was not 
fine, being of tin, but it served the purpose, and did 
not detract from the slaves' relish for the feast. The 
drinks were strictly temperance drinks  -  buttermilk 
and water. Some of the nicest portions of the meat 
were sliced off and put on a platter to send to the 
great house for Boss and his family. It was a pleasure 
for the slaves to do this, for Boss always enjoyed it. 
It was said that the slaves could barbecue meats best, 
and when the whites had barbecues slaves always did 
the cooking. When dinner was all on the table, the 
invitation was given for all to come; and when all 
were in a good way eating, Boss and the madam 
would go out to witness the progress of the feast, and 
seemed pleased to see the servants so happy. Everything 
was in abundance, so all could have plenty  -   
Boss always insisted on this. The slaves had the 
whole day off, and could do as they liked. After 
<pb id="hughes51" n="51"/>
dinner some of the women would wash, sew or iron. 
It was a day of harmless riot for all the slaves, and I 
can not express the happiness it brought them. Old 
and young, for months, would rejoice in the memory 
of the day and its festivities, and “bless” Boss for this 
ray of sunlight in their darkened lives.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>ATTENDANCE AT CHURCH.</head>
          <p>There was an observance of religious forms at 
least by the occupants of both the great house and 
the cabins. The McGee family were church-going 
people, and, except in very inclement weather, never 
failed to attend service on Sunday. They were 
Methodists, and their church was four miles from 
their residence. The Baptist church was but two 
miles distant, and the family usually alternated in 
their attendance between the two places of worship. 
I always attended them to church, generally riding 
behind while the Boss drove. Upon reaching church, 
my first duty was to run to a spring for a pitcher of 
fresh water, which I passed not only to the members 
of our party, but to any others desiring drink. 
Whatever may be thought of the religious professions 
of the slave-holders, there can be no question that 
many of the slaves were sincere believers in the
<pb id="hughes52" n="52"/>
Christian religion, and endeavored to obey the precepts 
according to their light.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>RELIGIOUS MEETINGS OF THE SLAVES.</head>
          <p>Saturday evening on the farm was always hailed 
with delight. The air was filled with happy shouts 
from men and boys, so glad were they that Sunday, 
their only day of rest, was near. In the cabins the 
women were washing and fixing garments for Sunday, 
that they might honor the Lord in cleanliness and 
decency. It was astonishing how they utilized what 
they had, and with what skill and industry they performed 
these self-imposed tasks. Where the family 
was large it was often after midnight before this 
work was done. While this preparation for the 
Sabbath was in progress in most of the cabins, the 
old men would gather in one for a prayer-meeting. 
As they began to sing some familiar hymn, the air 
would ring with their voices, and it was not long 
before the cabin was filled with both old and young, 
who came in their simple yet sincere way to give 
praise to God. It was common to have one or two 
exhorters on the plantation who claimed to be called 
to do service for God, by teaching their fellow men 
the principles of religion. God certainly must have
<pb id="hughes53" n="53"/>
revealed himself to these poor souls, for they were 
very ignorant  -  they did not know a letter of the Bible. 
But when they opened their mouths they were filled, 
and the plan of Salvation was explained in a way 
that all could receive it. It was always a mystery to 
the white brethren how the slaves could line out 
hymns, preach Christ and redemption, yet have no 
knowledge even of how the name of Christ was 
spelled. They were illiterate to the last degree, so 
there is but one theory, they were inspired. God 
revealed unto them just what they should teach their 
flock, the same as he did to Moses. I remember very 
well that there was always a solemnity about the 
services  -  a certain harmony, which had a peculiar 
effect  -  a certain pathetic tone which quickened the 
emotions as they sang those old plantation hymns. 
It mattered not what their troubles had been during 
the week  -  how much they had been lashed, the 
prayer-meeting on Saturday evening never failed to
be held. Their faith was tried and true. On Sunday 
afternoons, they would all congregate again to praise 
God, and the congregation was enthusiastic. It was 
pathetic to hear them pray, from the depths of their 
hearts, for them who “despitefully used them and
<pb id="hughes54" n="54"/>
persecuted them.” This injunction of our Saviour 
was strictly adhered to. The words that came from 
the minister were always of a consolatory kind. He 
knew the crosses of his fellow slaves and their hardships, 
for he had shared them himself. I was always
touched in hearing him give out the hymns. I can
hear old Uncle Ben now, as he solemnly worded out
the following lines:</p>
          <lg type="poem">
            <l>Must I be carried to the skies,</l>
            <l>On flowery beds of ease,</l>
            <l>While others fought to Win the prize,</l>
            <l>And sailed through bloody seas?</l>
          </lg>
          <p>After singing he would always speak to them of 
the necessity for patience in bearing the crosses, urging 
them to endure “as good soldiers.” Many tears 
were shed, and many glad shouts of praise would 
burst forth during the sermon. A hymn usually followed 
the sermon, then all retired. Their faces 
seemed to shine with a happy light  -  their very 
countenance showed that their souls had been refreshed 
and that it had been “good for them to be there.” 
These meetings were the joy and comfort of the slaves, 
and even those who did not profess Christianity were 
calm and thoughtful while in attendance.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="hughes55" n="55"/>
        <div2>
          <head>A NEIGHBORHOOD QUARREL.</head>
          <p>Opposite our farm was one owned by a Mr. Juval, 
and adjoining that was another belonging to one 
White. The McGees and the Whites were very fast 
friends, visiting each other regularly  -  indeed they had 
grown up together, and Mr. White at one time was 
the lover of the madam, and engaged to be married 
to her. This friendship had existed for years, when 
McGee bought the Juval farm, for which White had 
also been negotiating, but which he failed to get on 
account of McGee having out-bid him. From this 
circumstance ill feeling was engendered between the 
two men, and they soon became bitter enemies. McGee 
had decided to build a fence between the farm he 
had purchased and that of White, and, during the 
winter, his teamsters were set to hauling the rails; 
and, in unloading them, they accidently threw some 
of them over the line on to White's land. The latter 
said nothing about the matter until spring, when he 
wrote McGee a letter, asking him to remove the rails 
from his land. McGee paid no attention to the request, 
and he soon received a second note, when he 
said to his wife: “ That fellow is about to turn himself 
a fool  -  I'll give him a cow-hiding.“ A third and
<pb id="hughes56" n="56"/>
more emphatic note followed, in which White told the 
Boss that the rails must be removed within twenty-four 
hours. He grew indignant, and, in true Southern 
style, he went immediately to town and bought 
arms, and prepared himself for the fray. When he 
returned he had every hand on the plantation stop 
regular work, and put them all to building the fence. 
I was of the number. Ross and the overseer came 
out to overlook the work and hurry it on. About 
four o'clock in the afternoon White put in an appearance, 
and came face to face with McGee, sitting on 
his horse and having a double barreled shot gun 
lying across the pummel of his saddle. White 
passed on without saying a word, but Boss yelled at 
him: “Hello! I see you are about to turn yourself 
a d  -  d fool.” White checked up and began to swear, 
saying: “You are a coward to attack an unarmed man.”
He grew furious, took off his hat, ran his
fingers through his hair, saying: “ Here I am, blow
me to h  -  l, and I'll have some one blow you there before 
night.” During White's rage he said: “I'll 
fight you anywhere  -  bowie-knife fight, shot gun fight 
or any other.” He called, in his excitement, for his 
nephew, who was working on his farm, to come, and 
<pb id="hughes57" n="57"/>
immediately sent him to Billy Duncan's to get him a 
double barreled shot gun. Meantime, Mrs. McGee  
appeared on the scene, and began to cry, begging 
White to stop and allow her to speak to him. But he 
replied: “Go off, go off, I don't want to speak to 
you.” Boss grew weak and sick, and through his excitement, 
was taken violently ill, vomiting as if he 
had taken an emetic. He said to White: “I'll return 
as soon as I take my wife home,” but he never 
came back. As Boss and the madam rode off, White 
came galloping back, and said to Brooks, our overseer: 
“If I am shot down on foul play would you 
speak of it?” Brooks replied: “No, I don't care to 
interfere  -  I don't wish to have anything to do with 
it.” White was bloodthirsty, and came back at intervals 
during the entire night, where we were working, 
to see if he could find Boss. It is quite probable that 
White may have long cherished a secret grudge 
against Boss, because he had robbed him of his first 
love; and, brooding over these offenses, he became so 
excited as to be almost insane. Had McGee returned 
that night, White would certainly have shot him. 
Boss became so uneasy over the situation that he sent 
one of his slaves, a foreman, to Panola county, some
<pb id="hughes58" n="58"/>
seventy-five miles distant, to Mrs. McGee's father, to 
get her brother, a lawyer, to come and endeavor to 
effect a settlement. He came, but all his efforts were 
unavailing. The men met at a magistrate's office, but 
they came to no understanding. Our folks became 
dissatisfied, and did not care to remain longer in the 
place, so they began to look out for other quarters. 
Boss finally decided to buy a farm in Bolivar, Miss., and 
to remove his family to Memphis, where he secured a 
fine place, just outside of the city.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="Illustration">
        <pb id="hughes58a" n="58a"/>
        <p>
          <figure id="ill2" entity="hughes59">
            <p>[Image of Currency]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1>
        <pb id="hughes59" n="59"/>
        <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
        <head>SOCIAL AND OTHER ASPECTS OF SLAVERY.</head>
        <div2>
          <head>REMOVAL TO MEMPHIS, TENNESSEE.</head>
          <p>McGee had decided to build a new house upon the 
property which he had purchased at Memphis; and, 
in August 1850, he sent twenty-five of his slaves to 
the city, to make brick for the structure, and I went 
along as cook. After the bricks were burned, the 
work of clearing the ground for the buildings was 
commenced. There were many large and beautiful 
trees that had to be taken up and removed; and, when 
this work was completed, the excavations for the 
foundations and the cellar were undertaken. All of 
this work was done by the slaves. The site was a 
beautiful one, embracing fourteen acres, situated two 
miles southeast from the city, on the Memphis and 
Charleston railroad. The road ran in front of the 
place and the Boss built a flag-station there, for the 
accommodation of himself and his neighbors, which 
was named McGee Station.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="hughes60" n="60"/>
        <div2>
          <head>A NEW AND SPLENDID HOUSE.</head>
          <p>The house was one of the most pretentious in that 
region, and was a year and a half in building. It 
was two stories in height, and built of brick, the 
exterior surface being coated with cement and marked 
off in blocks, about two feet square, to represent 
stone. It was then whitewashed. There was a 
veranda in front with six large columns, and, above, 
a balcony. On the back there were also a veranda 
and a balcony, extending across that end to the 
servants' wing. A large hall led from front to rear, 
on one side of which were double parlors, and on the 
other a sitting room, a bedroom and a dining room. 
In the second story were a hall and four rooms, 
similar in all respects to those below, and above these 
was a large attic. The interior woodwork was of 
black walnut. The walls were white, and the centerpieces 
in the ceilings of all the rooms were very fine, 
being the work of an English artisan, who had been 
only a short time in this country. This work was so 
superior, in design and finish, to anything before seen 
in that region that local artisans were much excited 
over it; and some offered to purchase the right to 
reproduce it, but Boss refused the offer. However, 
<pb id="hughes61" n="61"/>
some one, while the house was finishing, helped himself 
to the design, and it was reproduced, in whole or 
in part, in other buildings in the city. This 
employment of a foreign artist was unusual there and 
caused much comment. The parlors were furnished 
with mahogany sets, the upholstering being in red 
brocade satin. The dining room was also furnished 
in mahogany. The bedrooms had mahogany bedsteads 
of the old-fashioned pattern with canopies. 
Costly bric-a-brac, which Boss and the madam had 
purchased while traveling in foreign countries, was 
in great profusion. Money was no object to Edmund 
McGee, and he added every modern improvement and 
luxury to his home; the decorations and furnishings 
were throughout of the most costly and elegant; and 
in the whole of Tennessee there was not a mansion 
more sumptuously complete in all its appointments, 
or more palatial in its general appearance. When all 
was finished  -  pictures, bric-a-brac, statuary and 
flowers all in their places, Mrs. McGee was brought 
home.</p>
          <p>In this new house Boss opened up in grand style; 
everything was changed, and the family entered upon 
a new, more formal and more pretentious manner of
<pb id="hughes62" n="62"/>
living. I was known no longer as errand boy, but 
installed as butler and body-servant to my master. I 
had the same routine of morning work, only it was 
more extensive. There was a great deal to be done 
in so spacious a mansion. Looking after the parlors, 
halls and dining rooms, arranging flowers in the 
rooms, waiting on the table, and going after the mail 
was my regular morning work, the year round. Then 
there were my duties to perform, night and morning, 
for my master; these were to brush his clothes, black 
his shoes, assist him to arrange his toilet, and do any 
little thing that he wanted me to. Aside from these 
regular duties, there were windows to wash, silver to 
polish and steps to stone on certain days in the week. 
I was called to do any errand neccessary, and sometimes 
to assist in the garden. A new staff of house 
servants was installed, as follows: Aunt Delia, cook; 
Louisa, chambermaid; Puss, lady's maid to wait on 
the madam; Celia, nurse; Lethia, wet nurse; Sarah, 
dairymaid; Julia, laundress; Uncle Gooden, gardener;  
Thomas, coachman.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>THE NEW STYLE OF LIVING.</head>
          <p>The servants, at first, were dazed with the splendor 
of the new house, and laughed and chuckled to
<pb id="hughes63" n="63"/>
themselves a good deal about mars' fine house, and 
really seemed pleased; for, strange to say, the slaves 
of rich people always rejoiced in that fact. A servant 
owned by a man in moderate circumstances was 
hooted at by rich men's slaves. It was common for 
them to say: “Oh! don't mind that darkey, he belongs 
to po'r white trash.” So, as I said, our slaves rejoiced 
in master's good luck. Each of the women servants 
wore a new, gay colored turban, which was tied 
differently from that of the ordinary servant, in some 
fancy knot. Their frocks and aprons were new, and 
really the servants themselves looked new. My outfit 
was a new cloth suit, and my aprons for wearing 
when waiting on the table were of snowy white 
linen, the style being copied from that of the New York 
waiters. I felt big, for I never knew what a white 
bosom shirt was before; and even though the grief at 
the separation from my dear mother was almost unbearable 
at times, and my sense of loneliness in 
having no relative near me often made me sad, there 
was consolation, if not compensation, in this little 
change. I had known no comforts, and had been 
so cowed and broken in spirits, by cruel lashings, that 
I really felt light-hearted at this improvement in my
<pb id="hughes64" n="64"/>
personal appearance, although it was merely for the 
gratification of my master's pride; and I thought I 
would do all I could to please Boss.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>THE ADORNMENT OF THE GROUNDS.</head>
          <p>For some time before all the appointments of the 
new home were completed, a great number of mechanics 
and workmen, besides our own servants, were 
employed; and there was much bustle and stir about 
the premises. Considerable out-door work was yet to 
be done  -  fences to be made, gardens and orchards to 
be arranged and planted, and the grounds about the 
house to be laid out and adorned with shubbery and 
flower beds. When this work was finally accomplished, 
the grounds were indeed beautiful. The walks were 
graveled, and led through a profusion of shrubbery 
and flower beds. There was almost every variety of 
roses; while, scattered over the grounds, there were 
spruce, pine and juniper trees, and some rare varieties, 
seldom seen in this northern climate. Around the 
grounds was set a cedar hedge, and, in time, the 
place became noted for the beauty of its shrubbery; 
the roses especially were marvelous in the richness 
and variety of their colors, their fragrance and the 
luxuriousness of their growth. People who have never
<pb id="hughes65" n="65"/>
traveled in the South have little idea of the richness 
and profusion of its flowers, especially of its roses. 
Among the climbing plants, which adorned the house, 
the most beautiful and fragrant was the African 
honeysucle  -  its order was indeed delightful.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>THE GARDEN.</head>
          <p>One of the institutions of the place was the vegetable 
garden. This was established not only for the 
convenience and comfort of the family, but to furnish 
employment for the slaves. Under the care of Uncle 
Gooden, the gardner, it flourished greatly; and there 
was so much more produced than the family could use, 
Boss concluded to sell the surplus. The gardner, 
therefore, went to the city, every morning, with a load 
of vegetables, which brought from eight to ten dollars 
daily, and this the madam took for “pin money.” 
In the spring I had always to help the gardner in setting 
out plants and preparing beds; and, as this was 
in connection with my other work, I became so tired 
sometimes that I could hardly stand. All the vegetables 
raised were fine, and at that time brought a 
good price. The first cabbage that we sold in the 
markets brought twenty-five cents a head. The first 
sweet potatoes marketed always brought a dollar a
<pb id="hughes66" n="66"/>
peck, or four dollars a bushel. The Memphis market 
regulations required that all vegetables be washed before 
being exposed for sale. Corn was husked, and 
everything was clean and inviting. Any one found 
guilty of selling, or exhibiting for sale, vegetables of 
a previous day was fined, at once, by the market 
master. This rule was carried out to the letter. 
Nothing stale could be sold, or even come into market. 
The rules required that all poultry be dressed before 
being brought to market. The entrails were cleaned 
and strung and sold separately  -  usually for about ten 
cents a string.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>PROFUSION OF FLOWERS.</head>
          <p>Flowers grew in profusion everywhere through the 
south, and it has, properly, been called the land of 
flowers. But flowers had no such sale there as have  
our flowers here in the north. The pansy and many  
of our highly prized plants and flowers grew wild in  
the south. The people there did not seem to care for 
flowers as we do. I have sold many bouquets for a 
dime, and very beautiful ones for fifteen and twenty 
cents, that would sell in the north for fifty to seventy-five 
cents.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="hughes67" n="67"/>
        <div2>
          <head>THE FRUIT ORCHARD.</head>
          <p>The new place had an orchard of about four acres, 
consisting of a variety of apple, peach, pear and 
plum trees. Boss hired an expert Gardner to teach 
me the art of grafting, and, after some practice, I 
became quite skilled in this work. Some of the pear 
trees that had been grafted had three different kinds 
of fruit on them, and others had three kinds of apples 
on them besides the pears. This grafting I did 
myself, and the trees were considered very fine by 
Boss. Another part of my work was the trimming of  
the hedge and the care of all the shrubbery.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>I PRACTICE MEDICINE AMONG THE SLAVES.</head>
          <p>McGee had a medicine chest built into the wall of 
the new house. The shelves for medicine were of 
wood, and the arrangement was very convenient. It 
was really a small drug store. It contained everything 
in the way of drugs that was necessary to use 
in doctoring the slaves. We had quinine, castor-oil, 
alcohol and ipecac in great quantities, as these were 
the principal drugs used in the limited practice in the 
home establishment. If a servant came from the field 
to the house with a chill, which was frequent, the 
first thing we did was to give him a dose of ipecac to
<pb id="hughes68" n="68"/>
vomit him. On the evening after, we would give 
him two or three of Cook's pills. These pills we 
made at home, I always had to prepare the medicines, 
and give the dose, the Boss standing by dictating. 
Working with medicine, giving it and caring for the 
sick were the parts of my work that I liked best. 
Boss used Dr. Gunn's book altogether for recipes in 
putting up medicines. He read me the recipe, while 
I compounded it.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>A SWELL RECEPTION.</head>
          <p>In celebration of the opening of the new house, 
McGee gave an elaborate reception and dinner. The 
menu embraced nearly everything that one could 
think of or desire, and all in the greatest profusion. 
It was a custom, not only with the McGees but among 
the southern people generally, to make much of eating  -  
it was one of their hobbies. Everything was 
cooked well, and highly seasoned. Scarcity was 
foreign to the homes of the wealthy southerners.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>RELATIVES VISIT AT THE MANSION.</head>
          <p>After the family had been settled about a month 
in the new home, their relatives in Panola Co., Miss., 
Mr. Jack McGee, known among the servants as “Old 
<pb id="hughes69" n="69"/>
Jack,” Mrs. Melinda McGee, his wife, Mrs. Farrington, 
their daughter who was a widow, and their other 
children Louisa, Ella and William, all came up for a 
visit, and to see the wonderful house. Mr. Jack 
McGee was the father of madam and the uncle of 
Boss. My master and mistress were therefore first 
cousins, and Boss sometimes called the old man father 
and at other times, uncle. Old Master Jack, as he 
alighted, said to those behind him: “Now be careful, 
step lightly, Louisa, this is the finest house you ever 
set foot in.” When all had come into the house, and 
the old man had begun to look around, he said: “I 
don't know what Edmund is thinking about-out to 
build such a house-house.” He was very old, and had 
never lost all of his Scotch dialect, and he had a habit 
of repeating a part or all of some words, as in the 
foregoing quotation. The other members of the 
visiting family were well pleased with the house, and 
said it was grand. They laughed and talked merrily 
over the many novel things which they saw. Mrs. 
Farrington, who was a gay widow, was naturally 
interested in everything. I busied myself waiting 
upon them, and it was late that night before I was 
through. So many made extra work for me.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="hughes70" n="70"/>
        <div2>
          <head>ONE OF THE VISITORS DISTRUSTS ME.</head>
          <p>The next morning, after breakfast, Boss and old 
Master Jack went out to view the grounds. They 
took me along so that if anything was wanted I could 
do it. Boss would have me drive a stake in some 
place to mark where he desired to put something, 
perhaps some flowers, or a tree. He went on through 
the grounds, showing his father how everything was 
to be arranged. The old man shook his head, and 
said: “Well, it's good, but I am afraid you'll spoil 
these niggers-niggers. Keep you eye on that boy Lou, 
(meaning me) he is slippery-slippery, too smart-art.” 
“Oh! I'll manage that, Father,” said Boss. “Well, 
see that you do-oo, for I see running away in his 
eyes.” One of the things that interested old Master 
Jack was the ringing of the dinner bell. “Well, I do 
think,” said the old man, “that boy can ring a bell 
better than anbody I ever heard. Why, its got a 
regular tune.” I used to try to see how near I could 
come to making it say, come to dinner.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>THE MADAM IN A RAGE.</head>
          <p>The four days soon passed, and all the company 
gone, we were once more at our regular work. Delia, 
the cook, seemingly had not pleased the madam in
<pb id="hughes71" n="71"/>
her cooking while the company were there; so, the 
morning after they left, she went toward the kitchen, 
calling: “Delia, Delia.” Delia said: “Dah! I wonder 
what she wants now.” By this time she was in the 
kitchen, confronting Delia.  Her face was flushed as 
she screamed out: “What kind of biscuits were those 
you baked this week?” “I think they were all right, 
Mis Sarh.” “Hush!” screamed out the madam, 
stamping her foot to make it more emphatic. “You 
did not half cook them,” said she; “they were not 
beat enough. Those waffles were ridiculous,” said 
the madam. “Well, Mis Sarh, I tried.”  “Stop!” 
cried Madam in a rage, “I'll give you thunder if you 
dictate to me.” Not a very elegant display in language 
or manner for a great lady! Old Aunt Delia, 
who was used to these occurances, said: “My Lord! 
dat woman dunno what she wants. Ah! Lou, there is 
nothing but the devil up here, (meaning the new 
home); can't do nothin to please her up here in dis 
fine house. I tell you Satan neber git his own til he 
git her.” They did not use baking powder, as we do 
now, but the biscuits were beaten until light enough. 
Twenty minutes was the time allotted for this 
work; but when company came there was so much to be
<pb id="hughes72" n="72"/>
done  -  so many more dishes to prepare, that Delia 
would, perhaps, not have so much time for each meal. 
But there was no allowance made. It was never 
thought reasonable that a servant should make a mistake  -  
things must always be the same. I was 
listening to this quarrel between madam and Delia, 
supposing my time would come next; but for that 
once she said nothing to me.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>THE MADAM'S SEVERITY.</head>
          <p>Mrs. McGee was naturally irritable. Servants 
always got an extra whipping when she had any 
personal trouble, as though they could help it. 
Every morning little Kate, Aunt Delia's little girl, 
would have to go with the madam on her rounds to 
the different buildings of the establishment, to carry 
the key basket. So many were the keys that they 
were kept in a basket especially provided for them, 
and the child was its regular bearer. The madam, with 
this little attendant, was everywhere  -  in the barn, 
in the hennery, in the smokehouse  -  and she always 
made trouble with the servants wherever she went. 
Indeed, she rarely returned to the house from these 
rounds without having whipped two or three servants, 
whether there was really any cause for the punishment
<pb id="hughes73" n="73"/>
or not. She seldom let a day pass without beating 
some poor woman unmercifully. The number 
and severity of these whippings depended more upon 
the humor of the madam than upon the conduct of 
the slaves. Of course, I always came in for a share 
in this brutal treatment. She continued her old habit 
of boxing my jaws, pinching my ears; no day ever 
passing without her indulging in this exercise of her 
physical powers. So long had I endured this, I came 
to expect it, no matter how well I did my duties; and 
it had its natural effect upon me, making me a coward, 
even though I was now growing into manhood. 
I remember once, in particular, when I had tried 
to please her by arranging the parlor, I overheard her 
say: “They soon get spirit  -  it don't do to praise
servants.” My heart sank within me. What good 
was it for me to try to please? She would find 
fault anyway. Her usual morning greeting was: 
“Well, Lou, have you dusted the parlors?” “Oh, 
yes,” I would answer. “Have the flowers been arranged?” 
“Yes, all is in readiness,” I would say. 
Once I had stoned the steps as usual, but the madam 
grew angry as soon as she saw them. I had labored 
hard, and thought she would be pleased. The result,
<pb id="hughes74" n="74"/>
however, was very far from that. She took me out, 
stripped me of my shirt and began thrashing me, saying 
I was spoiled. I was no longer a child, but old 
enough to be treated differently. I began to cry, for 
it seemed to me my heart would break. But, after the 
first burst of tears, the feeling came over me that I 
was a man, and it was an outrage to treat me so  -  to 
keep me under the lash day after day.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>A SHOCKING ACCIDENT.</head>
          <p>Not long after Mrs. Farrington had made her first 
visit to our house, she came there to live. Celia had 
been acting as her maid. When Mrs. Farrington had 
been up some months, it was decided that all the 
family should go down to old Master Jack's for a 
visit. Celia, the maid, had been so hurried in the 
preparations for this visit that she had done nothing 
for herself. The night before the family was to 
leave, therefore, she was getting ready a garment for 
herself to wear on the trip; and it was supposed that 
she sewed until midnight, or after, when she fell 
asleep, letting the goods fall into the candle. All at 
once, a little after twelve o'clock, I heard a scream, 
then a cry of “fire! fire!” and Boss yelling: “Louis! 
Louis!” I jumped up, throwing an old coat over me, 
<pb id="hughes75" n="75"/>
and ran up stairs, in the direction of Mrs. Farrington's 
room, I encountered Boss in the hall; and, as it 
was dark and the smoke stifling, I could hardly make 
any headway. At this moment Mrs. Farrington 
threw her door open, and screemed for “Cousin 
Eddie,” meaning McGee. He hurriedly called to me 
to get a pitcher of water quick. I grasped the pitcher 
from the stand, and he attempted to throw the water 
on Celia, who was all in a blaze, running  around like 
a mad woman; but the pitcher slipped from his hand 
and broke, very little of the water reaching her. She 
was at last wrapped in an old blanket, to extinguish 
the flames; but she was burned too badly to recover. 
Boss, being a physician, said at once: “Poor girl, 
poor girl! she is burned to death.” He did all he 
could for her, wrapped her in linen sheets, and endeavored 
to relieve her sufferings, but all was of no 
avail  -  she had inhaled the flame, injuring her internally, 
and lived only a few days.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>MASTER'S NEW COTTON PLANTATION.</head>
          <p>Shortly after Boss bought his home in Memphis, 
he bought a large farm in Bolivar, Miss. It was a 
regular cotton farm, on the Missippi river, embracing 
200 acres. The houses built for the slaves were 
<pb id="hughes76" n="76"/>
frame, eighteen in number, each to contain three or 
four families, and arranged on each side of a street 
that ran through the farm. This street was all grassed 
over, but there were no sidewalks. All the buildings 
the barn, gin-house, slaves' quarters and overseers' 
house  -  were whitewashed, and on this grass-grown 
street they made a neat and pretty appearance. The 
house where the Boss and the madam staid, when 
they went down to the farm, was about two hundred 
yards from the slaves' quarters. It was arranged in 
two appartments, one for the overseer and wife, and 
the other for the master and mistress upon the occasion 
of their visits. This building was separated 
from the other buildings by a fence. There was what 
was called the cook house, where was cooked all the 
food for the hands. Aunt Matilda was cook in charge. 
Besides the buildings already named, there were 
stables, a blacksmith shop and sawmill; and the 
general order of arrangement was carried out with respect 
to all  -  the appearance was that of a village. 
Everything was raised in abundance, to last from one 
crop to the next. Vegetables and meat were provided 
from the farm, and a dairy of fifty cows furnished all 
the milk and butter needed.</p>
          <pb id="hughes77" n="77"/>
          <p>The cane brakes were so heavy that it was common 
for bears to hide there, and, at night, come out 
and carry off hogs. Wolves were plenty in the woods 
behind the farm, and could be heard at any time. 
The cane was so thick that when they were clearing 
up new ground, it would have to be set on fire, and 
the cracking that would ensue was like the continuous 
explosion of small fire crackers.</p>
          <p>About one hundred and sixty slaves, besides 
children, all owned by McGee, were worked on the 
farm. Instead of ginning two or three bales of cotton 
a day, as at Pontotoc, they ginned six to seven bales 
here.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>INCIDENTS</head>
          <p>I remember well the time when the great Swedish 
singer, Jenny Lind, came to Memphis. It was during 
her famous tour through America, in 1851. Our 
folks were all enthused over her. Boss went in and 
secured tickets to her concert, and I was summoned 
to drive them to the hall. It was a great event. 
People swarmed the streets like bees. The carriages
and hacks were stacked back from the hall as far as 
the eye could reach.</p>
          <p>On another occasion, when the great prodigy,
<pb id="hughes78" n="78"/>
Blind Tom, came to Memphis, there was a similar 
stir among the people. Tom was very young then, 
and he was called the Blind Boy. People came from 
far and near to hear him. Those coming from the 
villages and small towns, who could not get passage 
on the regular trains, came in freight or on flat 
bottom cars. The tickets were $5.00 each, as I 
remember, Boss said it was expensive, but all must 
hear this boy pianist. Many were the comments on 
this boy of such wonderful talents. As I drove our 
people Home they seemed to talk of nothing else. 
They declared that he was indeed a wonder.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>LONGING FOR FREEDOM.</head>
          <p>Sometimes when the farm hands were at work, 
peddlers would come along; and, as they were treated 
badly by the rich planters, they hated them, and 
talked to the slaves in a way to excite them and set 
them thinking of freedom. They would say encouragingly 
to them:  “Ah! You will be free some 
day.” But the down-trodden slaves, some of whom 
were bowed with age, with frosted hair and furrowed 
cheek, would answer, looking up from their work:
“We don't blieve dat; my grandfather said we was to 
be free, but we aint free yet.” It had been talked of
<pb id="hughes79" n="79"/>
(this freedom) from generation to generation. Perhaps 
they would not have thought of freedom, if their 
owners had not been so cruel.  Had my mistress been 
more kind to me, I should have thought less of 
liberty. I know the cruel treatment which I received 
was the main thing that made me wish to be free. 
Besides this, it was inhuman to separate families as 
they did. Think of a mother being sold from all her 
children  -  separated for life! This separation was 
common, and many died heart-broken, by reason of it. 
Ah! I cannot forget the cruel separation from my 
mother. I know not what became of her, but I have 
always believed her dead many years ago. Hundreds 
were separated, as my mother and I were, and never 
met again. Though freedom was yearned for by 
some because the treatment was so bad, others, who 
were bright and had looked into the matter, knew it 
was a curse to be held a slave  -  they longed to stand 
out in true manhood  -  allowed to express their 
opinions as were white men. Others still desired 
freedom, thinking they could then reclaim a wife, or 
husband, or children. The mother would again see 
her child. All these promptings of the heart made 
them yearn for freedom. New Year's was always a 
<pb id="hughes80" n="80"/>
heart-rending time, for it was then the slaves were 
bought and sold; and they stood in constant fear of 
losing some one dear to them  -  a child, a husband, or 
wife.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>MY FIRST BREAK FOR FREEDOM.</head>
          <p>In the new home my duties were harder than ever. 
The McGees held me with tighter grip, and it was 
nothing but cruel abuse, from morning till night. 
So I made up my mind to try and run away to a free 
country. I used to hear Boss read sometimes, in the 
papers, about runaway slaves who had gone to 
Canada, and it always made me long to go; yet I 
never appeared as if I paid the slightest attention to 
what the family read or said on such matters; but I 
felt that I could be like others, and try at least to get 
away. One morning, when Boss had gone to town, 
Madam had threatened to whip me, and told me to 
come to the house. When she called me I did not go, 
but went off down through the garden and through 
the woods, and made my way for the city. When I 
got into Memphis, I found at the landing a boat 
called the Statesman, and I sneaked aboard. It was 
not expected that the boat would stay more than a 
few hours, but, for some reason, it stayed all night.
<pb id="hughes81" n="81"/>
The boat was loaded with sugar, and I hid myself 
behind four hogsheads. I could see both engineers, 
one each side of me. When night came on, I crept 
out from my hiding place, and went forward to search 
for food and water, for I was thirsty and very hungry. 
I found the table where the deck hands had been 
eating, and managed to get a little food, left from 
their meal, and some water. This was by no means 
enough, but I had to be content, and went back to my 
place of concealment. I had been on board the boat 
three days; and, on the third night, when I came out 
to hunt food, the second mate saw me. In a minute 
he eyed me over and said: “Why, I have a reward for 
you.” In a second he had me go up stairs to the 
captain. This raised a great excitement among the 
passengers; and, in a minute, I was besieged with 
numerous questions. Some spoke as if they were 
sorry for me. and said if they had known I was a poor 
runaway slave they would have slipped me ashore. 
The whole boat was in alarm. It seemed to me they 
were consulting slips of paper. One said: “Yes, he 
is the same. Listen how this reads:”</p>
          <p>“Ran away from Edmund McGee, my mulatto boy Louis, 
5 feet 6 inches in height, black hair, is very bright and
<pb id="hughes82" n="82"/>
intelligent. Will give $500 for him alive, and half of this
amount for knowledge that he has been killed.”</p>
          <p>My heart sprang into my throat when I heard two 
men read this advertisement. I knew, at once, 
what it all meant, remembering how often I had 
heard Boss read such articles from the papers and 
from the handbills that were distributed through the 
city. The captain asked me if I could dance. It 
seemed he felt sorry for me, for he said: “That's a 
bright boy to be a slave.” Then turning to me he 
said: “Come, give us a dance:” I was young and 
nimble, so I danced a few of the old southern clog 
dances, and sang one or two songs. like this:</p>
          <lg>
            <l>“Come along, Sam, the fifer's son,</l>
            <l>Aint you mighty glad your day's work's done?”</l>
          </lg>
          <p>After I finished singing and dancing, the captain 
took up a collection for me and got about two dollars. 
This cheered me a good deal. I knew that I would 
need money if I should ever succeed in getting on.</p>
          <p>On the following evening, when we reached West 
Franklin, Indiana, while the passengers were at tea, 
another boat pushed into port right after ours. Immediately 
a gentleman passenger came to me hurriedly,
<pb id="hughes83" n="83"/>
and whispered to me to go down stairs, jump out on 
the bow of the other boat, and go ashore. I was 
alarmed, but obeyed, for I felt that he was a friend to 
slaves. I went out as quietly as I could, and was not 
missed until I had gotten on shore. Then I heard 
the alarm given that the boy was gone  -  that the 
runaway was gone. But I sped on, and did not stop 
until I had run through the village, and had come to 
a road that led right into the country. I took this 
road and went on until I had gone four or five miles, 
when I came to a farm house. Before reaching it, 
however, I met two men on horseback, on their way 
to the village. They passed on without specially 
noticing me, and I kept on my way until reaching the 
farmhouse. I was so hungry, I went in and asked 
for food. While I was eating, the men whom I had 
met rode up. They had been to the village, and, 
learning that a runaway slave was wanted, and 
remembering meeting me, they returned in hot haste, 
in hope of finding me and securing the reward. They 
hallooed to the people in the house, an old woman 
and her daughter, whom they seemed to know, 
saying:  “There is a runaway nigger out, who stole 
off a boat this evening.”  The old lady said, “Come,”
<pb id="hughes84" n="84"/>
becoming frightened at once. When they came in 
they began to question me. I trembled all over but 
answered them. They said: “You are the fellow 
we want, who ran off the boat.” I was too scared to 
deny it; so I owned I was on the boat, and stole off. 
They did not tarry long, but, taking me with them, 
they went, about a mile and a half, to their house. 
They planned and talked all the way, and one said: 
“We are good for $75.00 for him any way.” The 
next morning they took me into the village. They 
soon found out that the engineer, by order of the 
captain, had stayed over to search for me. A lawsuit 
followed, and I was taken before the magistrate before 
the engineer could get possession of me. There was 
a legal course that had to be gone through with. A 
lawyer, Fox by name, furnished the $75.00 for the 
men who had caught me. That part of the case being 
settled, Fox and the engineer started for Evansville, 
Ind., that same night. Upon arriving there, Fox received 
from the captain of the boat the money he had 
advanced to the men who caught me; and we went 
on, arriving at Louisville, Ky., the next day. I was
then taken again before a magistrate, by the captain, 
when the following statement was read by that 
official:</p>
          <pb id="hughes85" n="85"/>
          <p>“Captain Montgomery brought forth a boy, and said he 
is the property of Edmund McGee, of Memphis, Tenn. Come 
forth owner, and prove property, for after the boy shall remain 
in jail six months he shall be sold to pay jail feed.”</p>
          <p>Mr. McGee was informed of my whereabouts, and 
it was not long before he and his cousin came to get 
me. When they came, I was called up by the nick-name 
they had given me, “Memphis.”  “Come out 
here, ‘Memphis,’” said the turnkey, “your master 
has come for you.” I went down stairs to the office, 
and found Boss waiting for me. “Hello, Lou!” 
said he, “what are you doing here, you dog?” I was 
so frightened I said nothing. Of course, some few 
words were passed between him and the officers.  I 
heard him say that I was a smart fellow, and he could 
not tell why I had run away; that he had always 
treated me well. This was to impress the officers with 
the idea that he was not unkind to his slaves. The 
slave-holders all hated to be classed as bad task-masters. 
Yet nearly all of them were. The clothes 
I wore were jail property, and he could not take me 
away in them; so we started to go up town to get
others. As we passed out the jailor, Buckhanon, said: 
“Ain't you going to put hand-cuffs on him?”  “Oh,
<pb id="hughes86" n="86"/>
no!” said Boss. After I was taken to the store and 
fitted with a new suit of clothes, he brought me back 
to the jail, where I washed myself and put on the 
new garments. When all was complete, and I seemed 
to suit master's fastidious eye, he took me to the Gault 
House, where he was stopping. In the evening we 
started for home, and reached Memphis the following 
day. Boss did not flog me, as I expected, but sent me 
to my regular routine work. We had been in this new 
home so short a time he did not want it to be rumored 
that he whipped his slaves, he was so stylish and rich. 
But the madam was filled with rage, although she did 
not say much. I think they saw that I was no longer a 
child  -  they feared I would go again. But after I had 
been home some three or four weeks, Madam Sarah 
commenced her old tricks  -  attempting to whip me, 
box my jaws and pinch me. If any little thing was 
not pleasing to her at meal time, it was a special delight 
for her to reach out, when I drew near to her 
to pass something, and give me a blow with her hand. 
Truly it was a monstrous domestic institution that 
not only tolerated, but fostered, such an exhibition of 
table manners by a would-be fine lady  -  such vulgar
spite and cruelty!</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="hughes87" n="87"/>
        <div2>
          <head>MY SECOND RUNAWAY TRIP.</head>
          <p>About three months after my first attempt to get 
away, I thought I would try it again. I went to 
Memphis, and saw a boat at the landing, called the 
John Lirozey, a Cincinnati packet. This boat carried 
the mail. She had come into port in the morning, 
and was being unloaded. I went aboard in the afternoon 
and jumped down into the hull. Boss had been 
there in the fore part of the afternoon inquiring for 
me, but I did not know it then. After I had been in the 
boat some time, the men commenced loading it. I 
crept up in the corner and hid myself. At first two 
or three hundred dry and green hides were thrown in, 
and these hid me; but later on two or three tiers of 
cotton bales were put in the center of the hull, and, 
when the boat started, I got upon the top of these, 
and lay there. I could hear the people talking above 
me, but it was so dark I could not see anything  -  it 
was dark as a dungeon. I had lain there two nights 
and began to get so weak and faint I could stand it no 
longer. For some reason the boat did not start the 
day I went aboard, consequently, I had not gotten as 
far from home as I expected, and my privations had 
largely been in vain. Despairing and hungry, on the
<pb id="hughes88" n="88"/>
third day, I commenced howling and screaming, hoping 
that some one would hear me, and come to my relief, 
for almost anything else would have been preferable 
to the privation and hunger from which I was 
suffering. But I could make no one hear, at least no 
one paid any attention to my screams, if they did 
hear. In the evening, however, one of the deck 
hands came in with a lantern to look around and see 
everything was all right. I saw the light and followed 
him out, but I had been out of my hiding only 
a short time when I was discovered by a man who 
took me up stairs to the captain. It was an effort for 
me to walk up stairs, as I was weak and faint, having 
neither eaten nor drank anything for three days. 
This boat was crowded with passengers, and it was 
soon a scene of confusion. I was placed in the pilot's 
room for safety, until we arrived at a small town in 
Kentucky called Monroe. I was put off here to be 
kept until the packet came back from Cincinnati. 
Then I was carried back to Memphis, arriving about 
one o'clock at night, and, for safe keeping, was put 
into what was called the calaboose. This was especially 
for the keeping of slaves who had run away 
and been caught. Word was sent to Boss of my 
<pb id="hughes89" n="89"/>
capture; and the next morning Thomas Bland, a fellow 
servant of mine, was sent to take me home. I 
can not tell how I felt, for the only thought that came 
to me was that I should get killed. The madam met 
us as we drove into the yard. “Ah!” she said to me, 
“you put up at the wrong hotel, sir.”  I was taken 
to the barn where stocks had been prepared, beside 
which were a cowhide and a pail of salt water, all 
prepared for me. It was terrible, but there was no escape. 
I was fastened in the stocks, my clothing removed, 
and the whipping began. Boss whipped me a 
while, then he sat down and read his paper, after 
which the whipping was resumed. This continued 
for two hours. Fastened as I was in the stocks, I 
could only stand and take lash after lash, as long as 
he desired, the terrible rawhide cutting into my flesh 
at every stroke. Then he used peach tree switches, 
which cracked the flesh so the blood oozed out. After 
this came the paddle, two and a half feet long and 
three inches wide. Salt and water was at once applied 
to wash the wounds, and the smarting was 
maddening. This torture was common among the 
southern planters. God only knows what I suffered 
under it all, and He alone gave me strength to endure
<pb id="hughes90" n="90"/>
it. I could hardly move after the terrible ordeal was 
finished, and could scarcely bear my clothes to touch 
me at first, so sore was my whole body, and it was 
weeks before I was myself again.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>PREACHING TO THE SLAVES.</head>
          <p>As an offset, probably, to such diabolical cruelties 
as those which were practiced upon me in common 
with nearly all the slaves in the cotton region of the 
south, it was the custom in the section of country 
where I lived to have the white minister preach to the 
servants Sunday afternoon, after the morning service 
for the whites. The white people hired the minister 
by the year to preach for them at their church. Then 
he had to preach to each master's slaves in turn. The 
circuit was made once a month, but there was service 
of some kind every Sunday. The slaves on some 
places gathered in the yard, at others in the white 
folks' school houses, and they all seemed pleased and 
eager to hear the word of God. It was a strong evidence 
of their native intelligence and discrimination 
that they could discern the difference between the 
truths of the “word” and the professed practice of 
those truths by their masters. My Boss took pride in 
having all his slaves look clean any tidy at the Sabbath
<pb id="hughes91" n="91"/>
service; but how would he have liked to have the 
slaves, with backs lacerated with the lash, appear in 
those assemblies with their wounds uncovered?  The 
question can never be answered. The master and 
most of his victims have gone where professions of 
righteousness will not avail to cover the barbarities 
practiced here.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>A FAMILY OF FREE PERSONS SOLD INTO SLAVERY.</head>
          <p>My wife Matilda was born in Fayette county, 
Kentucky, June 17th, 1830. It seems that her mother 
and her seven children were to have been free according 
to the old Pennsylvania law. There were two 
uncles of the family who were also to have been free, 
but who had been kept over time; so they sued for 
their freedom, and gained it. The lawyers in the 
case were abolitionists and friends to the slaves, and
saw that these men had justice. After they had 
secured their freedom, they entered suit for my wife's 
mother, their sister, and her seven children. But as 
soon as the brothers entered this suit, Robert Logan, 
who claimed my wife's mother and her children as his 
slaves, put them into a trader's yard in Lexington; 
and, when he saw that there was a possibility of their 
being successful in securing their freedom, he put 
<pb id="hughes92" n="92"/>
them in jail, to be “sold down the river.” This was 
a deliberate attempt to keep them from their rights, 
for he knew that they were to have been set free, 
many years before; and this fact was known to all the 
neighborhood. My wife's mother was born free, her 
mother, having passed the allotted time under a law, 
had been free for many years. Yet they kept her 
children as slaves, in plain violation of law as well as 
justice. The children of free persons under southern 
laws were free  -  this was always admitted. The 
course of Logan in putting the family in jail, for safe 
keeping until they could be sent to the southern 
market, was a tacit admission that he had no legal 
hold upon them. Woods and Collins, a couple of 
“nigger traders,” were collecting a “drove” of 
slaves for Memphis, about this time, and, when they 
were ready to start, all the family were sent off with 
the gang; and, when they arrived in Memphis, they 
were put in the traders' yard of Nathan Bedford 
Forrest. This Forrest afterward became a general in 
the rebel army, and commanded at the capture of 
Fort Pillow; and, in harmony with the debasing 
influences of his early business, he was responsible 
for the fiendish massacre of negroes after the capture
<pb id="hughes93" n="93"/>
of the fort  -  an act which will make his name forever 
infamous. None of this family were sold to the same 
person except my wife and one sister. All the rest 
were sold to different persons. The elder daughter 
was sold seven times in one day. The reason of this 
was that the parties that bought her, finding that she 
was not legally a slave, and that they could get no 
written guarantee that she was, got rid of her as 
soon as possible. It seems that those who bought 
the other members of the family were not so particular, 
and were willing to run the risk. They knew 
that such things  -  such outrages upon law and 
justice  -  were common. Among these was my Boss, 
who bought two of the girls, Matilda and her sister 
Mary Ellen. Matilda was bought for a cook; her 
sister was a present to Mrs. Farrington, his wife's 
sister, to act as her maid and seamstress. Aunt 
Delia, who had been cook, was given another branch 
of work to do, and Matilda was installed as cook. I 
remember well the day she came. The madam 
greeted her, and said: “Well, what can you do, girl? 
Have you ever done any cooking? Where are you 
from?”  Matilda was, as I remember her, a sad 
picture to look at. She had been a slave, it is true,
<pb id="hughes94" n="94"/>
but had seen good days to what the slaves down 
the river saw. Any one could see she was almost heart-broken  -  
she never seemed happy. Days grew into 
weeks and weeks into months, but the same routine 
of work went on.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>MY MARRIAGE  -  BIRTH OF TWINS.</head>
          <p>Matilda had been there three years when I married 
her. The Boss had always promised that he would 
give me a nice wedding, and he kept his word. He 
was very proud, and liked praise. The wedding that 
he gave us was indeed a pleasant one. All the slaves 
from their neighbor acquaintances were invited. One 
thing Boss did was a credit to him, but it was rare 
among slave-holders  -  he had me married by their 
parish minister. It was a beautiful evening, the 30th 
of November, 1858, when Matilda and I stood in the 
parlor of the McGee house and were solemnly made 
man and wife. Old Master Jack came up from Panola 
at that time, and was there when the ceremony was 
performed. As he looked through his fingers at us, 
he was overheard saying: “It will ruin them, givin 
wedins-wedins.” Things went on as usual after this. 
The-madam grew more irritable and exacting, always 
finding fault with the servants, whipping them, or
<pb id="hughes95" n="95"/>
threatening to do so, upon the slightest provocation, 
or none at all. There was something in my wife's 
manner, however, which kept the madam from whipping 
her  -  an open or implied threat perhaps that 
such treatment would not be endured without resistance 
or protest of some kind. This the madam 
regarded as a great indignity, and she hated my wife 
for it, and, at times, was ready to crush her, so great 
was her anger. In a year there were born to us twin 
babies; and the madam now thought she had my wife 
tied, as the babies would be a barrier to anything like 
resistance on her part, and there would be no danger 
of her running away. She, therefore, thought that 
she could enjoy, without hindrance, the privilege of 
beating the woman of whose womanhood she had 
theretofore stood somewhat in fear.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>MADAM'S CRUELTY TO MY WIFE AND CHILDREN.</head>
          <p>Boss said from the first that I should give my wife 
assistance, as she needed time to care for the babies. 
Really he was not as bad as the madam at heart, for 
she tried to see how hard she could be on us. She 
gave me all the extra work to do that she could think 
of, apparently to keep me from helping my wife in 
the kitchen. She had all the cooking to do for three
<pb id="hughes96" n="96"/>
heavy meals each day, all the washing and ironing of 
the finest clothes, besides caring for the babies between 
times.  In the morning she would nurse the 
babies, then hurry off to the kitchen to get breakfast 
while they were left in charge of a little girl.  Again 
at noon she repeated her visit to the babies, after 
cooking the dinner, then, in the evening, after supper, 
she would go to nurse them again.  After supper was 
over, dishes all washed and kitchen in order, she 
would then go to the little ones for the night.  One 
can see that she  had very little time with the children. 
My heart was sore and heavy, for my wife was almost 
run to death with work.  The children grew puny 
and sickly for want of proper care. The doctor said 
it was because the milk the mother nursed to them 
was so heated by her constant and excessive labors as to 
be unwholesome, and she never had time to cool before 
ministering to them. So the little things, instead 
of thriving and developing, as was their right, 
dwindled toward the inevitable end. Oh! we were 
wretched  -  our hearts ached for a day which we could 
call our own. My wife was a Christian, and had 
learned to know the worth of prayer, so would 
always speak consolingly. “God will help us,” she
<pb id="hughes97" n="97"/>
said: “let us try and be patient.” Our trial went on, 
until one morning I heard a great fuss in the house, 
the madam calling for the yard man to come and tie 
my wife, as she could not manage her. My wife had 
always refused to allow the madam to whip her; but 
now, as the babies were here, mistress thought she 
would try it once more. Matilda resisted, and madam 
called for Boss. In a minute he came, and, grabbing 
my wife, commenced choking her, saying to her: 
“What do you mean? Is that the way you talk to 
ladies?” My wife had only said to her mistress: 
“You shall not whip me.” This made her furious, 
hence her call for Boss. I was in the dining room, 
and could hear everything. My blood boiled in my 
veins to see my wife so abused; yet I dare not open 
my mouth. After the fuss, my wife went straight to 
the laundry. I followed her there, and found her 
bundling up her babies' clothes, which were washed 
but not ironed. I knew at a glance that she was 
going away. Boss had just gone to the city; and I 
did not know what to say, but I told her to do the best 
she could. Often when company came and I held the 
horses, or did an errand for them, they would tip me 
to a quarter or half a dollar. This money I always
<pb id="hughes98" n="98"/>
saved, and so had a little change, which I now gave 
to Matilda, for her use in her effort to get away from 
her cruel treatment. She started at once for Forrest's 
trader's yards, with the babies in her arms and, after 
she got into Memphis, she stopped outside the yard to 
rest. While she was sitting on the curb stone, Forrest 
came out of the yard by the back gate and saw 
her. Coming up to her he said: “My God! Matilda, 
what are you doing here?  You have changed so I 
would not have known you. Why have you come 
here?” Matilda said: “I came back here to be sold 
again.” He stepped back and called another “nigger 
trader,” Collins by name, from Kentucky. “Look 
here,” said Forrest, pointing to my wife. Collins 
took in the situation at once and said he would buy 
her and the children. “That woman is of a good 
family,” said he, “and was only sold to prevent her 
from getting her freedom.” She was then taken into 
the yard. “Oh!” said Forrest, “I know these McGees, 
they are hard colts.”  Word was then sent McGee 
that his cook was in the yard and had come to be 
sold. He went in haste to the yard. Collins offered 
to buy her, but McGee said no man's money could buy 
that woman and her children. I raised her husband
<pb id="hughes99" n="99"/>
and I would not separate them. She was brought 
back, and as they rode along in the rockaway, Boss 
said:  “When I am through with you I guess you 
won't run away again.” As they drove up I saw the 
madam go running out to meet them. She shouted to 
Matilda:  “Ah! madam, you put up at the wrong 
hotel.” They at once went to the barn where my 
wife was tied to the joist, and Boss and the madam 
beat her by turns. After they had finished the whipping, 
Boss said, tauntingly:  “Now I am buying you 
and selling you  -  I want you to know that I never 
shall sell you while my head and yours is hot.”  I was 
trembling from head to foot, for I was powerless to 
do anything for her. My twin babies lived only six 
months after that, not having had the care they 
needed, and which it was impossible for their mother 
to give them while performing the almost endless 
labor required of her, under threats of cruel beatings. 
One day not long after our babies were buried the 
madam followed my wife to the smoke house and said: 
“I am tempted to take that knife from you, Matilda, 
and cut you in two. You and old Ruben (one of the 
slaves) went all around the neighborhood and told the 
people that I killed your babies, and almost whipped 
<pb id="hughes100" n="100"/>
you to death.”  Of course, when the slaves were accused 
falsely, as in this case, they were not allowed 
to make any reply  -  they just had to endure in silence 
whatever was said.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>EFFORTS TO LEARN TO READ AND WRITE.</head>
          <p>Thomas, the coachman, and I were fast friends. 
We used to get together every time we had a chance and 
talk about freedom. “Oh!” Tom would say, “if I 
could only write.” I remember when Tom first began 
to take lessons at night from some plasterers, workmen 
of the neighborhood. They saw that he was so 
anxious to learn that they promised to teach him 
every evening if he would slip out to their house. I, 
too, was eager to learn to read and write, but did not 
have the opportunity which Tom had of getting out 
at night. I had to sleep in the house where the folks 
were, and could not go out without being observed, 
while Tom had quarters in another part of the establishment, 
and could slip out unobserved. Tom, 
however, consoled me by saying that he would teach 
me as soon as he knew how. So Tom one night put 
a copy of some figures on the side of the barn for me 
to practice from. I took the chalk and imitated him 
as near as I could, but my work was poor beside his,
<pb id="hughes101" n="101"/>
as he had been learning for some months, and could 
make the figures quite well and write a little. Still I 
kept trying. Tom encouraging me and telling me 
that I would learn in time. “Just keep trying,” 
said he. When this first lesson was over, I forgot to 
rub out the marks on the barn, and the next morning 
when Old Master Jack, who happened to be at our 
home just at that time, went out there and saw the 
copy and my imitation of it, he at once raised great 
excitement by calling attention to the rude characters 
and wanting to know who had done that. I was 
afraid to own that I had done it; but old Master Jack 
somehow surmised that it was Tom or I, for he said 
to Boss:  “Edmund, you must watch those fellows, 
Louis and Thomas, if you don't they will get spoilt  -  
spoilt. They are pretty close to town here  -  here.”
Tom and I laughed over this a good deal and how 
easily we slipped out of it, but concluded not to stop 
trying to learn all we could. Tom always said: 
“Lou, I am going to be a free man yet, then we will 
need some education; no, let us never stop trying to 
learn.” Tom was a Virginian, as I was, and was sold 
from his parents when a mere lad.  Boss used to 
write to his parents (owners) occasionally, that his
<pb id="hughes102" n="102"/>
people might hear from him. The letters were to his 
mother, but sent in care of the white folks. Tom 
had progressed very fast in his secret studies, and 
could write enough to frame a letter. It seems it had 
been over a year since Boss had written for him, but 
nothing was said until one morning I heard Boss telling 
Tom to come to the barn to be whipped. He 
showed Tom three letters which he had written to his 
mother, and this so startled him that he said nothing. 
I listened breathlessly to each word Boss said: 
“Where did you learn to write?” asked he, “and 
when did you learn? How long have you been writing 
to your mother?” At that moment he produced 
the three letters which Tom had written. Boss, it 
seems, had mistrusted something, and spoke to the 
postmaster, telling him to stop any letters which Tom 
might mail for Virginia to his mother. The postmaster 
did as directed, for slaves had no rights which 
postmasters were bound to respect; hence, the letters 
fell into the master's hands instead of going to their 
destination. Tom, not hearing from his first letter, 
wrote a second, then a third, never dreaming that 
they had been intercepted. Boss raged and Tom was 
severely whipped. After this nothing Tom did
<pb id="hughes103" n="103"/>
pleased any of the family  -  it was a continual pick on 
him. Everything was wrong with both of us, for 
they were equally hard on me. They mistrusted, I 
think, that I could write; yet I could not find out just 
what they did think.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>TOM STRIKES FOR LIBERTY AND GAINS IT.</head>
          <p>Tom stayed only a few weeks after this. He said 
to me, one morning:  “Lou, I am going away. If I 
can get a boat to-night that is starting off, why, I am 
gone from this place.” I was sad to see him go, for 
he was like a brother to me  -  he was my companion 
and friend. He went, and was just in time to catch 
the boat at the Memphis dock. He succeeded in 
getting on, and made an application to the captain to 
work on the boat. The captain did not hesitate to 
employ him, as it was common for slaves to be permitted 
to hire themselves out for wages which they 
were required to return, in whole or in part, to their 
masters. Of course all such slaves carried a written 
pass to this effect. Tom was shrewd; and, having 
learned to write fairly well, he wrote himself a pass, 
which was of the usual kind, stating his name, to 
whom he belonged, and that he was privileged to 
hire himself out wherever he could, coming and going
<pb id="hughes104" n="104"/>
as he pleased. Where the slave was an exceptional 
one, and where the owner had only two or three 
slaves, a pass would readily be given to hire himself 
out, or hire his own time, as it was generally called, 
he being required to turn over to his master a certain 
amount of his earnings, each month or week, and to 
make a report to his master of his whereabouts and 
receipts. Sometimes the slave would be required to 
turn in to his master a certain sum, as, for instance, 
fifty or one hundred dollars a year; and he would 
have to earn that before he could use any of his earnings 
for himself. If he was a mechanic he would 
have little trouble in doing this, as the wages of such 
were often quite liberal. This kind of a pass was 
rarely, if ever, given by the planters having large 
numbers of slaves. Another kind of pass read something 
like this:  “Pass my boy or my girl,” as the 
case-might be, the name being attached. These were 
only given to permit the slave to go from the farm of 
his own master to that of another. Some men had 
wives or children belonging on neighboring farms, 
and would be given passes to visit them. Without 
such a pass they were liable to be stopped and turned 
back to their homes. There was, however, a good
<pb id="hughes105" n="105"/>
deal of visiting without passes, but it was against the 
general rule which required them; and any slave 
leaving home without a pass was liable to punishment 
if discovered. On our plantation passes were never 
given, but the slaves did visit in the neighborhood, 
notwithstanding, and would sometimes slip into town 
at night. Tom had in this way seen the pass of a 
neighboring slave to hire out; and it was from this he 
learned the form from which he wrote his, and which 
opened his way to freedom. Upon reading Tom's 
pass, the captain did not hesitate, but hired him at 
once; and Tom worked his way to New Orleans, to 
which city the boat was bound. In the meantime 
Boss took me and we drove to numerous stations, 
where he telegraphed ahead for his run-away boy 
Tom. But Tom reached New Orleans without hindrance, 
and there fell in with the steward of a Boston 
steamer, and, getting aboard of it, was soon on the 
ocean, on his way to that city where were so many 
friends of the slave. Arriving there he made his way 
to Canada; which was, for so many generations, the 
only land of freedom attainable to American slaves.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>NEWS OF TOM'S REACHING CANADA.</head>
          <p>Now that Tom was gone, excitement prevailed at
<pb id="hughes106" n="106"/>
the house among the white folks  -  nothing had been 
heard of him or the method of his escape. All the 
servants expected that he would be caught, and I was 
alarmed every time Boss came from the city, fearing 
that he had news that Tom was caught. He had been 
gone about six months, when, one morning, I went to 
the postoffice and brought back a letter. It seemed to 
me that I felt that it contained something unusual, 
but I did not know what it was. It proved to be a 
letter from Tom to Boss. They did not intend that 
the servants should know it was from Tom, but one 
of the house maids heard them reading it, and came 
out and told us. She whispered: “Tom is free; he 
has gone to Canada; Boss read it in the letter Lou 
brought.”  This news cheered me, and made me eager 
to get away; but I never heard from him any more 
until after the rebellion. Tom gone made my duties 
more. I now had to drive the carriage, but Uncle 
Madison was kept at the barn to do the work there, 
and hitch up the team  -  I only had to drive when the 
family went out.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>M'GEE EXPECTS TO CAPTURE TOM.</head>
          <p>In the summer the McGees made up their minds to go 
down east, and come around by Niagara Falls, for
<pb id="hughes107" n="107"/>
this was the place from which Tom had written them. 
Boss had great confidence in himself, and did not 
doubt his ability to take Tom home with him if he 
should meet him, even though it should be in Canada. 
So he took a pair of handcuffs with him as a preparation 
for the enterprise. His young nephew had been 
to Niagara Falls, and seen and talked with Tom; 
but Boss said if he had seen him anywhere he would have 
laid hands on him, at once, and taken him home, at 
all hazards.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>MAKING CLOTHES.</head>
          <p>When the family went on this visit down east I 
was left in charge of the house, and was expected to 
keep everything in order, and also to make the winter 
clothes for the farm hands. The madam and I had 
cut out these clothes before she left, and it was my 
principal duty to run the sewing machine in their 
manufacture. Many whole days I spent in this work. 
My wife made the button holes and sewed on the 
buttons. I made hundreds of sacks for use in picking 
cotton. This work was always done in summer. 
When the garments were all finished they were shipped 
to the farm at Bolivar, to be ready for the fall and 
winter wear. In like manner the clothes for summer 
use were made in winter.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="hughes108" n="108"/>
        <div2>
          <head>A SUPERSTITION.</head>
          <p>It was the custom in those days for slaves to carry 
voo-doo bags. It was handed down from generation 
to generation; and, though it was one of the superstitions 
of a barbarous ancestry, it was still very 
generally and tenaciously held to by all classes. I 
carried a little bag, which I got from an old slave who 
claimed that it had power to prevent any one who 
carried it from being whipped. It was made of 
leather, and contained roots, nuts, pins and some other 
things. The claim that it would prevent the folks 
from whipping me so much, I found, was not sustained 
by my experience  -  my whippings came just the same. 
Many of the servants were thorough believers in it 
though, and carried these bags all the time.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>MEMPHIS AND ITS COMMERCIAL IMPORTANCE.</head>
          <p>The city of Memphis, from its high bluff on the 
Mississippi, overlooks the surrounding country for a 
long distance. The muddy waters of the river, when 
at a low stage, lap the ever crumbling banks that 
yearly change, yielding to new deflections of the current. 
For hundreds of miles below there is a highly 
interesting and rarely broken series of forests, cane 
brakes and sand bars, covered with masses of willows
<pb id="hughes108a" n="108a"/>
<figure id="ill3" entity="hughes108"><p>[Image of Currency]</p></figure>
<pb id="hughes109" n="109"/>
and poplars which, in the spring, when the floods 
come down, are overflowed for many miles back. It 
was found necessary to run embankments practically 
parallel with the current, in order to confine the 
waters of the river in its channel. Memphis was and 
is the most important city of Tenessee, indeed, the 
most important between St. Louis and New Orleans, 
particularly from the commercial point of view. Cotton 
was the principal product of the territory tributary 
to it. The street running along the bluff was 
called Front Row, and was filled with stores and business 
houses. This street was the principal cotton 
market, and here the article which, in those days, was 
personified as the commercial “king,” was bought 
and sold, and whence it was shipped, or stored, awaiting 
an advancing price. The completion of the Memphis 
and Charleston railroad was a great event in the 
history of the city. It was termed the marriage of 
the Mississippi and the Atlantic, and was celebrated 
with a great popular demonstration, people coming 
from the surrounding country for many miles. Water 
was brought from the Atlantic ocean and poured into 
the river; and water taken from the river and poured 
into the Atlantic at Charleston. It was anticipated
<pb id="hughes110" n="110"/>
that this railroad connection between the two cities 
would make of Charleston the great shipping port, 
and of Memphis the principal cotton market of the 
southwest. The expectation in neither of these cases 
has been fully realized. Boss, in common with 
planters and business men throughout that whole 
region, was greatly excited. I attended him and thus 
had the opportunity of witnessing this notable celebration.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="illustration">
        <pb id="hughes110a" n="110a"/>
        <p>
<figure id="ill4" entity="hughes111"><p>[Image of Currency]</p></figure></p>
      </div1>
      <div1>
        <pb id="hughes111" n="111"/>
        <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
        <head>SLAVERY AND THE WAR OF THE REBELLION.</head>
        <div2>
          <head>BEGINNING OF THE WAR.</head>
          <p>I remember well when Abraham Lincoln was 
elected. Boss and the madam had been reading the 
papers, when he broke out with the exclamation: 
“The very idea of electing an old rail splitter to the 
presidency of the United States! Well he'll never 
take his seat.” When Lincoln was inaugurated, Boss, 
old Master Jack and a great company of men met at 
our house to discuss the matter, and they were wild 
with excitement. Was not this excitement an admission 
that their confidence in their ability to whip the 
Yankees, five or six to one, was not so strong as they 
pretended?</p>
          <p>The war had been talked of for some time, but at 
last it came. When the rebels fired upon Fort Sumpter, 
then great excitement arose. The next day when 
I drove Boss to town, he went into the store of one 
Williams, a merchant, and when he came out, he
<pb id="hughes112" n="112"/>
stepped to the carriage, and said:  “What do you think? 
Old Abraham Lincoln has called for four 
hundred thousand men to come to Washington immediately. 
Well, let them come; we will make a 
breakfast of them. I can whip a half dozen Yankees 
with my pocket knife.”  This was the chief topic 
everywhere. Soon after this Boss bought himself a 
six shooter. I had to mould the bullets for him, and 
every afternoon he would go out to practice. By his 
direction, I fixed a large piece of white paper on the 
back fence, and in the center of it put a large black 
dot. At this mark he would fire away, expecting to 
hit it; but he did not succeed well. He would sometimes 
miss the fence entirely, the ball going out into 
the woods beyond. Each time he would shoot I would 
have to run down to the fence to see how near he 
came to the mark. When he came very near to it  -  
within an inch or so, he would say laughingly:  Ah! 
I would have got him that time.” (Meaning a 
Yankee soldier.) There was something very ludicrous 
in this pistol practice of a man who boasted that he 
could whip half a dozen Yankees with a jacknife. 
Every day for a month this business, so tiresome to 
me, went on. Boss was very brave until it came time
<pb id="hughes113" n="113"/>
for him to go to war, when his courage oozed out, and 
he sent a substitute; he remaining at home as a 
“home guard.” One day when I came back with the 
papers from the city, the house was soon ringing with 
cries of victory.  Boss said: “Why, that was a great 
battle at Bull Run.  If our men had only known, at 
first, what they afterwards found out, they would 
have wiped all the Yankees out, and succeeded in taking 
Washington.”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>PETTY DISRESPECT TO THE EMBLEM OF THE UNION.</head>
          <p>Right after the bombardment of Fort Sumpter, 
they brought to Memphis the Union flag that floated 
over the fort. There was a great jubilee in celebration 
of this. Portions of the flag, no larger than a 
half dollar in paper money, were given out to the 
wealthy people, and these evidences of their treason 
were long preserved as precious treasures. Boss had 
one of these pieces which he kept a long time; but, as 
the rebel cause waned these reminders of its beginning 
were less and less seen, and if any of them are 
now in existence, it is not likely that their possessors 
will take any pride in exposing them to view.</p>
          <p>As the war continued we would, now and then, 
hear of some slave of our neighborhood running
<pb id="hughes114" n="114"/>
away to the Yankees. It was common when the message 
of a Union victory came to see the slaves 
whispering to each other:  “We will be free.” I 
tried to catch everything I could about the war, I was 
so eager for the success of the Union cause. These 
things went on until</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>THE BATTLE OF SHILOH, APRIL 9, 1862.</head>
          <p>Boss came hurrying in one morning, right after 
breakfast, calling to me:  “Lou, Lou, come; we have 
a great victory! I want to go up and carry the boys 
something to eat. I want you and Matilda to get 
something ready as quickly as you can.” A barrel of 
flour was rolled into the kitchen, and my wife and I 
“pitched in” to work.  Biscuit, bread, hoe-cake, ham, 
tongue  -  all kinds of meat and bread were rapidly 
cooked; and, though the task was a heavy one for my 
wife and me, we worked steadily; and, about five 
o'clock in the afternoon the things were ready. One 
of the large baskets used to hold cotton was 
packed full these provisions. Our limbs ached from the 
strain of the work, for we had little help. One reason 
for the anxiety of the Boss for the preparation of this 
provision for the soldiers was that he knew so many 
in one of the companies, which was known as the
<pb id="hughes115" n="115"/>
“Como Avengers,” and he had a son, a nephew and a 
brother of his wife connected with it; the latter a 
major on Gen. Martin's staff. On the following morning 
I got up early, and hurried with my work to get 
through, as I had to go to the postofflce. Madam 
hurried me off, as she expected a letter from her husband, 
who had promised to write, at the earliest moment, 
of their friends and relatives. I rushed into 
the city, at full speed, got some letters and a morning 
paper, and, returning as rapidly as possible, gave 
them to her. She grasped them eagerly, and 
commenced reading the paper. In a short time I 
heard her calling me to come to her. I went in, and 
she said, in great excitement:  “Louis, we want to 
have you drive us into town, to see the Yankee 
prisoners, who are coming through, at noon, from 
Shiloh.” I went and told Madison to hitch up, as 
soon as he could. In the meantime I got myself 
ready, and it was not long before we were off for the 
city. The madam was accompanied by a friend of 
hers, a Mrs. Oliver. We were at the station in plenty 
of time. About twelve o'clock the train from Shiloh 
drew into the station; but the prisoners that were 
reported to be on board were missing  -  it proved to be
<pb id="hughes116" n="116"/>
a false report. While they were looking for the 
prisoners, Mrs. Oliver saw Jack, a servant of Edward 
McGee, brother of madam. “Oh! Look,” said Mrs. 
Oliver, “there is Edward's Jack. Lou, run and call 
him.” In a minute I was off the carriage, leaving the 
reins in madam's hands. Jack came up to the 
carriage, and the women began to question him: 
“Where is your Master, Ed,” asked both of them. 
“He is in the car, Missis  -  he is shot in the ankle,” 
said Jack. In a minute the women were crying. “I 
was going to get a hack,” said Jack, “to  -  ”  “No, 
No!” said both of them. “Go, Lou, and help Jack to 
bring him to our carriage. You can drive him more 
steadily than the hackman.”  Jack and I went to the 
car, and helped him out, and after some effort, got 
him into our carriage. Then I went and got a livery 
hack to take the women and his baggage home. 
When we reached home, we found there old Mrs. Jack 
McGee, mother of the madam, Mrs. Charles Dandridge, 
Mrs. Farrington, sisters of madam, and 
Fanny, a colored woman, Edward's housekeeper and 
mistress  -  a wife in all but name. All of these had 
come to hear the news of the great battle, for all had 
near relatives in it. Mrs. Jack McGee and Mrs. Dr. 
<pb id="hughes117" n="117"/>
Charles Dandridge had each a son in the terrible 
conflict.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>MOURNING IN MASTER'S FAMILY.</head>
          <p>In the afternoon, when all were seated in the 
library reading, and I was in the dining room, finishing 
up my work, I happened to look out of the window, 
and saw a messenger coming up the graveled 
walk. I went out to meet him.  “Telegram for Mrs. 
McGee,” he said. I took it to her; and, reading it 
without a word, she passed it to the next member of 
the family, and so it was passed around until all had 
read it except Mrs. Dandridge. When it was handed 
to her, I saw, at a glance, that it contained for her 
the most sorrowful tidings. As she read she became 
livid, and when she had finished she covered her face 
with her handkerchief, giving a great, heavy sob. 
By this time the whole family was crying and 
screaming: “Oh! our Mack is killed.”  “Mars, Mack 
is killed,” was echoed by the servants, in tones of 
heart-felt sorrow, for he was an exceptional young 
man. Every one loved him  -  both whites and blacks. 
The affection of the slaves for him bordered on 
reverence, and this was true not alone of his father's 
slaves, but of all those who knew him. This telegram
<pb id="hughes118" n="118"/>
was from Boss, and announced that he would be home 
the next day with the remains. Mrs. Farrington at 
once wrote to old Master Jack and to Dr. Dandridge, 
telling them of Mack's death and to come at once. 
After I mailed those letters nothing unusual happened 
during the afternoon, and the house was wrapped in 
silence and gloom. On the following morning I went 
for the mail as usual, but there was nothing new. At 
noon, the remains of the much loved young man 
arrived at our station, accompanied by Boss and Dr. 
Henry Dandridge, brother of the father of the deceased, 
who was a surgeon in the rebel army. I went 
to the station with another servant, to assist in bringing 
the body to the house. We carried it into the 
back parlor, and, after all had been made ready, 
we proceeded to wash and dress it. He had lain on the 
battlefield two days before he was found, and his face 
was black as a piece of coal; but Dr. Henry Dandridge, 
with his ready tact, suggested the idea of painting 
it. I was there to assist in whatever way they needed 
me. After the body was all dressed, and the face 
painted, cheeks tinted with a rosy hue, to appear as 
he always did in life, the look was natural and handsome. 
We were all the afternoon employed in this
<pb id="hughes119" n="119"/>
sad work, and it was not until late in the evening 
that his father and mother came down to view the 
body for the first time. I remember, as they came 
down the broad stairs together, the sorrow-stricken 
yet calm look of those two people. Mrs. Dandridge 
was very calm  -  her grief was too great for her to 
scream as the others did when they went in.  She 
stood and looked at her Mack; then turning to Boss, 
she said: “Cousin Eddie, how brave he was! He died 
for his country.”  Poor, sorrowing, misguided woman! 
It was not for his country he died, but for the perpetuation 
of the cruel, the infamous system of human 
slavery. All the servants were allowed to come in 
and view the body. Many sad tears were shed by 
them. Some of the older slaves clasped their hands, 
as if in mute prayer, and exclaimed, as they passed 
by the coffin:  “He was a lovin boy.” It seems that 
all his company but five or six were killed. At an 
early hour next morning the funeral party started for 
the home in Panola, where the body of the lamented 
young man, sacrificed to an unholy cause, was buried, 
at the close of the same day.</p>
          <p>Edward stayed at our house some six weeks, his 
ankle was so slow in getting well. At the end of
<pb id="hughes120" n="120"/>
that time, he could walk with the aid of crutches, and 
he took Fanny and went home.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>ALARM OF THE MEMPHIS REBELS.</head>
          <p>Not long after this the people were very much 
worked up over the military situation. The Yankees 
had taken Nashville, and had begun to bombard Fort 
Pillow. The officials of the Memphis and Ohio railroad 
company became alarmed at the condition of 
things, fearing for the safety of their stock. The officers, 
therefore, set about devising some plan by which 
they might get the cars down on the Memphis and 
Jackson road, where they imagine their property 
would be safe from the now terrible Yankees. The 
railroad officials at once set to work to buy the right 
of way through Main street, to give them the 
connection with the southern road named. At first it 
was refused by the city authorities, but finally the 
right of way was granted. When, however, the railroad 
men began to lay the ties and rails, the people 
grew furious. Some fled at once, for they imagined 
that this act of the railroad officials indicated that 
the Yankees must be coming pretty near. Boss became 
so excited, at this time, that he almost felt like 
going away too. The family grew more and more
<pb id="hughes121" n="121"/>
uneasy; and it was the continual talk:  “We must 
get away from Memphis. The companies are already 
moving their rolling stock, fearing the Yankees may 
come at any time and destroy everything; we must 
get away,” said Boss, speaking to the madam.”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>THE FAMILY FLEE FROM MEMPHIS.</head>
          <p>Things continued in this way until about June, 
1862. The Union troops had taken Fort Pillow. We 
had heard the firing of cannon, and did not know 
what it meant. One morning I was in the city after 
the mail, and I learned that a transient boat had just 
come down the river, which had lost a part of her 
wheelhouse. She was fired on from Fort Pillow, 
sustaining this serious damage from the shot. This 
increased the excitement among the people; and our 
folks became alarmed right away, and commenced 
talking of moving and running the servants away 
from the Yankees, to a place of safety. McGee was 
trying for some time to get some one to take the 
house, that is, to live in and care for it until after the 
war, while the family were gone. They never thought 
that slavery would be abolished, and so hoped to come 
back again. After some search, they found a widow, 
a Mrs. Hancock. She was to have full charge of the 
<pb id="hughes122" n="122"/>
house and continue keeping boarders, as she had been 
doing in Memphis. The vaunted courage of this 
man seems to have early disappeared, and his thought 
was chiefly devoted to getting his family and his 
slaves into some obscure place, as far away as possible 
from the Yankees, that were to be so easily 
whipped. We were about two weeks getting ready to 
leave, stowing away some of the things they did not 
want to move. The Boss and his family, my wife and 
I, and all the house servants were to go to Panola, to 
his father's. The family went by rail, but I had to 
drive through in a wagon.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>I AM TAKEN TO BOLIVAR FARM.</head>
          <p>Soon after the family all reached Master Jack's, 
Boss took me to his own farm in Bolivar county. This 
separated me for a time from my wife, for she remained 
with the family. I had to look after the 
house at the farm, attend the dining room, and, between 
meals, sew every day, making clothes for the 
hands. I could run on the machine eighteen to twenty 
pairs of pants a day, but two women made the button 
holes and did the basting for me, getting the goods 
all ready for the machine.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="hughes123" n="123"/>
        <div2>
          <head>CAPTURE OF A UNION TRADING BOAT.</head>
          <p>The Yankees had made a raid through Bolivar, before 
 I came, and the excitement had not abated, as 
 they were spreading themselves all through the state. 
 There was a Union trading boat, the Lake City, that 
 had been successful in exchanging her goods for 
 cotton that came from Memphis. She usually stopped 
 at Helena, Fryer's Point and other small towns; but 
 on a trip at this time she came about fifty miles 
 farther down the river, to Carson's Landing, right at 
 Boss' farm. She was loaded with all kinds of  
 merchandise  -  sugar, tobacco, liquor, etc. She had a 
 crew of about forty men, but they were not well prepared 
 for a vigorous defense. The rebel soldiers 
 stationed in the vicinity saw her as she dropped her 
 anchor near the landing, and they determined to make 
 an effort for her capture. They put out pickets just 
 above our farm, and allowed no one to pass, or stop to 
 communicate with the boat. Every one that sought 
 to pass was held prisoner, and every precaution taken 
 to prevent those on the boat from learning of the purposes 
 of the rebels, knowing that the boat would land 
 in the morning, if not informed of the danger, and 
 then it was anticipated that they could easily make
<pb id="hughes124" n="124"/>
her a prize. There was a small ferry boat behind the 
steamer, and as the latter dropped down stream, and 
then steamed up to the landing, the former stood off 
for a few moments. As the steamer touched shore, the 
rebels charged on her, and captured her without a 
struggle. In the meantime the ferry boat, seeing 
what had happened, sped away up stream, the soldiers 
firing at her, but doing little damage, except the 
breaking of the glass in the pilot house. The rebels, 
seeing that the ferry boat had escaped them, turned 
their attention to the unloading of the steamer. They 
sent out for help in this work, and the summons was 
answered by the neighbors far and near. Wagons 
were brought, two of which were from our farm, and 
loaded with goods, which were taken to Deer Creek, 
forty miles from Carson Landing. What goods they 
found themselves unable to carry away were packed 
in the warehouse. The steamer was then burned. 
McGee was present, and the rebel captain gave him a 
written statement of the affair to the effect that the 
residents were not responsible for it, and that this 
should be a protection for them against the Union 
forces. The officers and crew of the steamer to the 
number of forty were made prisoners, and taken to
<pb id="hughes125" n="125"/>
Deer Creek, the rebel headquarters of that region, 
and put in the jail there. The ferry boat that escaped 
went to Helena, Arkansas, and carried the
news of the affair to the Union forces there.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>BOSS TAKEN PRISONER.</head>
          <p>I was told by Boss to take my stand on our veranda, 
and keep watch on the river, and if I saw any 
boat coming down to let him know at once. I kept a 
close watch the next morning until about eight 
o'clock, when I saw a boat, but she had almost gone 
past our house before I discovered her. I ran into the 
house and told Boss. He ordered me to get his horse 
at once, which I did; and he mounted and went down 
to the landing as fast as he could. Upon reaching 
there, he was taken prisoner by the Union soldiers, 
who had just landed from the boat. All who came 
near were captured. The Union soldiers went to 
work and transferred all the goods which the rebels 
had put into the warehouse from the boat which they 
had captured, then setting fire to the warehouse and 
the postoffice, they pushed off yelling and shouting 
with glee.  Among those captured by the Union 
soldiers were three other rich planters besides Boss, 
all of whom were taken to Helena. After they had
<pb id="hughes126" n="126"/>
been there about a week, the planters offered to secure 
the release of the Unionists captured on the 
boat which the rebels had burned at Carson Landing, 
and who had been sent to the rebel jail at Deer Creek, 
if they were guaranteed their own release in exchange. 
They offered to bear the expense of a messenger 
to the rebel officer, at Deer Creek, with this 
proposition. The Union officer at Helena accepted 
the proposition, and the messenger was sent off. It 
was arranged that he should stop over at our house,
both on his way down and back. Upon his return, he 
stopped over night, and the next morning proceeded 
on his way. When he had gone about five miles, he 
saw a flat-boat at a landing, on which were people 
drinking and having a merry time. He stopped, and 
went aboard; and, in joining the carousal, he soon 
became so intoxicated that he was unable to go on 
with his journey. Among those present was one Gilcrease, 
a cousin of the McGees, who recognized the 
man as the messenger in this important business, went 
to him and asked him for the letters he carried. The 
fellow refusing to give them up, Gilcrease took them 
from him, and at once sent to our overseer for a reliable 
man by whom to forward them to the commandant
<pb id="hughes127" n="127"/>
at Helena. The overseer called me up from the 
cabin to his room, and told me that I was to go to 
Helena to carry some important papers, and to come 
to him for them in the morning, and make an early 
start. I left him and went back to my cabin.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>MY THIRD EFFORT FOR FREEDOM.</head>
          <p>I made up my mind that this would be a good 
chance for me to run away. I got my clothes, and 
put them in an old pair of saddle bags  -  two bags 
made of leather, connected with a strip of leather, 
and used when traveling horseback for the same purpose 
as a satchel is used in traveling in the cars. I 
took these bags, carried them about a half mile up 
the road, and hid them in a fence corner, where I 
could get them in the morning when I had started 
on my trip. Fryer's Point, the place to which I was to 
go, was about fifty miles from the farm. I started 
early in the morning, and, after I had gone twenty-five 
miles, I came to the farm of William McGee, a 
brother of the madam, and stopped to change horses. 
I found that William McGee was going, in the morning, 
down to old Master Jack's; so I took one of their 
horses, leaving mine to use in its place, went right to 
Fryer's Point, delivered the letters to a man there to
<pb id="hughes128" n="128"/>
carry to Helena, and got back to William McGee's 
farm that night. I made up my mind to go with 
William down to Panola, where madam was, to tell 
her about Boss being captured. The next morning, 
he started, and Gibson, his overseer and myself 
accompanied him. He questioned me about the 
capture of Boss, what the soldiers had done, etc., and 
I told him all I knew of the matter.  “Well, Lou,” 
he said, “why did you not bring us some whisky?” 
“I did bring a little with me,” I said. He laughed, 
saying: “Oh, well, when we come to some clear water 
we will stop and have a drink.”  Then I said:  “Mr. 
Smith will look for me tonight, but he wont see me. 
I am going to tell the madam that Boss is captured.” 
“Hey, ho!” he said, “then you are running away.” 
I replied: “Well I know Miss Sarah dont know Boss 
is in prison.”  We traveled on, all three of us, stopping 
at intervals to be refreshed. After two days, we 
arrived at Panola. Our journey was a tedious one. 
The streams were so swollen in places that we could 
hardly pass. The Tallehatchie we had to swim, and 
one of the men came near losing his horse and his 
life. The horses became tangled in a grape vine, as 
we were nearing the shore at which we aimed, and, 
<pb id="hughes129" n="129"/>
the current being very swift, we were carried below 
the landing place; but, finally, we got safely ashore, 
McGee landing, and we following.  Reaching Panola, 
wet and weary, I conveyed to madam the story of her 
husband's capture and imprisonment, a rumor of 
which had already reached her.</p>
          <p>The next morning was Christmas, and a number 
of the family had come to spend it together. They 
had heard that McGee was captured and in prison; 
but, now, as I told them every feature of the affair in 
detail, they grew excited and talked wildly about it. 
Among those who came were Dr. Dandridge and his 
wife, Blanton McGee and his wife, Tim Oliver and 
his wife. All these women were daughters of old 
Master Jack McGee, and sisters to the madam. Mrs. 
Farrington and old lady McGee were already there. 
These re-unions on Christmas were a long established 
custom with them, but the pleasure of this one was 
sadly marred by the vicisitudes and calamities of the 
war. A shadow hung over all the family group. 
They asked me many questions about Boss, and, of 
course, I related all I knew.</p>
          <p>After I had been there three days, they started me 
back with letters for Boss.  When I left it was near
<pb id="hughes130" n="130"/>
night, and I was to stop over at Master Jack's farm 
fifteen miles away. It was expected that I would 
reach Fryer's Point on the third morning, thus allowing 
me three days to go sixty miles; but I could not 
make much headway, as the roads were so heavy. 
The understanding was that I was to deliver the 
letters to the same gentleman, at Fryer's, to whom I 
delivered the others, for forwarding to Boss at Helena. 
I was then to go straight to the farm at Boliver, and 
report to Smith, the overseer. But after I had got about 
four miles away, I concluded that I would not 
go back to the farm, but try to get to the Yankees. I 
knew I had disobeyed Smith by going down to the 
madam's to tell her about Boss, because he told me 
not to go when I spoke to him about it. And now if 
I went back I feared he would kill me; for I knew 
there would be no escape for me from being run into 
the bull ring, and that torture I could not think of 
enduring. I, therefore, stopped, and, taking the 
bridle and saddle from the horse, hid them in the 
corner of a fence in a cornfield. Then I went into the 
woods. The papers which I had were in the saddlebag 
safe. The place where I stayed in the daytime 
was in a large shuck-pen  -  a pen built in the field to
<pb id="hughes131" n="131"/>
feed stock from, in the winter time. This pen was on 
Dr. Dandridge's farm; and the second night I worked 
my way up near the house. Knowing all the servants, 
I was watching a chance to send word to the coachman, 
Alfred Dandridge, that I wanted him to tell my 
wife that I was not gone. I went down to his cabin, 
in the quarters; and, after a short time he came. I 
was badly scared, and my heart was heavy and sore; 
but he spoke comfortingly to me, and I was cheered, 
somewhat, especially when he promised to see 
Matilda, and tell her of my whereabouts.  He gave 
me some food, and hid me away for the night in his 
house. I kept close all the next day; and, at night, 
when all was still, Alfred and I crept out, and went 
to old Master Jack's. The distance was not great, 
and we soon covered it. Alfred went in and told my 
wife that I was outside and wanted to see her. She 
came out, and was so frightened and nervous that she 
commenced sobbing and crying, and almost fainted 
when I told her, in low tones, that I was going to try 
to get to Memphis, and that Alfred was helping to 
plan a way to this end. The rebels occupied both 
roads leading to Memphis, and I was puzzled to know 
how to reach the city without coming in contact
<pb id="hughes132" n="132"/>
with them. Two days after I had talked with my 
wife, the rebel troops who were camped on the Holly 
Springs road left for some other point. My friend 
Alfred found this out, and came and told me the 
encouraging news. The following night I went to 
old Master Jack's and told my wife that the way now 
seemed clear, and that I was going at once. I was 
bent on freedom, and would try for it again.  I urged 
my wife not to grieve, and endeavored to encourage 
her by saying that I would return for her, as soon as 
possible, should I succeed in getting to a land freedom. 
After many tears and blessings, we parted, and 
I left, Uncle Alfred going with me some three miles, 
as I was not acquainted with the road. When he left 
me I went on alone with gloomy forebodings, but 
resolved to do my best in this hazardous undertaking, 
whatever might happen. The road passed over hills 
and through swamps, and I found the traveling very 
wearisome. I had travelled some hours, and thought 
I was doing well; when, about one o'clock in the 
night, I came up out of a long swamp, and, reaching 
the top of a hill, I stopped for a moment's rest, raising 
myself to an erect position from that of walking, 
inclined by reason of weariness and the weight of the 
<pb id="hughes133" n="133"/>
<sic>saddle - bags</sic> thrown across my shoulders. The 
weather was bad, a heavy mist had come up, and it 
was so dark that I could hardly see my way. As I 
started on, a soldier yelled at me from the mist: 
“Halt! advance and give the countersign.”  I stopped 
immediately, almost scared out of my wits.  “Come 
right up here,” said the soldier, “or I'll blow you into 
eternity.” I saw at once he was a rebel soldier. I 
knew not what to do. This place where I was halted 
was Nelson's farm, and the house was held as headquarters 
for a company of rebel soldiers, known as 
bushwhackers. While they belonged to the rebel 
army, they were, in a measure, independent of its 
regulations and discipline, kept back in the woods, 
ready for any depredation upon the property of unionists  -  
any outrage upon their persons. The soldier 
who had halted me took me up to the house, and all 
began to question me. I told them that I had been 
sent on an errand, and that I had lost my way. The 
next morning I was taken about a mile away down in 
the swamp, over hills and through winding paths, till 
at last we came to the regular rebel camp. I was in 
great fear and thought my end had come. Here they 
began to question me again  -  the captain taking the
<pb id="hughes134" n="134"/>
lead; but I still stuck to my story that I had been sent 
on an errand, and had lost my way. I knew that this 
was my only chance. They tried to make me say 
that I had come from the Yankees, as they were in 
camp near Holly Springs. They thought the Yankees 
had sent me out as a spy; but I said the same as at 
first  -  that I had lost my way. A soldier standing by 
said:  “Oh! we will make you talk better than that;” 
and stepping back to his horse, he took a sea-grass 
halter, and said:  “I'll hang you.” There was a law 
or regulation of the rebel government directing or 
authorizing the hanging of any slave caught running 
away; and this fellow was going to carry it out to the 
letter. I talked and pleaded for my life. My feelings 
were indescribable. God only knows what they were. 
Dr. Carter, one of the soldiers, who knew me and the 
entire McGee family, spoke up and said:  “You had 
better let me go and tell Mr. Jack McGee about him.” 
The captain agreed to this, and the doctor went. The 
following day, Old Jack came, and steadily refused to 
consent to my being hung. He said:  “I know Edmund 
would not have him hung-ung. He is too valuable-aluable. 
No, no! we will put him in jail and feed 
him on bread and water  -  too valuable a nigger to be 
hung-ung.”</p>
          <pb id="hughes135" n="135"/>
          <p>They tried again to make me say that I was with 
the Yankees. They whipped me a while, then 
questioned me again. The dog-wood switches that 
they used stung me terribly. They were commonly 
used in Mississippi for flogging slaves  -  one of the refinements 
of the cruelty of the institution of slavery. 
I refused to say anything different from what I had 
said; but when they had finished whipping me I was 
so sore I could hardly move. They made up their 
minds to put me in jail at Panola, twenty-two miles 
away, to be fed on bread and water. The next day  
was Sunday, and all arrangements having been made 
for taking me to the place appointed for those whose 
crime was a too great love for personal freedom, they 
started with me, passing on the way Old Master 
Jack's, where they halted to let him know that his 
advice respecting me was to be carried out. The old
man called to my wife:  “Come out and see Louis.” 
Some one had told her that they were going to hang 
me; and I shall never forget her looks as she came 
out in the road to bid me good-by. One of the 
soldiers was softened by her agony, and whispered to 
her:  “Don't cry, aunty, we are not going to hang 
him  -  we will only put him in jail.”  I saw this 
<pb id="hughes136" n="136"/>
changed my wife's looks in a minute. I said a few 
words to her, and, with a prayer for God's blessing on 
us both, we parted, and they moved on. After we had 
gone about seven miles, we met two soldiers, who belonged 
to the regiment at Nelson. They said: 
“Hello! where you going with that rigger?”  The 
two men in charge of me replied: “We are going to 
take trim to Panola jail.”  “Why,” said one of the 
soldiers, “there is no jail there; the Yanks passed 
through and pulled down the doors and windows of the 
jail, and let all the prisoners out.” This caused 
a stop; and a council of war was held in the fence 
corner, the result of which was a decision to take me 
back to old Jack McGee's. After we had gotten back 
there, they took me and gave me another flogging to 
satisfy the madam. I was never so lacerated before. 
I could hardly walk, so sore and weak was I. The 
law was given me that if ever I was caught out in the 
public road again, by any soldier, I was to be shot. 
Monday morning I was sent to the field to plow; and, 
though I was very stiff and my flesh seemed sore to 
the bone, my skin drawn and shriveled as if dead, I 
had, at least, to make the attempt to work. To have 
said:  “Master, I am too sore to work,” would only 
<pb id="hughes136a" n="136a"/>
<figure id="ill5" entity="hughes136"><p>[Image of Currency]</p></figure>
<pb id="hughes137" n="137"/>
have gotten me another whipping. So I obeyed without 
a word.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>REBELS BURN THEIR COTTON.</head>
          <p>The capture of Memphis by the Union troops 
closed the principal cotton market of the country, and 
there was, as a consequence, an immense accumulation 
of the product in the hands of the farmers of 
that region. They were, therefore, compelled to resort 
to temporary expedients for its protection from 
the elements. Old Master Jack had his piled up in a 
long rick, and shelters built over it. Other farmers 
did the same. As cotton was almost the only source 
of revenue for the farmers, and as there was now no 
opportunity of getting it to market, there was such a 
dearth of money as had seldom, if ever, been known, 
and a corresponding dearth of those necessaries of 
life which money was the only means of procuring. 
The accumulations of our family in this product were 
very great. While the rebel farmers were waiting for 
a time when they could turn their stores of this valuable 
article into money, proclamation was issued by 
the rebel government that all the owners of cotton 
that had it stored on their farms must prepare to have 
it burned, Hundreds of rebel soldiers marched to
<pb id="hughes138" n="138"/>
every section of Mississippi that they could reach, and 
applied the torch to these cotton ricks. The destruction 
was enormous. This was to prevent the cotton 
from falling into the hands of the Unionists. Jeff 
Davis said to his deluded followers that it was better 
for them to destroy this property than to risk its coming 
into the possession of their enemies, since that 
would equally impoverish themselves, while it might 
result to the pecuniary advantage of those with whom 
they were at war. I know that it was a terrible sight 
when our cotton was burned. Hundreds of bales were 
consumed, and it seemed like a wholly unnecessary 
destruction of property, and, therefore, unwise as a 
war measure. Many were sorry that they had acquiesced 
in the policy, as it cost them thousands of dollars, 
and made many poor. They thought that possibly 
their farms might have escaped the visits of the 
Union soldiers, and the property, so much needed, 
been saved in whole or in part. They reasoned, and 
reasoned correctly, that their condition would in no 
sense have been worse if their cotton had not been 
burned by their own soldiers, but might have been 
much better in many cases, without any real detriment 
to the rebel cause. The sacrifice of the property
<pb id="hughes139" n="139"/>
of their own people by the rebel authorities, was evidence 
of the desperation of the condition of the rebellion, 
and was so regarded by not a few at that 
time. Those were terrible days. One could see 
anxiety written on every face among the whites. 
The slaves even looked worried at times, though the 
war meant so much to them, as they were always 
looking forward to freedom, at its close, if the Union 
troops were successful.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>MY FOURTH RUNAWAY TRIP.</head>
          <p>After I had been working on the farm about two 
months, and had thoroughly talked the matter over 
with Alfred Dandridge, we planned to make a careful 
and persistent effort to escape from the land of bondage. 
We thought that as others, here and there, all 
through the neighborhood, were going, we would 
make trial of it. My wife and I were at old Master 
Jacks; and, after we had consulted with Alfred and 
Lydia, his wife, we all concluded to go at once. 
Alfred had been a teamster for Dandridge for many 
years, and was familiar with the road, as he had 
hauled cotton into Memphis for his master for so long 
a time he could hardly tell when he began. Matt 
Dandridge was a fellow servant, belonging to the
<pb id="hughes140" n="140"/>
same man, and both had, as was not unusual, taken 
their master's name, or, rather, were known by it. 
Matt had learned of our purpose to run away, and 
concluded to join our party. So one night, when all 
was still, we started. Uncle Alfred, as I always called 
him, was to be our leader. He was older than any of 
the rest of us, and had had a good deal of experience; 
we, therefore, all looked to him  -  in fact, we relied 
entirely upon him. After we had traveled about 
twelve miles, we came to a swamp, called Hicke-Halley. 
Here we stopped, as day was dawning, and 
settled down for the day, as we could travel only in 
the night, lest we should be seen and caught. We 
were wet  -  our clothes soaked through from the heavy 
dew. We had to travel through corn fields, cotton 
patches, oat fields and underbrush, not daring to take 
the main road. This is why we were so wet. Uncle 
Alfred traveled wholly by the stars  -  they were his 
guide. He knew by looking at them the four cardinal 
points of the compass. Many old slaves were guided 
in this way when traveling in the night, and some 
could tell the time of night by the position of the 
stars. We stayed in Hicke-Halley all day, and in the 
evening, when it was dark enough, we started on 
<pb id="hughes141" n="141"/>
again, Uncle Alfred offering up a prayer to God to 
guide us safely through. Cold Water was our next 
stopping place, and here a difficulty rose before us 
that made us fearful. We had nothing to wear but
what we had on, and not much of that, so had small 
space for carrying anything, and, therefore, had 
brought with us only a little bite to eat.  As we had 
lived on this small provision for a day, there was now 
but little left for our increasing wants; and the difficulty 
of securing anything from the houses without 
danger of detection was almost insurmountable. But 
we felt encouraged as we thought of what we were 
striving for, and sped on our way. But the way was 
hard, for sometimes we got completely stuck in brier 
patches, and had to turn and go back, in order to find 
a way out. Old logs and driftwood, that had been 
piled up year after year, were other obstacles in our 
way; and one can imagine how hard it was to make 
our way through such a mass of brush and forrest by 
the dim light of the stars as they struggled through 
the dense branches of the trees. We stumbled on, 
however, as best we could, each fearful, yet silently 
praying for guidance and help. When within four 
or five miles of Cold Water, Uncle Alfred stopped
<pb id="hughes142" n="142"/>
cautioned us not to speak above a whisper, as the 
rebel troops were camped on both sides of us. We 
were in a swamp between the two roads, gradually 
working our way through to the river, as we could not 
go on either of the roads for fear of detection. At 
the bridges, where these roads crossed the river, there 
were rebel camps, and it was useless for us to think of 
crossing either. We, therefore, worked our way carefully 
through the thicket that we were in until we 
came within sight of the river. Then Uncle Alfred 
went ahead, creeping a few steps, then stopping to 
see if the river was clear of soldiers. From this 
point it was some two and a half miles to the bridges, 
each way; and it was our idea that if we could cross 
here without being seen by the soldiers, we would be 
all right. Uncle Alfred came back to us and told us 
that he thought the way was clear.  “I can not hear 
a sound,” said he, “so let us go on.”  We followed 
the river down until we came to a place where we 
could cross. Here we found some drift-wood  -  an old 
tree had been blown down, nearly across the river, 
leaving a space of about twenty feet. Over this 
natural bridge we crept to the open space which we 
waded, the water being up to our knees; but we did 
<pb id="hughes143" n="143"/>
not mind this. There was no talking above a 
whisper, for fear of being heard by the soldiers. 
Daylight had begun to dawn, and we felt good that 
we had succeeded thus far. We went on quietly until 
we got entirely out of the swamp and reached some 
hills. The woods were on each side of us and still 
thick; so we stopped here, on the side of a hill, where 
the sun shone brightly on us, expecting to rest for the 
day. Our clothes had already become quite dry from 
the sunshine; and, so far, we felt all right. Alfred 
and I had made a turn around the place, listening to 
see if we could hear any noise, or see any trace of 
soldiers; but we discovered no trace of them, and 
went back to our stopping place. I had been asleep 
and some of the others were still asleep, when suddenly 
I heard the yelp of blood hounds in the distance. 
It seemed quite far away at first, but the sound came 
nearer and nearer, and then we heard men yelling. 
We knew now that they were on our trail, and became 
so frightened that we all leaped to our feet, and were 
about to run, when Uncle Alfred said:  “Stop children, 
let me oil you feet.”  He had with him a bottle 
of ointment made of turpentine and onions, a preparation 
used to throw hounds off a trail. All stopped; 
<pb id="hughes144" n="144"/>
and the women, having their feet anointed first, 
started off, Uncle Alfred telling them to run in different 
directions. He and I were the last to start. 
Alfred said:  “Don't let the bushes touch you;” at the 
same time he ran through the bushes with such a 
rattling noise one could have heard him a great distance. 
He wore one of those old fashioned oil cloth 
coats made in Virginia; and, as he ran, the bushes, 
striking against the coat, made a noise like the beating 
of a tin board with sticks. The funny part of it 
was that, having cautioned us to be careful about 
noise, he made more than all of us. By this time the 
woods were resounding with the yelping of the hounds 
and the cries of their masters. The hounds 
numbered some fourteen. The men howled and 
cheered in concert with the brutes, for they knew that 
they were on the right trail, and it would be but a 
short time before they caught us all. I had gotten 
further away than any of them. Having run about a 
mile, I came to a farm, and started across an open 
field, hoping to reach a wood beyond, where I might 
conceal myself. Before I was half way across the 
field, on looking back, I saw the dogs coming over the 
fence, and knowing there was no chance of my getting
<pb id="hughes145" n="145"/>
to the woods, I turned around, and ran back to a 
persimmon tree, and just had time to run up one of the 
branches when the dogs came upon the ground. I 
looked and saw the men, Williams the nigger-catcher, 
and Dr. Henry and Charles Dandridge. As soon 
as Williams rode up, he told me to come down, 
but I was so frightened I began to cry, yet came 
down trembling. The dogs laid hold of me at once, 
tearing my clothes and biting my flesh. Dr. Dandridge 
was just riding up, and seeing what was happening, 
yelled out to Williams: “I thought your 
dogs didn't bite.”  “Oh! well,” said Williams, “he 
aint hurt  -  we've got to let 'em bite a little.”</p>
          <p>They took us all back to the fence where I crossed 
over, all the others having been caught. Our hearts 
were filled with dismay. All looked as if they were 
condemned to be hung. We knew not what was to be 
done with us. The women were pitiful to see, crying 
and moaning  -  all courage utterly gone. They started 
back with us to Old Master Jack's, at Panola, and we 
stopped for the night at a small farm house. The old 
woman who kept it said, tauntingly: “You niggers 
going to the Yankees? You all ought to be killed.” 
We started on the following morning, and got back
<pb id="hughes146" n="146"/>
home at one o'clock in the afternoon. All of us were 
whipped. All the members of the family were very 
angry. Old Lady Jack McGee was so enraged that 
she said to my wife:  “I thought you were a Christian. 
You'll never see your God.”  She seemed to 
think that because Matilda had sought freedom she 
had committed a great sin.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>INCIDENTS.</head>
          <p>Ever since the beginning of the war, and the 
slaves had heard that possibly they might some time 
be free, they seemed unspeakably happy. They were 
afraid to let the masters know that they ever thought 
of such a thing, and they never dreamed of speaking 
about it except among themselves. They were a 
happy race, poor souls! notwithstanding their downtrodden 
condition. They would laugh and chat about 
freedom in their cabins; and many a little rhyme about 
it originated among them, and was softly sung over 
their work. I remember a song that Aunt Kitty, the 
cook at Master Jack's, used to sing. It ran something 
like this:</p>
          <lg>
            <l>There'll be no more talk about Monday, by and by,</l>
            <l>But every day will be Sunday, by and by.</l>
          </lg>
          <p>The old woman was singing, or rather humming,
<pb id="hughes147" n="147"/>
it one day, and old lady McGee heard her. She was 
busy getting her dinner, and I suppose never realized 
she was singing such an incendiary piece, when old 
Mrs. McGee broke in upon her:  “Don't think you are 
going to be free; you darkies were made by God and 
ordained to wait upon us.”  Those passages of Scripture 
which refer to master and servants were always 
cited to us when we heard the Word preached; and 
they were interpeted as meaning that the relation of 
master and slave was right and proper  -  that they 
were rightly the masters and we the slaves.</p>
          <p> I remember, not long after Jeff Davis had been 
elected president of the Confederacy, that I happened 
to hear old Master Jack talking to some of the members 
of the family about the war, etc. All at once the 
old man broke out:  “And what do you think! that 
rascal, Abraham Lincoln, has called for 300,000 more 
men. What is Jeff Davis doin'-doin'?”  He talked 
on, and seemed so angry that he gave no one a chance 
to answer:  “Jeff Davis is a grand rascal-rascal,” 
said he, “he ought to go into the field himself.”  At 
first all the Southerners were jubilant over Davis; but 
as they were losing so, and the Unionists gaining, 
they grew angry and denounced him oftentimes in unsparing 
terms.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="hughes148" n="148"/>
        <div2>
          <head>UNION RAID AT MASTER'S FARM.</head>
          <p>During the time the Union headquarters were at 
Helena, a Union gun-boat came down the river as far 
as Boliva, and stopped at Miles McGee's. The soldiers 
made a raid through the farm, taking chickens, 
turkeys, meat and everything that they could lay 
hands on. During this raid Miles McGee came out of 
the house with a gun, and shot the commanding officer 
of the party. He became alarmed over what he had 
done, and hid in the cabin of one of the servants. He 
never came near the house. The Union soldiers came 
three different times to catch him, but never succeeded. 
The last time they came, he made for the canebrake, 
and hid himself there until they were gone. But 
though he had escaped their righteous vengeance, he 
became so nervous that he left his hiding place in the 
canebraker, and went to Atlanta, Ga., and staid there 
among friends until things became more quiet. At last 
wearying of this, he determined to return to old 
Master Jack's, but not to his own home. Word had 
been received of his coming, and great preparations 
were made for his reception. After he had started on 
his return, he was taken ill on the train, and was left 
at a small town called Jackson, where he soon died. 
<pb id="hughes149" n="149"/>
I drove the family to the depot upon the day of his expected 
arrival, and as the train came in, the women 
waved their handkerchiefs; and, when the conductor 
stepped off, they asked him if Mr. McGee was aboard. 
He said no  -  “I have his remains.”  The scene that 
followed, I can not describe  -  such wailing and screaming! 
I could not but feel sad, even though they had 
treated me so meanly, causing the death of my children, 
and separating me from my wife. Their grief 
was indeed great. The sad news was conveyed to his 
mother, old Mrs. Jack McGee, at the house by an advance 
messenger, and we soon followed with the body. 
He was the favorite son of his mother, and her grief 
was very great. But for his wanton shooting of the 
Union officer, he would probably not have met 
his death as he did.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>UNION SOLDIERS PASS THE PANOLA HOME.</head>
          <p>One winter night, while I was at old Master 
Jack's, I was awakened by a rumbling noise like that 
of heavy wagons, which continued steadily and so 
long a time that I finally concluded it must be an 
army passing, and such I found to be the case, upon 
getting up and venturing out, the rumbling which had 
awakened me being caused by the passing artillery.                                            
<pb id="hughes150" n="150"/>
I was afraid to go out straight to the soldiers, but 
would take a few steps at a time, then stop and listen 
behind a tree or the shrubbery. All seemed quiet  -  
there was no talking. I had listened about twenty 
minutes when there seemed to be a halt at the creek, 
some distance from the house. Soon afterwards I
heard the command given: “Forward!” I at once 
made up my mind that they were Yankee soldiers. I 
got on my knees and crawled to the fence, not daring 
to go openly, fearing that they might hear or see 
me and shoot, supposing me to be a spy. I went back 
into the house and told my wife that they were 
Yankees who had just passed.  “Uncle George,” said 
I, “this would be a good time for us to go.”  “Oh, 
no,” said he, “we are not quite ready.” Uncle 
George's cabin was where my wife and I stayed while 
at old Master Jack's.  In the morning I was to carry 
a parcel to Como, a place not far from home, to Mr. 
James McGee, who was in the rebel army. It was 
not quite daylight when I made ready to go on my 
trip, for I was anxious to find out more about the 
soldiers. Going to the stable and saddling my horse, 
I mounted and rode out to the big gate leading to the 
main road, just as day was dawning. As I dismounted
<pb id="hughes151" n="151"/>
to open the gate, some soldiers were passing and an 
officer sung out to me, “Hello! which way are you 
going.” I said “to Como, to carry this parcel of 
clothing to my young master in the war.”  “You 
have a fine horse,” said the officer, “I guess I will 
exchange horses with you.” He took my package of 
clothing and some letters which I had to mail and my 
horse, leaving me his, which was a very poor animal. 
I was badly scared at this peformance, fearing that I 
would be severely whipped for the loss of the horse 
and package. Yet how could I help it? We knew 
nothing but to serve a white man, no matter what he 
asked or commanded. As a matter of course, I did 
not go to Como, as I had nothing to take  -  the officer 
had everything, but went back to the cabin. I supposed 
that the soldiers had all passed; but in about 
half an hour Aunt Kitty, on looking out of her cabin 
window, exclaimed: “My God! just look at the 
soldiers!”  The yard was covered with the blue coats. 
Another venerable slave said: “My Lord! de year of 
jubilee am come.” During the excitement I ran to the 
big house, and told the madam that the Yankees were 
there, and had taken my horse and everything I had. 
Old Master Jack had heard the news, but was not able 
<pb id="hughes152" n="152"/>
to come out. He had arisen, but, when he knew of 
the presence of the Yankees, he went back to bed, 
calling for Kitty to get him a mush poultice.  “Tell 
Kitty-ity-ity to get me a mush poultice-oltice.”  It 
was customary, after the beginning of the war, for 
him to take sick, and call for a poultice to be put upon 
his stomach whenever he heard of the Yankees being 
near. He and many like him were especially valorous 
only when the blue coats were far away. The soldiers 
went into the dairy and drank all the milk, helped 
themselves to butter, cheese, meat, bread and everything 
in sight which they wanted. Nothing was said 
to them by the white folks, but the slaves were glad, 
and whispered to each other:  “Ah! we's goin' to be 
free.”  Old Master Jack, lying on his couch would 
ask every little while:  “Where are they? Are they 
gone?”  After they had all left the premises, he said: 
“My God! I can't stand it. Them devils-evils are 
just goin' through the country destroyin' everything.”  
I was sent down to get Uncle Peter for old master, 
and when Peter came up the old man asked:  “Well, 
did any of the servants go away? And, sir, them 
devils took Louis' horse and the clothes he had for his 
young master.”</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="hughes153" n="153"/>
        <div2>
          <head>HIDING VALUABLES FROM THE YANKEES.</head>
          <p>Right after this the McGees commenced planning 
to put away their valuables, to keep them from the 
Union soldiers. All the servants had to fill up their 
bed-ticks with fine gin cotton  -  the lint part  -  for safe 
keeping.  Great boxes and barrels were packed full 
of their best things, and put into the cellar, under 
the house. It was not exactly a cellar, but a large 
shallow excavation, which held a great deal. We put 
all the solid silver ware, such as cake baskets, trays, 
spoons, forks, dishes, etc., in boxes, and buried them 
under the hen house. Great packages of the finest 
clothing I had to make up, and these were given in 
charge of certain servants whose duty it was to run 
into the big house and get them, whenever they heard 
that the Yankees were coming, and take them to their 
cabins. This was a shrewd arrangement, for the 
soldiers never went into the cabins to get anything. 
When the soldiers had passed, these packages were 
taken back to the house. It speaks well for the 
honesty and faithfulness of the slaves that such trusts 
could be devolved upon them, notwithstanding all the 
cruelties inflicted upon them by their masters.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="hughes154" n="154"/>
        <div2>
          <head>DEATH TO RUNAWAY SLAVES.</head>
          <p>It was about this time, that the law or regulation 
of the rebel government was promulgated, authorizing 
or directing the shooting or hanging of any slave 
caught trying to get away to the Union army. This 
barbarous law was carried out in many cases, for 
every little while we would hear of some slave who 
was caught running away, and hung or shot. A 
slave belonging to Boss, ran away, and got safely 
within the Union lines; but he returned to get his 
sister. They both got away from the house, but had 
gone only a few miles, when William McGee overtook 
them, and shot the man dead. William boasted of 
this, but told Uncle Peter, the foreman, that he never 
wanted it mentioned.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>SLAVES HUNG AND LEFT TO ROT AS A WARNING.</head>
          <p>Two slaves belonging to one Wallace, one of our 
nearest neighbors, had tried to escape to the Union 
soldiers, but were caught, brought back and hung. 
All of our servants were called up, told every detail 
of the runaway and capture of the poor creatures 
and their shocking murder, and then compelled 
to go and see them where they hung. I never 
shall forget the horror of the scene  -  it was sickening.
<pb id="hughes155" n="155"/>
The bodies hung at the roadside, where the 
execution took place, until the blue flies literally 
swarmed around them, and the stench was fearful. 
This barbarous spectacle was for the purpose of 
showing the passing slaves what would be the fate 
of those caught in the attempt to escape, and to secure 
the circulation of the details of the awful affair 
among them, throughout all the neighborhood. It 
is diffiicult at this day for those not familiar with 
the atrocities of the institution of slavery to believe 
that such scenes could ever have been witnessed in 
this or any other civilized land, as a result simply 
of a human being's effort to reach a portion of the 
country, where the freedom of which it was said to 
be the home, could be enjoyed without molestation. 
Yet such was the horrible truth in not one case 
alone, but in many, as I know only too well.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>RUNAWAY SLAVE CAUGHT AND WHIPPED.</head>
          <p>One day while I was waiting at dinner, some of 
the children from the slave quarters came running 
into the house, and said to old Master Jack: 
“Uncle John is going away  -  he is down to the 
creek.”  He had been put in the carpenter shop, 
fastened in the stocks, but by some means he had
<pb id="hughes156" n="156"/>
gotten the stocks off his feet, and got lose. All in 
the house immediately got up and ran out. Old 
master told me to run and catch the runaway. I 
did not like to do it, but had to obey. Old master 
and I ran in pursuit, and soon overtook him. He 
could not run, as the stocks were still on his arms 
and neck. We brought him back, and he was 
“staked out”  -  that is, four stakes were driven into 
the ground, the arms tied to two and the legs to 
the other two. He was then paddled with the 
whipping paddle upon the bottom of his feet, by 
old Master Jack, until blood blisters arose, when 
he took his knife and opened them. I was then 
sent for salt and water, and the bruises of the suffering 
chattel were washed as usual in the stinging 
brine.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>A HOME GUARD ACCIDENTALLY SHOOTS HIMSELF.</head>
          <p>After the capture of Memphis by the Union 
forces, the soldiers were in the habit of making 
raids into the surrounding country. These were a 
source of alarm and anxiety among the people, and 
they were constantly on the watch to defend their 
property and themselves, as best they could. One 
day Dr. Charles Dandridge went over to one of
<pb id="hughes157" n="157"/>
our neighbors, Mr. Bobor's, to practice shooting, 
and to see if he had heard anything new about the 
war. It was the custom of the home-guards to 
meet weekly, and practice with their fire-arms, in 
order to be the better prepared, as they pretended, 
for any sudden incursion of the now dreaded Yankee. 
Mr. Bobor had gotten a Yankee pistol from some 
friend, who was in the army, and Dr. Charles 
wanted to see and try it. It was shown him, and 
its workings explained. He took it and began 
shooting, and in showing the other men how 
quickly he could shoot a Yankee, and mount his horse, 
he accidentally shot himself under the short rib near 
his heart, and fell to the ground. All the men came 
running to him, picked him up and carried him into 
the house, immediately sending word to Mrs. Dandridge 
and Master Jack McGee, his father-in-law. 
The boys came hurrying in, and told us what had 
happened. I hitched up and drove Boss over to Mr. Bobor's. 
We found the wounded man rapidly sinking; 
and when, a little later, his wife came, he could not 
speak  -  only clasped her hand. He died that night, 
and we carried his body to the home, which so short a 
time before, he had left in health and high spirits.
<pb id="hughes158" n="158"/>
No casket was to be had  -  everything of that kind had 
been consumed or shut out by the war. Accordingly 
two slaves were ordered to make a coffin, which they 
did, using plain boards. It was then covered with 
black alapaca from a dress of the madam, and lined 
with the cloth from Mrs. Dandridge's opera cloak. The 
regular material used for these purposes was not to be 
had. By the time the coffin was ready, the body was 
so bloated, that it could not be got into it. Resort 
was then had to a plain box, and in this the body of 
another of the stricken family group was laid away. 
At the suggestion of old Master Jack, the coffin was 
put up in the carriage house, for safe keeping, he 
saying it would do for him to be burried in. Sorrow 
had come to this family with such crushing force, 
that their former pride and boastful spirit had given 
place to utter dejection.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>SUBSTITUTES FOR COFFEE.</head>
          <p>During the war everything was scarce and dear, 
and substitutes were devised for many of those things 
which had formely been regarded as the necessaries 
of life.  Sweet potatoes were peeled, then cut in 
small pieces and put out in the sun to dry. They 
were then used as a substitute for coffee, when that
<pb id="hughes159" n="159"/>
article became so scarce, toward the close of the war. 
Great quantities of this preparation were used. Okra 
was another substitute for coffee. It was dried in the 
pod, then the seeds shelled out, and these were dried 
again and prepared something as the coffee is. This 
made a delicious drink when served with cream, being 
very rich and pleasant to the taste. Quinine was a 
medicine that had been of almost universal use in the 
south; yet it became so scarce that it was sold at 
seven dollars a bottle, and could not often be had at 
that price. Lemon leaves were used as a substitute 
in cases of chills and fever. The leaves were made 
into a tea, and given to the patient hot, to produce 
prespiration. During an attack of chills, I was 
treated in this manner to some advantage. At any 
rate I got well, which can not always be said of all 
methods of treatment.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <pb id="hughes160" n="160"/>
      <div1>
        <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
        <head>REBELLION WEAKENING  -  SLAVES' HOPES
STRENGTHENING.</head>
        <div2>
          <head>M'GEES SLAVES TAKEN TO ALABAMA.</head>
          <p>While I was absent on my last runaway trip, the 
Yankees had made a raid through Panola; and our 
people had become greatly frightened. As soon as 
they had got back with me and my fellow runaways, 
they assembled a gang of slaves for the purpose of taking 
them to Atlanta, Ga., to get them out of the reach 
of the Union soldiers. Among the slaves selected for the 
transfer were myself, my wife Matilda, and the seamstress. 
The others all belonged to Dr. Dandridge and 
Blanton McGee. Both the Drs. Dandridge went with 
us to Atlanta. We traveled across the country until 
we came to Demopolis, Alabama, where we found Boss 
camped on the bank of the Tombigbee river with all 
the farm slaves from Bolivar county. This was the 
first time I had seen Boss since he was captured and 
taken to Helena. As my wife and I were the only
<pb id="hughes161" n="161"/>
ones in the gang who belonged to Boss, we left those 
with whom we had come and joined his gang. We 
all then went aboard a boat and were taken to the 
salt works, situated on the Tombigbee, ninety miles 
from Mobile. These salt works belonged to the rebel 
government. The first president of the works was 
Mr. Woolsey, of Salem, Alabama. During Mr. 
Woolsey's term, the first part of 1864, when we had 
been there some time, he wrote to Boss asking if he 
would sell myself and wife, and offering $3,000 for 
both of us. Boss was indignant at this and curtly refused. 
My wife acted as cook at the salt works, in 
the headquarters for the president, managers 
and clerks. Mr. Woolsey was delighted with her cooking; 
her bread and rolls, he said, could not be surpassed.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>M'GEE'S GREAT SCHEME.</head>
          <p>When the election of officers of the works came 
off in the fall, Mr. Gallatin McGee was chosen president. 
Boss then hired us all, about 100 in number, 
to labor in these works, but he, of course, received all 
the revenue. The work assigned me was that of 
butler at headquarters, and my wife was cook. Both 
women and children, as well as men, were employed 
in these works. After some months labor here, soon 
<pb id="hughes162" n="162"/>
after Gallatin McGee became president, Matilda and    
I were removed to the Montgomery headquarters,                                                          where we remained until nearly Christmas. A few                                                      days before that time, Boss came to Montgomery and                                               arranged for us to meet him in Mobile. We started  
at the appointed time, reached the city in the morning 
and I went directly to the hotel where he told me 
he would be. I found him at once, and he informed                                            
me all about his plans for the future, and what he expected 
to accomplish. He had purchased an island in 
the bay, a little way from Mobile, where he had decided 
to establish salt works of his own. All the 
brick and lumber for the buildings had been carried 
there, and work upon them was to be commenced immediately 
after Christmas. He intended to make a 
home for the family on the island; and, as soon as he 
could complete the works, to remove all his hands from 
the government works to his own. He was very 
enthusiastic over this scheme, claiming that he would 
make far more money by it than he was then receiving 
from hiring out his slaves. He told me that he 
would remain in Mobile two or three days and would 
go to Panola to spend the holidays, after which he 
intended to bring all the family to Mobile, and remain 
<pb id="hughes163" n="163"/>
there until the island was in readiness to be occupied. 
There was to be a general break up of the 
old home, and the beginning of a new manner of life. 
I stayed in his room at the hotel all the forenoon, 
listening to his plans; then I went back where my 
wife was stopping. As I left his room, he said: 
“Lou,” as he always called me, “I will see you and 
Matilda at the boat this evening.” We went to the 
boat at the appointed time and saw the Boss, but he 
did not come near us. As the boat was about to put 
off, I looked and saw him walking up and down the 
levee, apparently much excited, running his hands 
nervously through his hair  -  a habit common to him 
when he was worried. He seemed greatly distressed. 
The military situation troubled him, for the Union 
army had conquered nearly everything; and the fact 
now stared him in the face that he would soon lose his 
slaves. He never dreamed in the beginning of the 
war that the Unionists would conquer, and that the 
slaves would be freed; but now he saw that not only 
all his wealth in the bodies and souls of men was slipping 
away from him, but that much, if not all of the 
gain which these chattels had brought him was likely 
to “take wings and fly away.”</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="hughes164" n="164"/>
        <div2>
          <head>M'GEE'S DEATH.</head>
          <p>We returned to the salt works the morning after 
leaving Mobile. Boss remained two days in Mobile,    
and then started for Panola, the home of his father- in-law; 
but, on his way, he was taken sick, having 
contracted a heavy cold which ran into pneumonia, and 
he lasted only a short time, dying on New Year's day. 
He had taken cold in bringing the slaves from Bolivar 
over the river on barges. The river was over-flowed 
about fifty miles out, and the only way he 
could get the slaves across was by using large barges 
made of logs. They were several days floating down 
in this way, before he could get out to the railroad at 
Jackson, Miss., where he transferred them to the cars. 
This was too much of an exposure and it killed him.</p>
          <p>After Boss died all the plans were changed. Col. 
Hunting, son-in-law of old Master Jack, came down 
to the salt works and hired us all out there for another 
year. This was the beginning of the year 1865. Of 
master's plans concerning the island and his proposed 
salt works the family knew little, for they questioned 
me closely as to what he told me of the matter. What 
he spent on the island in lumber, brick, etc., was 
lost as they knew nothing of the particulars of the
<pb id="hughes164a" n="164a"/>
<figure id="ill6" entity="hughes165"><p>[Image of Currency]</p></figure>
<pb id="hughes165" n="165"/>
expenditure. The madam remained at her fathers, 
and the slaves at the works.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>I MAKE SOME MONEY.</head>
          <p>As I was here for another year, acting as butler, 
thought I would try and see if I could not make some 
money for myself. I asked Mr. Brooks, the manager of 
the works, if he could get me some tobacco by sending 
to Mobile for it. He said he could; and on the fourth 
day thereafter, in the evening, it came. I was anxious 
to get it the same evening, but Mr. Brooks said: 
“Oh! I guess you had better wait until morning, 
then when you finish your work come down to the 
office and get it  -  you will then have more time to see 
the boys in the works.” In the morning I was up 
early, and after doing my morning work I was off to 
Brooks' office. When I went in he said:  “There it 
is under the table.”  The package was so small I felt 
disappointed  -  a hundred dollars worth ought to be 
more, said I to myself; but I took it, and went out 
among the men. I thought I would try to sell it at 
five dollars a plug, and if I could not sell it at that I 
would take four dollars. I must make something, for 
I had borrowed the money to buy it with; and I saw 
that to clear anything on it, I must at least get four
<pb id="hughes166" n="166"/>
dollars a plug. The money which I had borrowed 
was from three fellow servants, who had been fortunate 
in earning some little time and had saved their 
money. The first man I met in the works bought 
two plugs, at five dollars each; and after I had been 
there about an hour all was sold. So I went back 
with a light heart. Mr. Brooks said to me at dinner: 
“Well, how did you get along with your tobacco?” 
“I did very well,” I said, “the only trouble was I did 
not have enough. I sold it for $180.”  “Well,” said 
he, “if you did, you made more clear money than the 
works here. How much a plug did you sell it for?” 
at the same time drawing out his pencil and commencing 
to figure it up. “I had thirty-six plugs,” said I, 
“and I sold them for five dollars a plug.” Nothing 
more was said just then, but after dinner Brooks and 
two of the clerks went out on the veranda to smoke. 
When they were in a good way smoking, Brooks 
slipped into the dining room, and said:  “Well, that 
was fine; you got five dollars a plug for the tobacco? ” 
“Oh, yes!” I said, “tobacco is scarce, and they were 
hungry for it; it went like hot cakes  - the price was 
not questioned, I sold at once.”  “What is the prospect 
for selling more?” he asked.  “Will you sell it 
<pb id="hughes167" n="167"/>
for half the profit if I furnish the tobacco?” I said 
“yes.” So he sent the same day for a box of tobacco  
-  about five hundred plugs. When the tobacco came 
the box was sawed in two and one-half sent up to my 
room. I put some fellows out as agents to sell for me  
-  Uncle Hudson, who took care of the horses and 
mules at the works; John at the hospital; William, 
head chopper, among the 100 men in the woods. Each 
brought in from $40.00 to $50.00 every two or three 
days, and took another supply. Sometimes, when I 
had finished my work in the afternoon, I would get an 
old pony and go around through the neighborhood 
and sell four or five plugs. It was a mystery to the 
servants how I got the tobacco; but I did not let on 
that Brooks was backing me. In two weeks we had 
taken in $1,600.00, and I was happy as I could be. 
Brooks was a fine fellow  -  a northerner by birth, and 
did just what he said he would. I received one-half 
of the money. Of course this was all rebel money, 
but I was sharp, and bought up all the silver I could 
find. Just as we got on the other half of the box, 
Brooks received word that the Yankees were coming, 
and to send all the hands to their masters. I was 
glad that I had made some money, knowing that I 
<pb id="hughes168" n="168"/>
would need it if I gained my freedom, which I now 
knew was quite probable, as the Union forces were 
gaining ground everywhere. But the message ended 
my money-making, and I prepared to go home to 
Panola.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>GOING BACK TO PANOLA.</head>
          <p>Mr. Brooks fixed the return papers so that my wife 
and I could leave the party of slaves at Demopolis, 
and go on thence to Panola by rail, to convey the 
news to madam that all hands were coming home; 
that the Yankees were expected to capture the salt 
works within a short time. At Jackson, some seven 
miles from the salt works, we were delayed over 
night by reason of lack of facilities for crossing the 
Tombigbee river. The report that the Yankees were 
coming through had created a panic among the white 
people; and hundreds, fleeing from their homes, had 
gathered at the river, waiting and clamoring for an 
opportunity to cross. Though slaves were property, 
and valuable on that account, the whites seemed to 
think that their own lives were in danger, and to be 
protected first. They therefore took precedence of us. 
In the morning about seven o'clock a steamer was 
seen coming at a distance; but it could not be discovered
<pb id="hughes168a" n="168a"/>
<figure id="ill7" entity="hughes168"><p>[Image of Currency]</p></figure>
<pb id="hughes169" n="169"/>
at once just what the character of it was. 
The whites became alarmed. Some said:  “The 
Yankees are coming.”  Other said:  “It is a gun 
boat  -  they will surely fire on us.”  But as the boat 
drew near the people saw that there was nothing to 
fear  -  it was only the regular passenger boat. Besides 
the hundreds of people, there were scores of wagons, 
filled with household goods to go over, and the passage 
was slow and tedious We finally got across 
and traveled as far as Demopolis, where Matilda and 
I left the other slaves, and took a train and went on 
to Panola. I delivered the papers to the madam from 
Brooks, which told her all the particulars concerning 
the break up at the salt works. She sent wagons 
right away after the other slaves who were coming 
back on foot. They were not brought back to Panola; 
but were hired out to different farmers along the road 
home  -  some in Jackson, some in Granda and others in 
Panola town. These were all small towns in Mississippi. 
My wife and I went to work at old Master 
Jack's, I on the farm and my wife at her old duties in 
the house. We longed for freedom, but were content 
for the time with hoping and praying for the coming 
of the day when it should be realized. It was sad to
<pb id="hughes170" n="170"/>
see the changes that had come to the white folks. 
Sorrow had left its impress upon all and we felt it, 
notwithstanding all that we had suffered at their 
hands. Boss had willed the homestead in Memphis 
to Mrs Farrington, and she was getting, ready to take 
possession. He had borrowed a great amount of 
money from her when he bought the island at Mobile; 
and the rapid coming on of the end of the rebellion 
destroyed all prospect of the success of his salt works 
scheme, even before his death, and really rendered him 
bankrupt. Hence the transfer of the Memphis 
property to her was the only way he could make good 
what he owed her. The madam now had no home, 
but was compelled to stay with her father, old Master 
Jack. She was sadly changed  -  did not appear like the 
same person. Her troubles and sorrows had crushed 
her former cruel and haughty spirit. Her mother had 
died a few months before, and then her husband had 
followed, dying suddenly and away from home. Then 
much of her property had been lost, and social 
pleasures and distinction were gone forever. Who 
shall say that the wrongs done her poor, helpless 
slaves were not avenged in this life? The last I knew 
of her she was still at her father's.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="hughes171" n="171"/>
        <div2>
          <head>INCIDENTS.</head>
          <p>A servant who belonged to Dr. Dandridge ran 
away and got to Memphis just after it was captured 
by the Union soldiers. He was put into the army and 
was stationed at one of the entrances to the city. He 
was to halt all persons passing to or from the city, no 
difference who they were, and learn their names and 
their business. Young William McGee and his sister,
Miss Cherry, one day went up to Memphis and, to 
their surprise, were halted by this former servant of 
their uncle. When they came home they were speaking 
of it to their father, and old Master Jack said: 
“And you halted, did you?”  “Why, yes,” replied 
William, “we had to do it.”  “Well,” said the old 
man,  “I would have died-died before I would have 
done it. To think that a servant should have halted 
you, and one who has belonged to the family like 
Anderson!” This old man, notwithstanding all his 
boasting in the absence of immediate danger, was the 
verriest coward when danger was present; and if he 
had been in the place of young William, he would 
have halted with the greatest alacrity.</p>
          <p>While at the salt works I had a little experience at 
nursing. A fellow slave was taken ill, and I was
<pb id="hughes172" n="172"/>
called on to care for him at night. I always liked this 
work; it was a pleasure to me to be in the sick room. 
Typhoid fever was a new case to me, but I remembered 
what instructions Boss had given me about it. I 
“pitched in” to do what I could; but the fever was so 
great he lasted only a few days.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>MY FIFTH STRIKE FOR FREEDOM IS A SUCCESS.</head>
          <p>We had remained at old Jack's until June, 1865, 
and had tried to be content. The Union soldiers were 
still raiding all through that section. Every day 
some town would be taken, and the slaves would 
secretely rejoice. After we came back from Alabama 
we were held with a tighter rein than ever. 
We were not allowed to go outside of the premises. 
George Washington, a fellow servant, and Kitty, his 
wife, and I had talked considerably about the 
Yankees, and how we might get away, We knew it 
was our right to be free, for the proclamation had long 
been issued  -  yet they still held us. I did not talk 
much to my wife about going away, as she was 
always so afraid I would be killed, and did not want 
me to try any more to escape. But George, his wife 
and I continued to discuss the matter, whenever we 
had a chance. We knew that Memphis was headquarters
<pb id="hughes173" n="173"/>
for the Union troops, but how to reach it was 
the great question.</p>
          <p>It was Sunday, and I had driven one portion of the 
family to church, and George the other. The family 
was now very large, as the madam and her family 
were there, in addition to Old Master Jack's, and all 
could not go in one carriage. On the way back, 
young William McGee came up through the farm, on 
horseback, a nearer way home from church, and encountered 
several servants belonging to some of the 
neighbors. He asked them what they were doing 
there, and if they had passes. To this last question 
all answered no.  “Well,” said he, “never come 
here again without having passes, all of you.” At 
this they all quickly disappeared. When Old Jack 
came home, Will told him what had passed; and he 
immediately called for George and Uncle Peter, the 
foreman, and told them that no one not belonging 
there was to come into the quarters without a pass; 
and any servant with a pass should be brought to the 
house, that the pass might be inspected. They 
thought, or feared, that if the servants were permitted 
to come together freely they might plan ways of 
escape, and communicate to each other what they 
<pb id="hughes174" n="174"/>
 knew about the war and the Yankees. George came 
 out, and finding me, told me what they had said. 
 “No slave from outside is to be allowed on the place,” 
 said he. I replied:  “If we listen to them we shall be 
 here until Christmas comes again.”  “What do you 
 mean?”  asked George. “I mean that now, today, is 
 the time to make a start.”  So, late in the afternoon, 
 during the servants' prayer meeting, of which I have 
 heretofore spoken, we thought would be a good time 
 to get away, as no one would be likely to see us. We 
 talked with John Smith, another servant, and told 
 him all about our plan, asking him not to say a word 
 about our being gone until he was through feeding 
 the stock. This would give us another hour to advance 
 on our journey, as the feeding usually took 
 about that time  -  from six o'clock until seven. Our 
 fear was that we might be overtaken by the bloodhounds; 
 and, therefore, we wished to get as far away 
 as possible before the white people knew we were 
 gone. It was Sunday afternoon, June 26th, 1865, 
 when George and I, having made ready for the start 
 for the Union lines, went to bid our wives good-bye. 
 I told my wife to cheer up, as I was coming again to 
 get her. I said to Kitty, George's wife:  “We are
<pb id="hughes175" n="175"/>
going, but look for us again. It will not be with us 
as with so many others, who have gone away, leaving 
their families and never returning for them. We will 
be here again.”  She looked up at me, smiling, and 
with a look of resolution, said:  “I'll be ready.”  She 
was of a firm, daring nature  -  I did not fear to tell her 
all my plans. As my wife was so timid, I said as 
little as possible to her. George and I hurriedly said 
our farewells to our wives. The parting was heart-rending, 
for we knew the dangers were great, and the 
chances were almost even that we should not meet 
again. I could hardly leave my wife, her agitation 
and grief were so great. But we were off in 
a few moments. We crept through the orchard, passing 
through farm after farm until we struck the railroad, 
about seven miles from home. We followed this 
road until we reached Senatobia, about half past seven 
in the evening. We felt good, and, stopping all night, 
we started the next morning for Hernando, Miss., 
another small town, and reached there at two o'clock 
in the afternoon. The most of the bridges had been 
burned, by the troops, and there were no regular railroad 
trains. Fortunately, however, flat cars, drawn 
by horses were run over the road; and on a train of
<pb id="hughes176" n="176"/>
this kind we took passage. On several occasions, the 
passengers had to get out, and push the car over a 
bridge, as it was not made so horses could cross on it, 
the horses meantime being driven or led through the 
stream, and then hitched to the car again. After we 
had gone through this process repeatedly, we at last 
reached Memphis, arriving about seven o'clock Monday 
evening. The city was filled with slaves, from 
all over the south, who cheered and gave us a welcome. 
I could scarcely recognize Memphis, things were so 
changed. We met numbers of our fellow servants 
who had run away before us, when the war began. 
Tuesday and Wednesday we spent in making inquiries; 
and I visited our old home at McGee's station. 
But how different it was from what it had been when 
the McGees were there. All was changed. Thursday 
we went to see Col. Walker, a Union officer, who 
looked after the colored folks, and saw that they had 
their rights. When we reached his office we found it 
so filled with people, waiting to see him, that we were 
delayed about two hours, before we had an opportunity 
of speaking with him. When our turn came, 
we went in, and told him that we were citizens of 
Memphis until the fall of Fort Pillow and Donelson,
<pb id="hughes177" n="177"/>
when our master had run us off, with a hundred other 
slaves, into Mississippi, and thence to the salt works 
in Alabama. He questioned us as to where we lived 
in Memphis. I answered:  “What is now headquarters 
of the Union forces was the home of master, 
Mr. Edmund McGee, who is now dead.”  After a few 
minutes, I said:  “Colonel, we want protection to go 
back to Mississippi after our wives, who are still held 
as slaves.” He replied:  “You are both free men to go 
and come as you please.”  “Why,” said I, “Colonel, 
if we go back to Mississippi they will shoot the gizzards 
out of us.”  “Well,” said he, “I can not grant 
your request. I would be overrun with similar applications; 
but I will tell you what you can do. There 
are hundreds of just such men as you want, who would 
be glad of such a scout.”  We thanked him and left.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>GOING BACK FOR OUR WIVES.</head>
          <p>After carefully considering the matter, we concluded 
to go back to Senatobia and see the captain of 
the Union troops there. The next day, Friday, we 
hired a two horse wagon, and made preparations to 
start on our perilous undertaking Saturday morning. 
It was our hope to find some one at Senatobia to go 
with us to Panola, and protect us in the effort to
<pb id="hughes178" n="178"/>
bring away our wives. So, early in the morning, we 
set out. Our first stop was at Big Springs camping 
ground, where we made preparations for refreshing 
ourselves and spending the night. Just as we had 
finished building a fire, for cooking and keeping off 
the mosquitoes, two soldiers came riding up to the 
spring.  “Hello,” said one, “which way are you 
traveling?”  “We are just from Memphis,” said 
George.  “Have you any whisky?” asked one of 
them. We replied  “yes.”  Will you give a fellow a 
horn?”  We answered the question by handing them 
the bottle. While they were drinking, George and I 
stepped aside, and, after a few moments talk, we decided 
to put the question to them of going with us to 
get our wives. I asked:  “Where are you from?” 
“Senatobia,” replied one. We at once laid our cause 
before them, telling them what Col. Walker had said 
regarding our getting some one to go with us on our 
enterprise. They listened attentively, and when we 
had finished, one of them asked:  “How much 
whisky have you?” George answered:  “Two bottles.” 
“What do you intend to do when you see the 
captain at Senatobia?”  “Lay our complaint before 
him,” said I. “Now my friend,” said one of the
<pb id="hughes179" n="179"/>
soldiers,  “I am afraid if you go to the captain you 
will be defeated. But I'll tell you what I'll do. Give 
my comrade and me one of your bottles of whisky, 
and we will put you on a straight track. The reason 
why I say this is that our captain has been sweetened 
by the rebel farmers. He is invited out to tea by them 
every evening. I know he will put you off. But I 
will write a note to some comrades of mine who, I 
know, will bring you out safe.”  We agreed at once 
to this proposition, and gave them the whisky. He 
wrote the note, and gave it to us, telling us to go to 
the last tent on the line in the camp, where we would 
find two boys to whom we should give it. “They 
are brave,”  said he,  “and the only two I know of that 
can help you. If they are not there don't give the 
note to any one else, but wait till they come back, on 
Tuesday night. I feel satisfied that they will go and 
help you out.”  With these words, they rode off. 
George and I felt good over our prospects.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>A HAZARDOUS TRIP.</head>
          <p>The next morning was Sunday, and we started on, 
reaching Senatobia about eleven o'clock. We went 
into the camp, following the directions given us, to 
go to the last tent in the line; but, when we reached
<pb id="hughes180" n="180"/>
there, the soldiers were out. We lingered around the 
grounds a short time, then went back, and found them 
there. We gave them the note; and, after reading it, 
they simply asked us where we had stopped our 
wagon. I told them outside the village.  “Go there,” 
said one of them,  “and remain until we come out to 
see you.”  Shortly they came out; and, after we had 
told them what we wanted, the distance to McGee's, 
which was about nineteen miles from Senatobia, and 
had given them such other information as they desired, 
they concluded that they would go.  “We 
want to be back,”  said I,  “before daylight Monday 
morning, because we must not be seen on the road; 
for we are well known in that section, and, if discovered, 
would be captured and killed.”  “Well,” 
said one of the soldiers,  “we will have to go back to 
camp, and arrange to be excused from roll call this 
evening, before we can make the trip.”  They went 
back to camp; and, in about ten minutes they came out 
again saying:  “All is right; we will go.”  We gave 
them each ten dollars; and promised, if they brought 
us out safely, to give each ten dollars more. It was 
now about half-past eleven o'clock.  They had to go 
to camp, and slip their horses out cautiously, so as not
<pb id="hughes181" n="181"/>
to be seen by the captain. Iu half an hour we were 
on our way; and, after we had ridden some two 
miles, we were overtaken by the two soldiers. It was 
Sunday afternoon; and our having a wagon attracted 
much attention from the farmers as we passed along. 
They looked at us so sharply that George and I felt 
decidedly uneasy; yet we kept up courage and pressed 
steadily on. After a long and weary ride we reached 
old Master Jack's a little after sundown. The soldiers 
rode into the yard ahead of us, and the first person 
they met was a servant (Frank) at the woodpile. 
They said to him:  “Go in and tell your master, Mr. 
McGee, to come out, we want to see him,” at the same 
time asking for Louis' and George's wives. Young 
William McGee came out and the soldiers said to him: 
“We want feed for seventy-five head of horses.” 
McGee said:  “We have not got it.”  Just then 
George and I were coming up. We drove in at the 
gate, through the grove, and passed the woodpile 
where McGee and the soldiers were talking.  McGee 
had just replied:  “We have not got that much feed 
to spare  -  we are almost out.”  “Well,” said the 
soldiers, “we must have it,” and they followed on 
right after the wagons. As we drove past them,
<pb id="hughes182" n="182"/>
young McGee went running into the house, saying to 
his mother:  “It is Louis and George, and I'll kill 
one of them to-night.”  This raised quite an alarm, 
and the members of the family told him not to do 
that, as it would ruin them. As soon as George and 
I drove up to the first cabin, which was my wife's and 
Kitty's, we ran in. Kitty met us at the door and 
said:  “I am all ready.”  She was looking for us. 
We commenced loading our wagon with our few 
things. Meanwhile the soldiers had ridden around a 
few rods and came upon old Master Jack and the 
minister of the parish, who were watching as guards 
to keep the slaves from running away to the Yankees. 
Just think of the outrage upon those poor creatures 
in forcibly retaining them in slavery long after the 
proclamation making them free had gone into effect 
beyond all question!  As the soldiers rode up to the 
two men they said:  “Hello! what are you doing 
here?  Why have you not told these two men, Louis 
and George, that they are free men  -  that they can go 
and come as they like?”  By this time all the family 
were aroused, and great excitement prevailed. The 
soldier's presence drew all the servants near. George 
and I hurried to fill up our wagon, telling our wives
<pb id="hughes183" n="183"/>
to get in, as there was no time to lose  -  we must go at 
once. In twenty minutes we were all loaded. My 
wife, Aunt Kitty and nine other servants followed the 
wagon. I waited for a few moments for Mary Ellen, 
sister of my wife; and as she came running out of the 
white folks' house, she said to her mistress, Mrs. Farrington: 
“Good-bye; I wish you good luck.”  “I 
wish you all the bad luck,” said she in a rage. But 
Mary did not stop to notice her mistress further; and, 
joining me, we were soon on the road following the 
wagon.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>TWO BRAVE MEN.</head>
          <p>Those soldiers were brave indeed. Think of the 
courage and daring involved in this scheme  -  only two 
soldiers going into a country of which they knew 
nothing except that every white man living in it was 
their enemy. The demand which they made for food 
for seventy-five horses was a clever ruse, invented by 
them to alarm the McGees, and make them think 
that there was a troop of horses near by, and that it 
would not be safe for them to offer any resistance to 
our going away with our wives. Had they thought 
that there were but two soldiers, it is certain that 
they would have endeavored to prevent us getting
<pb id="hughes184" n="184"/>
away again, and one or more of us would undoubtedly 
have been killed.</p>
          <p>As already stated, nine other slaves followed our 
wagon, as it moved off. They had no hats on; some 
were bare-footed,  -  they had not stopped to get anything; 
but, as soon as they saw a chance to get away, 
they went just as they were at the moment. Aunt 
Kitty was brave and forethoughtful, for during the 
week we were gone she had baked and cooked a large 
amount of substantial food that would keep us from 
starving while on our journey.</p>
          <p>At the first road crossing, the two soldiers thought 
they saw a large troop of soldiers in the distance, and 
they galloped ahead of us at full speed; but, on 
arriving at the spot, they found that what they 
had thought soldiers were only a herd of cattle. 
They rode on to the next crossing, we following as 
we conveniently could. Each poor slave was busy 
with his thoughts and his prayers. Now and then 
one would hear a moan or a word from some of the 
party. All were scared, even though the soldiers 
were with us. We came to the next cross road, and 
passed that safely. Our fear was that the McGees 
might get the neighborhood to join them and pursue
<pb id="hughes185" n="185"/>
us, or send the home guards after us; but Providence 
was seemingly smiling upon us at last, for no one 
followed or molested us. We moved on all night, 
until we came to a creek, at four o'clock in the morning 
of Monday. The banks of the creek were very 
steep, and as the horses and wagon went down into 
the stream, the mattress on top of the wagon, upon 
which my wife and her sister's children were sitting, 
was thrown off into the water. Immediately the horses 
stopped, and became balky. It was such a warm 
night that they did not want to move on out of the 
water, and would not start, either, until they got 
ready. As soon as the soldiers saw the mattress slide 
off with my wife and the children, one of them plunged 
into the water with his horse, and, in a minute, 
brought them all out. All had a good ducking  -  
indeed it seemed like a baptism by immersion. The 
drenched ones were wrapped in old blankets; and, 
after an hour's delay, we were again on our way. 
The soldiers said:  “Now we must leave you; the time 
is coming when we must be in camp for roll call. If 
you are not at our camp when roll call is over, we will 
come back and see about you.”  We gave them each 
the second ten dollars, as agreed upon, and just as
<pb id="hughes186" n="186"/>
they rode to the top of the hill they left us. We had 
a clear sweep from this point, and we came into Senatobia 
about nine o'clock in the forenoon. Our two 
soldier friends, who had brought us out so safely, 
came out of camp to see us. They cheered us, and 
seemed glad that they had rendered us service. We 
stopped at the camp until we had dried our clothes 
and had some breakfast; and, then, we made our way 
to Memphis.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>OUT OF BONDAGE AT LAST.</head>
          <p>My wife and her sister were shoeless, and the 
latter had no hat on  -  she had hurried out of the house 
in such excitement that she thought of nothing but 
getting away. Having to walk some of the way, 
as all could not ride in the wagon at the same time, we 
were all tired, dirty and rest-broken, and, on the 
whole, a pitiful crowd to look at, as we came into the 
city. One venerable old man, bent with age, whose 
ebony face shone with delight, came running out into 
the road as we appeared, exclaiming:  “Oh! here dey 
come, God bless 'em! Poor chil'en! they come fannin.” 
We used large palm leaves to fan ourselves with, as 
we were so warm. Those nine souls that followed us 
walked the whole distance, arriving shortly after we
<pb id="hughes187" n="187"/>
did. Thousands of others, in search of the freedom 
of which they had so long dreamed, flocked into the 
city of refuge, some having walked hundreds of 
miles.</p>
          <p>It was appropriately the 4th of July when we 
arrived; and, aside from the citizens of Memphis, 
hundreds of colored refugees thronged the streets. 
Everywhere you looked you could see soldiers. Such 
a day I don't believe Memphis will ever see again  -  
when so large and so motley a crowd will come together. 
Our two soldier rescuers looked us up after 
we were in Memphis, and seemed truly glad that we 
had attained our freedom, and that they had been instrumental 
in it. Only one thing we regret, and that 
is that we did not learn their names; but we were in 
so much trouble, and so absorbed in the business 
which we had in hand  -  so excited by the perils of our 
undertaking, that we never thought to ask them their 
names, or to what regiment they belonged. Then, 
after we got to Memphis, though we were most grateful 
for the service which they had rendered us, we 
were still so excited by our new condition and surroundings
that we thought of little else, and forgot 
that we had no means of establishing, at a later time,
<pb id="hughes188" n="188"/>
the identity of those to whom we owed so much. 
Freedom, that we had so long looked for, had come at 
last; and we gave praise to God, blessing the day 
when we met those two heroes. It is true that we 
should have been free, sooner or later; still, but for 
their assistance, my wife and I might never have met 
again. If I could not have gone back, which I could 
never have done alone, until long after, such changes 
might have occured as would have separated us for 
years, if not forever. Thousands were separated in 
this manner  -  men escaping to the Union lines, hoping 
to make a way to return for their families; but, failing 
in this, and not daring to return alone, never saw 
their wives or children more. Thanks to God, we 
were guided to these brave soldiers, and so escaped 
from so cruel a fate.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>A WORD FOR MY OLD MASTER.</head>
          <p>In closing this account of my years of bondage, it 
is, perhaps, but justice to say of my old master that 
he was in some respects kinder and more humane than 
many other slaveholders. He fed well, and all had 
enough to wear, such as it was. It is true that the 
material was coarse, but it was suited to the season, 
and, therefore, comfortable, which could not truthfully
<pb id="hughes189" n="189"/>
be said of the clothing of the slaves of other planters. 
Not a few of these did not have sufficient clothes to 
keep them warm in winter; nor did they have sufficient 
nourishing and wholesome food. But while my master 
showed these virtues, similar to those which a provident 
farmer would show in the care of his dumb 
brutes, he lacked in that humane feeling which should 
have kept him from buying and selling human beings 
and parting kindred  -  which should have made it impossible 
for him to have permitted the lashing, beating 
and lacerating of his slaves, much more the hiring 
of an irresponsible brute, by the year, to perform  
this barbarous service for him. The McGees were 
charitable  -  as they interpreted the word  -  were 
always ready to contribute to educational and 
missionary funds, while denying, under the severest 
penalties, all education to those most needing it, and 
all true missionary effort  -  the spiritual enlightenment 
for which they were famishing. Then our masters 
lacked that fervent charity, the love of Christ in the 
heart, which if they had possessed they could not 
have treated us as they did. They would have remembered 
the golden rule:  “Do unto others as ye would 
that men should do to you.”  Possessing absolute
<pb id="hughes190" n="190"/>
power over the bodies and souls of their slaves, and 
grown rich from their unrequited toil, they became 
possessed by the demon of avarice and pride, and lost 
sight of the most vital of the Christly qualities.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="illustration">
        <pb id="hughes190a" n="190a"/>
        <p>
<figure id="ill8" entity="hughes190"><p>[Illustration]</p></figure></p>
      </div1>
      <div1>
        <pb id="hughes191" n="191"/>
        <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
        <head>FREEDOM AFTER SLAVERY.</head>
        <div2>
          <head>COMING NORTH.</head>
          <p>As before stated, we arrived in Memphis on the 
Fourth of July, 1865. My first effort as a freeman 
was to get something to do to sustain myself and 
wife and a babe of a few months, that was born at 
the salt works. I succeeded in getting a room for us, 
and went to work the second day driving a public carriage. 
I made enough to keep us and pay our room 
rent. By our economy we managed to get on very 
well. I worked on, hoping to go further north, feeling 
somehow that it would be better for us there; 
when, one day I ran across a man who knew my wife's 
mother. He said to me:  “Why, your wife's mother 
went back up the river to Cincinnati. I knew her well 
and the people to whom she belonged.”  This 
information made us eager to take steps to find her. 
My wife was naturally anxious to follow the clue 
thus obtained, in hopes of finding her mother, whom
she had not seen since the separation at Memphis
<pb id="hughes192" n="192"/>
years before. We, therefore, concluded to go as far 
as Cincinnati, at any rate, and endeavor to get some 
further information of mother.  My wife seemed to 
gather new strength in learning this news of her 
mother, meager though it was. After a stay in 
Memphis of six weeks we went on to Cincinnati, 
hopeful of meeting some, at least, of the family that, 
though free, in defiance of justice, had been consigned 
to cruel and hopeless bondage  -  bondage in violation 
of civil as well as moral law. We felt it was almost 
impossible that we should see any one that we ever 
knew; but the man had spoken so earnestly and 
positively regarding my mother-in-law that we were not 
without hope. On arriving at Cincinnati, our first inquiry 
was about her, my wife giving her name and 
description; and, fortunately, we came upon a colored 
man who said he knew of a woman answering to the 
name and description which my wife gave of her 
mother, and he directed us to the house where she was 
stopping. When we reached the place to which we 
had been directed, my wife not only found her mother 
but one of her sisters. The meeting was a joyful one 
to us all. No mortal who has not experienced it can 
imagine the feeling of those who meet again after 
<pb id="hughes193" n="193"/>
long years of enforced separation and hardship and 
utter ignorance of one another's condition and place 
of habitation. I questioned them as to when and 
where they had met, and how it happened that they 
were now together. My mother-in-law then began 
the following narrative:</p>
          <p>“When I was sold from the Memphis trader's yard 
I was bought by a man who lived not far from Memphis. 
I never heard of any of the children, and knew 
nothing as to what had become of them. After the 
capture of Memphis by the Union army, the people to 
whom I belonged fled from their home, leaving their 
slaves; and the other slaveholders of the neighborhood 
did the same. The slaves, left to themselves, at 
once departed for Memphis, and I among the number. 
When I had been there but a short time a call was 
made for nurses to go into the hospital; and, after 
thinking of it for a few minutes, I concluded to 
answer the call, and was speedily installed in the 
work. When I had been there a short time I found, 
to my great surprise and delight, my eldest daughter 
was also employed there. She had come to Memphis 
as I had, because her master's family had fled; and, 
hearing the call for nurses, had entered the service at
<pb id="hughes194" n="194"/>
once. I can not tell my pleasure in meeting one of 
my children, for I had never expected to see any of 
them again. We continued our work in the hospital 
until Generals Sheridan and Grant said the city was 
getting too crowded with colored people  -  there was 
not room for them; some must be removed. So, large 
numbers of them were sent to Cincinnati, and my 
daughter and I were among them. This is why you 
see us here together.”</p>
          <p>When she had finished telling this story my wife 
and I were shedding tears of joy. My sister-in-law, 
Mary Ellen, whom Boss bought at the same time that 
he bought my wife, was with us; thus the mother and 
three daughters had met again most unexpectedly, 
and in a way almost miraculous. This meeting again 
of mother and daughters, after years of separation 
and many vicisitudes, was an occasion of the profoundest 
joy, although all were almost wholly destitute 
of the necessaries of life. This first evening we 
spent together can never be forgotten. I can see the 
old woman now, with bowed form and gray locks, as 
she gave thanks in joyful tones yet reverent manner, 
for such a wonderful blessing.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="hughes195" n="195"/>
        <div2>
          <head>IN CANADA.</head>
          <p>We did not remain long in Cincinnati, as houses 
were so scarce we could not get a place to stop in. 
My wife's mother had but one room, and we could not 
stay there. We went on to Hamilton, but stayed 
there only two months. I worked at whatever I could 
get to do  -  whitewashing and odd jobs of any kind. 
The women managed to get washing to do, so that 
we got on very well. Our aim was when we left 
Memphis to get to Canada, as we regarded that as the 
safest place for refugees from slavery. We did not 
know what might come again for our injury. So, 
now, as we had found some of my wife's people, we 
were more eager to go; and, as I could not get any 
steady work in Hamilton, we made ready to move on. 
We went straight to Detroit, and crossed over the 
river to Windsor, Canada, arriving there on Christmas 
1865. I succeeded in getting work as a porter at the 
Iron House, a hotel situated near the landing.  Here 
my wife also was employed, and here we remained 
until spring; when, as the wages were so small in 
Windsor, I went over to Detroit to seek for more 
profitable employment. After some effort, I succeeded 
in securing a situation, as waiter, in the Biddle House,
<pb id="hughes196" n="196"/>
and remained there two years, when the manager 
died, and it changed hands; and, much as I disliked 
to make a change in my work, I found it necessary. 
An opportunity soon offered of a position as sailor on 
the steamer Saginaw, which ran from Green Bay to 
Escanaba, in connection with the railroad.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>A CLEW TO MY BROTHER WILLIAM.</head>
          <p>While I was on this boat, one of the men who
worked with me said to me, one day:  “Have you a 
brother, Hughes?”  I said,  “Yes, but I don't know 
anything about him. We were sold from each other 
when boys, “Well,” said he,  “I used to sail with a 
man whose name was Billy Hughes, and he looked 
just like you.”  I told him there were three boys of us; 
that we were sold to different parties, and that I had 
never seen either of my brothers since. One brother 
was named William, but went by the nickname of 
Billy. “Has this man had his forefinger cut off,” 
asked I.  “Oh!” replied he,  “I don't know, Hughes, 
about that.”  “Well,” said I, “this is all I remember 
about Billy. I accidentally chopped off his forefinger 
one day, when we were small boys in Virginia. This 
is the only thing by which I could identify my brother 
William.”  Nothing more was said upon the matter,
<pb id="hughes197" n="197"/>
and it dropped out of my mind. I did not realize how 
important were the words of this man. It never 
occured to me that he held the clew that might bring 
us together again.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>WORK IN CHICAGO.</head>
          <p>When the sailing season had ended, the steamer 
tied up at Chicago for the winter. Upon going  
ashore, I at once tried to get something else to do, for  
I could not afford to be idle a day. One of the first 
men I met in Chicago was my old friend and fellow-servant 
Thomas Bland. He was glad to see me, and 
told me all about his escape to Canada, and how he 
had met Will McGee, at Niagara Falls. He was 
working at the Sherman House, having charge of the 
coat room. I told him that I had been sailing during 
the summer, but that the boat was now laid up, and 
that I was anxious for another job. He said he would 
try and see what he could do for me. He went to the 
proprietor of the hotel, Mr. Rice; and, to my surprise 
and delight, he was so fortunate as to secure me a 
position as porter and general utility man. My 
family were still at Windsor, Canada; and, when I 
had secured this place, I got leave of absence to make 
them a visit, and went there at once. Two babies had
<pb id="hughes198" n="198"/>
been born only a day before my arrival. I had hoped 
to be there on the interesting occasion, but was too 
late.  However, I was pleased to find two bright little 
girls to aid in the family greeting, which was delightful 
after the months of separation. My wife, her 
sister Mary and her two children, her mother and the 
sister we found at Cincinnati were all still here living 
together.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>ATTENDING NIGHT SCHOOL.</head>
          <p>After a visit of two weeks with my family, I 
returned to Chicago, and began my work at the 
Sherman House. I was full of energy and hope, and 
resolved to put forth every effort to make a man of 
myself, and to earn an honest living. I saw that I 
needed education; and it was one of the bitterest  
remembrances of my servitude that I had been cheated 
out of this inalienable right  -  this immeasurable
blessing. I, therefore, determined to do what was in 
my power to gain something of that of which I had 
been cruelly defrauded. Hence I entered the night-school 
for freedmen, which had been established in 
the city, and faithfully attended its sessions during 
the months it was kept open.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="hughes199" n="199"/>
        <div2>
          <head>I SETTLE IN MILWAUKEE.</head>
          <p>I worked at the Sherman House until August 1868, 
and, during this time, saw many travelers and business 
men, and made some lasting friends among them. 
Among these was Mr. Plankinton. He seemed to take 
a fancy to me, and offered me a situation in the 
Plankinton House, soon to be opened in Milwaukee.  I 
readily accepted it for I was not getting a large 
salary, and the position which he offered promised 
more. The Plankinton House was opened in September, 
and I was placed in full charge of the coat room; 
and, after I had been there some time, I had, in 
connection with my coat room duties, charge of the 
bell stand. My wife had charge of the waiter's rooms, 
a lodging house situated on Second street, one door 
from Grand Avenue. This was a brick building that 
stood where the west portion of the Plankinton now 
stands. The second floor was used as our living 
rooms; the third and fourth floors constituted the 
sleeping apartments of the hotel waiters. My wife 
looked after these apartments, saw that they were 
clean, and had a general supervision of them.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>BEGIN BUSINESS FOR MYSELF IN A SMALL WAY.</head>
          <p>After the hotel had been running a little over a
<pb id="hughes200" n="200"/>
year, I saw there was a chance for me to make something 
at laundry work. I was allowed to take washing 
from any of the guests who desired their work 
done privately. In this way I worked up quite a 
business. I still continued my coat room duties, as 
my wife managed the laundry work. Our laundry 
business increased so rapidly I deemed it best to 
change our quarters from Second street to 216 Grand 
avenue, which seemed better suited for our purpose. 
Here the business continued to grow until it reached 
proportions of which we had little idea when we began 
it.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>MEETING RELATIVES OF MY OLD MASTER.</head>
          <p>One day while I was at the Plankinton I happened 
to be coming through the hall, when whom should I 
meet but Col. Hunting, son-in-law of old Master Jack 
McGee, of Mississippi. We came face to face, and I 
knew him at once, but he only partially recognized 
me. He said:  “I know your face, but can not recall 
your name.”  I said:  “Don't you know Louis McGee?” 
He then remembered me at once.  “Why,” 
said he, “my wife, my brother and all his family are 
here. There is a party of us on a pleasure trip 
through the north.”  I soon learned that they had 
<pb id="hughes201" n="201"/>
visited at Waukesha springs, and had been at the 
hotel only a few hours, waiting for the boat for Grand 
Haven. I hastened to bring my wife to see them and 
got back with her just in time. They were already in 
the bus, but waited for us. We very cordially shook 
hands with them. They asked me why I had come so 
far north, and I replied that we kept traveling until 
we found a place where we could make a good living. 
They wished us success and the bus rolled away.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>FINDING MY BROTHER WILLIAM.</head>
          <p>While I was at the Plankinton House many of the 
traveling men seemingly liked to talk with me when 
they came to the coat room to check their things. I 
remember one day when conversing with one of these 
gentlemen, he asked, all of a sudden:  “Say, Hughes, 
have you a brother?”  I answered:  “Yes, I had 
two, but I think they are dead. I was sold from them 
when a mere lad.”  “Well,” said he, “if you have a 
brother he is in Cleveland. There is a fellow there 
who is chief cook at the Forest City Hotel who looks 
just like you.”  I grew eager at these words, and put 
the same question to him that I did to the man on the 
steamer when I was sailing:  “Has he one fore-finger 
cut off?”  He laughed and answered: “Well, I don't
<pb id="hughes202" n="202"/>
know, Hughes, about that; but I do know this:  His 
name is Billy and he resembles you very much. I'll 
tell you what I'll do, when I go back to Cleveland on 
my next trip I'll look and see if that fore-finger is off.” 
Now that the second person had called my attention 
to the fact that there was a man in Cleveland who 
looked very much like me, I became deeply interested  
-  in fact, I was so excited I could hardly do my work. 
I awaited the agents return with what of patience I 
could command; and, at last, one day, when I was 
least expecting him, I was greeted with these words: 
“Hello, Hughes! I have good news for you.”  I grew  
so excited I could hardly stand. still.  “Well,”  he 
said, “you told me that you had a brother whose 
name was William, but called Billy for short?” 
“Yes,” I said.  “Did your brother Billy have his 
fore-finger chopped off by his brother Louis, when, as 
boys, they were one day playing together?”  “Yes,” 
I replied.  “Then I have found your brother,” he 
said.  “I have seen the man in Cleveland, and he corroborates 
your story in every particular. He says 
that he was born in Virginia, near Charlottesville, 
and was owned by one John Martin.”  I knew now, 
beyond question, that this was my brother William.
<pb id="hughes203" n="203"/>
Words failed me to express my feelings at this news. 
The prospect of seeing my brother, lost so many years 
before, made me almost wild with joy. I thanked the 
agent for the interest he had taken in me, and for the 
invaluable and comprehensive information he had 
brought. He could hardly have done me a greater 
favor, or bound me to him by a more lasting obligation.</p>
          <p>My first step was to arrange for a leave of absence 
from my work, which I found no difficulty in accomplishing, 
and by night I was aboard the express going 
to Cleveland. My excitement did not diminish as I 
sped on my journey, and the speed of the express was 
too slow for my eager anticipations. Upon reaching 
Cleveland I went directly to the hotel where I was 
told my brother was employed, and inquired at the 
office for Billy Hughes. A bell boy was summoned to 
take me around to the department where he was. 
When we met neither of us spoke for some moments  -  
speech is not for such occasions, but silence rather, 
and the rush of thoughts. When the first flash of 
feeling had passed I spoke, calling him by name, and 
he addressed me as brother. There seemed to be no 
doubt on either side as to our true relationship,
<pb id="hughes204" n="204"/>
though the features of each had long since faded forever 
from the memory of the other. He took me to 
his house; and each of us related his story with such 
feelings as few can fully appreciate. He told me that 
he had never heard anything of our mother or brother. 
He went back to the old home in Virginia, after the 
close of the rebellion, but could get no trace of her.</p>
          <p>As we related our varied experiences  -  the hardships, 
the wrongs and sorrows which we endured and 
at last the coming of brighter days, we were sad, 
then happy. It seemed, and indeed was, wonderful 
that we should have met again after so long a separation. 
The time allotted to my visit with him passed 
most pleasantly, and all too quickly; and, as I looked 
into the faces of his wife and children, I seemed to 
have entered a new and broader life, and one in which 
the joys of social intercourse had marvelously expanded. 
When I came to saying good-bye to him, so 
close did I feel to him, the tie between us seemed 
never to have been broken. That week, so full of new 
experiences and emotions can never be erased from 
my memory. After many promises of the maintenance 
of the social relations thus renewed, we parted, to 
take up again the burdens of life, but with new 
inspiration and deeper feeling.</p>
          <pb id="hughes205" n="205"/>
          <p>I came back to my work with renewed vigor, and 
I could not but rejoice and give praise to God for the 
blessings that I had experienced in the years since my 
bondage, and especially for this partial restoration of 
the broken tie of kindred. I had long since learned 
to love Christ, and my faith in him was so firmly established 
that I gave him praise for each and every 
ray of happiness that came into my life.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>GROWTH OF THE LAUNDRY BUSINESS.</head>
          <p>I continued the laundry work, in connection with 
that at the hotel, until 1874. I had been in the 
Plankinton House then six years and a half. The 
laundry business had increased to such an extent that 
my wife could not manage it all alone. I, therefore, 
gave up my position at the hotel, and went into the 
laundry work on a somewhat larger scale than that 
upon which we had been conducting it. We were still 
doing business at 216 Grand avenue, and there we remained 
until 1876; when we removed to more commodious 
quarters at 713 on the avenue. But we remained 
there only a few months, when we removed to 
134 Fourth street in the rear. The establishment  
here was fitted up with all modern appliances; but I 
was not so successful as I anticipated. My losses
<pb id="hughes206" n="206"/>
were heavy; and though the facilities for doing the 
work were much better than those which we had before 
possessed, the location was not so accessible or 
inviting. We, therefore, went back to our former 
location at 713 on the avenue.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>EMPLOYED AS A NURSE.</head>
          <p>Not long after this, Dr. Douglas, a prominent 
physician of the city at that time, was in failing 
health, and, wishing a nurse, I was recommended to 
him for this service by a friend. I served the doctor 
in this capacity every night for three months. I then 
went with him to McComb, a village in southern 
Mississippi, which had been, in the days of slavery, a 
somewhat famous resort, but which had lost its prestige, 
and entered upon a general decline; the hotel 
and all its surroundings presenting the appearance of 
general dilapidation. I remained here with the 
doctor for two weeks  -  until they succeeded in getting 
another person to care for him. I then took a run 
down to New Orleans.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>A TRIP SOUTH.</head>
          <p>On this southern trip I had the opportunity of observing 
the condition of the country through which 
we passed. Many of the farms seemed neglected, the
<pb id="hughes207" n="207"/>
houses dilapidated, or abandoned, the fields either uncultivated 
and overgrown with bushes, or the crops 
struggling with grass and weeds for the mastery, and 
presenting but little promise of a paying harvest.  In 
some places the bushes and other undergrowth were 
fifteen feet high, and the landscape was peculiar and 
by no means inviting. I could remember the appearance 
of the cotton farms in slavery days; but how 
changed were things I now saw!  They did not look 
at all like those which I had been accustomed to see. 
Everything was dismal and uninviting. The entire 
country passed through in Mississippi looked like a 
wilderness. This deterioration was the natural 
result of the devastating war which had swept the 
country, and to the industrial revolution which followed 
and to which affairs had not been adjusted.</p>
          <p>When I arrived at New Orleans I found the levee 
filled with fruit. Oranges and bananas were piled in 
masses like coal, and the scenes in this portion of the 
city were very different from anything one sees in the 
north.  Among the many places of interest in the 
city were the cemeteries. Owing to the low level of 
the ground and its saturation with water, burials are 
seldom made in graves, but instead in tombs built of
<pb id="hughes208" n="208"/>
brick or marble or other stone, in which are constructed 
cells running back from the front and of a 
size and shape sufficient to admit a coffin. Then, as 
soon as filled, they are sealed up. These tombs contain 
from two to six or eight, or even more of these 
cells, and their general appearance from the front is 
not unlike that of a section of mail boxes in a postoffice. 
Other places of interest were the old French 
market, the public squares and gardens, the old 
Catholic churches, and some of the relics of slavery 
days in the shape of pens where slaves were exposed 
for sale. One of these was in the basement of the 
Hotel Royal, which would contain several hundred at  
once, and from which hundreds went to a bondage 
bitterer than death, and from which death was the 
only relief.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>I MAKE NURSING MY REGULAR BUSINESS.</head>
          <p>I came back to Milwaukee with a new idea. I 
liked nursing  -  it was my choice from childhood. 
Even though I had been deprived of a course of training, 
I felt that I was not too old to try, at least, to 
learn the art, or to add to what I already knew. Dr. 
Douglas gave me a splendid recommendation, and had 
some cards printed, bearing my name and address.
<pb id="hughes209" n="209"/>
These I distributed, and thus began the business which 
I have followed steadily since that time. Dr. Marks 
very kindly recommended me to well known men 
needing the service of a nurse, and to his professional 
associates; and through this means, and through his 
continued kindness and interest, I have been almost 
constantly engaged in this work. I am also indebted 
to Drs. Fox and Spearman and other prominent physicians 
for recommendations which have resulted in securing 
me employment which has proved remunerative to 
me, and which seemed to give entire satisfaction to the 
sick and their friends. This is no small part of the 
compensation in the difficult, often wearing, and 
always delicate duties of the nurse in the sick room. 
To every true man or woman it is one of the greatest 
satisfactions to have the consciousness of having been 
useful to his fellow beings. My duties as nurse have 
taken me to different parts of the state, to Chicago, 
to California and to Florida; and I have thus gained 
no little experience, not only in my business, but in 
many other directions. </p>
          <p>I have endeavored, in the foregoing sketch, to give 
a clear and correct idea of the institution of human 
slavery, as I witnessed and experienced it  -  its brutality,
<pb id="hughes210" n="210"/>
its degrading influence upon both master and 
slave, and its utter incompatibility with industrial 
improvement and general educational progress. 
Nothing has been exagerated or set down in malice, 
although in the scars which I still bear upon my 
person, and in the wounds of spirit which will never 
wholly heal, there might be found a seeming excuse 
for such a course. Whatever of kindness was shown 
me during the years of my bondage, I still gratefully 
remember, whether it came from white master or fellow 
slave; and for the recognition which has been so 
generously accorded me since the badge of servitude 
was removed, I am profoundly and devoutly thankful.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>