<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Memories of Childhood's Slavery Days: Electronic Edition.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) and corrected by </resp>
          <name id="kg">Katharyn Graham.</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Natalia Smith.</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1996</date>
</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>File size: ca. 180 K.</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, NC </pubPlace>
        <date>1996</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>This work is the property of the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely 
by individuals for research, teaching and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Call number E444 .B97 1909 (Wilson
Annex, UNC-CH)</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc default="NO">
        <bibl default="NO">
<title>Memoirs of Childhood's Slavery Days</title>
<author>By Annie L. Burton </author>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<publisher>Ross Publishing Company</publisher>
<date>1909</date>
</imprint>
</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc default="NO">
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South, or the Southern Experience in 
19th-century America.</hi>
</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl default="NO">
        <p>Running titles on each page of the text have not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, ampersand and dollar signs have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl default="NO">
            <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
            <edition>21st
edition, 1998</edition>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass default="NO">
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Burton, Annie L., b. 1858?</item>
            <item>Slaves -- United States -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slavery -- United States.</item>
            <item>Slaves' writings, American.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="cover image" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <p>
          <figure id="cover" entity="burtoncv">
            <p>[Cover Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="frontispiece image" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <p>
          <figure id="frontis" entity="burtonfp">
            <p>[Frontispiece Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="title page image" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="burtontp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">
            <emph rend="bold">Memories of Childhood's</emph>
          </titlePart>
          <titlePart type="main">
            <emph rend="bold">Slavery Days</emph>
          </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>By</byline>
        <docAuthor>Annie L. Burton</docAuthor>
        <docImprint>
<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
<publisher>ROSS PUBLISHING COMPANY</publisher>
<date>1909</date>
</docImprint>
      </titlePage>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="burton3" n="3"/>
        <head>
          <emph rend="bold">RECOLLECTIONS OF A HAPPY LIFE</emph>
        </head>
        <p>The memory of my happy, care-free childhood
days on the plantation, with my little white and black
companions, is often with me. Neither master nor
mistress nor neighbors had time to bestow a thought
upon us, for the great Civil War was raging. That
great event in American history was a matter wholly
outside the realm of our childish interests. Of course
we heard our elders discuss the various events of the
great struggle, but it meant nothing to us.</p>
        <p>On the plantation there were ten white children
and fourteen colored children. Our days were spent
roaming about from plantation to plantation, not
knowing or caring what things were going on in the
great world outside our little realm. Planting time
and harvest time were happy days for us. How
often at the harvest time the planters discovered
cornstalks missing from the ends of the rows, and
blamed the crows! We were called the  “little fairy
<pb id="burton4" n="4"/>
devils.” To the sweet potatoes and peanuts and sugar
cane we also helped ourselves.</p>
        <p>Those slaves that were not married served the 
food from the great house, and about half-past 
eleven they would send the older children with food 
to the workers in the fields. Of course, I followed, 
and before we got to the fields, we had eaten the 
food nearly all up. When the workers returned home 
they complained, and we were whipped.</p>
        <p>The slaves got their allowance every Monday 
night of molasses, meat, corn meal, and a kind of 
flour called “dredgings” or “shorts.”  Perhaps
this allowance would be gone before the next Monday
night, in which case the slaves would steal hogs 
and chickens. Then would come the whipping-post. 
Master himself never whipped his slaves; this was 
left to the overseer.</p>
        <p>We children had no supper, and only a little piece 
of bread or something of the kind in the morning. 
Our dishes consisted of one wooden bowl, and oyster 
shells were our spoons. This bowl served for about 
fifteen children, and often the dogs and the ducks 
and the peafowl had a dip in it. Sometimes we had 
buttermilk and bread in our bowl, sometimes greens 
or bones.</p>
        <p>Our clothes were little homespun cotton slips,
<pb id="burton5" n="5"/>
with short sleeves. I never knew what shoes were until I
got big enough to earn them myself.</p>
        <p>If a slave man and woman wished to marry, a 
party would be arranged some Saturday night among  
the slaves. The  marriage ceremony consisted of the   
pair jumping over a stick. If no children were born
within a year or so, the wife was sold.</p>
        <p>At New Year's, if there was any debt or mortgage 
on the plantation, the extra slaves were taken to 
Clayton and sold at the court house. In this way 
families were separated.</p>
        <p>When they were getting recruits for the war, we 
were allowed to go to Clayton to see the soldiers.</p>
        <p>I remember, at the beginning of the war, two colored
men were hung in Clayton; one, Caesar King, 
for killing a blood hound and biting off an overseer's 
ear; the other, Dabney Madison, for the murder of 
his master. Dabney Madison's master was really 
shot by a man named Houston, who was infatuated 
with Madison's mistress, and who had hired Madison 
to make the bullets for him. Houston escaped 
after the deed, and the blame fell on Dabney Madison, 
as he was the only slave of his master and 
mistress. The clothes of the two victims were hung 
on two pine trees, and no colored person would touch 
them. Since I have grown up, I have seen the
<pb id="burton6" n="6"/>
skeleton of one of these men in the office of a doctor in
Clayton.</p>
        <p>After the men were hung, the bones were put in 
an old deserted house. Somebody that cared for 
the bones used to put them in the sun in bright 
weather, and back in the house when it rained. Finally 
the bones disappeared, although the boxes that 
had contained them still remained.</p>
        <p>At one time, when they were building barns on 
the plantation, one of the big boys got a little brandy 
and gave us children all a drink, enough to make us 
drunk. Four doctors were sent for, but nobody could 
tell what was the matter with us, except they thought 
we had eaten something poisonous. They wanted 
to give us some castor oil, but we refused to take it, 
because we thought that the oil was made from the 
bones of the dead men we had seen. Finally, we
told about the big white boy giving us the brandy, 
and the mystery was cleared up.</p>
        <p>Young as I was then, I remember this conversation
between master and mistress, on master's return 
from the gate one day, when he had received the latest 
news: “William, what is the news from the seat 
of war?” “A great battle was fought at Bull Run, 
and the Confederates won,”  he replied. “Oh, good, 
good,”  said mistress, “and what did Jeff Davis
<pb id="burton7" n="7"/>
say?” “Look out for the blockade. I do not know 
what the end may be soon,” he answered. “What 
does Jeff Davis mean by that?” she asked. “Sarah 
Anne, I don't know, unless he means that the niggers 
will be free.” “O my God, what shall we do?” 
“I presume,” he said, “we shall have to put our 
boys to work and hire help.” “But,” she said, 
“what will the niggers do if they are free, Why,
they will starve if we don't keep them.” “Oh, 
well,” he said, “let them wander, if they will not 
stay with their owners. I don't doubt that many 
owners have been good to their slaves, and they 
would rather remain with their owners than wander 
about without home or country.”</p>
        <p>My mistress often told me that my father was a 
planter who owned a plantation about two miles 
from ours. He was a white man, born in Liverpool, 
England. He died in Lewisville, Alabama, in the 
year 1875.</p>
        <p>I will venture to say that I only saw my father a 
dozen times, when I was about four years old; and 
those times I saw him only from a distance, as he 
was driving by the great house of our plantation. 
Whenever my mistress saw him going by, she would 
take me by the hand and run out upon the piazza, 
and exclaim, “ Stop there, I say! Don't you want
<pb id="burton8" n="8"/>
to see and speak to and caress your darling child? 
She often speaks of you and wants to embrace her 
dear father. See what a bright and beautiful daughter 
she is, a perfect picture of yourself. Well, I 
declare, you are an affectionate father.” I well 
remember that whenever my mistress would speak 
thus and upbraid him, he would whip up his horse
and get out of sight and hearing as quickly as possible. 
My mistress's action was, of course, intended 
to humble and shame my father. I never spoke to 
him, and cannot remember that he ever noticed me, 
or in any way acknowledged me to be his child.</p>
        <p>My mother and my mistress were children together, 
and grew up to be mothers together. My 
mother was the cook in my mistress's household. 
One morning when master had gone to Eufaula, my 
mother and my mistress got into an argument, the 
consequence of which was that my mother was 
whipped, for the first time in her life. Whereupon, 
my mother refused to do any more work, and ran 
away from the plantation. For three years we did 
not see her again.</p>
        <p>Our plantation was one of several thousand acres,
comprising large level fields, upland, and considerable
forests of Southern pine. Cotton, corn, sweet 
potatoes, sugar cane, wheat, and rye were the principal
<pb id="burton9" n="9"/>
crops raised on the plantation. It was situated 
near the P-----  River, and about twenty-three miles 
from Clayton, Ala.</p>
        <p>One day my master heard that the Yankees were  
coming our way, and he immediately made preparations 
to get his goods and valuables out of their
reach. The big six-mule team was brought to the 
smoke-house door, and loaded with hams and provisions. 
After being loaded, the team was put in 
the care of two of the most trustworthy and valuable 
slaves that my master owned, and driven away. It 
was master's intention to have these things taken 
to a swamp, and there concealed in a pit that had 
recently been made for the purpose. But just before 
the team left the main road for the by-road that led 
to the swamp, the two slaves were surprised by the 
Yankees, who at once took possession of the provisions, 
and started the team toward Clayton, where 
the Yankees had headquarters. The road to Clayton 
ran past our plantation. One of the slave children 
happened to look up the road, and saw the Yankees 
coming, and gave warning. Whereupon, my master 
left unceremoniously for the woods, and remained 
concealed there for five days. The niggers had run 
away whenever they got a chance, but now it was 
master's and the other white folks' turn to run.</p>
        <pb id="burton10" n="10"/>
        <p>The Yankees rode up to the piazza of the great 
house and inquired who owned the plantation. They 
gave orders that nothing must be touched or taken 
away, as they intended to return shortly and take 
possession. My mistress and the slaves watched 
for their return day and night for more than a week, 
but the Yankees did not come back.</p>
        <p>One morning in April, 1865, my master got the 
news that the Yankees had left Mobile Bay and 
crossed the Confederate lines, and that the Emancipation 
Proclamation had been signed by President 
Lincoln. Mistress suggested that the slaves should 
not be told of their freedom; but master said he 
would tell them, because they would soon find it out, 
even if he did not tell them. Mistress, however, said 
she could keep my mother's three children, for my
mother had now been gone so long.</p>
        <p>All the slaves left the plantation upon the news 
of their freedom, except those who were feeble or 
sickly. With the help of these, the crops were gathered. 
My mistress and her daughters had to go to 
the kitchen and to the washtub. My little half-
brother, Henry, and myself had to gather chips, and 
help all we could. My sister, Caroline, who was
twelve years old, could help in the kitchen.</p>
        <p>After the war, the Yankees took all the good mules
<pb id="burton11" n="11"/>
and horses from the plantation, and left their old 
army stock. We children chanced to come across 
one of the Yankees' old horses, that had “U. S.” 
branded on him. We called him “Old Yank” and 
got him fattened up. One day in August, six of us 
children took  “Old Yank” and went away back on 
the plantation for watermelons. Coming home, we 
thought we would make the old horse trot. When 
“Old Yank” commenced to trot, our big melons
dropped off, but we couldn't stop the horse for some 
time. Finally, one of the big boys went back and got 
some more melons, and left us eating what we could 
find of the ones that had been dropped. Then all we 
six, with our melons, got on “Old Yank” and went 
home. We also used to hitch “Old Yank” into a 
wagon and get wood. But one sad day in the fall, 
the Yankees came back again, and gathered up their 
old stock, and took “Old Yank” away.</p>
        <p>One day mistress sent me out to do some churning
under a tree. I went to sleep and jerked the churn 
over on top of me. and consequently got a whipping.</p>
        <p>My mother came for us at the end of the year 
1865, and demanded that her children be given up 
to her. This, mistress refused to do, and threatened 
to set the dogs on my mother if she did not at once
<pb id="burton12" n="12"/>
leave the place. My mother went away, and remained 
with some of the neighbors until supper 
time. Then she got a boy to tell Caroline to come 
down to the fence. When she came, my mother told 
her to go back and get Henry and myself and bring 
us down to the gap in the fence as quick as she could. 
Then my mother took Henry in her arms, and my 
sister carried me on her back. We climbed fences 
and crossed fields, and after several hours came to a 
little hut which my mother had secured on a plantation. 
We had no more than reached the place, and 
made a little fire, when master's two sons rode up 
and demanded that the children be returned. My 
mother refused to give us up. Upon her offering to 
go with them to the Yankee headquarters to find out 
if it were really true that all negroes had been made 
free, the young men left, and troubled us no more.</p>
        <p>The cabin that was now our home was made of 
logs. It had one door, and an opening in one wall, 
with an inside shutter, was the only window. The 
door was fastened with a latch. Our beds were some 
straw.</p>
        <p>There were six in our little family; my mother, 
Caroline, Henry, two other children that my mother 
had brought with her upon her return, and myself.</p>
        <p>The man on whose plantation this cabin stood,
<pb id="burton13" n="13"/>
hired my mother as cook, and gave us this little home. 
We children used to sell blueberries and plums that 
we picked. One day the man on whom we depended 
for our home and support, left. Then my mother 
did washing by the day, for whatever she could get. 
We were sent to get cold victuals from hotels and 
such places. A man wanting hands to pick cotton, 
my brother Henry and I were set to help in this
work. We had to go to the cotton field very early
every morning. For this work, we received forty
cents for every hundred pounds of cotton we picked.</p>
        <p>Caroline was hired out to take care of a baby.</p>
        <p>In 1866, another man hired the plantation on which
our hut stood, and we moved into Clayton, to a little
house my mother secured there. A rich lady came
to our house one day, looking for some one to take
care of her little daughter. I was taken, and adopted
into this family. This rich lady was Mrs. E. M. Williams, 
a music teacher, the wife of a lawyer. We
called her “Mis' Mary.”</p>
        <p>Some rich people in Clayton who had owned slaves,
opened the Methodist church on Sundays, and began
the work of teaching the negroes. My new mistress 
sent me to Sunday school every Sunday morning,
and I soon got so that I could read. Mis' Mary 
taught me every day at her knee. I soon could read 
<pb id="burton14" n="14"/>
nicely, and went through Sterling's Second Reader, 
and then into McGuthrie's Third Reader. The first 
piece of poetry I recited in Sunday school was taught 
to me by Mis' Mary during the week. Mis' Mary's 
father-in-law, an ex-judge, of Clayton, Alabama, 
heard me recite it, and thought it was wonderful. It 
was this:</p>
        <lg type="poem" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <l part="N">“I am glad to see you, little bird,</l>
          <l part="N">It was your sweet song I heard.</l>
          <l part="N">What was it I heard you say?</l>
          <l part="N">Give me crumbs to eat today?</l>
          <l part="N">Here are crumbs I brought for you.</l>
          <l part="N">Eat your dinner, eat away,</l>
          <l part="N">Come and see us every day.”</l>
        </lg>
        <p>After this Mis' Mary kept on with my studies, and 
taught me to write. As I grew older, she taught me   
to cook and how to do housework. During this time 
Mis' Mary had given my mother one dollar a month 
in return for my services; now as I grew up to young 
womanhood, I thought I would like a little money of 
my own. Accordingly, Mis' Mary began to pay me 
four dollars a month, besides giving me my board 
and clothes. For two summers she “let me out” 
while she was away, and I got five dollars a month.</p>
        <p>While I was with Mis' Mary, I had my first sweetheart,
one of the young fellows who attended Sunday
<pb id="burton15" n="15"/>
school with me. Mis' Mary, however, objected to the
young man's coming to the house to call, because she 
did not think I was old enough to have a sweetheart.</p>
        <p>I owe a great deal to Mis' Mary for her good training 
of me, in honesty, uprightness and truthfulness. 
She told me that when I went out into the world all 
white folks would not treat me as she had, but that I 
must not feel bad about it, but just do what I was 
employed to do, and if I wasn't satisfied, to go elsewhere; 
but always to carry an honest name.</p>
        <p>One Sunday when my sweetheart walked to the 
gate with me, Mis' Mary met him and told him she 
thought I was too young for him, and that she was 
sending me to Sunday school to learn, not to catch 
a beau. It was a long while before he could see me 
again, - not until later in the season, in watermelon 
time, when Mis' Mary and my mother gave me permission 
to go to a watermelon party one Sunday 
afternoon. Mis' Mary did not know, however, that 
my sweetheart had planned to escort me. We met 
around the corner of the house, and after the party 
he left me at the same place. After that I saw him 
occasionally at barbecues and parties. I was permitted 
to go with him some evenings to church, but 
my mother always walked ahead or behind me and 
the young man.</p>
        <pb id="burton16" n="16"/>
        <p>We went together for four years. During that 
time, although I still called Mis' Mary's my home, I 
had been out to service in one or two families.</p>
        <p>Finally, my mother and Mis' Mary consented to 
our marriage, and the wedding day was to be in May. 
The winter before that May, I went to service in the 
family of Dr. Drury in Eufaula. Just a week before 
I left Clayton I dreamed that my sweetheart died 
suddenly. The night before I was to leave, we were 
invited out to tea. He told me he had bought a nice 
piece of poplar wood, with which to make a table for 
our new home. When I told him my dream, he said, 
“Don't let that trouble you, there is nothing in 
dreams.” But one month from that day he died, 
and his coffin was made from the piece of poplar 
wood he had bought for the table.</p>
        <p>After his death, I remained in Clayton for two or 
three weeks with my people, and then went back to 
Eufaula, where I stayed two years.</p>
        <p>My sweetheart's death made a profound impression 
on me, and I began to pray as best I could. 
Often I remained all night on my knees.</p>
        <p>Going on an excursion to Macon, Georgia, one 
time, I liked the place so well that I did not go back 
to Eufaula. I got a place as cook in the family of 
an Episcopal clergyman, and remained with them
<pb id="burton17" n="17"/>
eight years, leaving when the family moved to New 
Orleans. </p>
        <p>During these eight years, my mother died in Clayton, 
and I had to take the three smallest children 
into my care. My oldest sister was now married, 
and had a son.</p>
        <p>I now went to live with a Mrs. Maria Campbell, a
colored woman, who adopted me and gave me her 
name. Mrs. Campbell did washing and ironing for 
her living While living with her, I went six months 
to Lewis' High School in Macon. Then I went to 
Atlanta, and obtained a place as first-class cook with 
Mr. E. N. Inman. But I always considered Mrs. 
Campbell's my home. I remained about a year with 
Mr. Inman, and received as wages ten dollars a
month.</p>
        <p>One day, when the family were visiting in Memphis, 
I chanced to pick up a newspaper, and read the 
advertisement of a Northern family for a cook to go 
to Boston. I went at once to the address given, and 
made agreement to take the place, but told the people 
that I  could not leave my present position until Mr. 
Inman returned home. Mr. and Mrs. Inman did 
not want to let me go, but I made up my mind to go 
North. The Northern family whose service I was 
to enter had returned to Boston before I left, and
<pb id="burton18" n="18"/>
had made arrangements with a friend, Mr. Bullock, to see
me safely started North.</p>
        <p>After deciding to go North, I went to Macon, to 
make arrangements with Mrs. Campbell for the care 
of my two sisters who lived with her. One sister 
was now about thirteen and the other fifteen, both 
old enough to do a little for themselves. My brother 
was dead. He went to Brunswick in 1875, and died 
there of the yellow fever in 1876. One sister I 
brought in later years to Boston. I stayed in Macon 
two weeks, and was in Atlanta three or four days 
before leaving for the North.</p>
        <p>About the 15th of June, 1879, I arrived at the Old
Colony Station in Boston, and had my first glimpse 
of the country I had heard so much about. From 
Boston I went to Newtonville, where I was to work. 
The gentleman whose service I was to enter, Mr. E. 
N. Kimball, was waiting at the station for me, and 
drove me to his home on Warner Street. For a few 
days, until I got somewhat adjusted to my new circumstances,
I had no work to do. On June 17th the 
family took me with them to Auburndale. But in 
spite of the kindness of Mrs. Kimball and the colored 
nurse, I grew very homesick for the South, and would 
often look in the direction of my old home and cry.</p>
        <p>The washing, a kind of work I knew nothing about,
<pb id="burton19" n="19"/>
was given to me; but I could not do it, and it was 
finally given over to a hired woman. I had to do the 
ironing of the fancy clothing for Mrs. Kimball and 
the children.</p>
        <p>About five or six weeks after my arrival, Mrs. 
Kimball and the children went to the White Mountains 
for the summer, and I had more leisure. Mr. 
Kimball went up to the mountains every Saturday 
night, to stay with his family over Sunday; but he 
and his father-in-law were at home other nights, and 
I had to have dinner for them.</p>
        <p>To keep away the homesickness and loneliness as 
much as possible, I made acquaintance with the hired 
girl across the street.</p>
        <p>One morning I climbed up into the cherry tree that 
grew between Mr. Kimball's yard and the yard of his 
next-door neighbor, Mr. Roberts. I was thinking of 
the South, and as I picked the cherries, I sang a 
Southern song. Mr. Roberts heard me, and gave me 
a dollar for the song.</p>
        <p>By agreement, Mrs. Kimball was to give me three
dollars and a half a week, instead of four, until the
difference amounted to my fare from the South; 
after that, I was to have four dollars. I had, however, 
received but little money. In the fall, after the 
family came home, we had a little difficulty about my
<pb id="burton20" n="20"/>
wages, and I left and came into Boston. One of my 
Macon acquaintances had come North before me, 
and now had a position as cook in a house on Columbus 
Avenue. I looked this girl up. Then I went to 
a lodging-house for colored people on Kendall 
Street, and spent one night there. Mrs. Kimball had 
refused to give me a recommendation, because she 
wanted me to stay with her, and thought the lack of 
a recommendation would be an inducement. In the
lodging-house I made acquaintance with a colored 
girl, who took me to an intelligence office. The man 
at the desk said he would give me a card to take to 
24 Springfield Street, on receipt of fifty cents. I had 
never heard of an office of this kind, and asked a 
good many questions. After being assured that my 
money would be returned in case I did not accept 
the situation, I paid the fifty cents and started to find
the address on the card. Being ignorant of the 
scheme of street numbering, I inquired of a woman 
whom I met, where No. 24 was. This woman asked 
me if I was looking for work, and when I told her I 
was, she said a friend of hers on Springfield Street 
wanted a servant immediately. Of course I went 
with this lady, and after a conference with the
mistress of the house as to my ability, when I 
could begin work, what wages I should want, etc.,
<pb id="burton21" n="21"/>
I was engaged as cook at three dollars and a half
a week.</p>
        <p>From this place I proceeded to 24 Springfield 
Street, as directed, hoping that I would be refused, 
so that I might go back to the intelligence office and 
get my fifty cents. The lady at No. 24 who wanted 
a servant, said she didn't think I was large and 
strong enough, and guessed I wouldn't do. Then I 
went and got my fifty cents.</p>
        <p>Having now obtained a situation, I sent to Mr. 
Kimball's for my trunk. I remained in my new 
place a year and a half. At the end of that time the 
family moved to Dorchester, and because I did not 
care to go out there, I left their service.</p>
        <p>From this place, I went to Narragansett Pier to 
work as a chambermaid for the summer. In the fall, 
I came back to Boston and obtained a situation with 
a family, in Berwick Park. This family afterward 
moved to Jamaica Plain, and I went with them. 
With this family I remained seven years. They were 
very kind to me, gave me two or three weeks' vacation, 
without loss of pay.</p>
        <p>In June, 1884, I went with them to their summer 
home in the Isles of Shoals, as housekeeper for some 
guests who were coming from Paris. On the 6th of 
July I received word that my sister Caroline had
<pb id="burton22" n="22"/>
died in June. This was a great blow to me. I remained 
with the Reeds until they closed their summer 
home, but I was not able to do much work after 
the news of my sister's death.</p>
        <p>I wrote home to Georgia, to the white people who
owned the house in which Caroline had lived, asking 
them to take care of her boy Lawrence until I should 
come in October. When we came back to Jamaica 
Plain in the fall, I was asked to decide what I should 
do in regard to this boy. Mrs. Reed wanted me to 
stay with her, and promised to help pay for the care 
of the boy in Georgia. Of course, she said, I could 
not expect to find positions if I had a child with me. 
As an inducement to remain in my present place 
and leave the boy in Georgia, I was promised provision 
for my future days, as long as I should live. It 
did not take me long to decide what I should do. The 
last time I had seen my sister, a little over a year 
before she died, she had said, when I was leaving, 
“I don't expect ever to see you again, but if I die 
I shall rest peacefully in my grave, because I know 
you will take care of my child.”</p>
        <p>I left Jamaica Plain and took a room on Village 
Street for the two or three weeks until my departure 
for the South. During this time, a lady came to the 
house to hire a girl for her home in Wellesley Hills.
<pb id="burton23" n="23"/>
The girl who was offered the place would not go. 
I volunteered to accept the position temporarily, and 
went at once to the beautiful farm. At the end of a 
week, a man and his wife had been engaged, and I 
was to leave the day after their arrival. These new 
servants, however, spoke very little English, and I 
had to stay through the next week until the new ones 
were broken in. After leaving there I started for 
Georgia, reaching there at the end of five days, at 
five o'clock.</p>
        <p>I took a carriage and drove at once to the house 
where Lawrence was being taken care of. He was 
playing in the yard, and when he saw me leave the 
carriage he ran and threw his arms around my neck 
and cried for joy. I stayed a week in this house, 
looking after such things of my sister's as had not 
been already stored. One day I had a headache, and 
was lying down in the cook's room. Lawrence was 
in the dining-room with the cook's little girl, and the 
two got into a quarrel, in the course of which my 
nephew struck the cook's child. The cook, in her 
anger, chased the boy with a broom, and threatened 
to give him a good whipping at all costs. Hearing 
the noise, I came out into the yard, and when Lawrence 
saw me he ran to me for protection. I interceded 
for him, and promised he should get into no
<pb id="burton24" n="24"/>
more trouble. We went at once to a neighbor's house 
for the night. The next day I got a room in the yard 
of a house belonging to some white people. Here we 
stayed two weeks. The only return I was asked to 
make for the room was to weed the garden. Lawrence 
and I dug out some weeds and burned them, 
but came so near setting fire to the place that we 
were told we need not dig any more weeds, but that 
we might have the use of the room so long as we 
cared to stay.</p>
        <p>In about a week and a half more we got together 
such things as we wanted to keep and take away 
with us. </p>
        <p>The last time I saw my sister, I had persuaded her 
to open a bank account, and she had done so, and 
had made small deposits from time to time. When 
I came to look for the bankbook, I discovered that 
her lodger, one Mayfield, had taken it at her death, 
and nobody knew where it might be now. I found 
out that Mayfield had drawn thirty dollars from the
account for my sister's burial, and also an unknown 
amount for himself. He had done nothing for the 
boy. I went down to the bank, and was told that 
Mayfield claimed to look after my sister's burial 
and her affairs. He had made one Reuben Bennett, 
who was no relation and had no interest in the matter,
<pb id="burton25" n="25"/>
administrator for Lawrence, until his coming 
of age. But Bennett had as yet done nothing for 
him. The book was in the bank, with some of the 
account still undrawn, how much I did not know. I 
next went to see a lawyer, to find out how much it 
would cost me to get this book. The lawyer said
fifteen dollars. I said I would call again. In the 
meantime, I went to the court house, and when the 
case on trial was adjourned I went to the judge and 
stated my case. The judge, who was slightly acquainted 
with my sister and me, told me to have 
Reuben Bennett in court next morning at nine 
o'clock, and to bring Lawrence with me. When we 
had all assembled before the judge, he told Bennett 
to take Lawrence and go to the bank and get the 
money belonging to my sister. Bennett went and collected 
the money, some thirty-five dollars. The boy 
was then given into my care by the judge. For his 
kindness, the judge would accept no return. Happy 
at having obtained the money so easily, we went back 
to our room, and rested until our departure the next 
night for Jacksonville, Florida. I had decided to go 
to this place for the winter, on account of Lawrence, 
thinking the Northern winter would be too severe 
for him.</p>
        <p>My youngest sister, who had come to Macon from
<pb id="burton26" n="26"/>
Atlanta a few days before my arrival, did not hear 
of Caroline's death until within a few days of our 
departure. This youngest sister decided to go to 
Florida with us for the winter.</p>
        <p>Our trunks and baggage were taken to the station 
in a team. We had a goodly supply of food, given 
us by our friends and by the people whose hospitality 
we had shared during the latter part of our stay.</p>
        <p>The next morning we got into Jacksonville. My 
idea was to get a place as chambermaid at Green 
Cove Springs, Florida, through the influence of the 
head waiter at a hotel there, whom I knew. After I 
got into Jacksonville I changed my plans. I did not 
see how I could move my things any farther, and we 
went to a hotel for colored people, hired a room for 
two dollars, and boarded ourselves on the food which 
had been given us in Macon. This food lasted 
about two weeks. Then I had to buy, and my money 
was going every day, and none coming in. I did not 
know what to do. One night the idea of keeping a 
restaurant came to me, and I decided to get a little 
home for the three of us, and then see what I could 
do in this line of business. After a long and hard 
search, I found a little house of two rooms where we
could live, and the next day I found a place to start 
my restaurant. For house furnishings, we used at
<pb id="burton27" n="27"/>
first, to the best advantage we could, the things we 
had brought from Macon. Caroline's <sic>cookstove</sic> had 
been left with my foster-mother in Macon. After 
hiring the room for the restaurant, I sent for this 
stove, and it arrived in a few days. Then I went to 
a dealer in second-hand furniture and got such things 
as were actually needed for the house and the restaurant, 
on the condition that he would take them back 
at a discount when I got through with them.</p>
        <p>Trade at the restaurant was very good, and we 
got along nicely. My sister got a position as nurse 
for fifteen dollars a month. One day the cook from 
a shipwrecked vessel came to my restaurant, and in 
return for his board and a bed in the place, agreed 
to do my cooking. After trade became good, I 
changed my residence to a house of four rooms, and 
put three cheap cots in each of two of the rooms, and 
let the cots at a dollar a week apiece to colored men 
who worked nearby in hotels. Lawrence and I did 
the chamber work at night, after the day's work in 
the restaurant.</p>
        <p>I introduced “Boston baked beans” into my restaurant,
much to the amusement of the people at 
first; but after they had once eaten them it was hard 
to meet the demand for beans.</p>
        <p>Lawrence, who was now about eleven years old,
<pb id="burton28" n="28"/>
was a great help to me. He took out dinners to the
<sic>cigarmakers</sic> in a factory nearby.</p>
        <p>At the end of the season, about four months, it 
had grown so hot that we could stay in Jacksonville 
no longer. From my restaurant and my lodgers I 
cleared one hundred and seventy-five dollars, which 
I put into the Jacksonville bank. Then I took the furniture 
back to the dealer, who fulfilled his agreement.</p>
        <p>My sister decided to go back to Atlanta when she 
got through with her place as nurse, which would 
not be for some weeks. </p>
        <p>I took seventy-five dollars out of my bank account, 
and with Lawrence went to Fernandina. There we 
took train to Port Royal, S. C., then steamer to New 
York. From New York we went to Brooklyn for a 
few days. Then we went to Newport and stayed with 
a woman who kept a lodging-house. I decided to see 
what I could do in Newport by keeping a boarding 
and lodging-house. I hired a little house and agreed 
to pay nine dollars a month for it. I left Lawrence 
with some neighbors while I came to Boston and took 
some things out of storage. These things I moved 
into the little house. But I found, after paying one 
month's rent, that the house was not properly located 
for the business I wanted. I left, and with Lawrence 
went to Narragansett Pier. I got a place there as
<pb id="burton29" n="29"/>
“runner” for a laundry; that is, I was to go to the 
hotels and leave cards and solicit trade. Then Lawrence 
thought he would like to help by doing a little 
work. One night when I came back from the laundry, 
I missed him. Nobody had seen him. All night 
I searched for him, but did not find him. In the early 
morning I met him coming home. He said a man
who kept a bowling  alley had hired him at fifty cents 
a week to set up the pins, and it was in the bowling 
alley he had been all night. He said the man let him 
take a nap on his coat when he got sleepy. I went 
at once to see this man, and told him not to hire my 
nephew again. A lady who kept a hotel offered me 
two dollars a week for Lawrence's services in helping 
the cook and serving in the help's dining-room.
When the season closed, the lady who hired Lawrence 
was very reluctant to let him go.</p>
        <p>We went back to Newport to see the landlady 
from whom I had hired the house, and I paid such 
part of the rent as I could. Then I packed my things 
and started for Boston. On reaching there, I kept 
such of my things  as I needed, and stored the rest, 
and took a furnished room. In about a week's time 
I went to see the husband of the lady for whom I had 
worked at Wellesley Hills just previous to my departure 
for the South. He had told me to let him know
<pb id="burton30" n="30"/>
when I returned to Boston. He said a man and his 
wife were at present employed at his farm, but he 
didn't know how long they would stay. Before another 
week had passed, this gentleman sent for me. 
He said his wife wanted me to go out to the farm,
and that I could have Lawrence with me. The boy, 
he said, could help his wife with the poultry, and 
could have a chance to go to school. I was promised 
three dollars and a half a week, and no washing to 
do. I was told that the farm had been offered for 
sale, and of course it might change hands any day. 
I was promised, however, that I should lose nothing 
by the change.</p>
        <p>Lawrence was very lonely at the farm, with no
companions, and used to sit and cry.</p>
        <p>The place was sold about ten weeks after I went 
there, and I came into Boston to look about for a 
restaurant, leaving Lawrence at the farm. When 
the home was broken up, the owners came to the 
Revere House, Boston. Barrels of apples, potatoes 
and other provisions were given to me.</p>
        <p>I found a little restaurant near the Providence 
depot for  sale. I made arrangements at once to
buy the place for thirty-five dollars, and the next 
day I brought Lawrence and my things from Wellesley 
Hills. I paid two dollars a week rent for my little
<pb id="burton31" n="31"/>
restaurant, and did very well. The next spring I 
sold the place for fifty dollars, in time to get a place 
at the beach for the summer.</p>
        <p>Lawrence got a position in a drug store, and kept 
it four years. Then he went to Hampton College, 
Hampton, Va. After finishing there, he came back
and then went to the World's Fair in Chicago. After
that he took a position on one of the Fall River
line boats. At the outbreak of the Spanish War,
he enlisted in Brooklyn as powderman on the battleship
Texas. He was on the Texas when the first 
shot was fired. He was present at the decoration 
of the graves of the American soldiers in Havana 
and also at the decoration of the battleship Maine 
after she was raised. After the war, he came to 
Brooklyn and got an honorable discharge. Then 
he  served as valet to a rich New York man, who 
travelled a good deal. About the middle of last 
November (1906) Lawrence came to Boston to see 
me. He is now in Atlantic City, a waiter in the 
Royal Hotel.</p>
        <p>In 1888, I was married, at 27 Pemberton Street, 
to Samuel H. Burton, by Dr. O. P. Gifford. After 
my  marriage, Mr. Burton got a place in Braintree 
as valet to an old gentleman who was slightly demented, 
and he could not be satisfied until I joined
<pb id="burton32" n="32"/>
him. So I put our things into storage and went to 
Braintree. I remained there ten months, and then 
came back to Boston. Then I got a position as head 
matron in the help's dining-room in a hotel at Watch 
Hill, R. I. My husband was also there as waiter. At 
the end of the season we both came home, and rented 
a lodging-house, and lost money on it.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="burton33" n="33"/>
        <head>
          <emph rend="bold">REMINISCENCES</emph>
        </head>
        <pb id="burton35" n="35"/>
        <p>The times changed from slavery days to freedom's 
days. As young as I was, my thoughts were mystified 
to see such wonderful changes; yet I did not 
know the meaning of these changing days. But days 
glided by, and in my mystified way I could see and 
hear many strange things. I would see my master 
and mistress in close conversation and they seemed
anxious about something that I, a child, could not 
know the meaning of.</p>
        <p>But as weeks went by, I began to understand. I 
saw all the slaves one by one disappearing from the 
plantation (for night and day they kept going) until 
there was not one to be seen.</p>
        <p>All around the plantation was left barren. Day 
after day I could run down to the gate and see down 
the road troops and troops of Garrison's Brigade, 
and in the midst of them gangs and gangs of negro 
slaves who joined with the soldiers, shouting, dancing 
and clapping their hands. The war was ended, 
and from Mobile Bay to Clayton, Ala., all along the
<pb id="burton36" n="36"/>
road, on all the plantations, the slaves thought that 
if they joined the Yankee soldiers they would be 
perfectly safe.</p>
        <p>As I looked on these I did not know what it meant, 
for I had never seen such a circus. The Yankee soldiers 
found that they had such an army of men and 
women and children, that they had to build tents and 
feed them to keep them from starving. But from 
what I, a little child, saw and heard the older ones 
say, that must have been a terrible time of trouble. 
I heard my master and mistress talking. They said, 
“Well, I guess those Yankees had such a large family
on their hands, we rather guessed those fanatics 
on freedom would be only too glad to send some back 
for their old masters to provide for them.”</p>
        <p>But they never came back to our plantation, and 
I could only speak of my own home, but I thought 
to myself, what would become of my good times all 
over the old plantation. Oh, the harvesting times, 
the great hog-killing times when several hundred 
hogs were killed, and we children watched and got 
our share of the slaughter in pig's liver roasted on 
a bed of coals, eaten ashes and all. Then came the 
great sugar-cane grinding time, when they were 
making the molasses, and we children would be hanging 
round, drinking the sugar-cane juice, and awaiting
<pb id="burton37" n="37"/>
the moment to help ourselves to everything good. 
We did, too, making ourselves sticky and dirty with 
the sweet stuff being made. Not only were the 
slave children there, but the little white children from 
Massa's house would join us and have a jolly time. 
The negro child and the white child knew not the 
great chasm between their lives, only that they had 
dainties and we had crusts.</p>
        <p>My sister, being the children's nurse, would take 
them and wash their hands and put them to bed in 
their luxurious bedrooms, while we little slaves would 
find what homes we could. My brother and I would 
go to sleep on some lumber under the house, where 
our sister Caroline would find us and put us to bed. 
She would wipe our hands and faces and make up 
our beds on the floor in Massa's house, for we had 
lived with him ever since our own mother had run
away, after being whipped by her mistress. Later 
on, after the war, my mother returned and claimed 
us. I never knew my father, who was a white man.</p>
        <p>During these changing times, just after the war, I 
was trying to find out what the change would bring 
about for us, as we were under the care of our mistress, 
living in the great house. I thought this: that 
Henry, Caroline and myself, Louise, would have to 
go as others had done, and where should we go and
<pb id="burton38" n="38"/>
what should we do? But as time went on there were 
many changes. Our mistress and her two daughters, 
Martha and Mary, had to become their own servants, 
and do all the work of the house, going into 
the kitchen, cooking and washing, and feeling very 
angry that all their house servants had run away to 
the Yankees. The time had come when our good 
times were over, our many leisure hours spent among 
the cotton fields and woods and our half-holiday on
Saturday. These were all gone. The boys had to 
leave school and take the runaway slaves' places to 
finish the planting and pick the cotton. I myself 
have worked in the  cotton field, picking great baskets 
full, too heavy for me to carry. All was over! I 
now fully understood the change in our circumstances. 
Little Henry and I had no mere time to sit 
basking ourselves in the sunshine of the sunny south. 
The land was empty and the servants all gone. I 
can see my dainty mistress coming down the steps 
saying, “Rit, you and Henry will have to go and 
pick up some chips, for Miss Mary and myself have 
to prepare the breakfast. You children will have 
to learn to work. Do you understand me, Rit and 
Henry?” “Yes, Missus, we understand.” And away
we flew, laughing, and thinking it a great joke 
that we, Massa's pets, must learn to work.</p>
        <pb id="burton39" n="39"/>
        <p>But it was a sad, sad change on the old plantation, 
and the beautiful, proud Sunny South, with its masters 
and mistresses, was bowed beneath the sin 
brought about by slavery. It was a terrible blow to 
the owners of plantations and slaves, and their children 
would feel it more than they, for they had been 
reared to be waited upon by willing or unwilling 
slaves.</p>
        <p>In this place I will insert a poem my young mistress 
taught us, for she was always reading poems 
and good stories. But first I will record a talk I 
heard between my master and mistress. They were 
sitting in the dining-room, and we children were 
standing around the table. My mistress said, 
“I suppose, as Nancy has never returned, we had better 
keep Henry, Caroline and Louise until they are of
age.” “Yes, we will,” said Massa, Miss Mary and Miss
Martha, “but it is ‘man proposes and God disposes.’”</p>
        <p>So in the following pages you will read the sequel 
to my childhood life in the Sunny South.</p>
        <p>Right after the war when my mother had got settled 
in her hut, with her little brood hovered around 
her, from which she had been so long absent, we had 
nothing to eat, and nothing to sleep on save some 
old pieces of horse-blankets and hay that the soldiers
<pb id="burton40" n="40"/>
gave her. The first day in the hut was a rainy day; 
and as night drew near it grew more fierce, and we 
children had gathered some little fagots to make a 
fire by the time mother came home, with something 
for us to eat, such as she had gathered through the 
day. It was only corn meal and <sic>pease</sic> and ham-bone 
and skins which she had for our supper. She had 
started a little fire, and said, “Some of you close 
that door,” for it was cold. She swung the pot over 
the fire and filled it with the <sic>pease</sic> and ham-bone 
and skins. Then she seated her little brood around 
the fire on the pieces of blanket, where we watched 
with all our eyes, our hearts filled with desire, looking 
to see what she would do next. She took down 
an old broken earthen bowl, and tossed into it the 
little meal she had brought, stirring it up with water, 
making a hoe cake. She said, “One of you draw 
that griddle out here,” and she placed it on the few
little coals. Perhaps this griddle you have never 
seen, or one like it. I will describe it to you. This 
griddle was a round piece of iron, quite thick, having 
three legs. It might have been made in a blacksmith's 
shop, for I have never seen one like it before 
or since. It was placed upon the coals, and with an 
old iron spoon she put on this griddle half of the 
corn meal she had mixed up. She said, “I will put
<pb id="burton41" n="41"/>
a tin plate over this, and put it away for your breakfast.”
We five children were eagerly watching the 
pot boiling, with the <sic>pease</sic> and ham-bone. The rain 
was <sic>pattering</sic> on the roof of the hut. All at once 
there came a knock at the door. My mother answered 
the knock. When she opened the door, there stood a 
white woman and three little children, all dripping 
with the rain. My mother said, “In the name of the 
Lord, where are you going on such a night, with 
these children,” The woman said, “Auntie, I am 
travelling. Will you please let me stop here to-night, 
out of the rain, with my children?” My mother 
said, “Yes, honey. I ain't got much, but what I have got I 
will share with you.” “God bless you!” 
They all came in. We children looked in wonder at 
what had come. But my mother scattered her own 
little brood and made a place for the forlorn wanderers. 
She said, “Wait, honey, let me turn over 
that hoe cake.” Then the two women fell to talking, 
each telling a tale of woe. After a time, my mother 
called out, “Here, you, Louise, or some one of you, 
put some fagots under the pot, so these <sic>pease</sic> can 
get done.” We couldn't put them under fast enough, 
first one and then another of us children, the mothers 
still talking. Soon my mother said, “Draw that hoe 
cake one side, I guess it is done.” My mother said
<pb id="burton42" n="42"/>
to the woman, “Honey, ain't you got no husband?” 
She said, “No, my husband got killed in the war.” 
My mother replied, “Well, my husband died right 
after the war. I have been away from my little 
brood for four years. With a hard struggle, I have 
got them away from the Farrin plantation, for they 
did not want to let them go. But I got them. I was
determined to have them. But they would not let 
me have them if they could have kept them. With 
God's help I will keep them from starving. The 
white folks are good to me. They give me work, and 
I know, with God's help, I can get along.” The 
white woman replied, “Yes, Auntie, my husband left 
me on a rich man's plantation. This man promised 
to look out for me until my husband came home; but 
he got killed in the war, and the Yankees have set 
his negroes free and he said he could not help me any 
more, and we would have to do the best we could for 
ourselves. I gave my things to a woman to keep 
for me until I could find my kinsfolk. They live 
about fifty miles from here, up in the country. I 
am on my way there now.” My mother said, “How 
long will it take you to get there?” “About three
days, if it don't rain.” My mother said, “Ain't 
you got some way to ride there?” “No, Auntie,
<pb id="burton43" n="43"/>
there is no way of riding up where my folks live, the 
place where I am from.”</p>
        <p>We hoped the talk was most ended, for we were
anxiously watching that pot. Pretty soon my mother
seemed to realize our existence. She exclaimed, 
“My Lord! I suppose the little children are nearly 
starved. Are those <sic>pease</sic> done, young ones?” She 
turned and said to the white woman, “Have you-all 
had anything to eat?”  “We stopped at a house 
about dinner time, but the woman didn't have anything 
but some bread and buttermilk.” My mother 
said, “Well, honey, I ain't got but a little, but I will
divide with you.” The woman said, “Thank you, 
Auntie. You just give my children a little; I can do 
without it.”</p>
        <p>Then came the dividing. We all watched with all 
our eyes to see what the shares would be. My mother 
broke a mouthful of bread and put it on each of the 
tin plates. Then she took the old spoon and equally 
divided the pea soup. We children were seated 
around the fire, with some little wooden spoons. But 
the wooden spoons didn't quite go round, and some 
of us had to eat with our fingers. Our share of the 
meal, however, was so small that we were as hungry 
when we finished as when we began.</p>
        <p>My mother said, “Take that rag and wipe your
<pb id="burton44" n="44"/>
face and hands, and give it to the others and let them 
use it, too. Put those plates upon the table.” We 
immediately obeyed orders, and took our seats again 
around the fire. “One of you go and pull that straw 
out of the corner and get ready to go to bed.” We 
all lay down on the straw, the white children with us, 
and my mother covered us over with the blanket. 
We were soon in the “Land of Nod,” forgetting our 
empty stomachs. The two mothers still continued to 
talk, sitting down on the only seats, a couple of 
blocks. A little back against the wall my mother and 
the white woman slept.</p>
        <p>Bright and early in the morning we were called 
up, and the rest of the hoe cake was eaten for breakfast, 
with a little meat, some coffee sweetened with 
molasses. The little wanderers and their mother 
shared our meal, and then they started again on their 
journey towards their home among their kinsfolk, 
and we never saw them again. My mother said, 
“God bless you! I wish you all good luck. I hope 
you will reach your home safely.”Then mother said 
to us, “You young ones put away that straw and 
sweep up the place, because I have to go to my 
work.” But she came at noon and brought us a nice 
dinner, more satisfactory than the supper and breakfast 
we had had. We children were delighted that
<pb id="burton45" n="45"/>
there were no little white children to share our meal
this time.</p>
        <p>In time, my older sister, Caroline, and myself got 
work among good people, where we soon forgot all 
the hard times in the little log cabin by the roadside 
in Clayton, Alabama.</p>
        <p>Up to my womanhood, even to this day, these memories
fill my mind. Some kind friends' eyes may see 
these pages, and may they recall some fond memories 
of their happy childhood, as what I have written 
brings back my young life in the great Sunny South.</p>
        <p>I am something of the type of Moses on this 49th
birthday; not that I am wrapped in luxuries, but that 
my thoughts are wrapped in the luxuries of the 
heavenly life in store for me, when my life work is 
done, and my friends shall be blessed by the work I 
shall have done. For God has commanded me to 
write this book, that some one may read and receive 
comfort and courage to do what God commands them 
to do. God bless every soul who shall read this true 
life story of one born in slavery.</p>
        <p>It is now six years since the inspiration to write 
this book came to me in the Franklin evening school. 
I have struggled on, helped by friends. God said, 
“Write the book and I will help you.” And He has.</p>
        <p>It was through a letter of my life that the principal
<pb id="burton46" n="46"/>
of the Franklin school said, “Write the book and I 
will help you.” But he died before the next term, 
and I worked on. On this, my 49th birthday, I can 
say I believe that the book is close to the finish.</p>
        <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <l part="N">My life is like the summer rose</l>
          <l part="N">That opens to the morning sky,</l>
          <l part="N">But ere the shades of evening close</l>
          <l part="N">Is scattered on the ground to die.</l>
          <l part="N">Yet on the rose's humble bed</l>
          <l part="N">The  sweetest dews of night are shed,</l>
          <l part="N">As if she wept a tear for me,</l>
          <l part="N">As if she wept the waste to see.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <l part="N">My life is like the autumn leaf</l>
          <l part="N">That trembles in the moon's pale ray.</l>
          <l part="N">Its hold is frail, its date is brief,</l>
          <l part="N">Restless, and soon to pass away.</l>
          <l part="N">Yet, ere that leaf shall fall and fade,</l>
          <l part="N">The parent tree will mourn its shade,</l>
          <l part="N">The winds bewail the leafless tree;</l>
          <l part="N">But none shall breathe a sigh for me.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <l part="N">My life is like the prints which feet </l>
          <l part="N">Have left on Tampa's desert strand.</l>
          <l part="N">Soon as the rising tide shall beat</l>
          <l part="N">All trace will vanish from the sand.</l>
          <l part="N">Yet, as if grieving to efface</l>
          <l part="N">All vestige of the human race,</l>
          <l part="N">On that lone shore loud moans the sea.</l>
          <l part="N">But none, alas, shall mourn for me.</l>
        </lg>
      </div1>
      <div1 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="burton47" n="47"/>
        <head>
          <emph rend="bold">A VISION</emph>
        </head>
        <pb id="burton49" n="49"/>
        <p>There remains to be told the story of my conversion 
and how I came to write the foregoing history 
of my life.</p>
        <p>In 1875 I was taken sick. I thought I was going 
to die, and I promised the Lord I would serve Him 
if he would only spare my life. When I got well 
again, however, I forgot all about my promise. 
Then I was taken sick again. It seemed I had to 
go through a dark desert place, where great demons 
stood on either side. In the distance I could just 
see a dim light, and I tried to get to this light, but 
could not reach it. Then I found myself in a 
great marsh, and was sinking. I threw up my hands and 
said, “Lord, if Thou wilt raise me from this pit, 
I will never fail to serve Thee.” Then it seemed 
as if I mounted on wings into the air, and all the
demons that stood about made a great roaring. My 
flight ended on the top of a hill. But I was troubled 
because I could not find the light. All at once, at 
the sound of a loud peal of thunder, the earth
<pb id="burton50" n="50"/>
opened, and I fell down into the pits of hell. Again 
I prayed to God to save me from this, and again I 
promised to serve Him. My prayer was answered, 
and I was able to fly out of the pit, on to a bank. 
At the foot of the little hill on which I sat were some 
little children, and they called to me to come down. 
But I could not get down. Then the children raised 
a ladder for me, and I came down among them. A
little cherub took me by the hand and led me in 
the River of Badjied of Jordan. I looked at my 
ankles and shoulders and discovered I had little 
wings. On the river was a ship. The children, the 
cherub and I got into the ship. When we reached 
a beautiful spot, the little cherub made the ship
fast, and there opened before us pearly gates, and 
we all passed through into the golden street. The 
street led to the throne of God, about which we 
marched. Then the cherub conducted us to a table 
where a feast was spread. Then the children vanished. 
The cherub took me by the hand, and said, 
“Go back into the world, and tell the saints and sinners 
what a Savior you have found, and if you prove
faithful I will take you to Heaven to live forever, 
when I come again.”</p>
        <p>When I recovered from my sickness, I was baptized 
by the Rev. Dr. Pope, and joined the church
<pb id="burton51" n="51"/>
in Macon. When I came North, I brought my letter. 
Not finding any church for colored people, I came 
among the white people, and was treated so kindly 
that I became very much attached to them. The 
first church I became connected with in the North, 
was in Newtonville. When I came to Boston, I 
went to the Warren Avenue Baptist Church. Before 
my marriage I joined Tremont Temple, when 
Dr. Lorimer was its pastor. When the church was
burned, my letter was destroyed, but when I went 
South on a visit I had the letter duplicated, and took 
it to the new Temple. I am still a member of the 
Temple, and hope to remain there as long as God 
gives me life.</p>
        <p>Five years ago, I began to go to the Franklin 
evening school. Mr. Guild was the master. At one 
time he requested all the pupils to write the story of 
their lives, and he considered my composition so interesting 
he said he thought if I could work it up 
and enlarge upon it, I could write a book. He promised 
to help me. My teacher was Miss Emerson, and 
she was interested in me. But the next year Miss 
Emerson gave up teaching, and Mr. Guild 
died.</p>
        <p>In each of the terms that I have attended, I have 
received the certificates showing that I have been 
regular and punctual in attendance, have maintained
<pb id="burton52" n="52"/>
good deportment, and shown general proficiency in 
the  studies. I would have graduated in 1907, had it 
not been for sickness. The following was to have 
been my graduating composition.</p>
      </div1>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div1 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="burton53" n="53"/>
        <head>
          <emph>ABRAHAM LINCOLN</emph>
        </head>
        <byline>BY
<docAuthor>BY
ANNIE L. BURTON</docAuthor>
</byline>
        <pb id="burton55" n="55"/>
        <p>In a little clearing in the backwoods of Harding 
County, Kentucky, there stood years ago a rude 
cabin within whose walls Abraham Lincoln passed 
his childhood. An “unaccountable” man he has 
been called, and the adjective was well chosen, for 
who account for a mind and nature like Lincoln's 
with the ancestry he owned? His father was 
a thriftless, idle carpenter, scarcely supporting his 
family, and with but the poorest living. His mother 
was an uneducated woman, but must have been of 
an entirely different nature, for she was able to 
impress upon her boy a love of learning. During 
her life, his chief, in fact his only book, was the 
Bible, and in this he learned to read. Just before 
he was nine years old, the father brought his family 
across the Ohio River into Illinois, and there in the 
unfloored log cabin, minus windows and doors, 
Abraham lived and grew. It was during this time 
that the mother died, and in a short time the shiftless 
father with his family drifted back to the old
<pb id="burton56" n="56"/>
home, and here found another for his children in 
one who was a friend of earlier days. This woman 
was of a thrifty nature, and her energy made him 
floor the cabin, hang doors, and open up windows. 
She was fond of the children and cared for them 
tenderly, and to her the boy Abraham  owed many 
pleasant hours.</p>
        <p>As he grew older, his love for knowledge increased 
and he obtained whatever books he could, 
studying by the firelight, and once walking six miles 
for an English Grammar. After he read it, he 
walked the six miles to return it. He needed the 
book no longer, for with this as with his small collection 
of books, what he once read was his. He 
absorbed the books he read.</p>
        <p>During these early years he did “odd jobs” for 
the neighbors. Even at this age, his gift of story 
telling was a notable one, as well as his sterling 
honesty. His first  knowledge of slavery in all its 
horrors came to him when he was about twenty-one 
years old. He had made a trip to New Orleans, and 
there in the old slave market he saw an  auction. 
His face paled, and his spirits rose in revolt at the
coarse jest of the auctioneer, and there he registered 
a vow within himself, “If ever I have a chance 
to strike against  slavery, I will strike and strike
<pb id="burton57" n="57"/>
hard.” To this end he worked and for this he paid 
“the last full measure of devotion.”</p>
        <p>His political life began with a defeat for the Illinois
Legislature in 1830, but he was returned in 
1834, 1836, 1838, and declined re-election in 1840, 
preferring to study law and prepare for his future. 
“Honest Abe” he has been called, and throughout 
Illinois that characteristic was the prominent one 
known of him. From this time his rise was rapid. 
Sent to the Congress of the nation, he seldom spoke,
but when he did his terse though simple expression 
always won him a hearing. His simplicity and 
frankness was deceptive to the political leaders, and 
from its very fearlessness often defeated them.</p>
        <p>His famous debates with Senator Douglas, the 
“Little Giant,” spread his reputation from one end 
of the country to the other, and at their close there 
was no question as to Lincoln's position in the 
North, or on the vital question of  the day.</p>
        <p>The spirit of forbearance he carried with him to 
the White House, “with malice toward none, with 
charity for all.” This was the spirit that carried 
him through the four awful years of the war. The 
martyr's crown hovered over him from the outset. 
The martyr's spirit was always his. The burden of 
the war always rested on his shoulders. The
<pb id="burton58" n="58"/>
fathers, sons and brothers, the honored dead of
Gettysburg, of Antietam, all lay upon his mighty 
heart.</p>
        <p>He never forgot his home friends, and when occasionally
one dropped in on him, the door was always 
open. They frequently had tea in the good old 
fashioned way, and then Lincoln listened to the news 
of the village, old stories were retold, new ones told, 
and the old friendships cemented by new bonds.</p>
        <p>Then came the end, swift and sudden, and gloom 
settled upon the country; for in spite of ancestry, 
self-education, ungainly figure, ill-fitting clothes, the 
soul of the man had conquered even the stubborn 
South, while the cold-blooded North was stricken 
to the heart. The noblest one of all had been taken.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="burton59" n="59"/>
        <head>
          <emph>THE RACE QUESTION IN AMERICA</emph>
        </head>
        <byline>BY</byline>
        <docAuthor>
<emph>DR. P. THOMAS STANFORD</emph>
AUTHOR OF THE “TRAGEDY OF THE NEGRO IN AMERICA”</docAuthor>
        <pb id="burton61" n="61"/>
        <p>As a member of the negro race, I myself have suffered 
as a child whose parents were born in slavery, deprived of all
influences of the ennobling life, made obedient to the will of 
the white man by the lash and chain, and sold to the highest 
bidder when there was no more use for them.</p>
        <p>The first negro fact for white thought is that my 
clients, the colored people here in America, are not responsible 
for being here any more than they are responsible for 
their conditions of ignorance and poverty. They suddenly 
emerge from their prison house poor, without a home, without 
food or clothing, and ignorant. Now the enemies of God and 
of the progress of civilization in our country are to-day introducing 
a system of slavery with which they hope to again 
enslave the colored people. To carry out their evil designs 
they retain able politicians, lawyers and newspapers to represent 
them, such as Senator Tillman, the Hon. John Temple 
Graves of Georgia and the Baltimore Sun, and they are trying 
the negro on four counts which allege that the race is 
ignorant, cannot be taught, is lazy and immoral.</p>
        <pb id="burton62" n="62"/>
        <p>Now, are the negroes, as a whole, guilty of these charges? 
In the first place, the negro race of America is not ignorant. 
In the year 1833 John C. Calhoun, senator from South Carolina, 
is reported to have said that if he could find a single 
negro who understood the Greek syntax, he would believe 
the negro was human and would treat him as such. At that 
time it was a very safe test. God accepted the challenge in 
behalf of the negro race, and inspired his white sons and 
daughters both in the North and South to teach their brothers 
in black; and a few years afterward black men were examined 
and the world pronounced them scholars, while later 
still the schools were using a Greek grammar written by a
black man, W. S. Scarborough of Wilberforce, O. In his 
class were Frederick Douglas, Henry Highland Garnett, 
Robert Elliot, the Rev. J. C. Price and John M. Langstone, 
as defenders of the race. Bishop Allen Payne, Bishop Hood 
and John B. Reaver will ever be remembered for their godly 
piety and Christian example, as we shall also remember 
Bishop, Sumner and Bubois for their great literary productions, 
William Washington Brown as the greatest organizer 
and financier of the century, Prof. Booker Washington as the 
greatest industrial educator of the world, and last, but not 
least, Thomas Condon, the greatest crank for the spiritual 
training and higher education of the negro race.</p>
        <p>Under the leadership of such men, assisted by our white
friends and backed up by our colored race journals - the 
Christian Banner of Philadelphia, the Christian Recorder, the 
Star of Zion and the Afro-American Ledger of Baltimore,
<pb id="burton63" n="63"/>
Ind., the National Baptist Union of Pennsylvania, the Age 
of New York, the Christian Organizer of Virginia and the 
Guardian of Boston - our onward march to civilization is 
phenomenal and by these means we have reduced illiteracy 
50 per cent.</p>
        <p>“In the South we have over $12,000,000 worth of school
property, 3,000 teachers, 50 high schools, 17 academies, 125
colleges, 10 law and medical schools, 25 theological seminaries, 
all doing a mighty work for God and humanity.</p>
        <p>Now as to laziness. We have now in practice 14,000 
lawyers and doctors, and have accumulated over $150,000,000 
worth of church property. In the South we have over 150,000 farms and
houses, valued at $900,000,000, and personal property 
at $170,000,000. We have raised over $11,000,000 
for educational purposes. The property per capita for every 
colored man, woman and child in the United States is estimated 
at $75, and we are operating successfully several banks 
and factories; we have 7,500,000 acres of land, and the business 
activity of the colored people was never as thoroughly 
aroused as it is to-day.</p>
        <p>When I come to deal with the charge of immorality 
I bow my head and blush for shame, first because if the charge 
be true, I see they are getting like the white man every day. 
I know that at the close of the American civil war the 4,000,000 
negroes had more than 25 percent. of white blood coursing 
through their veins.</p>
        <p>What about this new educated negro? Just ask the 
Pullman Car Company, which employs hundreds of negroes
<pb id="burton64" n="64"/>
into whose care thousands of women and children of our best
American families are entrusted every day.</p>
        <p>Now, you cannot do without the negro, because if you 
send him away, you will run after him. He is here to stay. 
The only way to deal successfully with the colored race is 
God's way. First, recognize that he is your guest; second, 
recognize that you have robbed him of his birthplace, home, 
family and savings. It is these facts that are causing so much
unrest on the part of the whites in this country. The negro 
loves his country, which he has proved beyond a doubt in every 
American battle, in every act of loyalty to his country, and 
in his long and patient suffering. Pay him what you owe 
him by educating him. Give him an opportunity to live.
Allow him to live in decent parts of your city. Pay wages 
sufficient to support his children. Do this and God will remove 
the objectionable negro from the land.</p>
        <p>The Negro stands to-day upon an eminence that overlooks
more than two decades spent in efforts to ameliorate the condition
of seven million immortal souls by opening before 
their hitherto dark and cheerless lives possibilities of development 
into a perfect and symmetrical manhood and womanhood.</p>
        <p>The retrospect presents to us a picture of a people's moral
degradation and mental gloom caused by slavery. A people
absolutely sunk in the lowest depth of a poverty which reduced
them to objects of charity and surrounded them with
difficulties which have ever stood as impregnable barriers in
<pb id="burton65" n="65"/>
their way to speedy advancement in all those qualities that 
make the useful citizen. Every influence of state and society 
life seems to be against their progress and like some evil 
genius, these Negro hating ghosts are forever hunting them 
with the idea that their future must be one of subserviency 
to the white race.</p>
        <p>Hated and oppressed by the combined wisdom, wealth and
statesmanship of a mighty confederacy who watched and <sic>criticised</sic> their mistakes which were strongly magnified by those
who fain would write destruction upon the Emancipation; 
they are expected to rise from this condition.</p>
        <p>The idea of giving to the newly enfranchised a sound, practical
education was considered at the dawn of freedom, an 
easy solution of what as an unsolved problem threatened the 
perpetuity of republican institutions. Within a year from 
the firing on Sumter, benevolent and farsighted Northern 
friends had established schools from Washington to the Gulf 
of Mexico, which became centers of light penetrating the 
darkness and scattering the blessings of an enlightened manhood 
far and wide. </p>
        <p>The history of the world cannot produce a more affecting
spectacle than the growth of this mighty Christian philanthropy
which, in beginning amid the din of battle, has steadily 
marched on through every opposing influence, and lifted 
a race from weakness to strength, from poverty to wealth, 
from moral and intellectual nonentity to place and power 
among the nations of the earth.</p>
        <p>We have ten millions of colored people in the United States
<pb id="burton66" n="66"/>
whose condition is much better to-day than it was fifty years
ago. Then he had nothing, not even a name. To-day he 
has 160,000 farms under good cultivation and valued at
$4,000,000 and has personal property valued at $200,000,000. 
In the Southland the negroes own 160 first-class drug stores, 
nine banks, 13 building associations, and 100 insurance and 
benefit companies, two street railways and an electric at Jacksonville, 
Fla., which they started some few years ago when 
the white people passed the Jim Crow law for that state.</p>
        <p>Now it is reckoned that the negroes in the United States
are paying about $700,000,000 property taxes and this is 
only one-fifth of all they have accumulated, for the negro is
getting more like the white people every day and has learned
from him that it is not a sign of loyalty and patriotism to
publish his property at its full taxable value.</p>
        <p>In education and morals the progress is still greater. As
you all know, at the close of the war the whole race was
practically illiterate. It was a rare thing, indeed, to find a
man of the race who even knew his letters. In 1880 the
illiteracy had fallen to 70 per cent. and rapid strides along that 
line have been made ever since.</p>
        <p>To-day there are 37,000 negro teachers in America, of
which number 23,000 are regular graduates of high and
normal schools and colleges, 23 are college presidents, 169
are principals of seminaries and many are principals of higher 
institutions. At present there are 369 negro men and women 
taking courses in the universities of Europe. The negro 
ministry, together with these teachers have been prepared for
<pb id="burton67" n="67"/>
their work by our schools and are the greatest factors the
North has produced for the uplift of the colored man.</p>
        <p>To-day there are those who wish to impede the negro's
progress and lessen his educational advantages by industrializing 
such colleges as Howard University of Washington by 
placing on their Boards of Trustees and Managers the pronounced 
leaders of industrialism, giving as a reason that the 
better he is educated the worse he is; in other words, they 
say crime has increased among educated negroes. While stern 
facts show the opposite, the exact figures from the last census 
show that the greater proportion of the negro criminals are 
from the illiterate class. To-day the marriage vow, which by 
the teaching of the whites the negro held to be of so little 
importance before the war, is guarded more sacredly. The 
one room cabin, with its attendant evils, is passing away, 
and the negro woman, the mightiest moral factor in the life 
of her people, is beginning to be more careful in her deportment 
and is no longer the easy victim of the unlicensed passion 
of certain white men. This is a great gain and is a 
sign of real progress, for no race can rise higher than its 
women.</p>
        <p>Let me plead with the friends of the negro. Please
continue to give him higher ideals of a better life and stand
by him in the struggle. He has done well with the
opportunities given him and is doing something along all the
walks of life to help himself, which is gratitude of the best
sort. What he needs to-day is moral sympathy, which in his
condition years ago he could hardly appreciate. The sympathy
<pb id="burton68" n="68"/>
must be moral, not necessarily social. It must be the
sympathy of a soul set on fire for righteousness and fair play 
in a republic like ours. A sympathy which will see to it that 
every man shall have a man's chance in all the affairs of this 
great nation which boasts of being the land of the free and 
the home of the brave for which the black man has suffered 
and done so much in every sense of the word.</p>
        <p>Let this great Christian nation of eighty millions of people 
do justice to the Black Battalion, and seeing President Roosevelt
acknowledges that he overstepped the bounds of his power 
in discharging and renouncing them before they had a fair 
trial, and now that they are vindicated before the world, to 
take back what he called them, Cutthroats, Brutal Murderers, 
Black Midnight Assassins, and Cowards This and this 
alone will to some extent atone for the wrong he has done 
and help him to regain the respect and confidence of the world.</p>
        <p>Now in order to change the condition of things, I would
suggest: First, that an international, industrial association 
be formed to help Afro-Americans to engage in manufacturing 
and commercial pursuits, assist them to buy farms, 
erect factories, open shops in which their young men and 
women can enter and produce what the world requires every 
day for its inhabitants.</p>
        <p>If they were able to-day to produce the articles in common 
use as boots, shoes, hats, cotton and woolen goods, made-up
clothing and enterprises such as farming, mining, forging,
carpentering, etc., negroes would find a ready sale in preference
<pb id="burton69" n="69"/>
to all others, because of its being a race enterprise, doing
what no other corporation does, giving employment to members
of the race as tradesmen, and teaching others to become
skilled workers. These enterprises should be started in the  
northern and western states, where the the population 
will warrant such an undertaking.</p>
        <p>I would suggest “A School History of the Negro Race” 
to be placed in our public schools as a text book. The general 
tone of all the histories taught in our public schools 
points to the inferiority of the negro and the superiority of 
the white. It must be indeed a stimulus to any people to 
be able to refer to their ancestry as distinguished in deeds 
of valor, and particularly so to the colored people. With 
what eyes can the white child look upon the colored
child and the colored child look upon himself, when they have
completed the assigned course of United-States history, and in 
it found not one word of credit, not one word of favorable
comment for even one among the millions of his fore-parents
who have lived through nearly three centuries of his country's
history. In them he is credited with no heritage of valor,
the is mentioned only as a slave, while true historical records
prove him to have been among the bravest of soldiers and
a faithful producer of the nation's wealth. Though then a
slave to the government, the negro's was the. first blood shed
in its defence in those days when a foreign foe threatened
its destruction. In each and all of the American wars the
negro was faithful, yes, faithful in battle while members
of his race were being lynched to death; faithful to a land
<pb id="burton70" n="70"/>not his own in points of rights and freedom, all and that 
after he had enriched with his own life's blood, shouldered 
his musket to defend, when all this was done, regarded him 
with renewed terms, Black, Negro.</p>
        <p>Last but not least the negro needs a daily newspaper in 
every large city, managed and edited by members of the race.</p>
        <p>Such papers are needed to deal with questions of state and
reflect the thoughts of the social world, to enter the province
of ethics and tread the domain of morals and to give their 
opinion on the varying phases of religious truths and pass 
judgment on matters of a political nature.</p>
        <p>There are hidden wrongs perpetrated by the whites against 
the negro race that will never be brought to light until the 
race owns and controls its own daily newspapers which alone 
have the power to discover and enthrone truth, thus becoming 
a safe guide to all honest seekers of facts respecting the race 
whether from a moral, educational, political or religious field. 
To carry out the plans suggested, whether viewed from an 
intellectual, industrial, commercial, or editorial standpoint, 
the world must acknowledge that to-day the negro race has 
the men and women, who are true to their race and all that 
stands for negro progress.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="burton71" n="71"/>
        <head>
          <emph rend="bold">HISTORICAL COMPOSITION</emph>
        </head>
        <byline>BY</byline>
        <docAuthor>ANNIE L. BURTON</docAuthor>
        <pb id="burton73" n="73"/>
        <div2 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>
            <emph>HISTORICAL COMPOSITION</emph>
          </head>
          <p>It is only 132 years ago to-day that the British troops, 
who had occupied Boston, made a riding school of the Old 
South church, and otherwise sacrilegiously disported themselves, 
were persuaded to get out under the compulsion of 
the batteries set up on Dorchester Heights. But when the 
last company embarked for Halifax, it carried the last British flag 
ever unfurled by a military organization on Massachusetts 
soil. That was the end of foreign domination in 
Massachusetts. And by a happy coincidence this is the 
legendary anniversary of the birth of St. Patrick, the patron
saint of Ireland, whose memory has been an inspiration in 
the struggle of another race for Liberty.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <pb id="burton74" n="74"/>
          <head>
            <emph>A QUESTION OF ETHICS</emph>
          </head>
          <p>NEW YORK, Dec. 17. - Andrew Carnegie declared yesterday 
in a speech on the negro question that the negroes are 
a blessing to  America, and that their presence in the South 
makes this country impregnable and without need of a navy 
to defend itself.</p>
          <p>“Suppose,” said Mr. Carnegie,“Great Britain were to 
send her war fleets to America. It would amount to nothing. 
All that the President of the United States would have to 
do would be to say, ‘Stop exporting cotton.’ The war would 
be ended in four days, for England cannot do without our 
cotton.</p>
          <p>“We don't need a navy; we are impregnable. Because we 
have  9,000,000 colored men anxious and willing to work 
we hold this strong position, and I am interested in the negro 
from this material standpoint, as well as from the more 
humane point of view.”</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <div1 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="burton75" n="75"/>
        <head>
          <emph rend="bold">MY FAVORITE POEMS</emph>
        </head>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <pb id="burton77" n="77"/>
          <head>
            <emph rend="bild">Verses</emph>
          </head>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">On a green slope, most fragrant with the Spring,</l>
            <l part="N">One sweet, fair day I planted a red rose,</l>
            <l part="N">That grew, beneath my tender nourishing,</l>
            <l part="N">So tall, so riotous of bloom, that those</l>
            <l part="N">Who passed the little valley where it grew</l>
            <l part="N">Smiled at its beauty. All the air was sweet</l>
            <l part="N">About it! Still I tended it, and knew</l>
            <l part="N">That he would come, e'en as it grew complete.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">And a day brought him! Up I led him, where</l>
            <l part="N">In the warm sun my rose bloomed gloriously -</l>
            <l part="N">Smiling and saying, Lo, is it not fair?</l>
            <l part="N">And all for thee - all shine! But he passed by</l>
            <l part="N">Coldly, and answered, Rose? I see no rose, -</l>
            <l part="N">Leaving me standing in the barren vale</l>
            <l part="N">Alone! alone! feeling the darkness close</l>
            <l part="N">Deep o'er my heart, and all my being fail.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Then came one, gently, yet with eager tread,</l>
            <l part="N">Begging one rose-bud - but my rose was dead.</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <pb id="burton78" n="78"/>
          <head>
            <emph rend="bold">Verses</emph>
          </head>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">The old, old Wind that whispers to old trees,</l>
            <l part="N"> Round the dark country when the sun has set,</l>
            <l part="N">Goes murmuring still of unremembered seas</l>
            <l part="N">And cities of the dead that men forget -</l>
            <l part="N">An old blind beggar-man, <sic>distained</sic> and gray,</l>
            <l part="N">With ancient tales to tell,</l>
            <l part="N">Mumbling of this and that upon his way,</l>
            <l part="N"> Strange song and muttered spell -</l>
            <l part="N">Neither to East or West, or South or North,</l>
            <l part="N">His habitation lies,</l>
            <l part="N">This roofless vagabond who wanders forth</l>
            <l part="N">Aye under alien skies -</l>
            <l part="N">A gypsy of the air, he comes and goes</l>
            <l part="N">Between the tall trees and the shadowed grass,</l>
            <l part="N">And what he tells only the twilight knows . . .</l>
            <l part="N">The tall trees and the twilight hear him pass.</l>
            <l part="N">To him the Dead stretch forth their strengthless hands,</l>
            <l part="N">He who campaigns in other climes than this,</l>
            <l part="N">He who is free of the Unshapen Lands,</l>
            <l part="N"> The empty homes of Dis.</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>
            <emph rend="bold">Verses</emph>
          </head>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Out of the scattered fragments</l>
            <l part="N">Of castles I built in the air</l>
            <l part="N">I gathered enough together</l>
            <l part="N">To fashion a cottage with care;</l>
            <l part="N">Thoughtfully, slowly, I planned it,</l>
            <l part="N">And little by little it grew -</l>
            <l part="N">Perfect in form and in substance,</l>
            <l part="N">Because I designed it for you.</l>
          </lg>
          <pb id="burton79" n="79"/>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">The castles that time has shattered</l>
            <l part="N">Gleamed spotless and pearly white</l>
            <l part="N">As they stood in the misty distance</l>
            <l part="N">That borders the Land of Delight;</l>
            <l part="N">Sleeping and waking I saw them</l>
            <l part="N">Grow brighter and fairer each day;</l>
            <l part="N">But, alas! at the touch of a finger</l>
            <l part="N">They trembled and crumbled away!</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Then out of the dust I gathered</l>
            <l part="N"> A bit of untarnished gold,</l>
            <l part="N">And a gem unharmed by contact </l>
            <l part="N">With stones of a baser mold;</l>
            <l part="N">For sometimes a priceless jewel</l>
            <l part="N">Gleams wondrously pure and fair</l>
            <l part="N">From glittering paste foundations</l>
            <l part="N">Of castles we see in the air.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">So, I turned from the realms of fancy,</l>
            <l part="N">As remote as the stars above,</l>
            <l part="N">And into the land of the living</l>
            <l part="N">I carried the jewel of love;</l>
            <l part="N">The mansions of dazzling brightness</l>
            <l part="N">Have crumbled away, it is true;</l>
            <l part="N">But firm upon gold foundations</l>
            <l part="N">Stands the cottage I built for you!</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <pb id="burton80" n="80"/>
          <head>
            <emph rend="bold">Verses</emph>
          </head>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">You do but jest, sir, and you jest not well.</l>
            <l part="N">How could the hand be enemy of the arm,</l>
            <l part="N">Or seed and sod be rivals ? How could light</l>
            <l part="N">Feel jealousy of heat, plant of the leaf,</l>
            <l part="N">Or competition dwell 'twixt lip and smile?</l>
            <l part="N">Are we not part and parcel of yourselves?</l>
            <l part="N">Like strands in one great braid we intertwine</l>
            <l part="N">And make the perfect whole. You could not be</l>
            <l part="N">Unless we gave you birth: we are the soil</l>
            <l part="N">From which you sprang, yet sterile were that soil</l>
            <l part="N">Save as you planted. (Though in the Book we r
ead</l>
            <l part="N">One woman bore a child with no man's aid,?</l>
            <l part="N">We find no record of a man-child born</l>
            <l part="N">Without the aid of woman ! Fatherhood</l>
            <l part="N">Is but a small achievement at the best,</l>
            <l part="N">While motherhood is heaven and hell.)</l>
            <l part="N">This ever-growing argumen
t of sex</l>
            <l part="N">Is most unseemly, and devoid of sense.</l>
            <l part="N">Why waste more time in controversy, when</l>
            <l part="N">There is not time enough for all of love,</l>
            <l part="N">Our rightful occupation in this fife?</l>
            <l part="N">Why prate of our defects - of where we fail,</l>
            <l part="N">When just the story of our worth would need</l>
            <l part="N">Eternity for telling; and our best</l>
            <l part="N">Development comes ever through your praise,</l>
            <l part="N">As through our praise you reach your highest self?</l>
            <l part="N">Oh! had you not been miser of your praise</l>
            <l part="N">And le
t our virtues be their own reward,</l>
            <pb id="burton81" n="81"/>
            <l part="N">The old established order of the world</l>
            <l part="N">Would never have been changed. Small blame is ours</l>
            <l part="N"> For this unsexing of ourselves, and worse</l>
            <l part="N">
<sic>Effeminizing</sic> of the male. We were</l>
            <l part="N">Content, sir, till you starved us, heart and brain
. </l>
            <l part="N">All we have done, or wise or otherwise, </l>
            <l part="N">Traced to the root, was done for love of you.</l>
            <l part="N">Let us taboo all vain comparisons,</l>
            <l part="N">And go forth as God meant us, hand in hand,</l>
            <l part="N">Companions, mates and comrades evermore;</l>
            <l part="N">Two parts
 of one divinely ordained whole.</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>
            <emph rend="bold">Verses</emph>
          </head>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">A widow had two sons,</l>
            <l part="N">And one knelt at her knees,</l>
            <l part="N">And sought to give her joy</l>
            <l part="N">And toiled to give her ease;</l>
            <l part="N">He heard his country's call</l>
            <l part="N">And longed to go, to die</l>
            <l part="N">If God so willed, but saw</l>
            <l part="N">Her tears and heard her sigh.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">A widow had two sons,</l>
            <l part="N">One filled her days with care</l>
            <l part="N">And creased her brow and brought</l>
            <l part="N">Her many a whitened hair</l>
            <l part="N">His country called - he went.</l>
            <l part="N">Nor thought to say good-by,</l>
            <l part="N">And recklessly he fought,</l>
            <l part="N">And died as heroes die.</l>
          </lg>
          <pb id="burton82" n="82"/>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">A widow had two sons,</l>
            <l part="N">One fell as heroes fall,</l>
            <l part="N">And one remained and toiled,</l>
            <l part="N">And gave to her his all.</l>
            <l part="N">She watched “her hero's” grave</l>
            <l part="N">In dismal days and fair,</l>
            <l part="N">And told the world her love,</l>
            <l part="N">Her heart was buried there.</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>
            <emph rend="bold">Our Mission</emph>
          </head>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">In the legends of the Norsemen,</l>
            <l part="N">Stories quaint and weird and wild,</l>
            <l part="N">There's a strange and thrilling story,</l>
            <l part="N">Of a mother and her child.</l>
            <l part="N">And that child, so runs the story,</l>
            <l part="N">In those quaint old Norsemen books,</l>
            <l part="N">Fell one day from dangerous play ground,</l>
            <l part="N">Das
hed in pieces on the rocks;</l>
            <l part="N">But with gentle hand that mother</l>
            <l part="N">Gathered every tender part,</l>
            <l part="N">Bore them gently, torn and bleeding,</l>
            <l part="N">On her loving mother heart.</l>
            <l part="N">And within her humble dwelling,</l>
            <l part="N">Strong in faith and brave of soul
,</l>
            <l part="N">With her love-song low and tender</l>
            <l part="N">Rocked and sang the fragments whole.</l>
            <l part="N">Such the mission of the Christian,</l>
            <l part="N">Taught by Christ so long ago;</l>
            <l part="N">This the mark that bids us stay not,</l>
            <l part="N">This the spirit each should know:</l>
            <l part="N">Rent
 and torn by sin the race is,</l>
            <l part="N">Heart from heart. and soul from soul;</l>
            <l part="N">This our task with Christ's sweet love-song,</l>
            <l part="N">Join, and heal, and make them whole.</l>
          </lg>
          <signed>
            <hi rend="italics"> - Rev. E. M. Bartlett</hi>
          </signed>
        </div2>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <pb id="burton83" n="83"/>
          <head>
            <emph>Verses</emph>
          </head>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Lord over all! Whose power the <sic>sceptre</sic> swayed,</l>
            <l part="N">Ere first Creation's wondrous form was framed,</l>
            <l part="N">When by His will Divine all things were made;</l>
            <l part="N">Then, King Almighty was His name proclaimed.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">When all shall cease - the universe be o'er,</l>
            <l part="N">In awful greatness He alone will reign,</l>
            <l part="N">Who was, Who is, and Who will evermore</l>
            <l part="N">In glory most refulgent still remain.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Sole God ! unequalled and beyond compare,</l>
            <l part="N">Without division or associate;</l>
            <l part="N">Without commencing date, or final year,</l>
            <l part="N">Omnipotent He reigns in awful state.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">He is my God! my living Savior He!</l>
            <l part="N">My sheltering Rock in sad misfortune's hour!</l>
            <l part="N">My standard, refuge, portion, still shall be,</l>
            <l part="N">My lot's disposer when I seek His power.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Into His hands my spirit I consign</l>
            <l part="N">Whilst wrapped in sleep, that I again may wake,</l>
            <l part="N">And with my soul, my body I resign;</l>
            <l part="N">The Lord's with me - no fears my soul can shake.</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <pb id="burton84" n="84"/>
          <head>
            <emph rend="bold">THE CREATION</emph>
          </head>
          <byline>BY</byline>
          <docAuthor>ANNIE L. BURTON</docAuthor>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">The earth, the firmament on high,</l>
            <l part="N">With all the  blue ethereal sky, </l>
            <l part="N">Were made by God's creative power </l>
            <l part="N">Six thousand years ago or more.</l>
            <l part="N">Man, too, was formed to till the ground;</l>
            <l part="N">Birds, beasts, and fish to move around;</l>
            <l part="N">The fish to swim, the birds to fly,</l>
            <l part="N">And all to praise the Love most high.</l>
            <l part="N">This world is round, wise men declare,</l>
            <l part="N">And hung on nothing in the air. </l>
            <l part="N">The moon around the earth <sic>doth</sic> run;</l>
            <l part="N">The earth moves on its cente
r, too;</l>
            <l part="N">The earth and moon around the sun</l>
            <l part="N">As wheels and tops and pulleys do.</l>
            <l part="N">Water and land make up the whole,</l>
            <l part="N">From East to West, from pole to pole.</l>
            <l part="N">Vast mountains rear their lofty heads,</l>
            <l part="N">Rivers roll down their sandy be
ds;</l>
            <l part="N">And all join in one grand acclaim</l>
            <l part="N">To praise the Lord's almighty name.</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <div1 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <pb id="burton85" n="85"/>
        <head>
          <emph rend="bold">MY FAVORITE HYMNS</emph>
        </head>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <pb id="burton87" n="87"/>
          <head>
            <emph rend="bold">The Ninety and Nine</emph>
          </head>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">There were ninety and nine that safely lay</l>
            <l part="N">In the shelter of the fold,</l>
            <l part="N">But one was out on the hills away,</l>
            <l part="N">Far-off from the gates of gold - </l>
            <l part="N">Away on the mountains lone and bare,</l>
            <l part="N">Away from the tender Shepherd's care.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">“Lord, Thou hast here Thy ninety and nine:</l>
            <l part="N">Are they not enough for Thee?”</l>
            <l part="N">But the Shepherd made answer: “This of mine</l>
            <l part="N">Has wandered away from me,</l>
            <l part="N">And, although the road be rough and steep,</l>
            <l part="N">I go to the 
desert to find my sheep.”</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">But none of the ransomed ever knew</l>
            <l part="N">How deep were the waters crossed;</l>
            <l part="N">Nor how dark was the night that the Lord passed through</l>
            <l part="N">Ere he found His sheep that was lost.</l>
            <l part="N">Out in the desert he heard the cry - </l>
            <l part="N">Sick and helpless
, and ready to die.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">“Lord, whence are those blood-drops all the way</l>
            <l part="N">That mark out the mountain's track?”</l>
            <pb id="burton88" n="88"/>
            <l part="N">“They were shed for one who had gone astray</l>
            <l part="N">Ere the Shepherd could bring him back.”</l>
            <l part="N">“Lord, whence are Thy hands so rent and torn?”</l>
            <l part="N">“They are pierced tonight by many a thorn.”</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">But all through the mountains, thunder-riven,</l>
            <l part="N">And up from the rocky steep,</l>
            <l part="N">There arose a glad cry to the height of heaven,</l>
            <l part="N">“Rejoice! I have found my sheep!”</l>
            <l part="N">And the angels echoed around the throne:</l>
            <l part="N">“R
ejoice, for the Lord brings back His own!”</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>
            <emph rend="bold">My Faith looks up to Thee</emph>
          </head>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">My faith looks up to Thee,</l>
            <l part="N">Thou Lamb of Calvary,</l>
            <l part="N">Saviour divine!</l>
            <l part="N">Now hear me while I pray,</l>
            <l part="N">Take all my guilt away,</l>
            <l part="N">O, let me from this day </l>
            <l part="N">Be wholly Thine.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">May Thy rich grace impart</l>
            <l part="N">Strength to my fainting heart, </l>
            <l part="N">My zeal inspire; </l>
            <l part="N">As Thou hast died for me,</l>
            <l part="N">O, may my love to Thee</l>
            <l part="N">Pure, warm, and changeless be,</l>
            <l part="N">A living fire.</l>
          </lg>
          <pb id="burton89" n="89"/>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">When ends life's transient dream,</l>
            <l part="N">When death's cold, sullen stream</l>
            <l part="N">Shall o'er me roll,</l>
            <l part="N">Blest Saviour, then, in love, </l>
            <l part="N">Fear and distrust remove;</l>
            <l part="N">O, bear me safe above,</l>
            <l part="N">A ransomed soul.</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>
            <emph rend="bold">Jordan's Strand</emph>
          </head>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">My days are gliding swiftly by,</l>
            <l part="N">And I, a pilgrim stranger,</l>
            <l part="N">Would not detain them as they fly,</l>
            <l part="N">Those hours of toil and danger.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">
              <hi rend="italics">Chorus</hi>
            </l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">For, O we stand on Jordan's strand,</l>
            <l part="N">Our friends are passing over;</l>
            <l part="N">And, just before, the shining shore </l>
            <l part="N">We may almost discover!</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">We'll gird our loins, my brethren dear,</l>
            <l part="N">Our heavenly home discerning;</l>
            <l part="N">Our absent Lord has left us word,</l>
            <l part="N">“Let every lamp be burning.”</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Should coming days be cold and dark,</l>
            <l part="N">We need not cease our singing;</l>
            <l part="N">That perfect rest <sic>nought</sic> can molest,</l>
            <l part="N">Where golden harps are ringing.</l>
          </lg>
          <pb id="burton90" n="90"/>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Let sorrow's rudest tempest blow,</l>
            <l part="N">Each cord on earth to sever;</l>
            <l part="N">Our King says, “Come!” and there's our home,</l>
            <l part="N">Forever, O forever. </l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>
            <emph rend="bold">Over the Line</emph>
          </head>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">O tender and sweet was the Master's voice</l>
            <l part="N">As he lovingly call'd to me,</l>
            <l part="N">“Come over the line, it is only a step - </l>
            <l part="N">I am waiting my child, for thee.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">
              <hi rend="italics">Refrain</hi>
            </l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">“Over the line,” hear the sweet refrain,</l>
            <l part="N">Angels are chanting the heavenly strain:</l>
            <l part="N">“Over the line,”  - Why should I remain</l>
            <l part="N">With a step between me and Jesus?</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">But my sins are many, my faith is small,</l>
            <l part="N">Lo! the answer came quick and clear;</l>
            <l part="N">“Thou needest not trust in thyself at all,</l>
            <l part="N">Step over the line, I am here.”</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">But my flesh is weak, I tearfully said,</l>
            <l part="N">And the way I cannot see;</l>
            <l part="N">I fear if I try I may sadly fail,</l>
            <l part="N">And thus may dishonor Thee.</l>
          </lg>
          <pb id="burton91" n="91"/>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Ah, the world is cold, and I cannot go back</l>
            <l part="N">Press forward I surely must;</l>
            <l part="N">I will place my hand in his wounded palm</l>
            <l part="N">Step over the line, and trust. </l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>
            <emph rend="bold">O could I speak the Matchless Worth</emph>
          </head>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">O could I speak the matchless worth,</l>
            <l part="N">O could I sound the glories forth,</l>
            <l part="N">Which in my Saviour shine,</l>
            <l part="N">I'd soar, and touch the heav'nly strings,</l>
            <l part="N">And vie with Gabriel while he sings,</l>
            <l part="N">In notes almost divine.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">I'd sing the precious blood He spilt,</l>
            <l part="N">My ransom from the dreadful guilt</l>
            <l part="N">Of sin and wrath divine;</l>
            <l part="N">I'd sing His glorious righteousness,</l>
            <l part="N">In which all-perfect, heavenly dress</l>
            <l part="N">My soul shall ever shine.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">I'd sing the characters He bears,</l>
            <l part="N">And all the forms of love He wears</l>
            <l part="N">Exalted on His throne;</l>
            <l part="N">In loftiest songs of sweetest praise,</l>
            <l part="N">I would to everlasting days</l>
            <l part="N">Make all His glories known.</l>
          </lg>
          <pb id="burton92" n="92"/>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Well, the delightful day will come</l>
            <l part="N">When my dear Lord will bring me home,</l>
            <l part="N">And I shall see His face;</l>
            <l part="N">Then with my Saviour, Brother, Friend,</l>
            <l part="N">A blest eternity I'll spend,</l>
            <l part="N">Triumphant in His grace.</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>
            <emph rend="bold">O God, beneath Thy Guiding Hand</emph>
          </head>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">O God, beneath Thy guiding hand,</l>
            <l part="N">Our exiled fathers cross'd the sea;</l>
            <l part="N">And when they trod the wintry strand,</l>
            <l part="N">With pray'r and psalm they worshipp'd Thee.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Thou heard'st well pleased, the song, the prayer:</l>
            <l part="N">Thy blessing came and still its power</l>
            <l part="N">Shall onward through all ages bear</l>
            <l part="N">The memory of that holy hour.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Laws, freedom, truth, and faith in God</l>
            <l part="N">Came with those exiles o'er the waves;</l>
            <l part="N">And where their pilgrim feet have trod,</l>
            <l part="N">The God they trusted guards their graves.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">And here Thy name, O God of love,</l>
            <l part="N">Their children's children shall adore</l>
            <l part="N">Till these eternal hills remove </l>
            <l part="N">And spring adorns the earth no more.</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <pb id="burton93" n="93"/>
          <head>
            <emph rend="bold">America</emph>
          </head>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">My country, 'tis of thee,</l>
            <l part="N">Sweet land of liberty,</l>
            <l part="N">Of thee I sing;</l>
            <l part="N">Land where my fathers died,</l>
            <l part="N">Land of the pilgrim's pride,</l>
            <l part="N">From every mountain side</l>
            <l part="N">Let freedom ring.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">My native country, thee,</l>
            <l part="N">Land of the noble free,</l>
            <l part="N">Thy name I love;</l>
            <l part="N">I love thy rocks and rills,</l>
            <l part="N">Thy woods and templed hills;</l>
            <l part="N">My heart with rapture thrills</l>
            <l part="N">Like that above.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Let music swell the breeze,</l>
            <l part="N"> And ring from all the trees</l>
            <l part="N">Sweet freedom's song;</l>
            <l part="N">Let mortal tongues awake,</l>
            <l part="N">Let all that breathe partake,</l>
            <l part="N">Let rocks their silence break,</l>
            <l part="N">The sound prolong.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Our fathers' God to Thee,</l>
            <l part="N">Author of liberty,</l>
            <l part="N">To Thee we sing;</l>
            <l part="N">Long may our land be bright</l>
            <l part="N">With freedom's holy light;</l>
            <l part="N">Protect us with Thy might,</l>
            <l part="N">Great God our King.</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <pb id="burton94" n="94"/>
          <head>
            <emph rend="bold">In the Cross of Christ I Glory</emph>
          </head>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">In the cross of Christ I glory,</l>
            <l part="N">Towering o'er the wrecks of time;</l>
            <l part="N">All the light of sacred story</l>
            <l part="N">Gathers round its head sublime.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">When the woes of life o'ertake me,</l>
            <l part="N">Hopes deceive and fears annoy,</l>
            <l part="N">Never shall the cross forsake me:</l>
            <l part="N">Lo! it glows with peace and joy.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">When the sun of bliss is beaming</l>
            <l part="N">Light and love upon my way,</l>
            <l part="N">From the cross the radiance streaming,</l>
            <l part="N">Add more luster to the day.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Bane and blessing, pain and pleasure,</l>
            <l part="N">By the cross are sanctified;</l>
            <l part="N">Peace is there that knows no measure,</l>
            <l part="N">Joys that through all time abide.</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>
            <emph rend="bold">Guide Me, O Thou Great Jehovah</emph>
          </head>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Guide me, O Thou great Jehovah,</l>
            <l part="N">Pilgrim thro' this barren land;</l>
            <l part="N">I am weak, but Thou art mighty;</l>
            <l part="N">Hold me with Thy pow'rful hand;</l>
            <l part="N">Bread of heaven,</l>
            <l part="N">Feed me till I want no more.</l>
          </lg>
          <pb id="burton95" n="95"/>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Open now the crystal fountain</l>
            <l part="N">Whence the healing waters flow;</l>
            <l part="N">Let the fiery, cloudy pillar</l>
            <l part="N">Lead me all my journey through;</l>
            <l part="N">Strong Deliverer,</l>
            <l part="N">Be Thou still my strength and shield.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">When I tread the verge of Jordan,</l>
            <l part="N">Bid my anxious fears subside;</l>
            <l part="N">Bear me through the swelling current,</l>
            <l part="N">Land me safe on Canaan's side;</l>
            <l part="N">Songs of praises</l>
            <l part="N">I will ever give to Thee.</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>
            <emph rend="bold">Christ receiveth Sinful Men</emph>
          </head>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Sinners Jesus will receive;</l>
            <l part="N">Sound this word of grace to all</l>
            <l part="N">Who the heav'nly pathway leave,</l>
            <l part="N">All who linger, all who fall.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">
              <hi rend="italics">Chorus</hi>
            </l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Sing it o'er and o'er again:</l>
            <l part="N">Christ receiveth sinful men;</l>
            <l part="N">Make the message clear and plain:</l>
            <l part="N">Christ receiveth sinful men.</l>
          </lg>
          <pb id="burton96" n="96"/>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Come, and He will give you rest;</l>
            <l part="N">Trust Him, for His word is plain;</l>
            <l part="N">He will take the sinfulest;</l>
            <l part="N">Christ receiveth sinful men.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Christ receiveth sinful men,</l>
            <l part="N">Even me with all my sin;</l>
            <l part="N">Purged from every spot and stain,</l>
            <l part="N">Heav'n with Him I enter in.</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>
            <emph rend="bold">Some Day the Silver Cord will break</emph>
          </head>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Some day the silver cord will break,</l>
            <l part="N">And I no more as now shall sing;</l>
            <l part="N">But, O, the joy when I shall wake</l>
            <l part="N">Within the palace of the King!</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">And I shall see Him face to face,</l>
            <l part="N">And tell the story - Saved by grace.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Some day my earthly house will fall,</l>
            <l part="N">I cannot tell how soon 'twill be, </l>
            <l part="N">But this I know - my All in All</l>
            <l part="N">Has now a place in heaven for me.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Some day; till then I'll watch and wait,</l>
            <l part="N">My lamp all trimmed and burning bright,</l>
            <l part="N">That when my Saviour ope's the gate.</l>
            <l part="N">My soul to Him may take its flight.</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <div2 org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <pb id="burton97" n="97"/>
          <head>
            <emph rend="bold">Battle Hymn of the Republic</emph>
          </head>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Mine eyes have seen the glory of the coming of the Lord;</l>
            <l part="N">He is trampling out the vintage where the grapes of wrath are stored;</l>
            <l part="N">He hath loos'd the fateful lightning of His terrible swift sword;</l>
            <l part="N">His truth is marching on.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">I have seen Him in the watch-fires of a hundred circling camps;</l>
            <l part="N">They have builded Him an altar in the evening dews and damps;</l>
            <l part="N">I can read His righteous sentence in the dim and flaring lamps;</l>
            <l part="N">His day is marching on.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">I have read a fiery gospel writ in burnished rows of steel,</l>
            <l part="N">“As ye deal with my contemners, so with you My grace shall deal;</l>
            <l part="N">Let the hero born of woman crush the serpent with his heel</l>
            <l part="N">Since God is marching on.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">He has sounded forth the trumpet that shall never sound retreat,</l>
            <l part="N">He is sifting out the hearts of men before His judgment seat;</l>
            <l part="N">O, be swift, my soul, to answer Him, be jubilant, my feet!</l>
            <l part="N">Our God is marching on.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">In the beauty of the lilies Christ was born across the sea,</l>
            <l part="N">With a glory in His bosom that transfigures you and me;</l>
            <l part="N">As He died to make men holy, let us die to make men free,</l>
            <l part="N">While God is marching on.</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI.2>