<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
<emph rend="bold">How a One-Legged Rebel Lives.</emph>
REMINISCENCES OF<emph rend="bold">THE CIVIL WAR:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Robson, John S., b. 1844</author>
        <funder>Funding from the Library of Congress/Ameritech National Digital
Library Competition  supported the electronic publication of this
title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Shawna Schnorr</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Title page scanned by</resp>
          <name>Jill Kuhn</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Heather Bumbalough and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition,
<date>1998</date>
</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca. 250K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel
Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1998.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property
of the University of North Carolina
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by
individuals for research,
teaching and personal use as long as this statement of 
availability is included in the text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note anchored="yes" place="unspecified">Call number  973.78 R66H  1898
 (Library Service Center, UNC-CH)</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc default="NO">
        <bibl default="NO">
          <title>How a One-Legged Rebel Lives</title>
          <author>Robson,
John S.</author>
          <imprint>
            <pubPlace>Durham, NC</pubPlace>
            <publisher>The Educator Co.
Printers and Binders</publisher>
            <date>1898</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc default="NO">
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi>
</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl default="NO">
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line 
breaks have been removed, and the trailing part of a word has been
 joined to the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are
encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are
encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text
 using Author/Editor (SoftQuad) and Microsoft
 Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl default="NO">
<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
<edition>21st edition, 1998</edition>
</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage default="NO">
        <language id="la">Latin</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass default="NO">
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Robson, John S., b. 1844.</item>
            <item>Jackson, Stonewall, 1824-1863.</item>
            <item>Confederate States of America. Army. Virginia Infantry Regiment,
52nd. Company D.</item>
            <item>Soldiers -- Confederate States of America -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Confederate States of America. Army -- Military life.</item>
            <item>Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal
narratives.</item>
            <item>Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Regimental
histories.</item>
            <item>United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal
narratives, Confederate.</item>
            <item>United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Regimental
histories.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>1998-07-16, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager,</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished
TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1998-06-10, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Heather Bumbalough </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1998-05-30, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Shawna Schnorr </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="title page" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="robsontp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">
            <emph rend="bold">How a One-Legged Rebel Lives.</emph>
          </titlePart>
          <titlePart type="subtitle">REMINISCENCES OF
<lb/>
<emph rend="bold">THE CIVIL WAR.</emph>
</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="subtitle">THE STORY OF THE CAMPAIGNS OF
<lb/>
STONEWALL JACKSON,
<lb/>
AS TOLD BY A
<lb/>
HIGH PRIVATE IN THE “FOOT CAVALRY.”</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="subtitle">From Alleghany Mountain to Chancelorsville.
<lb/>
WITH THE COMPLETE REGIMENTAL 
ROSTERS OF BOTH THE GREAT ARMIES AT GETTYSBURG.</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>By</byline>
        <docAuthor>JOHN S. ROBSON,
<lb/>
LATE OF THE 52d REGIMENT VIRGINIA INFANTRY.</docAuthor>
        <titlePart type="verso">DURHAM, N. C.:<lb/>
THE EDUCATOR CO. PRINTERS AND BINDERS,<lb/>
1898.</titlePart>
      </titlePage>
      <pb id="robs3" n="3"/>
      <div1 type="preface" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <head>PREFACE.</head>
        <salute>
          <hi rend="italics">To the Reader  -  Greeting:</hi>
        </salute>
        <p>My chief object in this work is to get something to
support myself with - in fact, it is a scheme founded on food,
raiment and shelter, which I find hard to come at by one in
my situation, there being so few positions open to a man
maimed as I am, with no more education and business
training than I possess; but, nevertheless, I am no applicant
for charity.</p>
        <p>I honestly believe that my little book is well worth its
price, and I claim for it strict historic accuracy in all its
details.</p>
        <p>I have been materially aided in its preparation by
gentlemen well posted by experience and reading in the
history of the war, and not one-half of the collected data has
been used, because space could not be afforded, but I hope
to follow this by another, if this candidate for public favor
should be successful, and my experience in the past with the
big-hearted, generous people of this country  -  North and
South  -  justifies my promise to finish the work now begun,
and add some pages to the history of the “Cruel War” which
would otherwise be forgotten.</p>
        <pb id="robs4" n="4"/>
        <p>Entered according to Act of Congress, in the Year, 1898,
<lb/>
BY JOHN S. ROBSON.</p>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb id="robs5" n="5"/>
      <div1 type="text" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
        <head>
          <emph rend="bold">HOW A ONE-LEGGED REBEL LIVES.</emph>
        </head>
        <div2 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
          <p>In fulfilling the promise of my title page, I must begin
at the beginning, and tell how I came to be a “one-
legged” rebel, which interesting result was brought
about by the skill and enterprise of certain surgeons of
the C. S. A., who amputated the other leg; but it goes
without telling that the reason I was a rebel, “so-called,” 
was my Old Virginia birth, which occurred in
Rappahannock county on the 26th of March, 1844.</p>
          <p>I do not contemplate autobiography, nor very much
of general history, and if, in putting my story together, I
should fail to round my periods handsomely and omit
the high-toned and classic allusions to Achilles and
Hector, the Trojan Horse and Ulysses, Richard and
Saladin, these, more or less, of the boys who figured in
ages past, and which should adorn my pages, I hope
my lenient reader will travel the road far enough with
me to learn that I am, unfortunately, lacking in classic
lore, and cannot compare in erudition with a “Mosby,”
a Gen. “Dick” Taylor or a John Esten Cooke, who
<pb id="robs6" n="6"/>
would fight you a battle, gloriously, to-day with the
sword, and fight it over again for you to-morrow as
gracefully with the pen. I was “nothing but a private,”
and a very junior one at that, when the late disturbance
between the top and bottom of the map of the United
States occurred, but I took a very lively interest in the
arbitration from its very commencement.</p>
          <p>At that time I was a sixteen-year-old, under
instruction at Mossy Creek Academy, in Augusta
county  -  just the right age to have a good deal of fool
in my composition, and at exactly the right place to
<sic corr="develop">pevelop</sic> that quality, for if there was any one point more
than another, in all Virginia, where the war fever struck
hard, as an epidemic, it was in Augusta county; and it
required long time and strong medicine, too, to cure it
up there in the valley; but it <hi rend="italics">was</hi> cured, and now we no
more wish or expect to see the armed legions of
sectional hate wheeling and clanking through blood and
desolation in the beautiful Valley of Virginia.</p>
          <p>On the 16th of June, 1861, my patriotism boiled over,
and I volunteered under Capt. Joseph Huddel, in
Company D, 52d Regiment Virginia Infantry,
commanded then by that noble Virginia gentleman,
statesman and soldier, Col. John B. Baldwin, of
Staunton, and we remained near that place until the
10th of September; being licked into soldier
<pb id="robs7" n="7"/>
shape by dint of discipline, drill, and duty, when we
marched, by way of Buffalo Gap, to Crab Bottom, in
Highland county, at the head of Jackson River.</p>
          <p>At this place stands a barn, the property of Jacob
Hebner, from the eaves of which the
water flows north and south  -  one way into the
Potomac and the other into the James, the head-springs
of the two rivers being here only a stone's-throw apart;
and, like the sentiment of the country at that time,
taking the widest divergent direction to be brought
together again, after measuring their full course, in one
common destiny at the ocean.</p>
          <p>It is interesting, sometimes, to the old veterans, to go
back, in retrospect, to the days of 1861, when soldier-life
was gilded with the glory that was to be, and we were
making our first <sic corr="preparations">preprarations</sic> for the field in a war
which we were taught to think would be a very short
one  -  ninety days at most, but which tried our faith, 
nerve and patience, for four of the longest
years that are ever crowded into the lifetime of one
generation. And believing that some account of what
we did and how we managed at that time, will be of
interest to the general reader, and especially to the
children of the old soldiers, I have ventured to draw on
the treasury of memory, and the <sic corr="interesting">intererting</sic> little book
of my friend, Carlton McCarthy, for what is fast fading
away. We
<pb id="robs8" n="8"/>
who passed through it can smile now at our crude ideas
of what was then necessary to make up the outfit for
war of the infantry soldier, but it won't be long until we
shall all have passed “over the river,” and the memory
of those little things which made the Confederate
soldier what he was, will die too; and though the
historians will tell, with eloquent pen, of the grand
movements of armies and of the deeds of the Generals,
he will hardly stop to explain how the private soldier
was evolved from the farmer, the clerk, the mechanic,
the school-boy, and transformed into the perfect,
all-enduring, untiring and invincible soldier, who broiled his
bacon on a stick and baked his bread on a ramrod.</p>
          <p>The volunteer of 1861 was a very elaborate institution,
and entertained the idea that he was little, if any
inferior to Napoleon, in his capacity and possibilities,
and he of the South was very sure that he was a
match, in the field, for any five Yankees in the United
States; an idea which was, to a certain extent,
eliminated along with other erroneous ones which, at
the outbreak of the disturbance, were entertained.</p>
          <p>In his preparation for the campaign the Confederate
soldier was forced to depend upon home resources,
and in the first place he thought big boots, the <sic corr="higher">higer</sic> the
better, were essential to his military appearance; but he
learned after awhile that a broad
<pb id="robs9" n="9"/>
bottomed shoe was very much lighter to carry and
easier on his ankles.</p>
          <p>He also thought he must wear a very heavy padded
coat, with long tails and many buttons, but this too
proved an error, and a very short experience induced
him to lay aside the coat and substitute a short-waisted,
single-breasted jacket, which transformation gave the
“Rebs” the universal title of “Gray Jackets” by the
neighbors over the way - the Yankees.</p>
          <p>We went in heavy on fancy caps, wavelocks and
other cockady and stately head-gear, but these early
gave way to the comfortable slouch hat, and to this day
the Confederate veterans are much mystified when
they read of the French and Prussians wearing the
little caps and heavy helmlets on the march and in the
field, but the volunteer of '61 was a fearfully and
wonderfully gotten up representative of the Sons of
Mars in the first flush of his warfever. He carried
more baggage then than a major-general did
afterwards, and many of these “high privates” were
followed by their own faithful bodyservants, who did
their cooking, washing and foraging, blacked those
imposing boots, dusted his clothes, and bragged to the
other negroes of what a noble soldier and gentleman
“Massa Tom” or “Masse Dick” was.</p>
          <p>The knapsack was a terror, loaded with thirty
<pb id="robs10" n="10"/>
to fifty pounds of surplus baggage, consisting of all
manner of extra underwear, towels, combs, brushes,
blacking, looking-glasses, needles, thread, buttons,
bandages, everything thought of as necessary, and
strapped on the outside were two great, heavy blankets
and a gum or oilcloth. His haversack, too, hung on his
shoulder, and always had a good stock of provisions, as
though a march across the Sahara might at any time be
imminent. The inevitable canteen, with contents more
or less, was also slung from the shoulder, and most of
the boys thought a bold soldier's outfit for the war was
absolutely incomplete unless he was supplied with long
gloves. In fact, the volunteer of '61 made himself a
complete beast of burden, and was so heavily clad,
weighted and cramped that a march was absolute
torture, and the wagon trains of mess-chests and camp
equipage were so immense in proportion to the number
of men that it would have been impossible to guard
them in an enemy's country, or anywhere else, against
enterprising cavalry. However, wisdom is born of
experience, and before many campaigns have been
worried through the private soldier, reduced to the
minimum, consisted of one man, one hat, one jacket,
one pair pants, one pair draws, one pair socks, one pair
shoes, and his baggage was one blanket, one gum-cloth
and one haversack, while the wonderfully-constructed
mess-chests,
<pb id="robs11" n="11"/>
with lids convertable into cozy dining tables,
and with numerous divisions and sub-divisions in nooks
and cases for the holding of all imaginable necessaries
and luxuries, of tea and coffee, spices and condiments,
dishes, cups, vases and spoons, were <hi rend="italics">stored</hi>
nevermore to see the light in the army again, and the
company property consisted of two or three skillets and
frying-pans, which didn't take up much wagon room  - 
for the infantryman generally preferred to stick the
handle of the mess frying-pan into the barrel of a
musket and thus be sure of having it at a given point on
the march when the minimum weight soldier got there,
for the wagon got to be very unreliable for the
transportation of anything but amunition; but sometimes
they carried a small quantity of commissary stores,
generally for the use of the train quartermaster and his
staff.</p>
          <p>The most important <hi rend="italics">appearing</hi> personage in the
army was the aforesaid quartermaster, who always
managed to have saved for his own use, out of the
scanty supplies, an abundance of the best, and as all
drivers and assistants in his department held their
“bomb-proofs” at his supreme pleasure, he had it in his
power at all times to control freights. His handsome,
<sic corr="flashy">fiashy</sic>, lace-trimmed uniform of fine gray cloth,
adorned with the star or bar of his rank, caused the
folks along the line of march to
<pb id="robs12" n="12"/>
imagine they had the privilege of gazing at some of the
famous generals  -  Longstreet, Hill, Pickett, or
perhaps Lee himself  -  when in fact the generals, in
their dingy dress, had passed unnoticed, and this gayly
caparisoned cavalier was only a quartermaster
marshaling a little wagon train in rear of the army.</p>
          <p>The Confederate soldier held on to his haversack,
not to carry food in as is popularly supposed, but it was
the ever present recepticle for tobacco, pipes, strings,
buttons and the like, and very often, when, with great
display and bluster by the commissaries, three days'
rations were issued to the men, they would cook and
eat the whole lot at one meal, which was decidedly the
most convenient way of carrying it, and besides it was
usually the case that they had been without food for
from two to five meals, and it was not much of an
exploit to consume the small quantity issued for what
was termed “three days' rations,” and after eating it,
they would trust to luck and strategy for meals, or go
hungry, as usual, till the next ration day.</p>
          <p>The commissary department of the Southern
Confederacy was most scandalously mismanaged from
the beginning, and the commissary general was the
worst and most complete failure, North or South, of the
whole war, in consequence of which the men were
forced to forage for themselves. As the war
progressed and this stern “mother of invention”
<pb id="robs13" n="13"/>
and “neutralizer of all law,” Necessity and Hunger, her
child, made themselves felt in all their force, it was no
uncommon sight to see a whole brigade marching in
solid column along a road one minute and the next
scattered over a big briar field picking the blackberries,
but as soon as the gleaning was done all would return
to the ranks and resume the march as though nothing
had happened to break it, and in the Fall of the year a
persimmon tree would halt a column as long as a
'simmon was on it.</p>
          <p>We had no sutlers in our army; the blockade and
dearth of marketable funds prevented that, the nearest
approach to it being the occasional old darkey with his
cider cart or basket of pies and cakes  -  so called  - 
and it was almost marvelous to see how quick the old
contraband's stock would be cleaned out.</p>
          <p>The rebel soldier depended much upon the supplies
he could get from the enemy in battle, for the Yankees
were always abundantly supplied, and thus we had a
double incentive to win the fight.</p>
          <p>A federal officer who was conversing with General
Jackson in the street of Harper's Ferry, at its surrender
in September, 1862, says that an Orderly galloped up to
“Stonewall” and said: “General, I am ordered by
General McLaws to report to you that McClellan's
whole army is within six miles, and
<pb id="robs14" n="14"/>
coming this way.” Jackson took no notice of it at all,
and the Orderly turned to ride back when the General
called to him, “has General McClellan a drove of cattle
or a wagon train with him?” The
Orderly replied that he had. “All right,” said Jackson, “I
can whip any army that is followed by a drove of
cattle;” alluding to the hungry condition of his men,
and the good fighting qualities thereby developed when
beef was in sight.</p>
          <p>Stealing is a low vice, no matter who does it, but that
hungry men should take whatever they found in the
eating line is not to be wondered at, and the old Irish
adage, “There is no law for a hungry man,” should be
borne in mind when judging the soldier.</p>
          <p>In the early days, when the volunteers were being
mustered for “twelve months, unless sooner
discharged,” and the idea of a short war was being
industriously promulgated by the big men of the cross
roads, and the newspaper generals at the county seats,
the boys were very uneasy about it, for fear it would
wind up before they could get in.</p>
          <p>When the first Manassas was fought, the 52d
Virginia was sorely disgruntled, believing they had been
left out for a purpose, and jealously rankled hot in our
hearts at sight of the battery boys, and others, from
Staunton, who were sporting around town with bullet-wounds
and bloody bandages, the idols of the girls and
made heroes of by everybody. Fate
<pb id="robs15" n="15"/>
was against us, for we had not even seen the smoke of
that first great battle from afar, and we would have
resigned a kingdom without a murmur to have had one
of those wounds; even a very small wound would have
been thankfully received, and we noticed also that the
accounts and descriptions of the battle were considered
much more accurate and authentic when related by
some fellow with his arm in a sling and a general air
about him of - “stand aside! I am holier than thou,”
“been wounded at Manassas;” although it might be that
he got crippled under a waggon, and never saw a
Yankee.</p>
          <p>But every one of these veteran heroes of that battle
was supposed to have slain at least four Yankees, and
fought Sherman's battery with bowie knife. “Charging”
the batteries of the enemy was the favorite amusement
of the lucky fellows who were at Manassas, and every
one of them had “charged,” more or less, batteries that
day, and the men who captured the “Long Tom”
rifle-piece were wonderfully numerous.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
          <p>I must now return to the camp at Crab Bottom,
because our stay was brief, and the rumors of the
operations of our great Generals in the mountains were
numerous. There was always news, and
<pb id="robs16" n="16"/>
Floyd, Wise, Loring, Lee, Johnston, and other great
commanders of the Confederacy, were measuring
lances with Milroy, Roscrans, McClellan, Cox, Tyler,
Schenck, etc., of the Federal Army, for the control of
the empire of Western Virginia, and the time has come,
in my story, for the 52d to “mix in,” as Forrest, the
famous cavalryman, would say.</p>
          <p>We marched towards Moorefield, but stopped at a
camp called “Straight Creek,” in Highland county, and
were joined by Captain Shumaker, with his battery
from “Camp Bartow,” and here we did have a most
glorious time of it, in the perfect autumn weather of the
mountain glades and vales, and oh! such living! The
memory of the buckwheat and honey, the cakes, pies,
roast beef and wild turkey, lingers lingeringly, and I
would I were a boy again in camp with the old 52d; but
the regiment has made its last march on this side the
shadow land, and nothing is left but the glorious
memory of the good time gone.</p>
          <p>While here, an incident occurred which made quite
an impression on my boyish mind, and I very much
doubt if it has been forgotten by the oldest survivor.
Our camp was on the bank of a creek and just below
the point where a mill dam was located. It was quite a
large dam and had been sufficient, up to this time, to
hold the accumulated water in check, but now it chose
to give way, and
<pb id="robs17" n="17"/>
sweeping like a mighty flood through the camp it
overwhelmed tents, barracks, bunks, and all pertaining
to our little military, in one universal ruin. We were
completely washed out, and the disaster served in a
measure, to reconcile us, to the movement we were
soon called to make to Alleghany mountain; and now
our soldier life began to lose its gilding.</p>
          <p>Our regiment was ordered to report to Gen. H. R.
Jackson, of Georgia, a veteran of the Mexican war, in
which he was a Colonel of Volunteers, who had been
left with two brigades, by General Lee, to hold the
crossing at Greenbriar River of the turnpike leading
from Staunton to Parkersburg across Cheat Mountain,
and after passing through the intervening valley, and
then the Alleghany Mountain into our own Valley.</p>
          <p>Jackson's camp here was called “Camp Bartow,”
from one of the heroes of Manassas, the lamented
Colonel of the 8th Georgia.</p>
          <p>The Southern camp was on the south bank of the
river, here not more than twenty yards wide, but
Colonel Baldwin had by order of General <sic corr="Jackson">Jackeon</sic>,
posted our regiment at the Alleghany Pass, in our rear.
When the Federals learned of the withdrawal of the
large body of Southern troops towards the Kanawha,
they determined to move the balance of us, and
General Reynolds, of brilliant Gettysburg
<pb id="robs18" n="18"/>
fame, organized a force of 6,000 troops, with
twelve pieces of artillery, and moving from their camp,
on the summit of Cheat Mountain, on the 2d of
October, came down on Camp Bartow with great
gallantry; but Jackson's two little brigades, commanded
by Colonels Johnson and <sic corr="Taliaferro">Taliferro</sic>, stood their ground
so stubbonly that, after exhausting all their means to
drive them from the field, in a battle commencing early
on Thursday morning October 3, and continuing till half-past
two o'clock p. m., the Federals retreated in
confusion, losing over 300 men killed and wounded,
while Jackson's loss was 6 killed, 31 wounded and 12
missing.</p>
          <p>General Reynolds had intended to clear the turnpike,
and march to Staunton, but not succeeding in getting
“Camp Bartow,” he failed to approach our post at
Alleghany Pass and, to our chagrin, we had lost another
opportunity to fight the Yankees, so we grumbled
savagely  -  fully satisfied now that the war would end
and we would not have any show at all to distinguish
ourselves. However, we “roughed it,” soldier-fashion,
and grew very familiar with the mountains; in fact, we
might have been mistaken, from our language, for a
corps of topographical engineers, so extensively did we
talk of what was being done in our department. Go
where you would about the camp, such geographical
remarks as “General Lee is moving on the Yanks at
Elkwater.”
<pb id="robs19" n="19"/>
<sic corr="&quot;">'</sic>General Floyd is going to cut them off at
Meadow Bluffs,” “Old Governor Wise will knock 'em
out at Sewell Mountain,” “Rosecrans whipped at
Lewisburg;” “we will flank them by way of Carnifax
Ferry;” and we used to bet largely on what “Ned”
Johnson would do when Taliaferro's brigade joined him.
We had an idea that a regiment of Southern troops was
something fearful to run against, and as for a brigade  - 
well, it was simply irresistible  -  in fact every man was
a general, and knew exactly what to do next, no matter
what had been the result of the last movement. But
discouraging days were at hand, and when winter came
upon us great numbers of the men got sick, and the
mountain fogs and frosts were harder to contend with
than the enemy.</p>
          <p>When General Floyd made his march from the
Gauley River to Fayette Court-house, he had to
transport more than 800 sick men, and although he was
for twenty days engaged in skirmishing and fighting
the Yankees for the right of way, his killed and
wounded only amounted to 14. After the fight at
Greenbrier River, General H. R. Jackson was sent on
duty to Georgia; Taliaferro's brigade was withdrawn
towards Staunton; Camp Bartow was only occupied by
scouts and pickets, and our line of defence was drawn
back to Alleghany Mountain, fourteen miles from
Greenbriar River and the same
<pb id="robs20" n="20"/>
distance from Montery, with Colonel Edward Johnson
in command, with about 1,200 men, consisting of the 12th
Georgia, 31st Virginia, the 52d Virginia under Colonel
Baldwin, the battallions of Hansborough and Riger, and
two batteries of four 6-pounders under Captains
Anderson and Miller, also one company of cavalry
under Captain Flournoy, and here, with a scanty supply
of blankets and rations, in the keen, frosty air of the
mountains we actually suffered.</p>
          <p>About this time a name, afterwards well known in
the Valley was much talked of, and on the 13th of
December <sic corr="its">it</sic> owner, Gen. R. H. Milroy, appeared in
our front, with a force which, his own people said,
amounted to 8,000.</p>
          <p>His first move on our line was made at Slavin's
Crossing, about three miles from Camp Bartow, on the
18th, where Major Ross, with the volunteers of the
brigade, with 100 men, met the advance of the enemy
and checked their movement long enough for Colonel
Johnson to get ready for them; and the next morning
the <hi rend="italics">great</hi> General Milroy's army came up hunting a
fight, and I am of the opinion to this day that nobody
had to waste time hunting a fight around old Ed
Johnson without getting as much as was good for them
before night.</p>
          <p>The Virginians and Georgians had a hot breakfast all
ready for Milroy's folks as soon as they got
<pb id="robs21" n="21"/>
there, and the 31st Virginia, especially, was very
hospitable in their reception. This regiment was mostly
composed of Northwest Virginia men, and Milroy stood
between them and home, which appeared to make them
particularly severe on him, and their gallant commander,
Major Boykin, led them with dauntless spirit. I had a
splendid position in this battle and could see the whole
fight without having to take any part in it, and I
remember how I thought Colonel Johnson must be the
most wonderful hero in the world, as I saw him at one
point, where his men were hard pressed, snatch a
musket in one hand and, swinging a big club in the
other, he led his line right up among the enemy, driving
them headlong down the mountain, killing and wounding
many with the bayonet and capturing a large number of
prisoners; but the “boys in blue” fought stubbornly, and
many of our men were killed here on the left of the
road. On the right, the enemy, in strong force, posted in
a mountain clearing, among the fallen timber, stumps
and brush, was too much for the Rebs, until the veteran,
Captain Anderson, brought his battery into position and
thundered a storm of round shot and canister among
them, knocking their timber defences about their heads,
and making their nest too hot to hold them; and they,
too, retreated to Cheat Mountain, but for quite awhile
they were
<pb id="robs22" n="22"/>
pelted by Anderson's guns and by Miller's battery,
which got in in the nick of time.</p>
          <p>Captain Anderson was killed just as the Yankees
were breaking up into the retreat by a party he mistook
for some of our own infantry lying between his guns
and the enemy, and riding forward he called them to
come back into the line, at the same time beckoning to
them with his head, when they fired a full volley at him,
which killed him instantly. He had been through three
wars, and had taken part in fifty-eight pitched battles.</p>
          <p>Lieutenant Raines, of Lynchburg, took command of
Anderson's battery, and the other battery, under
Captain Miller, had been originally mustered into the
52d, but was taken out and organized as artillery during
the preceding summer.</p>
          <p>My recollections of Col. Edward Johnson, as he
appeared that day, is very distinct, partly, perhaps,
because it was the first real battle I had ever
witnessed, but mainly, I think, because he acted so
differently from all my preconceived ideas of how a
commander should act on the field of battle. He was a
native of Chesterfield county, Virginia, but at the
opening of the war was living in Georgia, and came
from there at the first outbreak of hostile preparations
in command of the 12th Georgia regiment. After this
battle he was made brigadier, and in February, 1863, was
promoted to major-general,
<pb id="robs23" n="23"/>
and commanded a division in Ewell's corps,
composed of the brigades of Walker, Stewart, J. M.
Jones and Nicholls.</p>
          <p>He was noted all through the war as a stubborn
fighter, and was known throughout the country after
this victory as “Alleghany” Johnson.</p>
          <p>In the battle of Alleghany Mountain the Federals
admitted a loss of four hundred killed and wounded,
while ours, by actual returns, was twenty-five killed
and ninety-seven wounded  -  not more than
skirmishing afterwards, but we rated it as a big battle
then.</p>
          <p>The next day I was on detail with the burial party,
and while putting away two dead Yankees who had
been in the party that killed Captain Anderson, we
found in their pockets the first greenbacks I had ever
seen. We considered the bills curiosities in the way of
currency and only valued them as such, not believing
that such money would be of any more value than the
continental currency was after the Revolution, for of
course the North was to be defeated and impoverished
by the war, and not able to redeem her promise to pay.
In fact, at that time, we would not have given ten cents
on the dollar for it in Confederate money, which goes to
sustain the statement elsewhere made that I, as a type
of the volunteer of 1861, had a considerable touch of <hi rend="italics">fool</hi>
in my composition, because
<pb id="robs24" n="24"/>
any person of common sense must have known
that the war money of an already established
government must, of necessity, have a better show for
value than that of an experiment, no matter who might
be the final winner in the contest, but the faith that was
in us was strong indeed.</p>
          <p>After the battle of Alleghany Mountain some half
dozen of our company died; in fact, nearly all the
wounded died from cold and exposure to the inclement
winter weather, and we all suffered severely. We soon
moved our camp to Shenandoah Mountain, where
General Johnson left us for awhile to attend to
important business in Richmond, and Colonel Baldwin
commanded the department, and we remained here
until the general movement of armies took place in
March, 1862. We made our winter quarters as
comfortable as we knew how, but we were green
campaigners, and the best we knew was awkward
enough. We had got some tents, and these, with log
huts and plenty of fire, kept us in some sort of comfort,
but during this bleak winter the boys talked a good deal
about their “twelve months'” term of enlistment expiring
in the spring, and not quite so much of their fear that
the war would be too short to give to them a taste. Our
next movement was to the old camp at West View, six
miles from Staunton, and in preparing for this we
burned up completely our
<pb id="robs25" n="25"/>
camp at Shenandoah Mountain, tents and all, which
puzzled exceedingly the generals of the rank and file,
and it has always remained a mystery to me why we
did it, for there was no enemy in threatening distance
so far as we knew.</p>
          <p>While waiting for developments, “us generals” were
passing through an ordeal of electioneering, because
the term of service for nearly the whole army had
expired and the time for reorganization of companies
and regiments had arrived, and enlistments “for the
period of the war.”</p>
          <p>To offer a man promotion in the early period of the
war was almost an insult, and the higher the social
position, the greater the wealth, the more patriotic it
would be to serve in the humble position of private in
the ranks; and I have seen many men of education and
ability refusing promotion, and carrying their muskets
under command of officers greatly their inferiors,
mentally and morally, as soldiers. It was not uncommon
to see ex-congressmen and judges, as well as
preachers, tramping along in ranks as privates, but one
year of soldiering had engendered a desire for
commissions in the hearts of many, and, in some cases,
much trickery was resorted to by aspirants to secure
the soldier vote for company offices. Our regiment, at
reorganization, had been changed somewhat, Colonel
Baldwin having been retired to a seat in the
Confederate States Congress.</p>
          <pb id="robs26" n="26"/>
          <p>Col. M. G. Harman commanded, with Lieut.-Col. J.
H. Skinner and Major Ross as field officers, and
Lieutenant Lewis, from the Institute (V. M. I.), was
Adjutant; Company A was commanded by Captain
Garber; Company B by Captain Long; Company C by
Captain Dabney; Company D by Captain Airhart;
Company E by Captain Watkins; Company F by
Captain Cline; Company G by Captain Bateman;
Company H by Captain Lilly; Company I by Captain
Humphreys, and Company K by Captain Walton.</p>
          <p>I could not give the roll of each company in the 52d
if I would, but I would if I could, for I think it ought to
be preserved, and I hope the names of the gallant boys
will yet be saved.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
          <p>Every story should have its hero, and as I have no
idea myself of posing as such, I can't think it at all
improper to make, for my central figure in this part of
my little book which treats of the war, the immortal
“Stonewall” Jackson, whose fortunes as a commander
I am proud to have followed from the day of
McDowell to that of his death. We had not heard
much of him, apart from the record he made at
Manassas, until reports of his <hi rend="italics">crazy</hi> battle at
<pb id="robs27" n="27"/>
Kernstown, as it was called, were received; and
although it was the custom in that war for both sides to
magnify their victories and depreciate their defeats, we
were pretty strongly impressed with the belief that
Jackson had been pretty badly worsted at Kernstown,
by that fighting Irishman, General Shields, whom we
rated always as a gentleman and a soldier; and when
we learned that Jackson was retreating up the Valley
before Banks, our faith was visibly weakened, for we
knew Milroy was pushing towards our own position
with a much larger force than we could muster.</p>
          <p>Our accounts from Jackson were not all painted in
black, for we learned that he had matched his four
thousand “foot cavalry” against Shields' ten thousand,
and had fought so fierce and fast that the high-blooded
Irishman thought Jackson had two thousand the most
men, and we trusted largely in his skill; and were not
totally dissatisfied when he turned up at West View, as
though to cut out some work for “Alleghany” Johnson's
men, which, of course, we thought unnecessary, all of
us being <hi rend="italics">generals</hi>, and able to lay our plans without his
supervision, but he seems to have been arranging
matters to suit General Banks, who, about this time,
telegraphed McClellan that he “had forced the Rebel,
Jackson, to permanently abandon the Valley and
retreat on Gordonsville in Eastern Virginia.”</p>
          <pb id="robs28" n="28"/>
          <p>This is a verbatim report of Banks' message, and
shows that he knew very little about Mr. Jackson, and
it also shows that Jackson had succeeded  -  so far as
the Federal generals knew  -  in getting completely lost,
a thing he took a great deal of interest in doing
repeatedly, during the progress of the war; but General
Milroy, marching from the west towards Staunton for
the express purpose of crushing Johnson, found
Jackson at McDowell, in Highland county, with his
chaplain, Dr. Dabney, holding worship in his camp.</p>
          <p>On May 7, 1862, General Johnson, with his six
regiments, was ready for the fray, and Jackson's
Valley division, formed of the brigades of Taliaferro,
Winder and Campbell, with the Lexington Cadets
under Gen. F. H. Smith, of the Institute, were on hand
to back us up with aid and comfort.</p>
          <p>General Johnson, who knew the country almost as
well as if he had made it, led the advance and drove
four regiments of the enemy from Shenandoah
Mountain, capturing their camps, with tents, clothes,
arms and commissary stores, and placed his men in
bivouac on the camp ground of the enemy. He had
already formed his forces into two brigades,
commanded by Colonels Scott and Connor, our boys
being under Colonel Scott, who had the 44th, 52d and
58th Virginia.</p>
          <p>The 52d took position on Sutlington Hill. When
<pb id="robs29" n="29"/>
the enemy advanced to the attack we received the full
assault of their first line and repulsed it, thus giving
time for the arrival of the other regiments. The enemy,
after being driven back, opened on us with their
artillery a rapid and incessant fire of case shot and
shell, but “us boys” laid low among the rocks and trees,
which afforded us ample protection, and also the angle
of elevation of their guns being so great, no damage,
except to the timber, resulted from this cannonade, and
the noise was all on the Yankees' side, we having no
artillery in position.</p>
          <p>About 5 o'clock General Milroy, having been joined
by General Schenck, advanced his whole force of
8,000 men, and the battle roared and raged along the
side of the hill with terrific force for a long time, but
our two little brigades held them back until Jackson got
his flank movement worked out, and then the Federals
gave way, as a matter of course. In the final closing up
of the business, just as Taliaferro's brigade reached the
field, the 52d, backed up by the 10th Virginia, made a
charge which drove them headlong down the hill, and
the battle ended at 8 o'clock p. m. It seemed to me we
had been at it about a week, but the other boys spoke
as though it was a very short half a day.</p>
          <p>The fight had been hotly contested, but Milroy made
it perfectly clear to all on both sides that he was no
match for Jackson in handling troops in battle,
notwithstanding his superiority in numbers.</p>
          <pb id="robs30" n="30"/>
          <p>Our loss was 71 killed and 390 wounded, but we
could not learn that of the enemy, as they still held their
main camp and carried away their dead and wounded
during the battle, with their well served ambulance corps,
but we found 103 dead on the mountain side next
morning; and during the night Milroy set the woods on
fire behind him, and retreated towards Franklin, whither
General Jackson followed the next day.</p>
          <p>On the 14th of May, about three miles from the
town, he drew up his little army in a small valley and
spoke a few words of commendation of their gallantry
at McDowell, in his short, curt tone, and appointed 10
o'clock that day as an occasion of prayer and
thanksgiving for the victory  -  which was duly
observed  -  notwithstanding the firing of Milroy's
cannon-balls over our heads, but many of us, during the
exercises, prayed with real devotion, by the book, “from
battle, murder, and sudden death, good Lord deliver us.”</p>
          <p>General Jackson stood motionless, with bent, bare
head, and as soon as the meeting was over, marched
his army back to McDowell, and the next day crossed
the Shenandoah Mountain, halting at Lebanon Springs,
where he gave his men some much needed rest,
and an opportunity to observe the day appointed by
the President for fasting and prayer.</p>
          <pb id="robs31" n="31"/>
          <p>But I must repeat that I am not attempting a history
of the war, only trying to follow in a weak, one-legged,
halting manner, the boys of the 52d, in doing which I
must call to mind the pleasant bivouac in the lovely
Mossy Creek valley, with headquarters at Major M. G.
McCue's house, and where all the people were so
hospitable and kind to the jaded Rebels, and from
whence we moved to Mt. Zion Church, near Mt.
Solon, and I had the pleasure of a day at my uncle's,
Dr. Geo. T. Robson, which place I had left one year
before, a gay young volunteer, marching to the war and
very much afraid I was too late to get any fighting; but
I confess I was not now so very much <hi rend="italics">afraid</hi> of
missing a battle as I had been, and I think that year had
taken some of the conceit out of me.</p>
          <p>However, we could not tarry long in our pleasant
quarters, for “Stonewall” was restless, and the Federal
generals  -  Banks, Fremont, Shields, McDowell and
Milroy  -   were either in, or threatening his beloved
Valley of Virginia, to surrender which, he declared,
was to give up Virginia; and in this <sic corr="campaign">compaign</sic> we soon
found that events were hurrying fast, and we must do
likewise or get left; which recalls to mind a true story
of Col. William Smith, of the 49th Virginia, universally
known as “Extra Billy.”</p>
          <p>On one occasion he was endeavoring to get his
<pb id="robs32" n="32"/>
men in marching order as quick as possible, but they
were very dilatory about it, and paid so little attention
to his oft-repeated command to “fall in here, men, fall
in, I say!” as to excite the Colonel's ire, whereupon he
testily exclaimed, “If you don't fall in here right away
now, I'll march the regiment off and leave every d--d
one of you behind!”</p>
          <p>Our “Stonewall” was no such Irishman as that, for
when he marched his army off he was pretty sure to
take it all along, and at this time, with all the odds the
fortune of war had arrayed against him, he surely
needed every man. It is, perhaps, not out of place here
to attempt a description of the impression “Stonewall”
Jackson made upon me and my comrades who had
never seen him, until he got lost from Mr. Banks and
turned up at Valley Mills near McDowell. I shall not
attempt any description of his person or appearance, for
that has been done so often that everybody who reads
Southern history at all know all about it, but on first view
I thought it hardly possible that he could be much of a
general, and if the vernacular of to-day had been in
vogue then, I think I should have reported that I had
seen a “crank,” and I believe most of the men of the 52d
would have pronounced the opinion correct; but my
reader must remember that most of us were still
generals ourselves to some extent, though we did not
consider our generalship quite so infallible as we
formerly thought, and the
<pb id="robs33" n="33"/>
killing and wounding of our comrades at Alleghany and
McDowell had opened our eyes wonderfully to the
probabilities of what might eventually grow out of this
war if something or somebody didn't stop it. Col. M. G.
Harman (Colonel of 52d Virginia) was wounded
severely in the arm, and many others of Company D
(the Company to which I belonged). But memory fails
me now, and I can not record, as my heart prompts me
to do, the names of the gallant boys who fought and
fell for the cause they loved so well and thought was
right.</p>
          <p>When the thought of our noble dead rolls over my
heart, I love to read the lines of Father Ryan, and get
comfort from the sentiments so beautifully expressed
by our charming soldier-poet:</p>
          <lg type="stanza" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">'Tis o'er, the fearful struggle o'er,</l>
            <l part="N">The bloody contest past,</l>
            <l part="N">And hearts oppressed with anxious care</l>
            <l part="N">Throb peacefully at last.</l>
            <l part="N">Those who were spared are with us now,</l>
            <l part="N">Some are in heaven, we trust;</l>
            <l part="N">But though the victory is not ours,</l>
            <l part="N">They're glorious in the dust.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">How many fell whose names and deeds</l>
            <l part="N">Are unrecorded here,</l>
            <l part="N">Save in some lonely, widowed heart, </l>
            <l part="N">Or by the orphan's tear!</l>
            <l part="N">Yet these were they who swelled the ranks </l>
            <l part="N">Of our brave Southern host,</l>
            <l part="N">And though no stone now marks their graves,</l>
            <l part="N">They're glorious in the dust.</l>
          </lg>
          <pb id="robs34" n="34"/>
          <lg type="stanza" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Long shall we mourn for those whose lives</l>
            <l part="N">Were offered up in vain;</l>
            <l part="N">We miss them in our vacant homes,</l>
            <l part="N">Nor can from tears refrain.</l>
            <l part="N">Forever cherished in our hearts,</l>
            <l part="N">Their names nor deeds can rust,</l>
            <l part="N">And tho' they sleep beneath the sod,</l>
            <l part="N">They're glorious in the dust.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">And there are names we may not speak,</l>
            <l part="N">But yet to all how dear,</l>
            <l part="N">For them our daily prayers ascend,</l>
            <l part="N">May God, in mercy, hear.</l>
            <l part="N">How have they suffered, maimed for life!</l>
            <l part="N">Their highest hopes, how crushed!</l>
            <l part="N">But with a manly spirit borne,</l>
            <l part="N">They're glorious in the dust.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">Bravely we fought and bravely fell,</l>
            <l part="N">Nor gained the victor crown,</l>
            <l part="N">Still we will prove that Southern hearts</l>
            <l part="N">Can suffer and be strong -</l>
            <l part="N">Strong in affection, honor, truth,</l>
            <l part="N">Strong in the Christian's trust;</l>
            <l part="N">'Tis trial brightens faith and hope,</l>
            <l part="N">We're glorious in the dust.</l>
          </lg>
          <p>If in my power, the names of those who fought and fell
for the “Lost Cause,” should be graven in golden
letters on a granite monument, to endure as time; as a tribute
to pure patriotism and unselfish devotion to home and native
land, in withstanding for all those bloody years the assaults
of myriads of all nations and tongues, marshalled for the
desolation of our loved Southern land and the
subjugation of our people.</p>
          <pb id="robs35" n="35"/>
          <p>The principles for which the Confederate soldier fought and died,
are to-day the harmony of this country, and so long as those
principles were held in obeyance the country was in turmoil and
almost ruin.</p>
          <p>The heart is greater than the mind, and it is not fair to demand
reasons for actions which are above reason, and the people of the
South, refusing to receive the dogmas of fanaticism as gospel, and to
submit to the tyranny of fanatics, they became Rebels. Being such
they must be punished, and for resistance they died; but their soldier
boys died with their “boots on,” and smoking guns in their hands. And
they fought all the odds of overwhelming numbers, thoroughly armed
and equipped with all the latest inventions of warfare; fought all the
host of ills which came from blockaded ports, empty treasury vaults,
the wails of distress from home, cold, hunger, nakedness; fought,
<hi rend="italics">without</hi> pay, the legions of the Northern army, who had regular
monthly pay, in good money, with big bounties, plenty to eat, and
abundance of clothing, blankets and tents, and superb hospital outfits,
with all that sanitary commission could suggest for the comfort of
sick and wounded; while the Confederate soldier could get no medicine
when sick; nor, often, when amputation was necessary, even
chloroform to numb the agony caused by the knife and
<pb id="robs36" n="36"/>
saw of the surgeon. The Confederate soldier fought
against the commerce of the United States, and all the
facilities for war which Europe could supply, and laid
down life for life with hireling hosts of Germans, Irish,
Italians, English, French, Chinese, Japanese, white,
black and brown.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
          <p>I had almost forgotten that we are on the march
with “Stonewall” Jackson down the Valley, and we
want to keep up, for although the complicated
movements of McClellan on the Peninsula, McDowell
in front of Washington, Banks in the Valley, Shields
along the Blue Ridge, and Fremont and Milroy in the
mountains of Western Virginia, were enough to puzzle
the brain of the most thorough master of the art of war
in any age, they do not appear to have disquieted or
embarrassed Jackson in the least. He looked right
through the cloud of mystery to the plain object to be
attained, viz: the diversion of re-enforcements from
McClellan's “grand army,” and he went at the
accomplishment of this purpose with the mathematical
accuracy and resistless force of a Corliss engine in
motion. Past Harrisonburg we tramped rapidly, and by
the 20th had reached New Market, on the
<pb id="robs37" n="37"/>
Valley pike, where the road to Luray across the
Massanutton  -  the glory of the Valley  -  leads into
the Page valley, and here, for the first time, we
up-country boys saw General Ashby, whose fame as a
cavalry leader had reached us so brilliantly, and
thenceforward the troopers of Ashby hung as an
impenetrable veil in front and flank, so perfectly
screening our movements that General Banks never
knew where to look for his tormentor  -  Jackson  -  
and it is doubtful if he yet knew whether or not this
“Rebel” was still at Gordonsville, in Eastern Virginia.</p>
          <p>We took the right-hand road at New Market, and at
night united with General Ewell's division, which had
come down the river from Swift Run Gap.</p>
          <p>On the afternoon of the next day  -  23d May, 1862,
when we had passed Luray a long distance - a funny
incident occurred, which, perhaps, General Jackson
may have been expecting. The column was marching
along at a swinging gait  -  getting over ground pretty
lively  -  when a young and rather good-looking woman
rushed out of the woods, so agitated and out of breath
that she could scarcely speak, but coming up to the
General, who had turned to meet her, she soon began
to talk with great volubility. We, of course, could not
hear what she was saying, nor could we even conjecture
<pb id="robs38" n="38"/>
the import of her mission, but it was
subsequently made known that this was the famous
woman spy and scout, Belle Boyd, and the information
she detailed right there to General Jackson with the
precision of a staff officer, was to the effect that Front
Royal was just beyond the woods, a short distance
ahead; that the town was full of Federal troops; that
their camp was on the west side of the river, where
they had cannon in position to cover the wagon bridge,
but none to protect the railroad bridge below; that the
Yankees believed Jackson's army was west of the
Massanutton near Harrisonburg, and knew nothing of
the movement of Ewell's division; that Banks had
moved his headquarters to Winchester, twenty miles
northwest of Front Royal, and was looking for the
Rebels to advance by the Valley pike, and when they
did he intended to strike their flank and rear with his
Front Royal detachment, all of which was absolutely
<sic corr="true">trne</sic>, but it was known to General Jackson the night we
left New Market and only needed Belle Boyd to
confirm it; and when the “foot cavalry” got knowledge
of this matter, as they did in a few days, their opinion of
their leader changed, and blind, awkward and queer as
he <hi rend="italics">seemed</hi> they knew he was anything but a crank.</p>
          <p>The movement to Front Royal was nearly to a focus
now, and Gen. “Dick” Taylor started his
<pb id="robs39" n="39"/>
Louisiana brigade  -  a “daisy” she was, too  -  at a
double, closely followed by the whole force, and pretty
soon we broke cover down a steep by-path into the
Gooney Manor road, not half a mile from town. Some
cavalry was first encountered, but almost instantly
brushed away, and our cavalry, making a sweep,
captured and brought out many prisoners.</p>
          <p>The Louisianians, led by the gallant General, went at
the railroad bridge, and then came Col. Bradley T.
Johnson, with his regiment, the 1st Maryland, in a fair,
square attack straight into Colonel Kenly's 1st
Maryland, of Bank's army, when “Greek literally met
Greek,” and the tug of war was desperate. Generals
Jackson and Ewell galloped along the field, like knights
of the olden time, cheering on their men; the “Tigers,”
of Major Wheat, and the Louisiana boys “waded in”
yelling, firing, fighting; while the Virginians joined in the
chorus, the 52d well up and doing her duty equal to any
on the field, and no man, woman or child, all the way
from Luray, knew we were coming until we had
passed, except Belle Boyd.</p>
          <p>I wish I could give a description of the battle of
Front Royal, with all the preceding incidents and
operations, showing the inspiration by which General
Jackson planned and brought through to complete
success his audacious movement right into the camps
of the enemy which surrounded him, and I
<pb id="robs40" n="40"/>
have always believed it was a piece of one of the
sublimest pictures of strategy ever performed in war.</p>
          <p>The enemy was pretty soon driven across the river,
and tried hard to destroy the bridge, but the pressure in
the rear was too great to give them time, and moreover
Ashby, with part of his cavalry, had crossed above, cut
the railroad and telegraph wires to Strasburg, and
prevented any help coming to the enemy from that
point, while at Buckton he drove them from the strong
position in the railroad cut and captured a train of cars.
Other portions of the cavalry overtook the retreating
Federals at Cedarville, and some companies of the 6th
Virginia cavalry, led by Captain Grimsley, of Culpeper,
in two gallant charges, broke them up completely, but
many good men of the cavalry were killed  -  among
them Captain Baxter, Company K, 6th Virginia, and
Captains Sheets and Fletcher of the Ashby Legion.</p>
          <p>There was considerable jealousy on the part of the
infantry against the cavalry, the “foot-pads” thinking the
riders had the easiest time, and seldom omitted an
opportunity to make game of them, especially when the
cavalry would be passing them on a march, and the old
chaff of “Come down out o' that hat, know yo're thar;
see your legs a hanging down!” “Get from behin'
them boots! needn't
<pb id="robs41" n="41"/>
say you aint thar; see your ears a workin'!” will be
remembered while any of the old soldiers live. But I
think the cutest thing I ever heard was by an old
infantry man, on the Valley pike, in 1863. He was
resting, his arms crossed on the muzzle of his musket,
when a dashing-looking cavalry man, wearing
considerable gold lace and feathers, rode up. The
infantryman eyed him quizzically, for a few minutes,
and then accosted him with, “Say, Mister, did you ever
see a dead Yankee?” and paused to enjoy the
contemptuously dignified, silent stare of the cavalier.
The old knapsack-toter then continued: “Cause if you
didn't, and you'll go along with us for about an hour
we'll show you one.” This failing to elicit any response,
he began again, in a very reassuring tone: “You needn't
be afeered, Mister, 'cause there haint none of our
cavalry got killed yet, and I hain't never heered of but
one of 'em gittin' hurt, and he was kicked while he was
currying of his creeter.” Of course there was a yell, as
the “wore out” cavalryman rode off as lively as he
could, and the footman set his trap for the next one.</p>
          <p>We boys didn't make so much sport of the cavalry
after Front Royal, and it was no uncommon sight to
see a dead man with spurs on during the Valley
campaign. The artillery, too, under the famous
commanders, Poague, Chew, Courtney, Carpenter,
<pb id="robs42" n="42"/>
Lattimer, Caskie, Raines, Luck, Miller, Cutshaw,
Wooding, and others, did splendid service. </p>
          <p>I do not think I ever saw a list of the regiments in
Jackson's first campaign in the Shenandoah Valley,
and believing it will interest the reader, will endeavor to
give, from memory and reading, what I believe to be a
correct statement of them:</p>
          <p>From Virginia, there were the 2d, 4th, 5th, 10th,
13th, 21st, 23d, 27th, 31st, 33d, 37th, 42d, 44th, 48th,
52d, and 58th regiments, and the 1st (Irish) battalion,
infantry.</p>
          <p>From Louisiana, the 6th, 7th, 8th and 9th regiments,
and Major Wheat's “Tiger” battalion, infantry.</p>
          <p>From Georgia, the 12th and 21st regiments,
infantry.</p>
          <p>From North Carolina, the 21st regiment, infantry.</p>
          <p>From Alabama, the 15th regiment, infantry.</p>
          <p>From Mississippi, the 16th regiment, infantry.</p>
          <p>From Maryland, the 1st regiment, infantry.</p>
          <p>The cavalry of General Ashby was the 7th and 12th
regiments, and the 17th battalion, Virginia, and the
brigade which came over with General Ewell was the
2d and 6th Virginia, with one company, under Ewell's
special orders, commanded by Capt. E. V. White, from
Loudoun county, Va.  -   making 27 regiments and 2
battalions of infantry, 4 regiments and 1 battalion of
cavalry, and, I think, 11 batteries, of about 44 guns
altogether.</p>
          <pb id="robs43" n="43"/>
          <p>Of course I am rambling, moving along the route
towards the point where I became a “one-legged
Rebel,” and I got there soon enough, but it took me by
Winchester, on Sunday morning, May 25, 1862, where I
helped all I could to crush the life out of General
Banks' army, and such a glorious welcome as met us
from the warm-hearted people of that famous old
town. There was some fighting in the streets, but the
happy inhabitants wouldn't stay indoors, not even the
women and babies; but almost almost frantic with
delight, they with one breath blessed us for coming, and
the next blamed us for letting so many Yankees get
away. They evidently expected impossible things from
“Stonewall's” men, such as catching crows on the wing,
or the “wild gazelle on Judah's hills,” either of which
was as possible as to overtake General Bank's
runaways.</p>
          <p>The singularly brilliant idea of Gen. Geo. H. Stuart,
who commanded the little cavalry brigade, composed
of the 2d and 6th regiments, that inasmuch as he
belonged to Ewell's division he was not subject to
General Jackson's immediate command, permitted
many of the enemy to make their escape, and the
whole cavalry force was so scattered as not to be
available for pursuit of the flying Federals, at the
proper moment, which was unfortunate for us, but we
told the Winchester folks that we had
<pb id="robs44" n="44"/>
done our best, and they showed their appreciation of
our efferts by standing on the streets with quantities of
good things to eat, which they pressed upon the
eagerly moving soldiers, and here allow me to say,
from personal experience, that it was perfectly safe,
under any circumstances, to force nice, roast beef,
ham, buiscuit, pies, cakes, pickles and the like upon any
marching column of Confederate soldiers, whether
they were pursuing a routed enemy or fighting him in
the streets of a town, and no person who did it was
ever hurt.</p>
          <p>We had done the best we could for Mr. Banks, and
were pretty well pleased with ourselves once more, so
that the old spirit of “generalship” again spread its
mantle over each soldier in the line, and he knew
exactly how to manage the campaign thenceforward
notwithstanding our ideas had not been strictly followed
by General Jackson in the opening of it, but we did not
fully agree as to preliminaries now, some of us being
strongly in favor of taking immediate march to
Harrisburg, Pa., and operating from that point as a
base, while many thought we should make an instant
attack on Washington City itself, and thereby draw
General McClellan out of his intrenched lines on the
Chicahominy, thereby giving General Johnston the
opportunity he was looking for to ruin him as we had
done the armies opposed to us.</p>
          <pb id="robs45" n="45"/>
          <p>We knew we were going to hold the Valley anyhow,
for of course the war was almost over now - and how
we did pity the fellows at home, youngsters and the
like, who wouldn't get any experience in camping,
marching and fighting, nor any share of the glory that
radiated around and all about “Stonewall” Jackson's
men.</p>
          <p>We had nearly made up our minds to elect
“Stonewall” President of the Confederate States at the
next election, although Beauregard was still the
soldiers' idol, and, as yet, we had heard very little of
“Marse Robert,” for Seven Pines had not been fought,
and “Joe Johnston,” the “great retreater,” was still
falling back somewhere about the Peninsula. But <hi rend="italics">we</hi>
were not falling back  -  were not of that kind! Come
to stay we had, and like Alexander, were sedulously
looking out for other armies to conquer. So it passed,
and we trotted about to hurry Banks' demoralized
legions over the border, and swelling with pride in <hi rend="italics">our</hi>
generalship.</p>
          <p>While the fighting at Winchester was in progress,
one of the staff suggested to General Jackson that he
was exposing himself too much, and the answer was,
“Tell the troops to push right on to the Potomac,” and
this became a kind of watchword with us; but General
Banks got there first, and promptly reported to his
government that “he had accomplished
<pb id="robs46" n="46"/>
a premeditated march of nearly sixty miles, in
the face of the enemy, defeating his plans and giving
him battle wherever found;” that he “had not suffered
an attack or rout,” but he naively added that “it is
seldom a river-crossing of such magnitude is achieved
with greater success, and there were never more
greateful hearts in the same number of men than when,
on the 26th, we stood on the opposite shore.” These
quotations are taken verbatim, by John Easton Cooke,
from the records of the War Department at
Washington, and if, after reading them, anybody has
anything to say, I give them liberty to say it. It may be
that “Stonewall” had some idea of making a
“premeditated march” himself, but if so he said nothing
to “us generals” about it; but we noticed that he took the
unnecessary precaution  -  as we thought - to start
Colonel Cunningham with his regiment, the 21st
Virginia, up the pike from Winchester, as quick as he
could get the stuff together, with 3,000 prisoners, 100
cattle, and a great train of wagons loaded with 34,000
pounds of bacon, with flour, salt, bread, coffee, sugar,
cheese, etc., in proportion, and $125,185.00 worth of
commissary stores, $25,000 worth of sutler's goods, an
immense quantity of medical and hospital supplies, and
9,354 small arms, with two pieces of artillery and a
great many cavalry horses and equipments. All such
<pb id="robs47" n="47"/>
goods as this, though rated on the quartermaster's
inventory as actual <hi rend="italics">cash</hi> value, had been bought and
paid for in another currency, more precious to many
than greenbacks, gold or silver, and we go to another
ledger to learn <hi rend="italics">that</hi> price, as shown by the list of killed
and wounded.</p>
          <p>On this advance movement down the Valley every
man was pressing to the front with a vim and
enthusiasm which gave the enemy no rallying point or
time to prepare a line of defence, and General Jackson
said that “the battles of Front Royal and Winchester
had been fought without a straggler.”</p>
          <p>Our loss was 68 killed, 327 wounded and three
missing, but I do not know that of the enemy. We
paroled 700 of their wounded and left them at
Winchester in their own hospitals, but I will not attempt
any calculation of their loss from the data. The letter of
a Northern correspondent at the time says: “Banks lost
over $2,000,000 in property,” and we know that Colonel
Connor, who was left by Jackson with one regiment at
Front Royal, destroyed nearly $300,000 worth of
property at that place when he was driven from there
by McDowell in advance. The Philistines had broken
up the political Sampson, but he “hadn't suffered
defeat,” so he told the Secretary of War. I hope my
readers will pardon my apparent exultation in passing
over this part of the road, because I can't help being
<pb id="robs48" n="48"/>
proud of the deeds my comrades did, and when I get
to campaigning in memory's fields with “Stonewall the
Great,” my pulses quicken like a race-horse. </p>
          <p>I don't mean any disrespect to anybody  -  but am a
little like the old “grayback” who, after the surrender,
went to the Provost Marshal, at Charlottesville, to be
paroled. After taking all the oaths required of him, he
asked the Provost if he wasn't all right. “Yes, ” said the
Captain, “you are.” “Good a Union man as anybody,
ain't I.” “Yes,” replied the Captain, “you are in the
Union now as a loyal citizen, and can go ahead all
right.” “Well, then,” said the old sinner; “didn't
‘Stonewall’ use to give <hi rend="italics">us</hi> h--l in the Valley.” You see
he was one of “Stonewall's foot cavalry,” and couldn't
help being proud of it.</p>
          <p>But I must return to the army of <hi rend="italics">generals</hi> who were
going to hold the Valley. We did not hold it until the
30th of May, down at the bottom end of it - Charleston,
Bunker Hill and vicinity - but a Courier came to
General Jackson, and among other curious matters,
related that Colonel Connor's force at Front Royal had
been captured by General Shields, who was advancing
by that route, that the “great pathfinder,” Fremont, was
moving from the west, both aiming to unite at Strasburg
with a combined force of nearly 40,000, which was
interesting
<pb id="robs49" n="49"/>
if true, and most of it proved true, for Jackson had only
15,000 effective men - all generals, however - and
under the circumstances each general unanimously
resolved to withdraw from the lower end of the Valley,
if he could, and abandon for the present any further
demonstrations on Harrisburg and Washington, thereby
relieving those threatened points from the pressure
which we had nearly resolved to bring upon them. In
fact, the pressure appeared to have been, for the
moment, applied in a totally different, and, to us
generals, a very unexpected locality, for we had not
had time in those four days' stay to familiarize
ourselves with the capacity and resources of that part
of the country. We managed to “hit the road” brisk
enough to become familiar with <hi rend="italics">that</hi> though, so much
so that the last of us made fifty miles, walked too, from
late in the afternoon of the 30th to the night of the 3Ist,
which put us at Strasburg.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
          <p>On Sunday morning, June 1st, 1862, we walked out on
the Wardonsville road and held service with General
Fremont's advance, which we checked, and finally
drove his people back so far as to give us wagon room
and let all of our trains get safely past this dangerous
point.</p>
          <pb id="robs50" n="50"/>
          <p>We fully expected General Shields to take part in
the exercises, which would have rendered them much
more interesting to us, and knowing him to have been
at Front Royal we knew it would be comparatively
easy for him to do, but his failure to appear satisfied
us that he had taken the Page Valley route, and now
we were in for a race to New Market Gap. It is
related, on good authority, that “once upon a time” a
traveler, found a boy, with hoe and crowbar, hard at
work digging under a big rock, and inquiring what he
was after. “Ground-hog under here,” was the sententious
reply. “Do you expect to get him out?” asked the traveler.
“<hi rend="italics">Expect to get him!</hi>” said the boy - “<hi rend="italics">got</hi> to get him; preacher
be at our house to-day, and we're out out of meat.”</p>
          <p>It was a “ground-hog case” now with “Stonewall,”
for this fourteen-mile wagon train carried the <hi rend="italics">visible</hi>
fruits of our victory over Banks, and we “<hi rend="italics">got</hi> to get” to
New Market Gap ahead of Shields or he'd cut our train
off. We did get there, but it was a busy job, especially
for Ashby and the rear guard, and the light batteries
and the sharp-shooters kept up one continual roar all
the way  -  day and night  -   as they contested, mile by mile, 
the advance of Fremont's column, which had taken the 
road in our rear when we left Strasburg. I don't believe he could
have saved his train from us, if the conditions
<pb id="robs51" n="51"/>
had been reversed, and Fremont had been
conducting the retreat, with Jackson leading the
advance, which brings up another pretty good war
anecdote; whether true or not, makes no difference so
far as the illustration is concerned:</p>
          <p>During the long and bloody battle of Cold Harbour,
between Grant and Lee, in 1864, a Yankee soldier went
to his Captain for a pass to army headquarters, saying
he had a plan for ending the war, which he knew
would work if he could get the authorities to adopt it,
but he positively refused to communicate it to any but
the commanding general. The Captain gave him the
pass, and after considerable difficulty in keeping his
secret, passing regimental, brigade, division and corps
commanders, the soldier reached Grant's headquarters  -
and returned. His Captain observed that he seemed
very much depressed in spirit, and promptly
interviewed him as to the result of his mission,
and by coaxing got a report. He said the General was
absent when he reached headquarters, but the staff
was so urgent, and made him believe that it was his
duty to <hi rend="italics">immediately</hi> give such important information to
the chief that he did so. Here he stopped, but the
Captain insisted upon knowing what occurred, and
finally the man said; “Well Captain, they don't want the
war to stop nohow, for as soon as I told them my plan
they kicked me out of the
<pb id="robs52" n="52"/>
tent and kept it up for fifty yards, clear down to the
woods; <hi rend="italics">and I came away.</hi>”</p>
          <p>“Now, then,” sad the Captain, “What was the plan
you proposed ?”</p>
          <p>“Well, Sir,” replied the soldier, “I told them to let
Grant and Lee swap armies and the war would end in
three weeks.”</p>
          <p>When we got to Woodstock we had to stop and
give Fremont a lesson, but after passing Mt. Jackson
and destroying the bridge over the Shenandoah, we
knew we were clear  -  for the fluttering signals on the
Massanutton told us that our cavalry had destroyed the
White House bridge on the Luray road, and stopped
Shields; so now “Stonewall” “like a weary lion,” as
Cook puts it, slowly dragged his spoils to his lair, and
although the enemy was up with us again we knew our
trains were safe. At New Market we got the news of
the battle at Seven Pines; the wounding of General
Johnson, and the assignment of Gen. R. E. Lee to the
command o the Army of Northern Virginia. <hi rend="italics">The war
had begun!</hi>
</p>
          <p>We had another brush with Fremont, near
Harrisonburg, on the 5th of June, in which General
Ashby was killed, which cast a gloom over the whole
army, and was felt to be an irreparable calamity by
every man in it. Our division, under General Ewell,
halted at Cross Keys, on the 7th, and
<pb id="robs53" n="53"/>
made arrangements for battle. In the old times there
had stood, at the intersection of several roads, an
old-fashioned tavern, upon the swinging sign of which was
painted two keys crossed, from which the name was
derived; and now it was to be made famous by Ewell's
fighting division, and given an enduring name on the
page of history.</p>
          <p>On Sunday, June 8th, 1862, we were ready again
for our usual Sabbath exercises, and Fremont was on
hand with his congregation. The 52d regiment got a
fair share of business in this engagement, and lost a
good many men. Major Ross was among the
wounded, so was Lieutenant Samuel Paul, of
Company D, whose leg was shivered by a shell, within
five steps of me, which caused amputation. He has
since been treasurer of Augusta county, and I have
often thought I would like to be treasurer of something
myself  -  but all the one-legged Rebels can't get their
living the same way, and Lieutenant Paul  -  gallant
soldier and good officer as he was  -  was equally as
good a citizen, and deserves all the success he
achieved. Lieutenant King, of Company B, was killed
here, and we were quite willing for Fremont's men to
retire when they had got as much as they wanted.</p>
          <p>Our brigade was commanded in this battle by
General George H. Stewart, and was posted on the
left centre of Ewell's line, sustaining and repulsing
<pb id="robs54" n="54"/>
four distinct charges, each made by fresh troops; but
they were mostly Dutch, and we fought them to the
best advantage, behind trees, which General Ewell's
judicious selection of the ground gave us.</p>
          <p>Fremont's Dutchman were no match for the “foot-cavalry,”
and although General Ewell himself says he
had less than 5,000 muskets, and Fremont's order to
march, which was taken from an aid of General Blenker
killed by one of Trimble's men, showed six
brigades, commanded by Blenker, Milroy, Stahel,
Steinwerh, and one other, of infantry, with one brigade
of cavalry, numbering in all about 20,000, yet their
dread of Jackson caused them to give way under
slight pressure, especially when General Trimble
struck them in flank.</p>
          <p>General Forrest, the famous cavalry commander of
Tennessee, was once asked a question as to the cause
of his almost constant success in his cavalry
operations, when other commanders so frequently
failed, and his answer was: “Well, I got thar first, with
the most men;” and that in a sentence, gives the key to
Jackson's generalship, if you add to it the Cromwellian
motto, “Trust in the Lord, and keep your powder dry.”
We left the battle ground of Cross Keys at midnight,
and took the road to Port Republic, where Jackson,
with his division, had been holding Shields in check; but
the gallant Irishman was now coming on again in
such force as
<pb id="robs55" n="55"/>
to make a concentration of our forces necessary.
General Fremont reported his total loss at Cross Keys
fight as 2,000, while General Ewell's official report of
our loss was 300 killed, wounded, and missing; a very
encouraging affair to Ewell's boys, who held the
battle-ground, and equally discouraging to Fremont's who
were forced to retreat.</p>
          <p>The village of Port Republic lies in the angle made
by the junction of the North and South Rivers, which
here form the south fork of the Shenandoah, along the
east side of which General Shield's was moving. The
Cross Keys road crosses the North River by a good
bridge, into the town, and another road runs northeast
from the town by a ford in the South River, and down
the south fork, by Conrad's store, to Luray. A third
crosses at the same ford and running southeast,
through Brown's Gap, in the Blue Ridge, leads to
<sic corr="Charlottesville">Charlottsville</sic>. I don't think it any harm to give this
much geography, even if all my readers should also be
posted in the big histories, but I am satisfied that many
will read this who never saw any of the aforesaid big
histories; and they will thus be better able to
comprehend the successful performance of all the
points of Jackson's magnificent strategy.</p>
          <p>The position then was, Fremont at Harrisonburg,
Shields at Conrad's Store  -  between which all the
bridges were destroyed - and Jackson at Port Republic,
<pb id="robs56" n="56"/>
forming a triangle, with sides fifteen miles long.
Behind Jackson was the road through Brown's Gap,
clear and open, so that he could fight them separately
or fall back to Charlottesville and Richmond, and his
operations up to this time had caused the troops of
McDowell, Fremont and Shields to be withheld from
McClellan, and at the same time put his own army
within easy reach of Richmond should General Lee
desire his assistance.</p>
          <p>Fremont with his 18,000 and Shields with his 15,000,
would have been too much odds for Jackson's 12,000,
to which he had been reduced since leaving
Winchester; and he had no idea of permitting them to
double on him, but he had got Fremont whipped by
Ewell so easily, at Cross Keys, that he determined to
double his own team and give Shields a trial. “Stonewall”
was a thorough and consistent Christian, so
far as I know, and was reported to do a great deal of
praying, but he certainly did practice a great deal of
deception on these two estimable gentlemen right here.
We crossed the bridge over the North River early in the
morning of June 9, 1862, and set it on fire as soon as
everything was over  -  thus preventing General
Fremont from coming to Shields' assistance  -  but the
ford of South River, owing to recent rains, was too
deep for us, and we made a bridge of wagons and
planks to get over on. Jackson's men were already
engaged
<pb id="robs57" n="57"/>
with the enemy and needed Ewell's assistance right
away, and here was illustrated the influence of trifles
on important events.</p>
          <p>We could see the “Stonewall Brigade” and Colonel
Harry Hayes' gallant 7th Louisiana, with the splendid
batteries of Poague and Carpenter hotly fighting, but
heavily overmatched, and we were hurrying as fast as
we could to their assistance when a plank in our
wagon-bridge slipped out, almost breaking up our
means of crossing, and did delay us considerably, so
much so that by the time we got over, formed our line
and commenced our advance upon the enemy, we met
General Winder's troops retiring in confusion.</p>
          <p>The 44th and 58th Virginia, by General Ewell's
directions, made a hot attack on the enemy's flank, but
could not hold him long, and the whole line fell back to
a piece of woods, losing one of Poague's 6-pounders
and a good many men. General Shields put a splendid
6-gun battery in a magnificent position to sweep the
field, and I don't think he had an imported Dutchman in
his army. They were all Western fellows, and stuck to
their ground as if they belonged there, and it is my
candid opinion that they were descendants of folks
who had, years before, emigrated to the great West,
from the Shenandoah Valley. Our advance, under
General Elzy, was through a fine field of wheat bordering
on the
<pb id="robs58" n="58"/>
river bottom, chin high, and their minnie balls clipped
the grain worse than reapers. It was a very bad job of
harvesting, the boys said  -  a harvest of death it
proved  -  and much as we tried to make it short, the
time dragged slowly enough, until it did seem that
Shields was fully a match for “Stonewall” Jackson.</p>
          <p>The two commanders maneuvered their men under
fire, just as the old-time warriors used to do before
long range weapons came into use, but still that terrible
6-gun battery held the key of the battle, and when
General Taylor rode up, Jackson turned to him and
said: “Can you take that battery?  -  it must be taken!”</p>
          <p>Taylor's answer was to gallop back to his brigade,
and pointing with his sword to the enemy's guns, called
out, in a voice like a bugle-blast, for thrilling wildness,
“Louisianians, can you take that battery?” They
answered, with a yet wilder thrill, “We're the boys that
can do that, General. You can bet on your boys!” and
the gallant son of “Old Rough and Ready” led them
forward.</p>
          <p>Three times the Louisiana brigade drove the enemy
back and captured the guns, but were as often
repulsed, in turn, by the splendid soldiers of Shields.
Taylor turned savagely for another trial, and Jackson
seeing that Shields was heavily re-enforcing
his left to protect the battery, brought all
<pb id="robs59" n="59"/>
he could to his own left, and as the Louisiana boys
made their last assault on the guns, threw all he had on
Shields' right, breaking it all up, and at the same time
Taylor took those dreadful guns, again turned them on
the enemy, and the victory was won; but, as Cowan
said to the devil  -  “'twas claw for claw,” and we had
fought as fine a body of troops as there was on the
Continent, fully justifying the assurance of the 6th
Louisiana  -  an Irish regiment  -  who said, when
Fremont was beaten the day before, “This isn't much,
but look out for to-morrow, for Shields' boys will be
after fighting.” The battle of Port Republic was one of
the most sanguinary of the war, and we lost nearly
1,000 men killed and wounded. I do not know the loss of
the enemy in killed and wounded, but we captured 7
pieces of artillery with limbers and caissons, 975
prisoners, and more than 1,000 small arms. One of the
prisoners said to us  - “You fired over our heads at
Winchester, but you fired under them here.”</p>
          <p>General Shields returned to Conrad's Store, but he
was never routed, and stopped when Jackson did. He
was badly crippled though, and Kernstown was atoned
for, and the “Great Pathfinder,” Fremont, was no
longer able to act offensively in the Valley  -  except
towards the citizens  -  but in this he was far superior
in magnanimity to Milroy and others.
<pb id="robs60" n="60"/>
General Shields was a favorite with the people among
whom he operated, and treated them with
consideration and kindness, but he was a terror when
it came to fighting.</p>
          <p>And now was accomplished the full purpose of
“Stonewall's” strategy, for it was fully guaranteed
that not another soldier could be spared from the
defences of Washington to arrest McClellan in the
Chickahominy, because of the unknown motions of the
man who could disappear and reappear so suddenly  
aud unexpectedly, and while making such audacious
marches right into the jaws of his powerful enemies,
deliver such fearful blows and get out whole.</p>
          <p>The very uncertainty and mystery which hung
around him was worth as army, for it kept an army of
the enemy unemployed while waiting for Jackson to
develop his plan.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
          <p>After Port Republic we enjoyed ourselves in our
pleasant June camps about Mt. Meridian, and begun
our planning and generalship again. There hadn't been
quite so much of that among us since we left
Strasburg, for the situation appeared to be mixed
to such an extent that for some time each
individual general had nearly decided that it
would
<pb id="robs61" n="61"/>
be as much as the bargain to get his own individual
baggage out safe, but now we had shaken off the
dogs of war which had howled at our heels and
gnashed at our flanks like blood-hounds hunting the
lion, and being free again were ready for a new
campaign.</p>
          <p>I think it best, from this time forward, to deal less in
general history, if I can, so long as the war lasts, and
give my readers more of the incidents that cluster
around the life of the soldier  -  but I couldn't help
talking as I did about the Valley campaign; and now
“Stonewall” was our hero and idol. His old, ambling
sorrel, was in our eyes, a war charger worthy of a
Cœur de Lion; and his dingy coat and mangy cap
were glorified. We didn't make game of him any more,
but one irreverent fellow started, as a conundrum,
“Why is General Jackson a better leader than Moses
was?” answering  -  “because it took Moses forty years
to march the children of Israel through the Wilderness,
and Jackson would have doubled-quicked them
through in three days.” The army had suffered all the
usual trials of military life  -  and death too  -  in time
of war, and the men had been hurried by day and by
night; in storm and sunshine; in hunger and cold; on
picket and camp guard; in the whistling tempest of
lead, and the howling, deamon shriek of shell; in the
mangling of comrades, and the hasty burial of our
<pb id="robs62" n="62"/>
dead on the field where they fell  -  and yet so
wonderfully recuperative is the mind of man, that as soon
as the pressure of adverse circumstances is removed,
he lights his candle at the burning torch of hope and
leaves the past behind him. Just so did we, the men
and boys, who had followed “Stonewall”
through his trying campaign, come out bright and
fresh, ready to follow again wherever the star of his
destiny might lead  -  for we wanted to follow that
destiny wherever it might be.</p>
          <p>The brigade to which my regiment was attached
was composed of the 13th Virginia regiment, made up
of companies from the counties of Culpeper, Louisia,
Orange, Frederick and Hampshire, and was
commanded, during the war, by Colonels A. P. Hill,
J. A. Walker and Terrell. The 31st Virginia, from
Upsher, Randolph, Gilmer, Barbour and Highland,
under Colonel Hoffman. The 49th Virginia, from
Rappahannock, Prince William, Fauquier, Nelson and
Amhurst, under Colonels Smith (extra) and Gibson.
And the 52d Virginia  -  my own old regiment  -  was
from Augusta, Rockbridge and Bath, and had for
Colonels, during the war, Baldwin, Harman, Watkins,
Skinner and Lilly. Our Brigadiers were Edward
Johnson, Elzey, Pegram and Stewart.</p>
          <p>These were all gallant soldiers and good officers,
whose names have gone into history gloriously, but
<pb id="robs63" n="63"/>
“us boys” made the wreaths of fame that bound their
brows, and we are proud that they wore them worthily.</p>
          <p>A. P. Hill reached the rank of Lieutenant-General,
and was killed near Petersburg, by a straggler, just as
the star of peace breaking through the clouds. Terrell
and Watkins were both killed, so was Board, and
Hoffman, a late judge in West Virginia, lost a foot; but
the old hero, Lieutenant-General J. A. Early, more
thoroughly lied on than any, and with whom more
ability than all his traducers combined, is now dead;
while Gibson, of Culpeper, is one of the most
prominent lawyers of Middle Virginia, and may yet be
Governor, carries on his person the scars of ten
wounds received in battle. It used to appear very
much as if fate, and not accident, had control of the
bullets in battle, for some men went bravely through
battle after battle with never a scratch to show for it,
and were finally killed in some little insignificant
skirmish, where not a dozen shots were fired; and then
again there were men who would be wounded in
every battle if they came in cannon shot of the field. I
know one instance where as good a soldier as fought
in the Southern Army got hit with a ball every time he
went into a fight, but not one serious wound among
them, and his brother, in the same company, equally as
good a soldier, who never missed a battle,
<pb id="robs64" n="64"/>
went safely through the war with only one wound.</p>
          <p>Some soldiers seemed to move in a charmed circle
of safety, while others appeared to be bright
particular objects of special favoritism when wounds
were to be distributed, and in the latter part of the
war the soldier was thought by his comrades to be
especially lucky when he got a <hi rend="italics">furlough</hi> wound  -    
one that didn't quite kill, but allowed him to stay
at home while it was healing.</p>
          <p>We remained in the Valley long enough to get rested
up good, and then moved through Brown's Gap, and
“on to Richmond,” for the new general of the army
there was tired of McClellan's parallels, redoubts,
salients and other engineering schemes on the
Chicahominy, and desired to put a “Stonewall” across
the road.</p>
          <p>I remember picking up a Richmond paper about this
time which contained a letter from a young lady in the
country to her friend in the city, inviting her to pay a
visit, and the ingenious working in of the names of our
Generals interested me so much that I retained it in
memory. The <sic corr="letter">latter</sic> ran thus  -</p>
          <lg type="stanza" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">“Come, leave the noisy <hi rend="italics">longstreet</hi>,</l>
            <l part="N">And come to the <hi rend="italics">fields</hi> with me,</l>
            <l part="N">Tip o'er the <hi rend="italics">heath</hi> with flying feet</l>
            <l part="N">And skip along the <hi rend="italics">lea</hi>.</l>
            <l part="N">There <hi rend="italics">ewell</hi> find the flowers that be</l>
            <l part="N">Along the <hi rend="italics">stonewall</hi> still.</l>
          </lg>
          <pb id="robs65" n="65"/>
          <lg type="stanza" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">And pluck the buds of flowering pea</l>
            <l part="N">That bloom on <hi rend="italics">'appy hill</hi>,</l>
            <l part="N">Across our <hi rend="italics">rodes</hi> the <hi rend="italics">forrest</hi> boughs</l>
            <l part="N">A stately <hi rend="italics">arch</hi>way form</l>
            <l part="N">Where sadly pipes the <hi rend="italics">early</hi> bird</l>
            <l part="N">Which failed to catch the worm.”</l>
          </lg>
          <p>Do for a school-girl pretty well I thought.</p>
          <p>Coming out of the mountain pass we entered
Albemarle county just when the cherries were ripe,
and there were oceans of them, too. We got all we
could of them, but time was too precious to waste in
gathering cherries, for this march was to be made
without the knowledge of the enemy, and in order to
do this the soldiers were forbidden to tell the
citizens what commands they belonged to, and were
instructed to answer all questions in regard to the
army with  -  “I don't know.”</p>
          <p>The people all kept open house in Albemarle, and the
“foot cavalry” enjoyed many a good, square meal among
them. We sang the song of “Old Virginia
Never Tire,” and were very proud of our old State
when the Alabama, North Carolina and Mississippi
boys praised our people for their kindness and hospitality.</p>
          <p>General “Dick” Taylor tells of a breakfast he had
with some old friends and relatives of his father in
Orange county, on this march, which I think of sufficient
interest to repeat it in his own language:</p>
          <p>“ * * * That night we camped between Charlottesville
<pb id="robs66" n="66"/>
and Gordonsville, in Orange county, the birthplace of
my father. A distant kinsman, whom I had never met,
came to invite me to his house in the neighborhood.
Learning that I always slept in camp, he seemed so
much distressed as to get my consent to breakfast with
him if he would engage to have breakfast at the
barbarous hour of sunrise. His home was a little distant
from the road, so the following morning he sent a
mounted groom to show the way. My aide, young
Hamilton, accompanied me, and Tom followed, of
course. It was a fine old mansion, surrounded by
well-kept grounds. This immediate region had not yet been
touched by war. Flowering plants and rose trees, in full
bloom, attested the glorious wealth of June. On the
broad portico, to welcome us, stood the host with his
fresh, charming wife, and, a little retired, a white-hearted
butler. Greetings over with host and lady this
delightful creature, with ebon face beaming hospitality,
advanced holding a salver on which rested a huge
silver goblet filled with Virginia's nectar, mint julep.
Quantities of cracked ice rattled refreshingly in the
goblet, sprigs of fragrant mint peered above its broad
rim, a mass of white sugar too sweetly indolent to melt
rested on the mint, and, like rosebuds on a snowbank,
luscious strawberries crowned the sugar. Ah! that
julep! Mars ne'er received such tipple from the hands
of Ganymede! Breakfast
<pb id="robs67" n="67"/>
was announced, and what a breakfast! A beautiful
service, snowy tablecloth, damask napkins  -  long
unknown; above all, a lovely woman in crisp gown, with
more and handsomer roses on her cheek than in her
garden. 'Twas an idyl in the midst of the stern realities
of war! The table groaned beneath its viands. Sable
servitors brought in, hot from the kitchen, cakes of
wonderous forms, inventions of the tropical imaginations
of Africa inflamed by Virginian hospitality. I was rather
a moderate trencherman, but the performance of
Hamilton was Gargantuan, alarming. Duty dragged us
from this Eden; yet in the hurried adieus I did not forget
to claim of the fair hostess the privilege of a cousin. I
watched Hamilton narrowly for a time. The youth wore
a sodden, apoplectic look, quite out of his usual brisk
form. A gallop of some miles put him right, but for
days he dilated on the breakfast with the gusto of one
of Hannibal's veterans on the delights of Capau.”</p>
          <p>In order to the better understanding of the allusions
to Hamilton and Tom, I will give the information that
Lieutenant Hamilton was a grandson of General
Hamilton, of South Carolina, and was a cadet, in his
second year, at West Point when the war commenced.
Tom was the General's servant, three years his senior,
and was his foster brother and early playmate. Tom's
uncle, Charles Porter
<pb id="robs68" n="68"/>
Strother, had been body servant to General Zachary
Taylor, following him in his Indian and Mexican
campaigns, and Tom had served as aide to his uncle in
Florida and Mexico. The General says Tom could light
a fire in a minute, make the best coffee, and was
superb at all manner of camp stews and roasts. He
was an excellent horse groom as well as an expert at
washing and ironing. He was always cheerful, but
never laughed, and never spoke unless spoken to.
General Taylor thinks there was a mute sympathy
between General Jackson and Tom, and gives the
following story in evidence of it:</p>
          <p>He says he has often noticed them as they sat silent
by his camp fire, Jackson gazing abstractedly into the
fire and Tom, respectfully withdrawn, gazing at
Jackson. When General Taylor's brigade went into
action at Strasburg, he left Tom on a hill where all was
quiet. After awhile, from some change in the enemy's
dispositions, the place became rather hot, and Jackson,
passing by, advised Tom to move; but he replied, if the
General pleased, his master told him to stay there, and
he would know where to find him, and he did not
believe the shells would bother him. Two or three
nights later, General Jackson was at Taylor's camp
fire, and Tom came up to bring them some coffee,
whereupon Jackson rose and gravely shook him by
<pb id="robs69" n="69"/>
the hand, and then told General Taylor how Tom
had held his position on the hill.</p>
          <p>This little “side issue” to my story may not interest my
readers, but it did me, very much, and I give it at a
venture, and will now resume the march.</p>
          <p>Our objective point was Ashland, R. F. &amp; P. R.,
and our route led us between the army of McDowell
and the right wing of McClellan. As before stated, our
Generals did not allow us to know anything at all, and
so all us private generals gave the thing up and went
ahead blindfolded, with no guide but our unswerving
faith in General Jackson.</p>
          <p>Some of the fellows had got on very familiar terms
with him, indeed, so much so that they addressed him
in common conversation as “Old Jack!”  -  that is,
when he was not exactly present. When he <hi rend="italics">was</hi>
present it was our custom to throw up our hats and
give him a rolling, rousing cheer, which usually had
the effect to hurry him along, and I doubt very much
if he liked it, for, although he always took off his cap
when passing this ordeal of homage, I noticed he got
out of reach of it as fast as the “old sorrel” would
take him.</p>
          <p>But our pride in our General was still more
increased when our sweeping fight, beginning at
Mechanicsville, brought the great, high generals of
<pb id="robs70" n="70"/>
Lee's army over to our side of the Chickahominy to
report to “Stonewall,” and we saw Longstreet, A. P.
and D. H. Hill, Hood, Branch, Stuart, Whiting and
others, taking their orders gracefully from our great
Valley Chieftain; and we noticed the difference in their
clothes, too, and notwithstanding they were
better dressed, we could see a still brighter glow of
glory over the damaged “duds” of <hi rend="italics">our</hi> Jackson. We
were proud of glorious “Old Dick” Ewell, too, who took
everything so calmly, <hi rend="italics">except when he was excited</hi>,
and was always ready, just as he was in 1847, when he
led that squadron of Kearney's dragoons in their wild,
dashing charge right up to the gates of the City of
Mexico; but I want my reader not to forget that <hi rend="italics">our</hi>
“Stonewall” is the prince and hero of this little story as
far as it has been spun yet, and I want them further to
understand that the statements are historically
accurate and correct, to the best of my knowledge and
belief. I don't think there can be any excuse for
“knowingly or willingly” incorporating falsehood in this
little retrospective view, and if I do record anything not
true, I do it unintentionally. There was but <hi rend="italics">one</hi>
Jackson.</p>
          <p>This Chickahominy country is not much like the
royal Valley of Virginia, and we always felt lost in it.
No glimpse of the Blue Ridge charmed our eyes,
nothing but flat, sedgy fields, piney woods
<pb id="robs71" n="71"/>
with cypress trimmings, and scrubby, tangled mazes of
wilderness, and swamps with stagnant, currentless
streams of coffee-colored water. The air was not
bracing and invigorating like our own grand, mountain
country, but came lazily creeping through the woods
and sedges in a languid, half-and-half style, and the
whole thing bore on our spirits with a depressing
influence. We missed the splendid, gushing springs of
pure water we had always had at home, but never
appreciated until now, and it gave us infinite trouble to
rid ourselves of the ticks and chiggers that camped on
us and entrenched themselves in our flesh. We knew
that our depression was caused by the general
sleepiness of this dreary, dismal country, which we had
never seen before, for it resembles the whole Southern
lowland country from which came those gallant
regiments of North Carolina, Georgia, Mississippi,
Alabama and Louisiana, that had helped us redeem the
Valley, and the effect of our mountain air and water,
with the magnificent views of our rolling Valley, and its
clear, bright, rushing rivers upon those whole-souled
Southern men, was the very reverse of what this
country had upon us, but our boys said it was all right
for a battle-ground, because it was impossible to spoil
it, and it seemed fit for nothing else.</p>
          <p>No Virginian of the Valley ever ought to make
<pb id="robs72" n="72"/>
a home beyond the view of the mountains, for he will
not be content, and will always feel an aching, longing
to lay eyes on their billowy blue, no matter how long
he may stay away from them. “Absence cannot
conquer love.”</p>
          <p>“Bury me in the Valley of Virginia!” said
“Stonewall” Jackson, on his death-bed; and not one of
our boys but felt in their hearts the same desire,
should the fate of war require the sacrifice of his life,
but we didn't think as much of dying as the
circumstances surrounding us justified; nor did the
soldiers realize the nearness of death, when they were
campaigning, more than people do who plod along
through their daily duty in the piping times of peace.
As it had been in our Alleghany Mountain campaign,
in 1861, with the names of mountains, streams and
bridges, so now we learned new ones to us, and soon
our tongues, glibly rounded
off, in conversation, a long string of local names, such
as “Grapevine Bridge,” 
“Bottoms Bridge,” 
“Long
Bridge,” “York River Railroad,” 
“White House,”
“Pamunky,” “Williamsburg Road,” 
“Charles City,”
“Nine Mile Road,” 
“New Kent,” 
“Hanover,” etc. But
there was <hi rend="italics">one</hi> road, much mentioned too, which
made an impression on the mind of the school-boy,
and it was known all about as the “Darbytown Road,”
but spelled <hi rend="italics">Enroughty</hi> road. Some of Fremont's
Dutchmen
<pb id="robs73" n="73"/>
might have managed to make “Darby” out of that
<sic corr="conglomeration">comglomeration</sic> of letters, but “us boys” wasn't
generals enough for that yet; in point of fact we fell
into line at once, as <hi rend="italics">full privates</hi> when we struck the
“Enroughty-Darbytown Road,” and obeyed orders
just the same as if we had never held birthrights to
general's commissions.</p>
          <p>Pawhick Creek was also a very interesting position
to us, about the 27th of June, for behind it, beyond the
New Bridge Road, we found the skillfully constructed
fortifications which, with their massive banks of earth,
protected McClellan's men at the now doubly famous
Cold Harbour.</p>
          <p>In moving down from Mechanicsville to the York
River Railroad we came to another of those sluggard
streams, known as Tottapotamoi Creek, the bridge
over which was burning, and we heard the enemy's
axes chopping rapidly in the woods beyond, felling
trees to obstruct our march, and making an almost
solid barricade, but General Hood put Riley's battery in
position, and a few shells broke up the chopping so
quick that when we again moved forward we found
the axes sticking in the trees, but the choppers had
disappeared. That day was as near perfect as it could
be; air balmy, sky bright and cloudless, and nature
doing her full share to make the “OId Virginia low
lands low,” looked decent, but we had not come down
here
<pb id="robs74" n="74"/>
to enjoy the scenery of nature nor gather the delicious
blackberries that lined the swamps and fields.</p>
          <p>Just here I will introduce another extract from Gen.
“Dick” Taylor, most astonishing I admit; and yet, from
the high character of the evidence, not to be set aside
without thought, but I must say that I have never, in
all my reading of the history of the war, met anything
like it:</p>
          <p>“At the beginning of operations in the Richmond
campaign Lee had 75,000 and McClelland 100,000, in
round numbers  -  these figures taken from official
sources. A high opinion has been expressed of the
strategy of Lee, by which Jackson's forces were
suddenly thrust between McDowell and McClellan's
right, and it deserves all praise; but the tactics on the
field were vastly inferior in the strategy. Indeed, it
may be confidently asserted that from Cold Harbour
to Malvern Hill, inclusive, there was nothing but a
series of blunders, one after another, and all huge. The
confederate commanders knew no more about the
topography of the country than they did about Central
Africa. Here was a limited district, the whole of it
within a day's march of Richmond, the Capital of
Virginia and the Confederacy, almost the first spot
on the continent occupied by the English people * * *
and yet we were profoundly ignorant of the country,
<pb id="robs75" n="75"/>
were without maps or guides, and nearly as helpless as
if we had been suddenly transferred to the banks of
the Lualaba. The day before the battle of Malvern
Hill President Davis could not find a guide with
sufficient intelligence to conduct him from one of our
columes to another. * * * For two days we lost
McClellan's great army in a few miles of woodland,
and never had any definite knowledge of its
movements. * * * When it is remembered that
General McClellan's first operations in the Peninsula
indicated the line of the Chicahominy as to the most
probable, for the defence of Richmond, the
Confederate <sic corr="commander">cammander</sic> up to the battle of Seven
Pines, General Johnson, had been a topographical
engineer in the United States army, while his
successor General Lee, also an engineer, had been on
duty at the War Office in Richmond, and in constant
intercourse with President Davis, who was
educated at West Point and served seven years * * *
everyone must agree that our ignorance, in a military
sense, of the battleground was simply amazing. * * *
General McClellan was as superior to us in knowledge
of our own land as were the Generals to the French in
their war of 1870. * * * And so we blundered on like
people trying to read without knowledge of their
letters.”</p>
          <p>I am not conceited enough to give any opinion
<pb id="robs76" n="76"/>
of my own upon this subject even if I had one, but
reading what General Taylor has written, and
reflecting upon it, calls to mind much that was nearly
forgotten, and my revived memory can only account
for many things that I saw in the military operations of
the “Seven Days” by taking what he says as true. I
know we had no pillow of <sic corr="cloud">clowd</sic> by day or of fire by
night to lead us, but we also know that General
McClellan moved his army and trains by one single
road after he commenced his retreat to the James, and
only through ignorance somewhere on our part could
he have accomplished it as successfully as he did.
That General Lee had beat him in strategy, and “wore
out” his grand army with three men to his four is true,
and that McClellan had previously determined, after
Jackson's Valley campaign had locked up all his
hoped-for re-enforcements, to change his base to the
James River is also true, but that he was forced by
inexorable fate, in the person of Lee, to make that
change under pressure and before he was ready is as
true as any of it. And he was compelled to face his
fate as best he could, but in doing it his army was
ruined and the star of the “Young Napoleon” went
down in blood among the Chicahominy swamps as
the “Great” Napoleon's had done fifty years before
amid the snows of Russia and the flames of Moscow.</p>
          <pb id="robs77" n="77"/>
          <p>The result had proved General Lee to be one of the
greatest soldiers of history, and his throne in the hearts
of his soldiers was thenceforward secure, but we do
not want to lose sight of his admirable Lieutenants:  - 
Longstreet, the “War Horse,” as General Lee called
him, could always be relied on to hold the centre,
where the hardest blows were given; and A. P. Hill,
the dashing, chivalric, headlong commander of the
“Light Division,” who always in feeble health, was
never sick on battle days; Ewell, the blunt and fierce
bulldog soldier, confided in by Jackson; Magruder, the
boiling, tempestous, enterprising leader; Hood the giant
Texan, daring and indomitable, “bravest of the brave;”
Stuart, the prince of cavalrymen, chivalrous as a knight
of the Round Table; and all the way down the line,
generals of divisions and brigades, colonels of
regiments, commanders of squadrons and battalions,
captains of companies, all co-operated with the troops;
and the private soldier, “the true hero of the war,”
without the incentive or motive which controls the
officer, who hopes to live in history; without hope of
reward, actuated only by duty and patriotism, he
claimed the cause as his own, and went into the war to
“conquer or die,” to be free or not to be at all.</p>
          <p>History will yet award the chief glory where it
belongs  -  to the private soldier. All these joined
<pb id="robs78" n="78"/>
and executed the plans of General Lee, which resulted
in throwing General McClellan's magnificent army
back from the gates of the Southern capital, to tremble
and cower beneath the guns of their fleet at Harrison's
Landing, and the long agony was over. But we had
met soldiers who “fought like brave men, long and
well,” and their army was not routed, though defeated.</p>
          <p>We had worn many trophies from our foes; embracing
fifty pieces of artillery, many thousands of
small arms, millions of dollars worth of property,
and thousands of prisoners; but the supreme result was
the deliverance of the city of Richmond.</p>
          <p>It had cost us a heavy price to do this, and Jackson's
men had poured out precious blood in the lowlands, as
they had other precious blood in the Valley and among
the Alleghanies.</p>
          <p>Many of our gallant comrades slept their last sleep
beneath the slopes of Hanover, in the gloomy swamps
of the Chickahominy, and under the sighing pines of
New Kent and Charles City.</p>
          <lg type="stanza" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">“Lowly they lie, forms of spirits departed;</l>
            <l part="N">Lie, where in battle they struggled and fell,</l>
            <l part="N">Unknelt by their graves, by the 'reft, broken-hearted.</l>
            <l part="N">No marble enduring their noble deeds tell.”</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <pb id="robs79" n="79"/>
        <div2 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
          <p>I am no statesman, nor do I wish to be considered
one, but I think I represent the rank and file of the
Southern Army, and will try, roughly to tell what the
private soldiers thought about the war, after a year's
experience. We had our own ideas as to what it was
for, and I know that the maintenance, or perpetuation
of African slavery had no part in the motives which
impelled us to endure the privations of the camp, the
march, and all the tribulations which a state of war
brought to us, including the danger and death of the
battlefield. We did not think of slavery at all in
connection with the war. Many of us did not think
there was sufficient reason for the war anyway, and
like our old commander, General J. A. Early, opposed
<sic corr="secession">sesession</sic> as much, and as far as we could, but we
were citizens of Virginia; we, who could, had voted for
delegates to the State Convention with an honest
determination  -  as good citizens  -  to abide by the
result of their action. We believe the Federal
Government was a creature of the States, ordained for
the general good of all, but we felt that we owed
paramount allegiance to Old Virginia, and when our
State Convention, honestly and fairly elected, decided
to withdraw the State from the Union, and there action
was endorsed by an overwhelming majority of our
people, we would have held ourselves to be
<pb id="robs80" n="80"/>
traitors, <sic corr="ungrateful">ungreatful</sic> dogs, and death-deserving rebels, if
we had failed to enlist under her “<hi>
<foreign lang="la">Sic Semper
Tyrannis</foreign>
</hi>” banner.</p>
          <p>We couldn't fight the Union and the State both, nor
could we sit still and allow the Federal Government to
the throttle, stifle and crush our proud old
Commonwealth, for doing that which we believed she
had a perfect righ to do, viz: resume all the rights and
powers which she had delegated to the Federal
Government. There had been no coercion used to
compel her to enter the Union which, through her
distinguished sons, she had been one of the foremost to
promote, nor did we believe that our old-time fathers
had knowingly bound her to a hateful partnership with
a section bent on her ruin, by a tie which she had no
right or power to sever.</p>
          <p>We belonged first of all to Virginia, the blood of
whose sons had at times been shed from Quebec to
Boston, from Boston to Savannah, for the liberty we
enjoyed, and now where she required our services we,
as loyal children, dared to go. And I know that for the
first two years of the war slavery and its abolition did
not draw the young men of the West into the Northern
army, for I talked with many of them whom the fortune
of war had made our prisoners, and without exception
they declared they were fighting for the Union and the
old Constitution, not to free the negro, who, they said,
ought
<pb id="robs81" n="81"/>
not to be free among the white people. Nor do I
believe that Abraham Lincoln went into the war to
free the slaves, at least he <hi rend="italics">said</hi> he did not, and I
believe he was honest, and am satisfied that if the
South had surrendered any time during the first or
second year of the war slavery would not have been
abolished. The restoration of the <hi rend="italics">old</hi> Union, under the
old Constitution, would have left slavery intact, and in
order to accomplish its entire removal it was necessary
to establish a <hi rend="italics">new</hi> covenant and <hi rend="italics">new</hi> laws, which was
ultimately done, but for four years we were the true
defenders of the principles of the Constitution as it
was, and if the States of the South had been guided by
the counsels of that noble old Virginian, Henry A.
Wise, and instead of secession had held on to the old
flag, the equal rights of all the States, in the territories
and elsewhere, would have been maintained, and the
other fellows who equipped and sent forth John Brown
on his mission of destruction would have been the
rebels in the “irrepressible conflict.”</p>
          <p>But the hand of the God of Israel was in it, and he led us
by a way that we knew not, through the flood and the fire,
to the positive and emphatic removal of the disturbing
elements which did so torment and distract us, and made
the American Union of to-day  -  what it never was and
never could be under the original confederation  -  <hi rend="italics">a
nation!</hi>
</p>
          <pb id="robs82" n="82"/>
          <p>And now I know you will say I am wandering from
my story, but before I return to “Stonewall,” I will tell
you of the famous “Louisiana Tigers,” whose gallant
commander, Major Wheat, was killed on the 27th of
June in the hottest of the fight at Cold Harbor. Nearly
every account of the war which I have read by
Northern writers gives great prominence in every
battle to the “Tigers,” and I am of the opinion that
every soldier in the Union Army actually thought he
fought the “Tigers.” I cannot estimate the number they
must originally have mustered, according to the amount
of fighting they are represented by the boys in blue to
have done, but there was certainly more than a million
of them, or they wouldn't “go around.” It is something
like the Yankee boys at Gettysburg, where every
mother's son of them fought and slew the men of
“Pickett's Division,” and also a little like the “Gray
Jackets” who are fond of detailing desperate combats
with the “Pennsylvania Bucktails.” Nearly every
regiment in Lee's army has, on one or more occasions,
“locked horns” with the “Bucktails.” It is unquestionably
a compliment to the “Tigers,” to “Pickett's Division,”
and to the “Bucktails,” to be selected as special
antagonists by men who were hunting “foemen worthy
of the steel,” but it is a fact that “Pickett's Division” at
Gettysburg did not number 5,000, and on
<pb id="robs83" n="83"/>
the authority of General “Dick” Taylor, who was their
brigade commander as long as they had an
organization, I will now tell who and what the “Tigers”
were:</p>
          <p>Before the first battle of Manassas there were some
three companies from Louisiana unattached to
regiments that were thrown together as a battalion. The
strongest of the three, and giving character to all, was
called the “Tigers,” and was recruited on the levees and
in the alleys of New Orleans, and might have come out
of “Alsatia,” where they would have been most worthy
subjects of “Duke Hildebrod.” This company was
raised and commanded by Wheat himself in the
beginning, but on the formation of the battalion and his
promotion to Major it was under Captain White, a man
of many <hi rend="italics">aliases</hi> and unsavory character, and so
villainous was the reputation of this battalion that no
brigadier desired the honor of commanding it, but by
hard discipline and some executions by sentence by
court-marshal, General “Dick” got them in some sort of
subjection, but he says they always would plunder in
spite of his orders, unless he was with them in person,
at every battle. His account of them the 24th of May,
1862, when with Jackson at Front Royal, reads like this:</p>
          <p>“In the morning Jackson led the way; my brigade, a
small body of cavalry, and a section of the
<pb id="robs84" n="84"/>
Rock-bridge battery formed the column. Major Wheat,
with his battalion of “Tigers,” was directed to keep
close to the guns. Sturdy marchers, they trotted along
with the cavalry and artillery at Jackson's heels, and
after several hours were some distance in advance of
the brigade, with which I remained. A volley in front
stirred us up to a “double,” and we speedily came upon
a moving spectacle. Jackson had struck the Valley
pike at Middletown, along with a large body of Federal
cavalry, with many wagons, and hastening North. He
had attacked at once with his handful of men, and
overwhelming resistance, had captured prisoners and
wagons. The gentle ‘Tigers’ were looting quite merrily,
diving in and out of wagons with the activity of rabbits
in a warren; but this occupation was abandoned on my
approach, and in a moment they were in line, looking
as solemn and virtuous as deacons at a funeral.”</p>
          <p>The redoubtable Major Bob Wheat was always a
character in war, if there <hi rend="italics">was</hi> any war anywhere. The
son of an Episcopalian clergyman, he ran off from
school and followed General Zachary Taylor through
the <sic>the</sic> battles of Palo Alto, Resaca de la Palma, and
Monteray, until he was badly wounded. After the
Mexican war he went with Lopez to Cuba, where he
was wounded in a desperate fight with the Spanish
troops and captured, but his guardian 
<pb id="robs85" n="85"/>
angel saved him, somehow, from the garrote,
which crushed the necks of all his comrades in this
reckless enterprise, and he escaped to follow General
Walker, the “gray-eyed man of destiny,” in his
fillibuster expedition to Nicaragua, where the
incapacity of the South American patriots so
disgusted him that he left them to their vacillations,
and crossed the Atlantic, he joined Garibaldi, in Italy,
in whose army of ragamuffins he did noble service in
the cause of liberty; but his keen scent of war brought
him home to America, early in 1861, in time to catch a
bullet at first Manassas. At Harrisonburg, Va., on the
5th of June, 1862, where General Ashby was killed; and
one of the last dashes he made, with his famous
cavelry, was to capture Colonel Sir Percy Wyndham,
of Fremont's cavalry; Colonel Wyndham was brought
to the rear a prisoner. No one knew him, but the
troops jeered at him, some as the big “<hi rend="italics">Yankee</hi>
Colonel,” and the Colonel, being an Englishman, hated
the name of <hi rend="italics">Yankee</hi> worse than anything else, which
caused a fearful scowl to settle on his features. As
soon as Wheat laid eyes on him, he sprang from his
horse with a glad cry of, “Why, Percy! old boy!
where did you come from?” at the same time
throwing his arms around the Colonel's neck; and
Wyndham, with a responsive thrill, exclaimed, as he
returned the embrace of his old-time mess-mate in
<pb id="robs86" n="86"/>
the Garabaldi wars: “Why, Bob! God bless you; <hi rend="italics">is</hi> this
you?” Nobody applied the insulting epithet of <hi rend="italics">Yankee</hi>
to Colonel Wyndham again, while Major Wheat was
about.</p>
          <p>The gallant Bob Wheat met his death as before
stated, in the battle of Cold Harbour, just at sunset, and
the last words from his lips were, “boys, we've won
the fight, bury me on the field!”</p>
          <p>With Major Wheat gone no one could hold his men
together, and the Louisiana Tigers, in <hi rend="italics">fact</hi>, ceased to
exist, but the Northern soldiers in <hi rend="italics">fancy</hi>, continued to
fight the Tigers for two years more.</p>
          <p>We will now return to “Stonewall” near Richmond,
his army merged into the A. N. V., waiting for
McClellan to get reinforcements and rest up his Army
of the Potomac for another movement against our
modern Rome, the seven-hilled city on the James.</p>
          <p>About the time we began to tremble for our cause,
in consequence of the fearful disasters about to be
brought upon this devoted army of martyrs by the
<hi rend="italics">Pope</hi>. Not the gentle Roman pontiff, Pius IX, but a
greater than all pontiffs combined, to-wit: Major-General
John Pope, U. S. A., commanding the “Army
of Virginia.” This most wonderful, all conquering, and
invincible commander, had come, as he informed us in
general orders, from the West, where he had never
seen any more of his enemies
<pb id="robs87" n="87"/>
than their backs, and the common idea of his own folks
was that the spirit of Julius Cæsar: <hi rend="italics">
<foreign lang="la">veni, vidi, vici</foreign>
</hi>, and
all, had been again incarcerated in John Pope,
Major-General. It was, moreover, matter of scientific
knowledge to the most eminent astrologers, that the
planets, Jupiter and Mars, were in conjunction at the
precise moment of his birth. The regular astronomer of
his native town had requested that he be christened
“Jupiter Mars” Pope, which would have looked
remarkably well at the foot of a general order issued
from “Headquarters in the saddle,” but his parents
were afraid to risk it. Still, the more orderly name of
“John,” with which he was invested, did not prevent his
development into a mighty man for thunder. No
question as to the location of his “headquarters” could
ever arise, for he tells us himself that they are “in the
saddle;” an eminently proper location for the
headquarters of a commanding general of the army for
the reason, that in the event of small parties of the
enemy's cavalry demonstrating in the neighborhood, the
headquarters can be moved with promptness and
facility.</p>
          <p>The portions of the general orders which caused us
most concern were those bearing directly upon our
own conduct, as Rebels, because he fulminated so
fiercely against stray rebels committing “overt acts of
war” upon any, or sundry sutler wagons,
<pb id="robs88" n="88"/>
horses, or what not; and in case we should in anywise
be thus guilty of depredations, in the limits of his
department, no less than five Southern citizens were to
be held accountable, in each instance in their persons,
goods, and chattels. He was <hi rend="italics">particularly</hi> severe upon
the citizens in the matter of “<sic corr="overt">over</sic> acts of war”
committed by Rebel soldiers, and we grew very uneasy,
lest Jackson, or Ewell, or somebody, might lead us into
some indiscretion with the “Major-General commanding
Army of Virginia,” might construe into an “overt act,”
etc. We had been watching “Stonewall” pretty closely,
and noticing that he did not read the papers of the day,
we feared he might, through ignorance of the General's
general order, do something we should all regret, as
being distasteful to Major-General Pope.</p>
          <p>Another clause of “general orders” also gave us
great uneasiness, and we were glad that Jackson did
<hi rend="italics">not</hi> read the papers, when this came to our knowledge,
but self-respect required, as we thought, some action in
regard to it at our hands. The Major-General, in this
clause, applied some very ugly names to us  -  in
fact  -  he called us “disaster and shame,” and we knew
he had particular reference to Jackson's men, for his
language was, that “disaster and shame,” as aforesaid,
“lurked in the rear;” and it was generally known that
“Stonewall” was a bad man for lurking in the rear; but
we had never
<pb id="robs89" n="89"/>
had such epithets applied to us before, by any of the
commanding generals, not even Banks. We consulted
and took counsel together  -  we generals of the rank
and file -  but we couldn't exactly determine what to do
about it; whether to write to Major-General Pope
asking him to modify his severe language, or to disband
and go to Texas, singly or in pairs, as would be most
expedient. We remained in this state of doubt and
uncertainty, not unmixed with dread until the 19th of
July, 1862, when “Stonewall” roused up, shook his
mane, growled a little, and started towards
Gordonsville. We did all we could to persuade him
against “lurking,” but we went along, for we couldn't
think of permitting him to get out of our sight, for fear
he might do some “overt act,” and about this time we
got some more news from General Pope which
rendered it doubly important for us to keep an eye
pretty closely on Jackson. The “Major-General
commanding,” had been before the congressional
committe on the conduct of the war, and had there
declared that, “with such an army as McClellan had in
March, 1862, he would engage to sweep the country
from Washington to New Orleans,” and we estimated
that if the United States Government should give him
such a one we would hardly be safe in Texas.</p>
          <p>When we reached Gordonsville it became necessary
<pb id="robs90" n="90"/>
to learn positively the whereabouts of the “Army of
Virginia,” and it was not very long until we had it
located. We found it particularly active in Madison and
Orange counties, engaged in heavy forays on citizens
and their property of every description, and when
Major-General Pope had swept the country to the
Rapidan the most noticeable result of his victorious
march was the complete stamping out, in the mids of
the inhabitants of the conquered territory, of the heresy
of secession. One of his staff officers reports stopping
at a house in Culpeper where the family was just
sitting down to dinner, and in fifteen minutes the
soldiers had not only swallowed the dinner but had
swept up and carried away everything portable or
eatable, live-stock and all, indoors and out, and a little
son of the proprietor said to his staff officer, “Pap says
he wouldn't vote the secession ticket again if he had
the chance,” which, the officer said, was extremely
gratifying to him.</p>
          <p>The reconversion of the territory from treasonable
proclivities to loyality was, of course, equal in extent to
the spread of the wings of his army  -  which was from
the Blue Ridge to the junction of the rivers Rapidan
and Rappahannock, and it was only necessary to
continue the movement to the Gulf of Mexico in order
to <sic corr="completely">competely</sic> restore the
love of the Union in the hearts
of all the people. A Northern
<pb id="robs91" n="91"/>
correspondent who accompanied the army wrote: “The land
was green when they came, but they left a desert
behind them;” and General Pope, to more fully
establish loyality in his department, issued what he
called his expatation order, which required that “all
male citizens disloyal to the United States should be
immediately arrested, the oath of allegiance proffered
them, and if they took it <hi rend="italics">and furnished sufficient
security for its observance</hi>, they should be released.
If they declined taking it they should be sent beyond
the extreme Federal pickets, and found again within his
lines should be treated as spies and shot.” Another
order had a very salutary effect on the home folks,
which was, that “the prominent citizens of the district
should be arrested and detained as hostages for the
good behavior of the inhabitants, and made to suffer in
their persons for the acts of partisans and
bushwhackers.” If any of the Federal troops were
“bushwhacked,” one of the hostages should suffer
death.</p>
          <p>All this and much more us generals had on our minds
to distract us, and it made us anxious to <sic corr="prevent">prevant</sic>
General Jackson from committing depredations on the
army lines of General Pope, so that we lost a good deal
of sleep watching him. We kept all such information
from him as much as possible, knowing, from the
nature of the man, that if he
<pb id="robs92" n="92"/>
should get full accounts of Pope's proceedings it would
excite him, and perhaps cause him to commit some
“overt act.” However, some indiscreet person gave him
a newspaper one day, and then the “fat was in the fire,”
and we gave up the idea of being generals any more
until <hi rend="italics">somebody</hi> should get “wore out.”</p>
          <p>Jackson crossed the Rapidan at Barnett's Ford on the
8th of August, and marched us steadily forward
towards Culpeper Courthouse, right into the jaws of
destruction “us boys” thought<sic corr=".">,</sic> The next day we reached
Cedar Run, eight miles from the Courthouse, and right
here we came square up against the centre of
Major-General Pope's army. How I wish he had been named
“Jupiter Mars” for plain “John” seems too plain and
simple and naked to clothe the Julius Cæsar of North
America. Anyhow, “Stonewall” drove his wedges right
into the centre of the “Army of Virginia,” which here
consisted of 32,000 men, according to official reports of
Major-General J. Pope, but we soon learned from
prisoners that General Banks was in command here,
and the horizon began to clear, for we knew if that was
the case that we wouldn't go to Texas, yet awhile. We
didn't believe General Banks could drive Jackson out of
Culpeper if Pope would give him the job.</p>
          <p>We got to business on the 9th, about the middle
<pb id="robs93" n="93"/>
of the afternoon, and after considerable skirmishing
and cannon-firing General Early moved his brigade
along the Culpeper road, drove the enemy's cavalry
before him, and pushed his line to the crest of a hill, but
the Federal batteries opened such a furious cannoned
upon the hill that he withdrew his troops below the
crest and hurried up his own batteries to reply. A large
body of cavalry appeared on our left flank, and we
fixed ourselves to attend to them, but Captains Brown
and Dement opened on them with their batteries which
settled that matter pretty soon. While all this was going
on, General Winder, with Jackson's old division, moved
upon our left, and a column of Federals made a drive
straight at our batteries, but General Early put his
whole line forward, and the battle was joined along our
entire front, and raged furiously till night.</p>
          <p>Jackson's army was composed of his own division,
commanded by Winder; Ewell's division, and part of
A. P. Hill's. General Thomas' brigade, of Hill's came
to General Early's support just when he needed help;
and we succeeded in driving them to the woods,
where they held on for awhile, but finally a general
charge swept them through the woods and away
towards the Court-house. They made a last attempt to
drive us back with cavalry, but Taliaferro and Branch
ruined them, and their dashing charge ended in a rout,
leaving General Prince,
<pb id="robs94" n="94"/>
their commander, a prisoner. We had 223 killed and
1,060 wounded. I don't know the enemy's loss, but we got
over 400 prisoners, 5,300 small arms, one Napoleon
gun and caisson and the caissons of two other guns.
We had given Major General J. Pope's army a trial
and had come out “on top.” Our infantry had beaten
his fairly in the open field, giving them a choice of
position, and our artillery had outshot his.</p>
          <p>It is not hard for one who is engaged in battle to
comprehend a written description of it, but these
descriptions are not often written by men who were
actually engaged in the line of battle.</p>
          <p>The soldier sees very little of the general
engagement, and when he attempts to describe the
field he does so on other people's information, not
his own knowledge. A battlefield, where only five or
ten thousand troops are engaged, is a much more
extensive area than most people suppose, and when
large bodies of soldiers  -  say fifty thousand on a
side  -  are in it, a man on a good horse could hardly
gallop from point to point, over the whole field, during
the continuance of the battle. The field is large, but
each soldier only knows what is being done in his own
vicinity, generally, the space occupied by his own
company, and sometimes not that much.</p>
          <p>When we are preparing for the battle you will
notice that the columns, which have been moving
<pb id="robs95" n="95"/>
steadily forward all day halt, and seem to hesitate, like
a swarm of bees, whether to light or not; whether to go
forward or back. The men don't ask, “what's the
matter,” for they know, most of them, exactly what it
is, and the old infantry soldier don't need any body to
tell him when he is on the edge of a battle. They notice
that the Colonels are talking with the Generals, and
they see officers and couriers galloping, some towards
the front and others to the rear. The infantry opened
their columns, and the cavalry, with jingling spurs and
clanking sabres, trot forward. The ammunition wagons
roll heavily up, and the ambulances move along; the
sergeants chatting cheerfully with each other, and the
men are all jokey and chatty. There is a good deal of
handling of field glasses by the general officers, and
the Colonels and Captains show a good deal of cool,
calm anxiety to have their men well in hand. No
hurrying or confusion about it, not so much as if they
were going out on a review, but it seems to do them
good to see the boys cheerful and in good heart. After
awhile somebody rides up to the quiet looking Colonel,
on the gray horse, and says a few words, and he turns
around to the regiment, with a short, prompt manner,
and says quietly, but clearly and sharp: “Attention 21st,”
or whatever the number may be  -  “forward!” and
away goes the leading regiment to the front. You
<pb id="robs96" n="96"/>
can see them marching quick and strong in column, for
a bit, and then you hear the Colonel say, “front into line,
march!” then on they go, up the hill to the fence, which
the men jump over, and you hear the guns  -  pop! pop!
bang! bang! the familiar “Rebel yell” breaks <sic corr="forth">fourth</sic>,
and the firing grows in volume  -  quick, spiteful,
rattling. You, perhaps, think this is a battle, and I
imagine it would pass for one in Revolutionary times,
but it is only skirmishers advancing now, and
they trot along cheerfully, about ten or fifteen feet
apart, firing and loading rapidly, calling funny remarks
to each other, laughing, shouting and cheering  -  but
advancing. Some of them drop out of the line and limp
to the rear, some lay flat on the ground, dead or too
badly hurt to travel, but the line moves forward all the
same and the vacant places are filled by the men
moving over to the right or left, and presently they
reach the timber, where every man posts himself
behind a tree, stump, rock, anything that offers shelter;
and, in the most deliberate manner keep up the firing,
which now changes its rattling tone to something like a
roar, but it is not a battle yet, for our boys have only
driven the enemy's skirmishers back on their line of
battle, and developed their position; and now a battery
gallops up and hurries into position, unlimbers the heavy
trails and the Captain commands: “Commence firing.”
The
<pb id="robs97" n="97"/>
artillerymen step in briskly and cheerfully, and load the
pieces, then step aside; a blaze of fire flies from the
muzzle of the first gun, in a puff of white smoke, and
away goes a howling shell, over the heads of the
skirmish line, to explode in the enemy's line, and you
hear that yell again. Gun after gun blazes forth its
shrieking shell with all the rapidity possible, sometimes
so fast as to fire three rounds a minute from each gun,
and all the while that skirmish line is “pop! pop! bang!
banging away?” Now comes another movement, as the
brigade forms up in line; a thousand, yes, two thousand
ramrods rattle down into the barrels of as many
muskets! then the long drawn command, “forward!”
rings down the line, and the skirmishers are relieved,
but not a minute too soon, for they have been
compelled to lie down flat on the ground, with their
heads against the trees in front, unable either to
advance or retire without meeting certain death, but
when their brigade comes up, they yell with joy, pride,
excitement, jump to their feet and charge right on with
the “old brigade;” for they are proud of <hi rend="italics">their</hi> “old
brigade.” It may be known among the line as Early's or
Taylor's, or Winder's, or maybe the <corr>“</corr>‘Stonewall’ bridge,”
but those men know it as “<hi rend="italics">our</hi> brigade,” and now you
are safe in reporting that the battle has begun.</p>
          <p>The sharply sparkling, rattling roar of the rifles
<pb id="robs98" n="98"/>
of the skirmishers is swallowed up in the rolling,
booming thunder of the musketry, which, in tone like a
mighty, rushing wind, rises, swells, lulls, and roars
again along the line, and now it is that the spectator,
who is viewing the first battle, thinks, as the smoke-cloud
rolls up above the trees and he hears the horrible
clashing volleys blending together, that no man can be
left alive. It is a busy time, and the couriers, aides and
staff-officers gallop and dash from place to place on
foaming steeds, bearing orders along the hotly-contested
line. Brigades and divisions wheel into
position and press forward, and blazing batteries
crown every hill. The ammunition wagons get up,
somehow, in reach of the troops, and the light riding,
empty ambulances spin along, right up to the line of
fighting, soon to return, solemnly moving to the
rear with their ghastly loads of mangled
soldiers, while the shells and bullets fly about
in an indiscriminate, aimless sort of way, anywhere at
all, and are liable to hit anybody at all. Now the
enemy's batteries are in position and warmed to their
work, and the “sulphurous canopy” darkens all the field
and forest for miles, the musket-balls rap and whack
on the guns and cannon wheels, while occasionally a
caisson of artillery amunition is blown up by an
exploding shell, and the burned and mangled bodies of
the men near it whirl up into the air. The battle is in
<pb id="robs99" n="99"/>
full blast now, and the time has come to test the metal
and discipline of the troops, but if “Stonewall” is on the
field we will soon hear a roll of musketry or crashing
battery roar away off on the flank or rear of the sturdy
fighting blue line in our front, and soon we see
their battries limber up hastily and gallop back; for the
guns must be saved, at all risk; then their infantry line
slowly gives ground, and our cannoneers break out in a
wild cheer, which is taken up by the infantry, and the
shout of victory rings gloriously, up through the smoky
pall, from the thousands of throats that we thought
awhile ago were all still in death. And here come the
cavalry, in columns and squadrons, galloping after the
retiring enemy, charging into their cavalry and light
batteries, which are covering the retreat. This keeps up
for long distances, generally, and we see streams of
wounded men, and parties of dejected looking
prisoners coming back, with perhaps a captured
cannon, and wagons now and then, for defeat and rout
means irretrievable ruin to the army that suffers it, if
our “Stonewall the great” commands the army that
wins.</p>
          <p>But this last part is about all the private soldier sees
of a battle. However, after it is over, each man tells
his neighbor what he saw, and by tomorrow each one
of us imagines he saw the whole battle, for it is a rare
school for the cultivation of imagination;
<pb id="robs100" n="100"/>
and we tell the whole story  -  thus picked up and
patched together  -  until <hi rend="italics">some</hi> of <hi rend="italics">us</hi>, after a while,
<hi rend="italics">swear</hi> to being an eye witness to every scene and
movement of that battle; nor can you blame us, for it is
not every one that can go through a four-year
experience like that and be able to tell about it
afterwards, and the stirring times of that war made a
deep impression on our minds, but we old veterans are
growing old, our ranks are thinned and thinning, and
soon we'll cross over to camp with the majority. To
this new man, who has just got a glimpse of his first
battle, one of the strangest things is the cheerfulness of
the soldiers under fire, and their general jollity amid the
hailstorm of battle. He wonders how that artilleryman,
at Gettysburg, while doing his duty at his gun in the
battery, could sing, as he did  -</p>
          <lg type="verse" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">“Backward, turn backward, oh, time in thy flight!</l>
            <l part="N">Make me a child again, <hi rend="italics">just for this fight!</hi>”</l>
          </lg>
          <p>or his comrade, near, respond  -  “Yes, and a gal child
at that.”</p>
          <p>We have an anecdote, well vouched for, of a gallant
sergeant, in a Union regiment, in one of the Wilderness
battles. A Rebel battery was spreading havoc over the
field and the General ordered the Colonel to take it.
The Colonel turned to his regment and exclaimed, “Men,
the General says he wants that battery. Can't we take it for him?”
<pb id="robs101" n="101"/>
This Sergeant stuttered, or stammered, some folks call
it: Said he, “S-s-say  -  Colonel  -  l-l-let's t-t-take up a
c-c-collection and b-b-buy the b-bl-blamed thing. I'll th-throw
in my sh-share,” but we are told that the
regiment did take the battery, and the sergeant did his
duty no less manfully and bravely, for his joke.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
          <p>Now I must go back to my hero, “Stonewall the
Great,” for he is about to make another “lurking”
expedition to the “rear” of Major-General John Pope,
inasmuch as General Lee has moved the whole army
up from Richmond and “us generals” have determined
to do what we can for the “Army of Virginia” before
the “Army of the Potomac” can reach it, for we don't
care to yoke up to General McClellan right away. He
gave us all we wanted from him in that last interview
at Malvern Hill, and we had much rather fight the
great annihilator, Major-General Pope, now that we
have got his measure, than bother with “Little Mac.”
We had been loafing around in Orange county since
Cedar Run until July 1st, when we moved up to Mt.
Pisgah church. General Jackson now had under his
command  -  1st, Ewell's division, composed of the
brigades of Lawton, Early, Trimble
<pb id="robs102" n="102"/>
and Hayes, with the batteries of Brown, Dement,
Lattimer, Balthus and D'Aquin; 2d, A. P. Hill's division,
of the brigades of Branch, Gregg, Field, Pender, Archer
and Thomas, and the batteries of Braxton, Latham,
Crenshaw, McIntosh, Davidson and Pegram; 3d,
Jackson's old division, under Brigadier-General W. B.
Taliaferro, with the brigades of Winder (Colonel
Baylor); Campbell (Major Seddon); Taliaferro (Colonel
A. G. Taliaferro); and Starke, with the batteries of
Brockenborough, Wooding, Poague, Caskie, Carpenter
and Raines. The cavalry of General Stuart was
everywhere, front, flank and rear, and were continually
doing some “overt act of war” to the annoyance and
displeasure of Major-General Pope, and right in his
department too, where he found himself utterly unable
to control the <sic corr="operations">opperations</sic> of these rough-riders by
arresting and holding citizens responsible for
depredations by soldiers against his troops and trains.</p>
          <p>Some Federal cavalry played a splended joke on
Stuart himself by surprising him at Vidersville while he
was at breakfast, and causing him to mount his horse
in haste and gallop off bare-headed, while they retired
in triumph, carrying off his hat, cloak and haversack.
It was the first time Stuart was ever “caught napping,”
and “his wreath had lost a rose,” but he made it
bloom again a few days after by a
<pb id="robs103" n="103"/>
gallant foray in Pope's rear at Catlett's Station, where
he captured his headquarter wagons with the “great
annihilator's” money-chest, dispatch book, and hat with
its ostrich plume, and Stuart was himself again.</p>
          <p>I wish I could drop the generalities of history and
move along as I should with the “shameless” disaster
hunting gray jackets of “Stonewall,” but I must keep
up. We moved on the 20th of August from Mt. Pisgah,
by way of Somerville Ford, to Stevensburg, in
Culpeper, and now we were almost in Major-General
Pope's trap, for he had said “publicly” that 
“he did not intend to take any step backward,” 
and if he shouldn't, and Jackson kept on
advancing, it was very clear that we would have to join
Pope or break up before belong. His columns were very
numerous, and his batteries crowned every hill on the
other side of the Rappahannock, but in spite of it all we
moved up to Beverly's Ford on the 21st, and all day long
the booming cannon and bursting shells kept up the
concert. On the 22d we moved up the river, over the
Hazel to Freeman's Ford, but this was strongly guarded
too, so we went on to Warrenton Springs. General
Jackson had evidently been reading another newspaper,
and it looked to us now as if he was bent on finding out if
Pope had any rear. General Early crossed the river here
with his brigade, and, by the way, it is
<pb id="robs104" n="104"/>
a noticeable fact that both Lee and Jackson were prompt
to select our Brigadier “Old Jubilee,” as his men called him,
for delicate and dangerous operations; but the rains
descended and the floods came, and it looked mighty
dark for Early, with only one brigade, in the midst of the
whole army of the “Great Annihilator,” and cut off from all
help by the foaming, bankful Rappahannock, but he held
out till Jackkson got a bridge built, and came out of the lion's
den, like Daniel of old, with never a scratch on him. General
Lee, by aid of the papers and order-book of Pope, brought
in by Stuart when he went after his hat, now planned a
magnificent scheme for flanking towards the left and
getting in the enemy's rear, and of course “Stonewall”
must lead the movement, and away we went on Monday,
25th of August, through Amissville, over the river at Hinson's
Ford, by Orleans, in Fauquier, to Salem, on the M. G. R. R.</p>
          <p>I have before alluded to the reprehensible practice
of deception by this “blue light” Presbyterian elder, in his
military operations, but on this occasion he out-did himself,
and grossly deceived John Pope  -  Major-General, etc.  -  as
to his real purpose. He gave out, incidentally, that he was
moving to the Valley; and, to fix this impression in the mind
of the great commander of the “Army of Virginia,” who was
“careless of lines of retreat,” and who
<pb id="robs105" n="105"/>
“took no step backwards,” he sent out couriers with curiously
written dispatches to the effect that his movement was a
Valley one, and actually caused these couriers to take routes
by which he knew <hi rend="italics">some</hi> of them would be captured, and their
papers fall into the hands of General Pope, which actually
occurred, and by such false pretenses relieved that great
General's mind of any further trouble in regard to the Rebel
column, which his signal posts reported to be moving towards
Blue Ridge. It was a <hi rend="italics">moving</hi> column, truly, and taking “nigh cuts,”
across lots, we got to Salem at midnight, without a straggler,
and still marching. On the 26th we walked through Thoroughfare
Gap and “lurked,” with 
“disaster and shame,” right down on
Manassas Junction, leaving Major-General Pope still operating
on the Rappahannock, under the deluded idea that Jackson
had run off to the Valley, and he was about to dispose of what
Rebels were left in his front, take Richmond, and sweep right
on to New Orleans.</p>
          <lg type="verse" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">“At midnight in his guarded tent,</l>
            <l part="N">The Turk was dreaming of the hour,” etc.</l>
          </lg>
          <p>But  - </p>
          <lg type="verse" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
            <l part="N">“At midnight in the forest shades,</l>
            <l part="N">Bozzaris ranged his Sulite band.”</l>
          </lg>
          <p>History repeats itself, and we have only to wait to see that  -  “the
thing which is, is that which hath been, and there is no new thing
under the sun.”</p>
          <pb id="robs106" n="106"/>
          <p>We had marched fast and long, and had also <hi rend="italics">fasted</hi>
long, but when the vast magazines of supplies,
captured right between Pope and Washington City,
were opened to us, the boys hardly knew what to lay
hands on first in the way of eatables. No pen can
describe the rollicking antics of Jackson's men, as they
revelled among the good things spread in prodigal
profusion around them  -  in army goods and sutler
stores. It was more than funny to see the ragged,
rough, dirty fellows, who had been half living on roasted
corn and green apples, for days, now drinking Rhine
wine, eating lobster salad, potted tongue, cream biscuit,
pound cake, canned fruits, and the like; and filling
pockets and haversacks with ground coffee, tooth-brushes,
condensed milk, silk handkerchiefs. The
captures at Manassas are thus summed up, in General
Jackson's report: “Eight pieces artillery, seventy-two
horses and equipments, three hundred prisoners, two
hundred negroes, two hundred new tents, one hundred
and seventy-five extra horses, ten locomotives, two
railroad trains loaded with stores worth several millions
of dollars, 50,000 pounds bacon, 1,000 barrels of beef,
20,000 barrels pork, several thousand barrels of flour,
and a very large quantity of sutler's stores.” The folks
at Washington made an effort to save it, by sending
General Taylor, with his brigade of New Jersey troops,
by rail, to drive us away; but
<pb id="robs107" n="107"/>
the “Old Blue Hen's Chickens” were not strong
enough to whip the “Stonewall Gray Jackets” out of
that place, for we got together, with our guns, killed
the General and tore the brigade to atoms. Jackson
always said his men would fight for something to eat.</p>
          <p>This was the morning of the 27th, and we pretty
soon learned that General Pope had been notified that
his army supplies, “in his rear,” were in danger, for his
whole army came trooping back in clouds, and we had
to pack up and move out. So we filled up all we could
carry of the good things and fired the balance. It was
hard on us to see so much good eatables burned up,
but it made a splendid blaze, and we knew Pope's
army couldn't fight without rations. Of course all
manner of rumors and reports were flying around
among the soldiers, and we believed all we heard  -  a
little  -  but most of them were spoken of “as reports
by <hi rend="italics">grapevine</hi> telegraph,” an expression denoting lack
of faith in their reliability; and, speaking of the
telegraph reminds me of the prompt action taken by a
keen cavalryman of, I think Colonel Munford's
regiments, at Manassas. He had never seen a
telegraph instrument before, and came upon one here
which was ticking away in fine business style, and, to
his excited imagination, it was some “infernal machine”
arranged to explode the magazine or something,
<pb id="robs108" n="108"/>
and perhaps kill the whole army. Taking the matter
and its consequence in at a glance, he gallantly
resolved to sacrifice himself to save his comrades,
and springing upon it, with the suddenness of a
tiger, he kicked the mysterious ticker to atoms with his
big boots, and rushing out of the office,
exclaimed  -  “Boys! they was a tryin' to blow us up,
but I seen their triggers a workin' and busted 'em.”</p>
          <p>About this time Pope began to use his “grapevine
telegraph” quite freely, and when General Ewell used
the 6th and 8th Louisiana regiment and the 60th
Georgia, at close range, to hold the two leading
brigades of the Federal army in check, until the stuff at
Manassas was all destroyed  -  and held his ground so
obstinately, by aid of the cavalry regiments of Colonels
Munford and Rosser, (2d and 5th Virginia), that Pope
got his army in line for a general engagement, when
Ewell withdrew his little force, leaving General Early,
with his brigade and the cavalry, to protect his rear,
and retired to Manassas; General Pope immediately
telegraphed to Washington that he “had routed <sic corr="and">aud</sic> cut
off Jackson and his whole force;” which was fully
believed all over the North, and not long afterwards he
telegraphed to Baltimore to “make room for Jackson
and 16,000 prisoners,” which he “had bagged,” as he
called it.</p>
          <p>The Federal army could not stand the destruction
<pb id="robs109" n="109"/>
of stores at Manassas, and when Fitz. Lee struck out
for Fairfax Courthouse, with his cavalry, preventing
supply trains coming from Washington, Pope was in a
condition to be starved in the open field, something
almost unheard of in military history of superior
armies, and his main apology  -  apart from the Fitz
John Porter “scape-goat” business  -  for his defeat at
Manassas was the want of rations for his men and
forage for his horses.</p>
          <p>It always seemed to the folks who were looking at
the campaign that the “invincible annihilator” of Lee's
army was premature in “discarding lines of retreat and
bases of supplies” so promptly in the beginning of his
operations, because we all thought “Stonewall” was
the man to attend to those little matters for him; and
the shadow of Jackson did rest heavily on Pope's
army when it entered Manassas on the 28th August.</p>
          <p>At this time, while fighting and maneuvering to hold
our own until General Lee could get to us with the
balance of the army, a shell was thrown into our ranks
from the Warrenton road, exploding in Company C, of
the 52d Regiment, which killed and wounded eighteen
men, seven of them being killed on the spot. Among
the wounded by this fatal shell was Col. James H.
Skinner, of Staunton, Va., commanding the regiment.
Colonel Skinner was afterwards wounded at Gettysburg by a shell
<pb id="robs110" n="110"/>
which exploded on the ground in front of him, and
blinded for several months by the dirt and gravel
thrown into his eyes. In the battle of Spottsylvania
Courthouse, Colonel Skinner was again wounded by a
musket ball, which passed through both his eyes.</p>
          <p>The 28th was the day Pope concentrated, as well as
he knew how to do it, his whole army of 50,000 men on
Jackson's 22,000, but the modern Cæsar was no match
in generalship for our “Stonewall,” who was now
engaged in the “overt act of war” right between Pope
and his capital city, and only a day's march from it. But
I shall not attempt any description of the three days'
battle of Manassas No. 2, in which the shallow,
braggart, persecutor of Virginia women and children  -
John Pope  -  was whipped, and, so far as fame and
character are concerned, personally annihilated  -  “the
deserter desolate.” Nor have I any apology for
expressing so much of an opinion of him, which, so far
as my knowledge goes, is shared by all decent people
North and South, by his own soldiers as well as ours;
and, moreover, the great marauder of hen-roosts,
milk-houses and wardrobes is <hi rend="italics">still living.</hi>
</p>
          <p>We used to notice one curious difference between
the Northern and Southern generals during the war.
Their commanding generals of armies and army corps
on battle-days kept at their headquarters,
<pb id="robs111" n="111"/>
long distance from the field, and using their well-appointed
staff officers and couriers
exclusively in <sic corr="communicating">commnnicating</sic> their orders to the troops,
while the Southern generals were up among their men,
directing and leading their movements, and
encouraging them at the critical points.</p>
          <p>I am sure that if the Northern soldiers had been thus
led and handled, so they could have had the same
confidence in their generals the Southern men had,
they would have ended the war in less than four years.
Everything else being equal, one man is as good as
another, but one soldier, having confidence in his
commander, is worth ten half-hearted fellows, who
have little faith in their general and only see him at
review. We did not have the same discipline -  in
regard to our generals anyhow  -  that the Northern
army had, and ours did not make the same display of
“fuss and feathers” with brilliant staff officers, nor
require the same flourishing of caps and saluting with
arms presented whenever they met us. Ours met
spontaneous salutes of cheers right from the hearts of
their admiring soldiers, and I have seen Jackson, Ewell
and others do some very hard riding, bareheaded, along
the columns to escape the noisy homage of their
devoted followers.</p>
          <p>Any school boy would have known that Pope's
proper course was to crush Jackson's corps out of
<pb id="robs112" n="112"/>
existence, and then turn on Longstreet and perform the
same service for him  -  General Lee's disposition of his
army having put it in the power of the Federal
commander to do this easily; but General Lee knew his
man thoroughly, and trusted fully to his blundering
incompetency to admit Longstreet to march his corps
through Thoroughfare Gap and unite with Jackson at
Manassas, which was done by the 29th. True, General
Pope defends himself by bringing charges of “delay,”
“inefficiency,” and even disloyalty against General
Porter and others; but the rejoinders of these officers,
backed by clouds of witnesses, are fatal to General
Pope's character for generalship and veracity, and the
fact remains perfectly clear that he was out-generaled
and out-fought by “Stonewall the Great.” Gen. Ulysses
S. Grant, in his last days, after he had taken the time to
examine the case against Porter, fully vindicated him
and left Pope's reputation beyond redemption. But the
“boys in blue” made a splendid fight, and attacked our
position in charge after charge, only to be driven back
with slaughter, and when General Early found they had
gotten possession of the railroad cut immediately in his
front, he promptly attacked them, drove them out and
for two hundred yards into the woods. Here occurred a
personal matter which afforded me much pleasure in
after years, though at the time only
<pb id="robs113" n="113"/>
done under the promptings of humanity. As we
pressed across the railroad bank, where lay numbers
of dead and wounded Federals, I inadvertently
stepped on the foot of a wounded man, which brought
a groan of pain, and I asked his pardon for the
accident. After our line halted  -  which was in a short
distance  -  I returned to the poor fellow, gave him
water, and asked if I could do anything for him. He
was very grateful, but thought nothing could be done
then; however, I asked my Captain, Airhart, a
noble-souled christian gentleman, to assist me, and we
moved the man to a more comfortable position under a
tree, where Captain Airhart, who had considerable
knowledge of surgery, dressed his wounds, and I did
what I could to make him comfortable, and, after
exchanging slips of paper with our names written on
them, I rejoined my Company, and in the busy scenes
then and afterwards being enacted, almost forgot the
incident.</p>
          <p>In 1885 I was canvassing for a book, trying to make a
living for a certain “one-legged rebel,” and found
myself in Jonesboro, Tenn. In the course of business I
called on a Mr. Locke, of that town  -  but I will give
the account as it was published in the Jonesboro
<hi rend="italics">Herald and Tribune</hi> of May 15, 1885:</p>
          <p>“Only a few weeks ago it was telegraphed over the
country that Bill Arp, the noted Georgia
<pb id="robs114" n="114"/>
humorist, had received from Pennsylvania an autograph
album that had been taken from his wife's (then
his sweetheart) house more than twenty years ago.
Last week a much more remarkable incident happened
in Jonesboro. On Wednesday, Mr. John S. Robson, of
Virginia, and formerly a member of the 52d Regiment
of that State, in the Confederate service, came here to
canvass for the sale of a book he is publishing, giving
incidents of the camp and march as he saw them.</p>
          <p>“Mr. Robson had but one leg, having contributed the
other to his side of the game, in one of the battles of
1864. In the course of the day he met Mr. J. C. Locke, a
citizen of Jonesboro. As soon as Mr. Locke observed
the missing leg he remarked to Mr. Robson that he
(Locke) had also lost a leg in the war, mentioning the
engagement, the second battle of Bull Run, August 29,
1862. Mr. Locke then began to tell of the kind treatment
he had received that day from a young Rebel named
Robson. ‘Why,’ exclaimed Mr. Robson, ‘I am the
young Rebel that took care of you that day.’ And sure
enough he was. A comparison of incidents established
the fact beyond a doubt. Mr. Locke was a member of
Company E, 100th Pennsylvania (Roundhead)
Regiment. In the second engagement at Bull Run he
was badly wounded in the leg, just as his command
was forced to fall back. While
<pb id="robs115" n="115"/>
stretched upon the field, in the agonies of a wound
that was to cost him his leg, he was approached by a
boyish-looking Rebel, who asked him if he would not
like to be moved to a more comfortable place, at the
same time offering to have his wounds dressed by his
officer, Captain Airhart, who had some knowledge of
surgery. The young Rebel advised Locke that if he
had anything in his knapsack which he cared to
preserve, he had better put it in his blouse pocket. This
he did, presenting his Rebel savior with a razor from a
shaving outfit he carried. When the wounded Federal
was comfortably fixed, the two soldiers parted, each
writing down the other's name. The Rebel was Mr.
John S. Robson.</p>
          <p>“The two men never met or heard of each other
from that day until Wednesday of last week, though
they had often thought of one another. Of course the
meeting was a happy one, for it was the renewal of an
undying friendship, formed in the midst of war's
carnage. No doubt, during the rebellion, there occurred
many incidents similar to the nobility exhibited by the
Virginian to the Pennsylvanian, but it is rare the actors
meet, as our two soldiers did, after so many years
have intervened.”</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="robs116" n="116"/>
        <div2 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>CHAPTER IX.</head>
          <p>I have straggled again, but will join the march once
more. After Manassas we turned our faces towards
the Potomac, and had more hard marching before us,
and scant rations again. The roasted corn and green
apples had not given out yet, but our wagon trains failed
to get up, and we longed for the quantity of good things
that were burned up at Manassas. Our march led us
into Loudoun county, Virginia, and here we fared better
than among the pines and red gullies of Prince William.
At our camp near Leesburg, a good story of McLaws'
men got out. It seems that when General McLaws'
division went into bivouac, hunger had got the better of
their morals, and many of them made a raid on a
cornfield for rations. The owner called on the General
to protect his property, and he ordered guards to
surround the field, arrest every man coming out with
corn, and bring him and his plunder to headquarters. It
was not long until the “pirouters” began to appear,
under guard, in the presence of the irate commander,
and as each one, with his arm load of corn, halted
before him, the General opened on him like this:
“Where did you get that corn?” and the culprit would
begin: “Why, General, I had nothing to eat for three
days, and I didn't know when the wagons would
come”  -  but there the General stopped him with
<pb id="robs117" n="117"/>
the order: “Put it down there on the ground and go join
your command immediately!” This movement, being
many times repeated, caused quite a large pile of corn
to grow up in front of the General's quarters, and in
answer to the savage-toned query  -  “What are you
going to do with that corn?” every one made the same
excuse of “hungry,” “wagons not come up,” etc., and in
each case the order was, “throw it down on that pile
and go join your command <hi rend="italics">immediately</hi>.” Finally, one
“gray jacket,” who had “caught on” to the manner and
form of the proceedings, was brought up and accosted
fiercely, with the question: “What are you going to do
with that corn?” “Why, sir,” said the culprit, briskly, “I'm
going to throw it down on that pile thar, and go and join
my command immejitly, I <hi rend="italics">am!</hi>” The General broke
down, the guards roared, and the cute Reb slid out
“immejitly,” but the quartermaster took charge of the
corn and issued it to the men, who made it last until the
wagons came up with rations.</p>
          <p>On the 5th September we crossed the Potomac at
White's Ford, and stood on Maryland soil, but it was
only a remnant of the “Army of Northern Virginia” that
went over. Thousands of our boys had lagged, worn
out, bare-footed, sick, hungry, they <hi rend="italics">could not</hi> keep up,
and so, from actual necessity, twenty thousand men of
Lee's army <sic corr="stayed">staid</sic> in Virginia
<pb id="robs118" n="118"/>
and crept, as best they could, to the rendezvous
indicated to them by the General for a rallying point  -  
Winchester. We got to Frederick City on the 6th, and
behaved ourselves like good boys, while the good
people of Maryland treated us very kindly; but there
was no doubt about our having struck them at the
wrong time or place. We Rebels didn't have <hi rend="italics">many</hi>
songs peculiarly our own. We had no “Yankee
Doodle,” no “Star Spangled Banner,” no “Hail
Columbia,” no “Tramp, Tramp, The Boys Are
Marching,” no “John Brown's Body Lies a Moldering
in the Clay,” no “Rally Round the Flag, Boys,” like our
blue-backed friends over the way. We had our old
stand-by, “Dixie”  -  good yet  -  and “Bonnie Blue
Flag,” but we had another  -  “Maryland, My
Maryland”  -  which, up to this time, we had sung with a
good deal of hope and vim, for this song asserted
positively that, “She Breathes, She Burns, She'll Come,
She'll Come,” etc., but it didn't take “us generals” of the
ranks very long to see that there was a mistake about it
somewhere. “Some one had blundered,” for <hi rend="italics">she didn't
“come”</hi> worth a cent; and the people of this portion of
Maryland didn't flock to the “Bonnie Blue,” in defence
of Southern rights quite as unanimously as we had been
led to expect  -  according to the song  -  but everything
was grand, and the invasion a pleasure trip, so long as
we
<pb id="robs119" n="119"/>
<hi rend="italics">knew</hi> Major-General Pope commanded the “boys in
blue.”</p>
          <p>However, we soon learned that “Little Mac” was
again at the head of the army, and then the idea
occurred to “us generals” that our Maryland business
had better be attended to promptly. We were not much
afraid of them, but they might intimidate the Maryland
folks, and prevent them, to some extent, from joining
us; and, moreover, while we fully intended to locate
our winter quarters on the Susquehanna, we wished to
enjoy ourselves a little while in this plentiful country,
and get some fat on our bones before breaking up
another army for General McClellan.</p>
          <p>It is not surprising, I think, that the Maryland folks
looked with some doubt and distrust of final success
upon the army of rag-tag-and-bobtail which General
Lee marched into their midst. These <hi rend="italics">might</hi> be the
gallant soldiers of “Dixie” who had vanquished the
great generals of the North in the Valley of Virginia,
the swamps of the Chickahominy and on the plains of
Manassas, but they didn't <hi rend="italics">look</hi> like it. Those tattered
battle-flags <hi rend="italics">might</hi> be crowned with the glory of
Kernstown, McDowell, Front Royal, Cross Keys, Port
Republic, Seven Pines, Cold Harbor and the Seven
Days, Cedar Run, Bristoe, Manassas Nos. 1 and 2, but
it didn't appear to those Maryland eyes. Nor could
they see the
<pb id="robs120" n="120"/>
scalps of Milroy, Shields, Fremont, Banks, McDowell,
McClellan, and Pope, which swung from the belt of
the A. N. V. The appearance of the army didn't justify
the faith in those deeds, and notwithstanding the gate
was open and the bars down, they wouldn't walk into
the Confederacy yet. And, since Maryland wouldn't
fall into line with her Southern sisters, we determined
to move on to the North, but before doing this, General
Lee thought it advisable to take Harper's Ferry back
into the Confederate States at any rate, and on the
10th September he sent “Stonewall” to attend to that
little matter, and we went along.</p>
          <p>We marched by Boonsboro to Williamsport, reaching
Martinsburg on the 12th, capturing a large
quantity of stores from General White at that place,
and sending him with his folks to join General Miles in
Harper's Ferry, so that we could get them all at once.
On the 13th we reached Bolivar, and waited until
Generals McLaws and Walker  -  the first on the
Maryland and the second on the Loudoun Heights  -
answered our signals. The whole United States force at
the Ferry was estimated at 11,000, with plenty of
cavalry and artillery. On Monday morning, 15th
September, “Stonewall,” having the bird in hand, closed
his fingers on it by opening a concentric fire of artillery
from all commanding points on the Federal forts
<pb id="robs121" n="121"/>
and camps, thus illustrating the opinion expressed by
General Jo Johnston in 1861, of Harper's Ferry as a
strategic point. At that time the Richmond government
desired him to hold the place against Patterson, the
Federal general, but Johnston refused, saying that he
didn't propose to be “penned in the mouth of a tunnel,”
but this is exactly the predicament General Miles
found himself in, and General White had “brought his
ducks to the same market.”</p>
          <p>About an hour of this cannonading brought a white
flag out on the enemy's works, and Harper's Ferry
was ours. General Miles was killed at the moment the
flag was displayed, and General White made the
surrender, which actually included 11,000 prisoners,
13,000 small arms, 73 cannon, 200 wagons, and an
immense amount of camp and garrison furniture. As
soon as General Jackson knew the enemy had given
up the fight, he laid down by a log and went to sleep,
thoroughly worn out with fatigue and loss of sleep.
Gen. A. P. Hill brought General White out to see him,
and waking him up, announced: “General, General
White, of the United States Army, desires to arrange
the terms of surrender.” Jackson made a courteous
movement with his hand, and went back to sleep.
General Hill roused him a second time, and then
“Stonewall” said: “General White, the
<pb id="robs122" n="122"/>
surrender must be unconditional, every indulgence can
be granted afterwards.” That ended it, for he was
asleep again, and Hill walked back with White, but
when his nap was out he was himself again, and
accorded the most generous terms to his captives.</p>
          <p>Our next difficulty was of a much more serious
nature, for McClellan was mustering his army at
Sharpsburg, on the Antietam; and “us generals” freely
expressed our unfeigned regret that Major-General J.
Pope had been <sic corr="superceded">superceeded</sic>.</p>
          <p>We left Harper's Ferry on the 16th, and joined
General Lee the same evening, and our commanders,
on both sides, were busy arranging for the big battle
that was to come off tomorrow, as coolly as farmers
getting ready to plant corn. It was no new business to
us now  -  for the novelty was all worn off  -  but we
did wish for our twenty thousand stragglers in Virginia.
The ball opened at daylight, on the 17th, and as one old
soldier expressed it, “we fought all day before
breakfast, and went on picket all night before supper.”
“Fighting” Jo Hooker was immediately in front of
Jackson's line; anybody that complained of
employment that day was hard to satisfy.</p>
          <p>The thing got very hot among the battery boys, after
the preliminary skirmishing had cleared the floor for
the dance of death; but about sunrise the infantry
advanced in heavy force, their batteries
<pb id="robs123" n="123"/>
moving forward with them and pouring grape and
canister among us at close range. This trouble lasted for
some time, and then Hooker threw his whole column
suddenly against our line, and the firing was heavy and
incessant. The object was to turn General Lee's left,
but for more than two hours Jackson's men sustained
the almost overwhelming assaults of the best troops
McClellan had, and he sent heavy <sic corr="re-enforcements">re-enforecements</sic> to
Hooker, so that this wing of our army might be driven
back and General Lee forced to retreat. More than
half of our men were killed or wounded and then, to
crown the trouble, our ammunition gave out. Our two
division commanders were gone, General Starke killed
and <sic corr="General">Ceneral</sic> Lawton, of our division, wounded; and
every regimental commander in two brigades were
killed or wounded.</p>
          <p>General Jackson himself gave the order to “retire
slowly,” which he did, and the movement seemed to
inspire “Fighting Jo's” men, and they crowded us hotter
than ever, but now General Hood came to our support
with his two brigades, and then the fight begun. Up hill
and down, through the woods and the corn-fields, over
the ploughed land and the clover, the line of fire swept
to and fro as one side or the other gained a temporary
advantage. General Sumner's corps came to “Fighting
Jo's” assistance, and now it seemed that Jackson
would have to give
<pb id="robs124" n="124"/>
way, which, if he did, would decide the battle in favor
of the Federal army; but he still hung on with the
tenacity of a bull-dog, and just at the last moment his
relief came in the brigades of Semmes, Anderson, and
part of Barksdale's and McLaw's divisions. These men
got quickly into line, and pretty soon Jackson rushed
everything forward in a determined charge, which
compelled Hooker's men to surrender all the ground
they had gained from us, and pressing on we forced
them from and beyond the woods for more than a
mile. Of course our whole army had been fighting hard
all day to prevent McClellan's men from crossing at
the various bridges over the Antietam Creek, and more
than two hundred cannon were thundering along that
line all the time, but General McClellan's report shows
that the result of his assaults on Jackson's position was
regarded by him as decisive of the battle; but Jackson
did not stop at regaining and holding his original
position, but moved forward promptly with General
Stuart's cavalry in front, and attempted to turn
McClellan's right. This movement he was compelled to
stop, however, because the enemy's batteries so
completely swept the narrow passage between their
right flank and the Potomac, that he would not expose
his men to their fire.</p>
          <p>More than once during this battle Jackson's men
<pb id="robs125" n="125"/>
had held on until they had fired their last round, and
each time help came to hold the line of battle until we
could fill our cartridge-boxes again, and the battle
ended at dark. We <sic corr="stayed">staid</sic> on the battleground all day, in
line, waiting for General McClellan's boys to come
again, but they didn't do it, and at night, on the 18th,
crossed the river into Virginia again.</p>
          <p>The invasion was ended, and we decided <hi rend="italics">not</hi> to
winter on the Susquehanna, perhaps because it was
too far north for us, and we feared the climate would
not agree with us, but when General McClellan sent a
column over the river at Shepherdstown, on the 20th,
to beat up our quarters and keep us from resting, we
let A. P. Hill and General “Jubilee” Early go see about
it, and when they got there it was very troublesome
for awhile, but our boys drove them into the river,
where a great many were drowned. By their own
account one division lost 3,000 killed and drowned.
Our loss was 261, and we got 300 prisoners.</p>
          <p>General Lee's army lost at Sharpsburg 8,790 men,
killed and wounded; General McClellan's army lost
12,469, killed and wounded. What a commentary on war,
for it was a drawn battle!</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="robs126" n="126"/>
        <div2 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>CHAPTER X.</head>
          <p>I find that I am consuming too much space in my
attempt to keep my story going along, in a consecutive
line, with the history of the operations of Jackson's
men, for it of necessity comes into connection with
what was done by the whole army, and yet, in
following out my original plan, I cannot avoid it. I have
also to deal somewhat with the operations of the
enemy, for the story of a war with no reference to
what the fellows over the fence did, would out-Hamlet
old Hamlet himself, if there was no Hamlet. However,
the campaigns of 1862 were now about ended, and we
spent the gloriously beautiful month of October in our
own beloved Valley of the Shenandoah  -  resting,
getting fat and strong, and that was the happiest time
we ever spent during the four years. We did very little
except camp duty, unless the destruction of all the
railroads in our vicinity might be called duty; and
“Stonewall” seems to 
“go for” a railroad like the fellow
who killed the splendid Anaconda in the museum,
because “it was his rule to kill snakes wherever he
found them,” just because it was his rule to destroy all
railroads he could get at; and we demolished the
Baltimore and Ohio from Hedgesville to Harper's
Ferry; the Winchester and Potomac we swept entirely
off the face of the earth; but it
<pb id="robs127" n="127"/>
never was much of a railroad anyhow, and the
Manassas Gap from Strasburg to Piedmont.</p>
          <p>“Stonewall” was the grand object of all the
sightseers, and much curiosity was evinced by
strangers to get a look at him. In Martinsburg, where
the ladies crowded around him, he said: “Ladies, this is
the first time I was ever surrounded;”  - but they cut
nearly all the buttons off his clothes  -  stripped his coat
entirely  -  and took from him “his mangy old cap,” as
Gen. Dick Taylor called it, giving him, instead, a
handsome, tall, black hat, but he damaged that as
much as he could by turning the brim down all around
wearing it so.</p>
          <p>In November, when we were marching through
Middletown on our way to Fredericksburg, a very old
woman, who had a grandson somewhere in the army,
hailed the General with the question  -  “Are you Mr.
Jackson?” He told her he was, and asked what she
wanted. “I want to see my grandson; I've brought him
some clothes and victuals. His name is George Martin,
and he belongs to your company!” The General asked
her what regiment or brigade he was in, but she
couldn't tell, didn't know the name of his captain even;
only knew he was in Mr. Jackson's company.</p>
          <p>In her distress, she exclaimed: “Why, Mr. Jackson,
you certainly know little George Martin! He's been
with you in all your battles, and they do say he fit as
hard as any of them.”</p>
          <pb id="robs128" n="128"/>
          <p>At this, some of the younger members of the staff
laughed, but the General turned quickly around, with a
blaze in his eye and a thunder cloud on his brow, and
that laugh didn't go around  -  wasn't enough of it; for
Jackson looked as if he wanted to find the party who
laughed, but the party wasn't laughing then.</p>
          <p>Dismounting from his horse, he took the old
woman's hand, whose tears were rolling down her
face, and in the kindest manner, and simplest words,
explained why he didn't know her grandson; but gave
her such simple and complete directions as would
enable her to find him. We didn't think any the less of
“Stonewall,” for such foolishness as this, of course, but
we wanted to hear those staff fellows laugh some
more.</p>
          <p>It is hardly necessary to say that “Stonewall” had us
at Fredericksburg on time, and on the 13th December
he wore a brand new coat, staff buttons, stars, wreath
and all, the same one shown in nearly all the pictures
of Jackson I have ever seen, and his men hardly knew
him at first. I am not going to tell much about the battle
of Fredericksburg. Everybody knows the story of it,
from the bombardment and burning of the town by
General Burnside's orders to his last crossing, on the
night when he took his shivered columns back to
Stafford. No doubt but Burnside was fairly beaten and
badly
<pb id="robs129" n="129"/>
broken up, but I am not going to <sic corr="criticize">criticise</sic> General Lee
for allowing him to get away with his army, for I am
not a general any more, and the newspaper critics, as
well as fireside generals, have about used up that
battle in their discussion of it.</p>
          <p>Just here I will introduce a neat bit of satire from
General Lee himself, which seems to me to tell it all:
In a chat with the Hon. Ben H. Hill, he said: “We
made a great mistake in the beginning of our struggle,
and I fear, in spite of all we can do, it will prove a fatal
mistake.” This was after General Bragg had been
removed from command of the army of Tennessee.
“What mistake is that, General?” asked Mr. Hill. “Why,
sir, in the beginning we appointed all our <hi rend="italics">worst</hi> generals
to command our armies, and all our <hi rend="italics">best</hi> generals to
edit our newspapers. I have done the best I could in
the field, and have not succeeded as I could wish. I
am willing to yield my place to these <hi rend="italics">best</hi> generals, and
I will do my best for the cause editing a newspaper.
Even as poor a soldier as I am can generally discover
mistakes after it is all over, but if I could only induce
these wise gentlemen who see them so clearly
<hi rend="italics">beforehand</hi> to communicate with me in advance,
instead of waiting until the evil has come upon us, to
let me know what <hi rend="italics">they</hi> knew all the time, it would be
far better for the country.”</p>
          <p>After reading the above I have very little disposition
<pb id="robs130" n="130"/> 
to <sic corr="criticize">criticise</sic> the actions of General Lee in permitting
Burnside's army to lay along the river for nearly two
days, and on the night of the 15th of December, under
the terrible peltings of that awful storm, to get his
remnants over the river again, but my memory of the
<sic corr="situation">situartion</sic> at the time checks me, for I can see yet
those splendid batteries of great big, heavy cannon,
planted on the <sic corr="heights">hights</sic> of Stafford, which would have
ground up many a “gray jacket” if our general had put
us across the space from Marye's Hill to the
Rappahannock, and, knowing that General Burnside
was effectually disposed of, I shall let the
matter rest.</p>
          <p>His was one more added to our list of scalps, but I
am told that it was a matter of some uneasiness to
General Lee. During the Revolution, so says Irving,
General Putnam devised a scheme to raid the British
camp in New York town and carry off in a boat no
less a personage as prisoner than Sir Henry Clinton
himself, the Commander-in-Chief of their army. This
he communicated to General
Washington, who sent his aid, Colonel Hamilton, to make an
inspection, and report as to the feasibility of it.
Hamilton performed his task and reported that the
thing could be done pretty easily, but recommended
that the idea be at once given up. Washington, in
surprise, inquired his reason, and Hamilton replied that
we knew Sir Henry well
<pb id="robs131" n="131"/>
and understood him perfectly, but that if he was
removed his government might put a man in his place
we did not understand, and who might cause us a
great deal more trouble than Clinton was doing.
General Washington saw the point, and gave orders to
let Sir Henry alone.</p>
          <p>General Lee said that he didn't like so many changes
of commanders of the Army of the Potomac, for they
might find a man after a while who he could not
understand, and it would cause trouble for <hi rend="italics">us.</hi>
</p>
          <p>The winter of 1862-'3 we spent in winter quarters
below Moss Neck, about ten miles below Fredericksburg,
in barely tolerable comfort; a great deal of the
time picketing on the river near Port Royal, with the
enemies' pickets just opposite ours, and while I know
there was a good deal of deserting going on from their
side, I do not think many of our men deserted. We had
seen the McDowell-Scott campaign, by way of
Manassas, cut short quick  -  and we had heard and
read of the clamor raised by the Northern great
Generals, who edited their newspapers, when
McClellan took the Peninsula route; many of them
insisting on a direct march by the Rappahannock line,
and General Burnside had given them that as much as
they wanted, and, like the others, had come to grief. Of
course, we could not tell what their next move would
be, but we expected
<pb id="robs132" n="132"/>
General Lee to put us right in the road whenever the
movement was made, and we were very confident of
the result; but the inexplicable decree of Divine
Providence, which men so often see, yet cannot
comprehend, was to be wrought to its full completion,
and now we <hi rend="italics">know</hi> and <hi rend="italics">realize</hi> the good that was to
come to us out of the gloom and blood and suffering of
the afflictive school of civil war.</p>
          <p>When spring came and the roads became passable
we began to hear from the boys in blue, on the
other side of the Rappahannock; how they had a new
commander named  -  and rightly too  -  “Fighting Joe
Hooker,” and that their army was in better condition,
better equipped, if possible, and more fully determined
than ever to capture Richmond. Their General had
published to his troops, an order in which he called
their attention to the fact that the “Army of the
Potomac” was the “finest army on this planet,” and that
when he put them on the south bank of the
Rappahannock, General Lee's army “must either
ingloriously fly, or come out from behind their defences
and give us battle on our own ground, where certain
destruction awaits them.” All of which sounded to us a
good deal like the programme laid down by Major-General
J. Pope, of bombastic memory. After the
affair near Harrisonburg, in the Valley, when Col. Sir
Percy
<pb id="robs133" n="133"/>
Wyndham had assumed the special business of
“bagging Ashby,” and in putting the matter into
execution, had, by failure of some part of the
arrangement, been snugly bagged himself; one of
Ashby's staff, who had been a prisoner at Colonel
Wyndham's headquarters, and heard his boasting
declarations of how he was going to do it, made his
escape, rejoined General Ashby and gave him a full
account of Sir Percy's actings and doings at the time
he started on his “bagging expedition.”</p>
          <p>Ashby remarked, “it is bad habit in a commander to
boast of what he is going to do  -  <hi rend="italics">especially when he
doesn't do it.</hi>”</p>
          <p>“Fighting Joe” was no such commander as the great
Julius C. Pope, however, for he made no war on the
women and children of the country, dominated by “the
finest army on the planet.” He said their situation was
bad enough, surrounded as they were by the
unavoidable discomforts <hi rend="italics">naturally</hi>
inhering to a state
of war, without bringing the <hi rend="italics">persecuting</hi>
power of a
military rule to bear upon them; which sentiment
contravens those of General Tecumseh Sherman,
when marching through Georgia, after armed
resistance to his legion had ceased. His men burned all
houses, and destroyed everything they could not carry
away, leaving the helpless people utterly destitute; and,
when appealed to on the plea of common humanity,
he replied: “War is cruelty and you cannot refine it.”</p>
          <pb id="robs134" n="134"/>
          <p>General Hooker commenced to move his army on
Monday, April 27th, 1863, and, of course, <hi rend="italics">we
generals</hi>  knew all about it immediately; and were
wide-awake. We wished much that our “Old
Warhorse,” General Longstreet, might be with us; but
as he was campaigning in Tennessee with his veteran
corps of the centre, we decided to use what we had,
and as the boys said  -  “give them the best we had in
the shop.”</p>
          <p>We had been through the swamps of the
Chickahominy, and ranged in many lands, but
the Spottsylvania Wilderness was the worst for a
battle ground that had been presented to us up to this
time.</p>
          <p>Chancellorsville itself, consisted of a large brick
mansion with ample wings; and in the days of “Auld
Lang Syne” had been used as a tavern for the
entertainment of travelers journeying to and from the
busy town of Fredericksburg, which rated then as one
of the most prominent business centres of the country.
“That was <hi rend="italics">all</hi> the town of Chancellorsville, just one
house and the out-buildings. In front were extensive
fields, but towards the river was the
wilderness  - dense, impassible for miles, and the most
mournful appearing country, especially at night, I had
ever seen; and it seemed a good place to die in, where
the interminable shadows twined and laced with the
mournful, melancholy piping of
<pb id="robs135" n="135"/>
the <sic corr="whippoorwill">whippowill</sic>; and many a poor fellow did breathe out
his life in those gloomy shades, with the weird requiem
of “<sic corr="whippoorwill">whippowill</sic>” filling all the space of sound about him.</p>
          <p>General Lee had to check Hooker's march more by
generalship and strategy than by fighting, for he hadn't
enough men to meet him in the field. We <hi rend="italics">soldiers</hi> of
Dixie never set up any claim that the Army of the
Potomac wouldn't fight. That army <hi rend="italics">would</hi> fight;
always fought, and fought hard. They knew they had
the advantage of numbers, but they also knew that
they were badly handled by their generals; a
knowledge that will take the heart out of a soldier
quicker than want of ammunition; but they drove right
on, and I doubt if any other two commanders than
Robert E. Lee and “Stonewall” Jackson, could have
taken their sixty-seven thousand men and beaten the
one hundred and fifty-nine thousand three hundred
troops of “Fighting” Jo Hooker's Army; and
Major-General Peck of the United States Army, gives that as
their number.</p>
          <p>No finer body of troops could be wished for by a
general than Hooker then commanded, nor could it
possibly be better equipped  -  arms of every
description, of the latest and most approved styles and
kinds: and from the smallest items of clothings, all
through the several departments of commissary,
quartermaster, ordnance, engineer, medical, nothing
<pb id="robs136" n="136"/>
that the most lavish expenditure of money, with open
ports through which to draw from all the world, was
lacking to fit the grand army for this final struggle, as it
was then thought to be; for it was pretty generally
understood that Lee's army was the backbone of the
Confederacy, and that broken, the collapse would be
inevitable.</p>
          <p>Now back to “Stonewall” again, for the last time,
May the 2, 1863. My regiment was not with Jackson
in this fight, it began with that gallant and stubborn old
fighting soldier, General Jubal A. Early who, with his
divisions, was at Fredericksburg, holding Sedgwick's in
check at that point. It seems to have been Hooker's
design to demonstrate on our right with his army of
General Sedgwick, consisting of the 1st, 3d and 6th
corps, “Army of the Potomac,” including General Lee
to suppose that the main movement was to be from that
direction, and after getting Lee to concentrate at
Fredericksburg, he (General Hooker) would move to
Kelly's Ford, twenty-seven miles above, with the corps
of Meade, Howard, Slocum and Couch, cross the
Rapidan at Ely's and Germanna Fords, turn Lee's left
and strike for Gordonsville, thus compelling our army to
retreat rapidly on Richmond with General Sedgwick in
pursuit; and to render his victory more certain, he sent
General Stoneman with ten thousand cavalry on a raid
towards Richmond
<pb id="robs137" n="137"/>
to cut and break up General Lee's railroad
communication, and now he announced to his troops
that “the Rebel army is the legitimate property of the
Army of the Potomac.” I suppose everybody has
heard schoolboys quarrel, and noticed that just on the
edge of a fight over a game of marbles one or the
other would pipe up in a high-keyed tone, “You don't
know who you're foolin' with!” And that comes pretty
near expressing the condition of “Fighting Jo.” He
didn't know who <hi rend="italics">he</hi> was fooling with. One of the chief
“maxims of Napoleon” was that “the first necessity of
a general is to study the character of his opponent,”
and by this we <hi rend="italics">know</hi> that Hooker was deficient in
generalship, for he should by this time have been
sufficiently acquainted with the character of Lee to
understand that he could not be cheated by such
bungling strategy as was now displayed, and further,
when after he had entrenched himself at
Chancellorsville, he learned that “Stonewall” Jackson
with a heavy force was in retreat towards
Gordonsville, he should have judged that movement by
Jackson's character as it had been developed in the
war, and he would have understood perfectly what
was brewing, for he knew that “retreat without a
battle” was no part of the man of Kernstown's
philosophy, and that the soldier who had flanked
McClellan out of the Chickahominy and Pope from the
Rappahannock, would be quite likely to attempt the
same strategy against General Hooker.</p>
          <pb id="robs138" n="138"/>
          <p>A Northern journal of that time, <sic corr="criticizing">criticising</sic> General 
Hooker's movements in the Chancellorsville campaign,
says that “if General Lee had furnished General
Hooker with a plan it could not have been more to his
liking, for he concentrated first on Hooker and then on
Sedgwick, beating both by detail.”</p>
          <p>A colonel in Hooker's army, who was captured and
sent to Richmond after this battle related that just
before Jackson's guns opened on their flank, and while
they were talking about his retreat to Gordonsville the
surgeon of the colonel's regiment offered to bet a
hundred dollars that “Jackson would turn up in the
rear.” The colonel at once took the bet, firmly
believing that such a move was utterly impossible, but
it had hardly been closed when firing broke out “in the
rear,” the “Rebel yell” came ringing above the din of
battle, “Howard's Flying Dutchmen” broke like horses
from the woods, a <sic>a</sic> ragged Confederate demanded
the Colonel's surrender, and the surgeon claimed the
stakes.</p>
          <p>I shall not attempt any account of this battle, for I
was on the right, and I know that General Early
hampered General Sedgwick  -  eight thousand of us
against twenty-four thousand “boys in blue”  -  long
enough for General Jackson to break up Hooker's lines
and for General Lee to drive them over the river and
then come down to us, and then Sedgwick,
<pb id="robs139" n="139"/>
when the night got dark enough to conceal his
movements, retreated, by Banks' Ford across the
Rappahannock. The battle was over and the victory
was ours, but it cost us dear.</p>
          <p>Out of our army we had lost in killed, wounded and
captured, ten thousand, two hundred and eighty-one   -
fully one-fourth of what we had, while Hooker's loss
was seventeen thousand, one hundred and ninety-seven.</p>
          <p>But worse than all we had lost our General and hero,
our idol   -  “Stonewall the Great” was gone from us
forever, and the army was in mourning for the victory
that had cost us our chief treasure. We had only one
“Stonewall,” and we could not give him up. We wept
for our loss; no soldier thought of pity for Jackson; the
soldiers left <hi rend="italics">behind</hi> were more needy of sympathy.
No man said “poor Jackson,” or grieved for <hi rend="italics">him</hi> in
sympathy. <hi rend="italics">He</hi> was the “Great,” the “Glorious,” the
“Triumphant,” walking with his God beyond the gates
of paradise, but <hi rend="italics">we</hi> were the bereaved; <hi rend="italics">our</hi> staff was
broken and <hi rend="italics">our</hi> hearts were sad. Better it was for our
General  -  we believed  -  to go hence and be at rest;
but woe hung over our souls like a cloud, and we could
not see the light beyond as we can see it now. Let us
put twice two together and see if they make four.
General Lee said  -  not long before his death  -  that if
he could have had Jackson with him at Gettysburg he
<pb id="robs140" n="140"/>
would have beaten General Meade's army, and
Southern independence would have been established;
and it is universally conceded that such a result would
have surely followed a Southern victory there.</p>
          <p>Count that two. Now take Mayor Hewitt of New
York city, in the year of grace, 1888. He says, “it was
the South, and not the North that won in the war
between the States.” Maybe the old Confederates will
not agree with him, but they would if they could realize
the immense progress the South has made, to the
detriment of the North, since and in consequence of
their surrender, and would conclude that the
Secessionists, after all, “builded better than they
knew.” Another broad-minded Northern man says, in a
speech at a dinner given by the Southern Society, at
New York, on the 22d of February, this year:</p>
          <p>“I have heard your fight spoken of as the ‘Lost
<sic corr="Cause">Couse</sic>.’ It has paid you better than any other cause.
The South never lost its cause. When everything the
South held most dear was swept away, and you were
sweeping in the valley of the shadow of death, you
came to the resurrection which is making the South the
garden of this land; which is filling it with wealth won
by the labor of freemen and not of slaves. You never
knew what you had until you lost the frail crop on
which you had planted all your
<pb id="robs141" n="141"/>
fortunes. God had filled your land with every element of
wealth, but it remained undeveloped in the presence of
the blight which you neither understood nor realized.
Now you have fumed your attention to the resources
which God has given you, and the “irrepressible conflict”
is taking a new shape. It is a conflict between the
manufacturing States of the North and the South, and
victory is already perching on your banners, and before
the lapse of the century the Southern States will far
outstrip Pennsylvania and the manufacturing States of
the North. It was the North that lost by the outcome of
the rebellion, not you; the victory of the North was, in
reality, its defeat.”</p>
          <p>That is the other <hi rend="italics">two</hi>. Add 'em up?</p>
          <p>But we still have our “Stonewall” in memory's heart, as
he lived, fought, prayed and died for the independence of
the Southern land: died at the precise moment of time and
under the exact circumstances best calculated to
perpetuate his glory and fame, which today belongs to our
common country, North and South, and we, his old
veterans, were proud when at the unveiling of his statue in
Richmond, on the 27th of October, 1875, an almost
universal congratulation came to us from our Northern
brethren, and such words as these, from the Cincinnati
<hi rend="italics">Enquirer</hi>, were echoed from the Northern press:</p>
          <pb id="robs142" n="142"/>
          <p>“In truth, the character of Stonewall Jackson lifts
him above the narrow confines of State or even
National limits. His military genius elevates him among
the great soldiers of the world, among the select few
who belong to the universal history of mankind. He
was one of the few born soldiers with whom the
conduct of battle was an inspiration, and whose
prophetic eye always fixed upon the issue of a struggle
as a certainty. Such men are too rare to be confined
within the narrow pages of local history, too grand to
be repressed by the weight of sectional hostility. They
assert their right to universal appreciation and honor.
We are rapidly approaching the point when all of us,
both North and South, can honor and respect a great
name, no matter on which side it came to distinction.”</p>
          <p>I find I am using too much space for the limits of
my little book, and will add but little more, although my
idea of the story I have to tell is barely half developed,
but I propose to give after awhile the balance of the
story, and trust to a generous public to aid the
one-legged Rebel still further along his life journey.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="robs143" n="143"/>
        <div2 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>CHAPTER XI.</head>
          <p>My closing chapter of this section of my story of
“How a One-Legged Rebel Lives,” would not be
complete without some personal reminiscence, and I 
recall a true story of dismay and death which, to my
then excited imagination, gave my life upon the altar of
the bloody god of war, during the battle of Sharpsburg.
In the progress of that all-day, busy battle, the color-bearer
of my regiment was shot down, and I, with
some difficulty, detached the death-grip of his
stiffening fingers from the staff and, raising the colors,
carried them forward in their proper place, in the
center of our line.</p>
          <p>As we advanced I came upon a canteen which had
been dropped by some one, and quickly snatching it up,
found it was filled, and with the fine instinct which
distinguished the average Confederate soldier,
concluded that it would be a very laudable scheme to
convey that canteen and <hi rend="italics">contents</hi> to where I was
going, and so slinging its strap over my shoulder, I
pressed forward, and soon after was dropped by a
bullet. I made an examination as soon as I could, and
by the quantity of blood flowing from my wounded
side, was thoroughly satisfied that my wound was
mortal and my time short.</p>
          <p>I grew rapidly weaker, and after awhile a friend
came to me with the intention of assisting me far
enough towards the rear to get me in reach of a
<pb id="robs144" n="144"/>
surgeon, but I was, by this time, too weak to be moved
in any other manner than on a stretcher, and my friend
proceeded to try his surgical skill in checking the flow
of blood. A short examination of the wound brought
from him some decidedly emphatic language, and soon
he assured me that I wasn't wounded at all, except in
the <hi rend="italics">canteen</hi>, and so it proved, for a bullet had gone
through that canteen, and its contents, running down
my side clear to my shoes, gave me, in connection
with the shock, the impression that it was life-blood,
when, in reality, the canteen had been full of molasses.
It was long before the boys gave up their chaff about
blood and molasses.</p>
          <p>Since the war I have had many hard knocks in my
efforts to get a living, sometimes succeeding fairly, but
often the reverse. Yet still I managed it somehow.
One venture, by aid of friends, was successful beyond
my most sanguine expectations, and I was in a fair
way to achieve a competency  -  furnishing supplies
and running a boarding house on the Chesapeake and
Ohio Railroad, but in the full tide of success the
contractors failed, the hands were left without pay,
and my last dollar was swept away, but I paid my
obligations with one hundred cents to the dollar.</p>
          <p>I filled the office of constable for a considerable
time, and my experience in that line was mixed
<pb id="robs145" n="145"/>
with dark and bright color, but the gilding was scarce.
I doubt if many country constables, in Virginia, ever
achieved great wealth of sheckles.</p>
          <p>My best success has been in traveling with books,
and I have found kind friends and much sympathy
wherever I have gone, many, I know, only taking a
book from me to help the one-legged Rebel, and many
a hearty reception have I met from the old veterans of
the Northern army. “The bravest are the tenderest;
the loving are the daring,” and it is easy to read the
character of a soldier by his treatment of the maimed
victims of the war. True, I have met many veterans
who were on the down grade, and had little to help
themselves with, but the hearty hand grasp and
sympathetic greeting showed the soul within to be of
the dauntless host of gallant soldiers of America, who
believed that it was blessed to die for the right, and
would go at blazing batteries, if necessary.</p>
          <p>I have found much kindness among the visitors to,
and patrons of, the various watering places and
summer resorts which I have canvassed, and always
regardless of section or politics; but I must tell of a
gentleman from Michigan, whom I met in Warrenton,
Va., a few weeks ago. He was an old soldier from
the “Wolverine” State, who had seen much service,
but, in bad health, was wintering in Virginia, and
hearing of me, made me a call, and
<pb id="robs146" n="146"/>
we had many pleasant, social and friendly chats. He
made himself friends all around, and although much of
the conversation was in regard to the war, and that,
too, in the extreme ultra-southern town of Warrenton,
the capital of Mosby's Confederacy, and called by the
<hi rend="italics">great</hi> General Pope the “South Carolina of Virginia.”
Yet my Michigan friend came out ahead nearly every
round. One day a number of us, he among the rest,
were discussing the war and fighting our battles over
again, when “Michigan” remarked that he had killed a
Rebel in the Valley, at the given date then under
discussion. This brought out a somewhat indignant
remark from a young man in the party, who demanded
the particulars. “ Well, sir,” said “Michigan,” “I was
over in the Shenandoah Valley with Sheridan, in 1864,
and I did the killing in one of our battles with General
Early. It was on a very hot, dry day in August, and my
regiment was trying to hold a ridge in an open field,
about a quarter of a mile in front of a woods. The
Rebels were pressing us hotly; which, together with the
weather and want of water, made our situation very
distressing, and when they finally advanced upon us
with fixed bayonets, we jumped up and made for the
woods. A Rebel soldier, who appeared to me to be
about nine feet high, with a gun and bayonet the full
length of a fence rail, was about
<pb id="robs147" n="147"/>
twenty yards from me when I started from the ridge,
and on my rapid retreat to the woods I could hear his
feet pounding the ground behind me, and apparently
getting closer to me. I put on all the steam my boiler
would carry, for I particularly didn't fancy the contact
with that enormous bayonet, which the Rebel evidently
intended to use on me, and I fairly flew. Pretty soon I
noticed that his foot-falls were growing more indistinct,
and with hope renewed, I glanced back at him. That
glance revealed to me my opportunity, for overcome
with the heat and rapid locomotion, which my speed
made it necessary for him to use, he was just in the act
of falling to the ground, and I then realized for the first
time that I had killed a Rebel. He dropped stone-dead,
and I reached the timber in safety. My comrades said
the man ran himself to death, trying to catch me, but I
shall always contend that I killed him with that last
spurt.”</p>
          <p>I myself have cause to remember campaigning in the
Valley in 1864, for it was at the battle of Cedar Creek,
on the 19th of October, that I received the wound
which made me a one-legged Rebel. At this time I was
acting as a courier for Gen. John Pegram, commanding
Early's old division, and this battle, sometimes called
Belle Grove, was one of the most singular of the war.
General Early planned it in order to prevent General
Sheridan from sending 
<pb id="robs148" n="148"/>
troops to Grant at Petersburg, and because of
Sheridan's enormous superiority in numbers, he was
compelled to operate by a surprise flank movement,
which, in conception and execution, was equal to the
most brilliant of Stonewall Jackson's pieces of
strategy, and was completely successful in the early
part of it, our boys gallantly driving three corps of the
enemy (the 6th, 8th and 19th) clear out of their camps,
capturing fifteen hundred prisoners and eighteen
pieces of artillery. The surprise was complete, and the
Yankee boys fled in panic along the Valley pike, with
General Early pressing them with their own artillery,
but our soldiers failed to stick to their colors, and so
many of them left their ranks to plunder the rich stores
of the captured camps that the enemy, under the
gallant General Wright, had the opportunity to rally in
front of Middletown, and by 11 o'clock had brought up
enough troops to move on us, and then these stragglers
and plunderers of ours came to grief.</p>
          <p>Wright's men recovered their camps, and their
cavalry pursued our men so closely that they were
forced to retreat to Strasburg. All the success of the
morning had been lost, and for the first time in the
whole war a victory almost won had been thrown
away by the misconduct of Southern soldiers. Owing
to the breaking down of a bridge at the very narrow
part of the road between Strasburg
<pb id="robs149" n="149"/>
and Fisher's Hill, just above Strasburg, where there
was no other passway, all the artillery, ordnance wagons
and ambulances which had not passed that point, were
captured by a small body of Sheridan's cavalry, our force,
which would have defended and brought them out, having
been broken when the gallant Ramseur was killed.</p>
          <p>This battle ended my campaigning for that war, after
passing through the mill, and after receiving my severe
wound that afterwards caused the amputation of my
right leg.</p>
          <p>The boys in the hospitals had their jokes on the
surgeons, and this propensity for joking and fun among
our soldiers, was worth almost as much as medicine.
One case they reported was that of a man brought in,
dangerously wounded in three places. After the
examination by the surgeon, an assistant asked:
“Doctor, is the man badly hurt?” “Yes,” said the
surgeon, “two of the wounds are mortal, but the third
can be cured, provided the man is kept perfectly quiet
for six weeks.”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>CHAPTER XII.</head>
          <p>As a matter of interest to the old veterans of the
war, into whose hands this little book may fall, I
append here the battles fought in Virginia, together
with the rosters of the two great armies which
<pb id="robs150" n="150"/>
contended at Gettysburg, that being generally
conceded to be the decisive battle.</p>
          <p>We understand that at the opening of the campaign
the two armies were more evenly matched, as to
numbers, than at any other period of the war, and from
the best obtainable information that General Hooker
had a force of eighty thousand infantry divided into
seven corps. So he himself wrote to President Lincoln,
and proudly called it “the finest army on the planet.”</p>
          <p>General Lee's army, by the last of May, had seventy
thousand infantry  -  in three corps  -  and ten thousand
cavalry, and, as General Longstreet expressed it, “was
in a condition to undertake anything.”</p>
          <p>The actual force of General Lee's army at
Gettysburg, after making details to guard the lines of
communication, etc., was about sixty-two thousand
men; and General Meade, by the aid of re-enforcements,
brought forward by stress of the
invasion, numbered about one hundred and twelve
thousand.</p>
          <pb id="robs151" n="151"/>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>RELATIVE NUMBERS IN BOTH ARMIES.</head>
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Number of white males in the Northern States in
1861 subject to military duty, ..... 4,559,872</item>
            <item>Number of colored troops enrolled, ..... 99,337</item>
            <item>Number of white troops from Southern States in
U. S. Army,..... 86,009</item>
            <item>Number of Indians in U. S. Army, ..... 3,530</item>
            <item>4,748,748</item>
            <item>Number of white males in the Southern
States subject to military duty in 1861, ..... 1,064,193</item>
            <item>Number of troops from Northern States
enrolled in Confederate Army, ..... 19,000</item>
            <item>1,083,193</item>
            <item>Number in Union Army and subject to enrollment
over and above the Southern States, ..... 3,665,555</item>
          </list>
          <p>It will be seen from the reports in the War Department at
Washington, that there was a vast difference between the
two armies as to numbers.</p>
          <list type="simple">
            <item>The Union Army is put at the enormous figures of ..... 2,800,000</item>
            <item>The Confederate Army at the small number, ..... 600,000</item>
            <item>A total in favor of U. S. Army, ..... 2,200,000</item>
          </list>
          <p>With this difference in numbers, the war lasted only four years,
as all the Confederate ports were blockaded, and the Confederacy
was not able to recruit from Europe, Asia and Africa, and the
islands of the seas.</p>
          <pb id="robs152" n="152"/>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>RECORDS OF BATTLES IN VIRGINIA.</head>
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Abingdon, Glade Springs, Saltville and Marion (Stoneman's
Raid), December 12 to 21, 1864.</item>
            <item>Aldie, June 17, 1863.</item>
            <item>Amelia Springs, near Amelia Court-house, April 3, 1865.</item>
            <item>Annandale, December 4, 1861.</item>
            <item>Appomattox Courthouse, Lee Surrenders, April 9, 1865.</item>
            <item>Arthur's Swamp, October 1, 1864.</item>
            <item>Auburn, October 14, 1863.</item>
            <item>Ball's Bluff (near Leesburg), October 21, 1861.</item>
            <item>Ball's Cross Roads, August 27, 1861.</item>
            <item>Barboursville, July 12, 1861.</item>
            <item>Barnett's Ford, February 7, 1864.</item>
            <item>Beaver Dam Station, South Anna Bridge, Ashland and
Yellow Tavern, Sheridan's Cavalry Raid in Virginia, May
9 to 13, 1864.</item>
            <item>Bealeton, January 14, 1864.</item>
            <item>Bermuda Hundred, May 16 to 30, 1864, June 2, 1864,
August 24 and 25, 1864, and November 17, 1864.</item>
            <item>Berryville, December 1, 1862, October 18, 1863, and
September 3 and 4, 1864.</item>
            <item>Berryville Pike, Sulphur Springs Bridge and White Post,
August 10, 1864.</item>
            <item>Beverly Ford and Brandy Station, June 9, 1863.</item>
            <item>Big Bethel, June 10, 1861, and April 4, 1862.</item>
            <item>Blackburn's Ford, July 18, 1861.</item>
            <item>Bloomfield and Union, November 2 and 3, 1862.</item>
            <item>Boydton and White Oak Roads, March 31, 1865.</item>
            <item>Brandy Station, August 20, 1862.</item>
            <item>Brentsville, February 14, 1863, and February 14 1864.</item>
            <item>Bristoe Station, October 14, 1863, and April 15, 1864.</item>
            <item>Buckland Mills, October 19, 1863.</item>
            <pb id="robs153" n="153"/>
            <item>Buckton Station, May 23, 1862.</item>
            <item>Buford's Gap, June 21, 1864.</item>
            <item>Bull Run Bridge, August 27, 1862.</item>
            <item>Bull Run or Manassas, July 21, 1861, and August 30, 1862.</item>
            <item>Burke's Station, March 10, 1862.</item>
            <item>Camp Advance, Munson's Hill, September 29, 1861.</item>
            <item>Cedar Creek, Sheridan's Ride, October 16, 1864.</item>
            <item>Cedar Mountain, or Mitchell's Station, August 9, 1862. </item>
            <item>Chancellorsville, May 1 to 4, 1863.</item>
            <item>Chantilly, September 1, 1862.</item>
            <item>Chickahominy, May 24, 1862, June 27, 1862.</item>
            <item>City Point, Naval Engagement on James River, May 6,
1861, Explosion, August 9, 1864.</item>
            <item>Chester Station, May 6 and 7, 1864.</item>
            <item>Clendennin's Raid, below Fredericksburg, May 20 to 28,
1863.</item>
            <item>Coggin's Point, July 31, 1862.</item>
            <item>Cold Harbor, Gaines' Mill, Salem Church, and Hawe's
Shop, June 1 to 12, 1864.</item>
            <item>Coyle Tavern, August 24, 1863.</item>
            <item>Crooked Run, Front Royal, August 16, 1864.</item>
            <item>Cross Keys, or Union Church, June 8, 1862.</item>
            <item>Culpepper, July 12, 1862, and September 13, 1863.</item>
            <item>Culpepper and White Sulphur Springs, October 12 and 13,
1863.</item>
            <item>Dalmey's Mills, Hatcher's Run, February 5 to 7, 1865.</item>
            <item>Darbytown Road, October 7, and 13, 1864.</item>
            <item>Deserted House or Kelley's Store, January, 30, 1863.</item>
            <item>Dinwiddie C. H., March 31, 1865.</item>
            <item>Drainesville, November 26, 1861, December 20, 1861,
February 22, 1864.</item>
            <item>Dumfries, December 27, 1862.</item>
            <item>Dutch Gap, Naval Engagement, June 21, 1864.</item>
            <pb id="robs154" n="154"/>
            <item>Dutch Gap, August 5, 1863.</item>
            <item>Fairfax C. H., (near Alexandria), June 1, 1861, and March
8, 1863.</item>
            <item>Fair Oaks, October 27 and 28, 1864.</item>
            <item>Fall of Richmond, April 3, 1865.</item>
            <item>Falmouth, April 18, 1862.</item>
            <item>Farmville, April 7, 1865.</item>
            <item>Fisher's Hill, August 15, 1864.</item>
            <item>Five Forks, April 1, 1865.</item>
            <item>Fort Darling, Naval Engagement, May 16, 1862.</item>
            <item>Fort Darling, Drewry's Bluff, May 12 to 16, 1864.</item>
            <item>Franklin's Crossing, Rappahannock river, June 5, 1863.</item>
            <item>Fredericksburg and Salem Heights, May 1 to 4, 1863.</item>
            <item>Fredericksburg, December 13, 1862.</item>
            <item>Front Royal, May 23, <sic corr="1862">1852</sic>, and May 30, 1862.</item>
            <item>Frazier's Farm, June 30, 1862.</item>
            <item>Fort Hell, September 10, 1864.</item>
            <item>Fort Steadman, March 25, 1865.</item>
            <item>Gaine's Mill or Cold Harbor, June 27, 1862.</item>
            <item>Glendale, June 30, 1862<sic corr=".">,</sic>
</item>
            <item>Gloucester, November 17, 1862.</item>
            <item>Gordonsville, December 28, 1864.</item>
            <item>Gravel Hill, August 14<sic corr=",">.</sic> 1864.</item>
            <item>Great Falls, July 7, 1861.</item>
            <item>Groverton and Gainesville, August 28 and 29, 1862.</item>
            <item>Hampton Roads Naval Battle(with Monitor and Merrimac)
March 8 and 9, 1862.</item>
            <item>Hampton, August 7, 1861.</item>
            <item>Hanover Court-house, May 27, 1862.</item>
            <item>Hanoverton, Hawe's Shop, and Salem Church, May 27
and 28, 1864.</item>
            <item>Hanover and Ashland, May 30, 1864.</item>
            <item>Harrisonburg, June 6, 1862.</item>
            <pb id="robs155" n="155"/>
            <item>Haymarket, October 18, 1862.</item>
            <item>Hatcher's rum, October 27, and December 8 and 9, 1864.</item>
            <item>High Bridge, on the Appomattox River, April 6, 1865.</item>
            <item>Jeffersonton, October 12, 1863.</item>
            <item>Jones' Bridge and Samaria Church, June 23 and 24, 1864.</item>
            <item>Jonesville, January 3, 1864.</item>
            <item>Kelly's Ford, March 17, 1863, and November 7, 1863.</item>
            <item>Kilpatrick's Raid, Stevensburg to Richmond February 28
to March 4, 1864.</item>
            <item>Kernstown, March 23, 1862.</item>
            <item>Lacey's Springs, December 20, 1864.</item>
            <item>Laurel Hill and Ny River, May 8 to 18, 1864.</item>
            <item>Lee's Mills, April 16, 1862, July 12 and 30, 1864.</item>
            <item>Lewinsville, September 11, 1861.</item>
            <item>Locust Grove, November 26 to 28, 1863.</item>
            <item>Lovettsville, August 8, 1861.</item>
            <item>Luray, June 30, 1862.</item>
            <item>Lynchburg, June 17 and 18, 1864.</item>
            <item>Malvern Hill, July 1, 1862.</item>
            <item>Malvern Hill, August 5, 1862.</item>
            <item>Manassas Gap and Chester Gap, July 21 to 23, 1863.</item>
            <item>Manassas or Bull Run, July 21, 1861, and August 30,
1862.</item>
            <item>Mason's Neck, Occoquan, February 24, 1862.</item>
            <item>Mattaponi or Thornburg, August 6, 1862.</item>
            <item>Matthias Point, Potomac River, June 27, 1861.</item>
            <item>McDowell, or Bull Pasture, May 8, 1862.</item>
            <item>McLean's Ford, or Liberty Mills, October 15, 1863.</item>
            <item>Mechanicsville, or Ellison's Mills, June 26, 1862.</item>
            <item>Middletown, June 11, 1863.</item>
            <item>Mine Run, Raccoon Ford, New Hope, Robertson's Farm,
Bartlett's Mills, and Locust Grove, November 26 and 28,
1863.</item>
            <pb id="robs156" n="156"/>
            <item>Monterey (N. W. of Waynesboro), April 12, 1862.</item>
            <item>Mount Jackson, November 17, 1863.</item>
            <item>Muddy Run, November 8, 1863.</item>
            <item>Near Snicker's Gap, August 13 and 19, 1864.</item>
            <item>Namozine Church and Willicomack, April 3, 1865.</item>
            <item>Nelson's Farm, June 30, 1862.</item>
            <item>New Market Crossroads, June 30, 1862.</item>
            <item>New Market, May 15, and October 7, 1864.</item>
            <item>New Market Heights, or Laurel Hill, September 28 to 30,
1864.</item>
            <item>New Market Bridge, December 22, 1861.</item>
            <item>Newport News, June 5, 1861.</item>
            <item>Newton and Cedar Springs, November 12, 1864.</item>
            <item>North Anna River, Jericho Ford, or Taylor's Bridge, and
Totopotomy Bridge, May 23 to 27, 1864.</item>
            <item>Occoquan, March 5, 1862.</item>
            <item>Occaquan Creek, November 12, 1861.</item>
            <item>Occoquan Bridge, January 29, 1862.</item>
            <item>Old Church, June 13, 1862.</item>
            <item>Orange C. H., August 2, 1862.</item>
            <item>Otter Creek (near Liberty), June 16, 1864.</item>
            <item>Peach Orchard, and Savage Station, June 29, 1862.</item>
            <item>Panther Gap, and Buffalo Gap, June 3 to 6, 1864.</item>
            <item>Petersburg and vicinity: Chester Station, May 6 and 7,
1864.</item>
            <item>Petersburg, June 10, 1864.</item>
            <item>Philomont, November 1, 1862.</item>
            <item>Poplar Springs Church, October 1, 1864.</item>
            <item>Port Republic, June 9, 1862.</item>
            <item>Quaker Road, March 23, 1865.</item>
            <item>Rapidan Station, September 14, 1863.</item>
            <item>Rapidan Station, September 19, 1863, and October 10,
1863.</item>
            <pb id="robs157" n="157"/>
            <item>Rappahannock Station, November 7, 1863. </item>
            <item>Rappahannock Station, Brandy Station, and Kelly's Ford, August 1 to 3, 1863. </item>
            <item>Reams's Station, August 25, 1864. </item>
            <item>Rectertown and Loudon Heights, January 1 to 10, 1864. </item>
            <item>Richmond and vicinity: Fort Darling (Naval Engagement),
May 15, 1862, Seven Pines and Fair Oaks, May 31 to June
1, 1862.</item>
            <item>Robertson's Farm, Bartlett's Mills, and Locust Grove,
November 26 to 28, 1863.</item>
            <item>Sailor's Creek, April 6, 1865.</item>
            <item>Salem, June 21, 1864.</item>
            <item>Saltville, October 2, 1864.</item>
            <item>Samaria Church, Malvern Hill, June 15, 1864.</item>
            <item>Seven Pines and Fair Oaks, May 31 to June 1, 1862.</item>
            <item>Seige of Petersburg, June 15, 1864, to April 2, 1865.</item>
            <item>Six Miles Station, August 18, 19 and 21, 1864.</item>
            <item>Slatersville, or New Kent C. H., May 9, 1862.</item>
            <item>Snicker's Gap and Island Ford, July 16 and 17, 1864.</item>
            <item>Somerville Heights, May 7, 1862.</item>
            <item>Spottsylvania C. H., April 30, 1863.</item>
            <item>Spottsylvania, Fredericksburg Road, Laurel Hill, and Ny
River, May 8 to 18, 1864.</item>
            <item>Stanardsville and Burton's Ford, March 1, 1864.</item>
            <item>Stevenson's Depot, Darkville, and Winchester, July 19
and 20, 1864.</item>
            <item>Stony Creek Station, December 1, 1864.</item>
            <item>Strasburg and Staunton Road, June 1 and 2, 1862.</item>
            <item>Strasburg, October 13, 1864.</item>
            <item>Strawberry Plains or Deep Bottom, August 14 to 18, 1864.</item>
            <item>Suffolk Siege, from April 12 to May 4, 1863.</item>
            <item>Suffolk Battle, March 9, 1864.</item>
            <item>Summit Point, Berryville, and Flowing Springs, August
21, 1864.</item>
            <pb id="robs158" n="158"/>
            <item>Swift Creek and Arrowfield Church, May 9 and 10, 1864.</item>
            <item>Sylvan Grove, Waynesboro, and Brown's Crossroads, 
November 26 to 29, 1864.</item>
            <item>Todd's Tavern, May 8, 1864.</item>
            <item>Tom's Brook, Fisher's Hill, and Strasburg, October 9,1864.</item>
            <item>Trevillian's Station, June 11 and 12, 1864.</item>
            <item>Tunstall's Station, June 14, 1862.</item>
            <item>Turkey Bend, June 30, 1862.</item>
            <item>Upperville, June 21, 1863.</item>
            <item>Vienna, June 17, 1861, December 3, 1861, and September 2, 1862.</item>
            <item>Warrenton Junction, May 3, 1863.</item>
            <item>Waterloo Bridge, Lee Springs. Freeman's Ford and Sulphur Springs, Skirmishers, August 23 to 25, <sic corr="1862">1852</sic>.</item>
            <item>Waynesboro, October 2, 1864. </item>
            <item>Weldon Railroad (now Petersburg R. R.). June 22 to 30, 1864.</item>
            <item>Weldon Railroad Expedition, December 7 to 11, 1864.</item>
            <item>West Point, May 7, 1862.</item>
            <item>White Oak Swamp Bridge, August 4, 1862 and June 13,
1864. </item>
            <item>White Oak Smamp, Charles City Cross Roads, June 30, 1862.</item>
            <item>White Post, December 6, 1864.</item>
            <item>Williamsburg, May 2, 1862, and July 11, 1862.</item>
            <item>Williamsburg Road, June 18, 1862.</item>
            <item>Wilson's Wharf, May 24, 1864.</item>
            <item>Wilderness, May, 5 to 7, 1864.</item>
            <item>Winchester, May 25, 1862.</item>
            <item>Winchester and Kernstown, March 23, 1862.</item>
            <item>Winchester, June 13 and 15, 1863.</item>
            <item>Winchester, August 17, 1864.</item>
            <item>Winchester, July 23 and 24, 1864. </item>
            <item>Winchester and Fisher's Hill, September 19 to 22, 1864.</item>
            <item>Wytheville, June 17, 1863.</item>
            <item>Yorktown, April 11 and 26, 1862.</item>
          </list>
          <pb id="robs159" n="159"/>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
          <head>BATTLES FOUGHT IN VIRGINIA.</head>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">Organization of the Army of Northern Virginia, June
1, 1863  -  Gen. Robert E. Lee, Commanding.</hi>
          </p>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>STAFF.</head>
            <item>Col. W. H. Taylor, Adjutant-General.</item>
            <item>Col. C. S. Venable, A. D. C.</item>
            <item>Col. Charles Marshall, A. D. C.</item>
            <item>Col. James L. Corley, Chief Quartermaster.</item>
            <item>Col. R. G. Cole, Chief Commissary.</item>
            <item>Col. B. G. Baldwin, Chief of Ordnance.</item>
            <item>Col. H. E. Peyton, Assistant Inspector-General.</item>
            <item>Gen. W. N. Pendleton, Chief of Artillery.</item>
            <item>Dr. L. Guild, Medical Director.</item>
            <item>Col. W. Porcher Smith, Chief Engineer.</item>
            <item>Maj. H. E. Young, Assistant Adjutant-General.</item>
            <item>Maj. G. B. Cook, Assistant Inspector-General.</item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">First Corps - Lieutenant-General James Longstreet,
Commanding.</hi>
          </p>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>M'LAWS' DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Major-General L. McLaws, commanding.</item>
            <item>Kershaw's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General J. B. Kershaw,
commanding; 15th South Carolina regiment, Col. W. D.
DeSaussure; 8th South Carolina, Col. J. W. Memminger; 2d
South Carolina, Col. John D. Kennedy; 3d South Carolina,
Col. James D. Nance; 7th South Carolina, Col. D. Wyatt
Aiken; 3d (James)
<pb id="robs160" n="160"/>
Battalion, South Carolina Infantry, Lieutenant-Colonel R. C.
Rice.</item>
            <item>Benning's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General H. L. Benning,
commanding; 50th Georgia regiment, Col. W. R. Manning;
51st Georgia regiment, Col. W. M. Slaughter; 53d Georgia
regiment, Col. Jas. P. Simms; 10th Georgia regiment,
Lieutenant-Colonel John B. Weems.</item>
            <item>Barksdale's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Wm. Barksdale,
commanding; 13th Mississippi regiment, Col. J. W. Carter;
17th Mississippi regiment, Col. W. D. Holder; 18th
Mississippi regiment, Col. Thomas M. Griffin; 21st
Mississippi regiment, Col. B. G. Humphreys.</item>
            <item>Wofford's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General W. T. Wofford,
commanding; 18th Georgia regiment, Maj. E. Griffs; Phillips'
Georgia legion, Col. W. M. Phillips; 24th Georgia regiment,
Col. Robert McMillan; 16th Georgia regiment, Col. Goode
Bryan; Cobb's Georgia legion, Lieutenant-Colonel L. D.
Glewn.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>PICKETT'S DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Major-General George E. Pickett, commanding.</item>
            <item>Garnett's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General R. B. Garnett,
commanding; 8th Virginia regiment, Col. Eppa Hunton; 18th
Virginia regiment, Col. R. E. Withers; 19th Virginia regiment,
Col. Henry Gantt; 28th Virginia regiment, Col. R. C. Allen;
56th Virginia regiment, Col. W. D. Stuart.</item>
            <item>Armistead's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General L. A. Armistead,
commanding; 9th Virginia regiment, Lieut.-Col. J. S. Gilliam;
14th Virginia regiment, Col. J. G.
<pb id="robs161" n="161"/>
Hodges; 38th Virginia regiment, Col. E. C. Edmonds; 53d
Virginia regiment, Col. John Grammar; 57th Virginia regiment,
Col. J. B. Magruder.</item>
            <item>Kemper's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General J. L. Kemper,
commanding; 1st Virginia regiment, Col. Lewis B. Williams,
Jr.; 3d Virginia regiment, Col. Jos. Mayo, Jr.; 7th Virginia
regiment, Col. W. T. Patton; 11th Virginia regiment, Col.
David Funsten; 24th Virginia regiment, Col. W. R. Terry.</item>
            <item>Corse's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General M. D. Corse,
commanding; 15th Virginia regiment, Col. T. P. August; 17th
Virginia regiment, Col. Morton Marye; 30th Virginia
regiment, Col. A. T. Harrison; 32d Virginia regiment, Col. E.
B. Montague (this brigade was not at Gettysburg, having
been left at Hanover Junction).</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>HOOD'S DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Major-General John B. Hood.</item>
            <item>Robertson's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General J. B. Robertson,
commanding; 1st Texas regiment, Col. A. T. Rainey; 4th
Texas regiment, Col. J. C. G. Key; 5th Texas regiment, Col. R.
M. Powell; 3d Arkansas regiment, Col. Van H. Manning.</item>
            <item>Laws' Brigade  -  Brigadier-General E. M. Laws,
commanding; 4th Alabama regiment, Col. P. A. Bowles; 44th
Alabama regiment, Col. W. H. Perry; 15th Alabama regiment,
Col. James Canty; 47th Alabama regiment, Col. J. W.
Jackson; 48th Alabama regiment, Col. J. F. Shepherd.</item>
            <item>Anderson's Brigade  -  <sic corr="Brigadier">Brigadies</sic>-General G. T. Anderson,
<pb id="robs162" n="162"/>
commanding; 10th Georgia battalion, Maj. J. E. Rylander; 
7th Georgia regiment, Col. W. M. White; 8th Georgia regiment, 
Lieut.-Col. J. R. Towers; 9th Georgia regiment, Col. B. F. Beck; 
11th Georgia regiment, Col. F. H.
Little.</item>
            <item>Jenkins' Brigade  -  Brigadier-General M. Jenkins, 
commanding; 2d South Carolina Rifles, Col. Thomas Thompson; 
1st South Carolina regiment, Lieut.-Col. David Livingstone; 
5th South Carolina regiment, Col. A. Coward; 6th South 
Carolina regiment, Col. John Bratton; Hampton's Legion, Col. M. W. Gary.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>ARTILLERY OF THE FIRST CORPS.</head>
            <item>Colonel J. B. Walton, commanding.</item>
            <item>Battalion  -  Col. H. C. Cabell, Major Hamilton.</item>
            <item>Batteries  -  McCarty's, Manly's, Carlton's, Frazer's.</item>
            <item>Battalion  -  Major Henry.</item>
            <item>Batteries  -  Bachman's, Reilly's, Latham's, Gordon's.</item>
            <item>Battalion  -  Major Dearing, Major Reed.</item>
            <item>Batteries  -  Macon's, Blount's, Stribbling's, Caskie's.</item>
            <item>Battalion  -  Col. E. P. Alexander, Major Huger.</item>
            <item>Batteries  -  Jordan's, Rhett's, Moody's, Parker's, Taylor's.</item>
            <item>Battalion  -  Major Eshleman.</item>
            <item>Batteries  -  Squire's, Miller's, Richardson's, Norcom's.</item>
            <item>Total number of guns  -  Artillery First Corps  -  83.</item>
          </list>
          <pb id="robs163" n="163"/>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">Second Corps  -  Lieutenant-General Richard S. Ewell.</hi>
          </p>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>EARLY'S DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Major-General Jubal A. Early, commanding.</item>
            <item>Hays' Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Harry S. Hays, 
commanding; 5th Louisiana regiment, Col. Henry Forno; 
6th Louisiana regiment, Col. Wm. Monaghan; 7th Louisiana 
regiment, Col. D. B. Penn; 8th Louisiana regiment, Col. Henry 
B. Kelly; 9th Louisiana regiment, Col. A. L. Stafford.</item>
            <item>Gordon's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General J. B. Gordon, 
commanding; 13th Georgia, Col. J. M. Smith; 26th Georgia, 
Col. E. N. Atkinson; 31st Georgia, Col. C. A. Evans; 38th 
Georgia, Maj. J. D. Matthews; 60th Georgia, Col. W. H. Stiles; 
61st Georgia, Col. J. H. Lamar.</item>
            <item>Smith's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General William Smith, 
commanding; 13th Virginia regiment, Col. J. E. B. Terrell; 31st 
Virginia, Col. J. S. Hoffman; 49th Virginia, Colonel Gibson; 
52d Virginia, Colonel Skinner; 58th Virginia, Col. F. H. Board  - 
13th Virginia was left in Winchester to guard the stores captured 
from Milroy, and 58th Virginia was left in Staunton to guard prisoners 
captured from Milroy.</item>
            <item>Hoke's Brigade  -  Col. J. B. Avery, commanding 
(Gen. R. F. Hoke being absent, wounded); 6th North Carolina 
regiment, Col. J. E. Avery; 21st North Carolina, Col. 
W. W. Kirkland; 54th North Carolina, Col. J. C. T. McDonald; 
57th North Carolina, Col. A. C. Godwin; 1st North Carolina battalion, 
Maj. R. H. Wharton.</item>
          </list>
          <pb id="robs164" n="164"/>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>RHODES' DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Major-General R. E. Rhodes.</item>
            <item>Daniel's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Junius Daniel, 
commanding; 32d North Carolina regiment, Col. E. C. Bravale; 
43d North Carolina, Col. Thos. S. Keenan; 45th North Carolina, 
Lieut.-Col. Samuel H. Boyd; 53d North Carolina, Col. W. A. Owens; 
2d North Carolina battalion, Lieut.-Col. H. S. Andrews.</item>
            <item>Doles' Brigade  -  Brigadier-General George Doles, 
commanding; 4th Georgia, Lieut.-Col. D. R. E. Winn; 12th Georgia, 
Col. Edward Willis; 21st Georgia, Col. John T. Mercer; 44th Georgia, 
Col. S. P. Lumpkin.</item>
            <item>Ramseur's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General S. D. Ramseur, 
commanding; 2d North Carolina regiment, Maj. E. W. Hurt; 
4th North Carolina, Col. Bryan Grimes; 14th North Carolina, 
Col. R. T. Bennett; 30th North Carolina, Col. F. M. Parker.</item>
            <item>Iverson's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Alfred Iverson, 
commanding; 5th North Carolina regiment, Capt. S. B. West; 
12th North Carolina, Lieut.-Col. W. S. Davis; 20th North Carolina,
 Lieut.-Col. N. Slough; 23d North Carolina, Col. D. H. Christie.</item>
            <item>Rhodes' Brigade  -  Col. E. A. Oneal, commanding; 
3d Alabama regiment, Col. C. A. Battle; 5th Alabama, 
Col. J. M. Hall; 6th Alabama, Col. J. N. Lightfoot; 12th Alabama, 
Col. S. B. Pickens; 26th Alabama, Lieut.-Col. J. C. Goodgame.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>JOHNSON'S DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Major-General Edward Johnson.</item>
            <item>Stuart's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Geo. H. Stuart,
<pb id="robs165" n="165"/>
commanding; 10th Virginia regiment, Col. E. T. H. Warren; 
23d Virginia, Col. A. G. Taliaferro; 37th Virginia, Col. T. V. 
Williams; 1st North Carolina regiment, Col. J. A. McDowell; 
3d North Carolina, Lieutenant-Colonel Thurston.</item>
            <item>Stonewall Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Jas. A. Walker, 
commanding; 2d Virginia regiment, Col. J. G. A. Nadensbousch; 
4th Virginia, Col. Chas. A. Ronald; 5th Virginia, Col. J. H. S. Funk; 
27th Virginia, Col. J. K. Edmondson; 33d Virginia, Col. F. M. Holliday.</item>
            <item>Jones' Brigade  -  Brigadier-General John M. Jones, 
commanding; 21st Virginia regiment, Captain Moseley; 42d 
Virginia, Lieutenant-Colonel Withers; 44th Virginia, Captain 
Buckner; 48th Virginia, Col. T. S. Garnett; 50th Virginia, 
Colonel Vandevauter.</item>
            <item>Nicholls' Brigade  -  Colonel J. M. Williams, commanding 
(Gen. F. T. Nicholls wounded); 1st Louisiana regiment, Col. Wm. 
R. Shivers; 2d Louisiana regiment, Col. J. M. Williams; 
10th Louisiana regiment, Col. E. Waggaman; 14th Louisiana 
regiment, Col. Z. York; 15th Louisiana regiment, Colonel
Edward Pendleton.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>ARTILLERY OF THE SECOND CORPS.</head>
            <item>Colonel S. Crutchfield, commanding.</item>
            <item>Battalion  -  Lieut.-Col. Thos. H. Carter, Maj. Carter M. Braxton.</item>
            <item>Batteries  -  Captain Page's, Fry's, Carter's, Reese's.</item>
            <item>Battalion  -  Lieut.-Col. H. P. Jones, Major Brockenborough.</item>
            <pb id="robs166" n="166"/>
            <item>Batteries  -  Carrington's, Garber's, Thompson's and Tanner's.</item>
            <item>Battalion  -  Lieut.-Col. S. Andrews, Major Lattimer.</item>
            <item>Batteries  -  Brown's, Dermot's, Carpenter's, Raines'.</item>
            <item>Battalion  -  Lieut.-Col. Nelson, Major Page.</item>
            <item>Batteries  -  Kirkpatrick's, Massie's, Milledge's.</item>
            <item>Battalion  -  Col. J. T. Brown, Major Hardaway.</item>
            <item>Batteries  -  Dance's, Watson's, Smith's, Huff's and Graham's.</item>
            <item>Total number guns  -  Artillery Second Corps  -  82.</item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">Third Corps  -  Lieut.-Gen. A. P. Hill, Commanding.</hi>
          </p>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>ANDERSON'S DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Major-General R. H. Anderson.</item>
            <item>Wilcox's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Cadmus M. Wilcox; 
8th Alabama regiment, Col. T. L. Royster; 9th Alabama, Col. S. Henry; 
10th Alabama, Col. W. H. Forney; 11th Alabama, Col. J. C. C. Saunders; 
14th Alabama, Col. L. P. Pinkhard.</item>
            <item>Mahone's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Wm. Mahone; 
6th Virginia regiment, Col. G. T. Rogers; 12th Virginia, Col. D. A. 
Weisiger; 16th Virginia, Lieut.-Col. Joseph H. Ham; 41st Virginia, 
Col. W. A. Parham; 61st Virginia, Col. V. D. Groner.</item>
            <item>Posey's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Carnot Posey; 
46th Mississippi, Col. Joseph Payne; 16th Mississippi, Col. S. E. 
Baker; 19th Mississippi, Col. John Mullins; 12th Mississippi, 
Col. W. H. Taylor.</item>
            <item>Wright's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General A. R. Wright; 
2d Georgia battalion, Maj. G. W. Ross; 3d Georgia
<pb id="robs167" n="167"/>
regiment, Col. E. J. Walker; 22d Georgia regiment, Col. R. H. 
Jones; 48th Georgia regiment, Col. Wm. Gibson.</item>
            <item>Perry's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General E. A. Perry; 2d Florida
regiment, Lieut.-Col. S. G. Pyles; 5th Florida, Col. J. C. Hately; 
8th Florida, Col. David Long.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>HETH'S DIVISION.</head>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Pettigrew; 42d, 11th, 
26th, 44th, 47th, 52d, 17th North Carolina regiments.</item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Field; 40th, 55th, 
47th Virginia regiments.</item>
            <item>Third Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Archer; 1st, 7th, 14th 
Tennessee  regiments, 13th Alabama regiment.</item>
            <item>Fourth Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Cook; 15th, 27th, 
46th, 48th North Carolina regiments.</item>
            <item>Fifth Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Davis; 2d, 11th, 42d 
Mississippi, 55th North Carolina regiments.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>MAJOR-GENERAL PENDER'S DIVISION.</head>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Brigadier-General McGowan; 1st, 12th, 13th,
14th South Carolina regiments. </item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Lane; 7th, 
18th, 28th, 33d, 37th North Carolina regiments. </item>
            <item>Third Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Thomas; 14th, 
35th, 45th, 49th Georgia regiments. </item>
            <item>Fourth Brigade  -  Pender's old brigade; 13th, 16th, 22d, 34th, 38th
North Carolina regiments.</item>
          </list>
          <pb id="robs168" n="168"/>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>ARTILLERY OF THE THIRD CORPS.</head>
            <item>Colonel R. Lindsay Walker, commanding.</item>
            <item>Battalion  -  Maj. D. G. McIntosh, Maj. W. F. Poague.</item>
            <item>Batteries  -  Hurt's, Rice's, Luck's, Johnson's.</item>
            <item>Battalion  -  Lieut.-Col. Garnett, Maj. Richardson.</item>
            <item>Batteries  -  Lewis', Maurin's, Moore's, Grandy's.</item>
            <item>Battalion  -  Major Cutshaw.</item>
            <item>Batteries  -  Wyatt's, Woolfolk's, Brooke's.</item>
            <item>Battalion  -  Maj. Willie P. Pegram.</item>
            <item>Batteries  -  Brunson's, Davidson's, Crenshaw's, Magraw's,
Marye's.</item>
            <item>Battalion  -  Lieut.-Col. Cutts, Maj. Lane.</item>
            <item>Batteries  -  Wingfield's, Ross', Patterson's.</item>
            <item>Total number guns  -  Artillery Third Corps  -  83.</item>
            <item>Total number guns  -  Army Northern Virginia  -  248.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>CAVALRY CORPS A. N. V.</head>
            <item>Major-General J. E. B. Stuart.</item>
            <item>Hampton's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Wade Hampton, commanding.</item>
            <item>Fitz. Lee's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Fitzhugh Lee, commanding.</item>
            <item>W. H. F. Lee's Brigade - Colonel Chambliss, commanding.</item>
            <item>Robertson's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General B. H. Robertson, commanding.</item>
            <item>Jones' Brigade  -  Brigadier-General W. E. Jones, commanding.</item>
            <item>Imboden's Brigade  -  Brigadier-General J. D. Imboden, commanding.</item>
            <pb id="robs169" n="169"/>
            <item>Jenkens' Brigade  -  Brigadier-General A. G. Jenken's, commanding.</item>
            <item>White's Battalion  -  Lieut.-Col. E. V. White, commanding.</item>
            <item>Baker's Brigade - </item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">Roster of the Federal Army Engaged in the 
Battle of Gettysburg, Wednesday, Thursday and Friday, 
July 1, 2 and 3, 1863  -  Major-General George G. Meade, 
Commanding.</hi>
          </p>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>STAFF.</head>
            <item>Maj.-Gen. Daniel Butterfield, Chief of Staff.</item>
            <item>Brig.-Gen. M. R. Patrick, Provost Marshal-General.</item>
            <item>Brig.-Gen. Seth Williams, Adjutant-General.</item>
            <item>Brig.-Gen. Edmund Schriver, Inspector-General.</item>
            <item>Brig.-Gen. Rufus Ingalls, Quartermaster-General.</item>
            <item>Col. Henry F. Clarke, Chief Commissary of Subsistence.</item>
            <item>Maj. Jonathan Letterman, Surgeon, Chief of Medical Department.</item>
            <item>Brig.-Gen. G. K. Warren, Chief Engineer.</item>
            <item>Maj. G. W. Flagler, Chief of Ordnance.</item>
            <item>Maj.-Gen. Alfred Pleasanton, Chief of Cavalry.</item>
            <item>Brig.-Gen. Henry J. Hunt, Chief of Artillery.</item>
            <item>Capt. L. B. Norton, Chief Signal Officer.</item>
            <item>Maj.-Gen. John F. Reynolds, commanding the First, 
Third and Eleventh Corps on July 1.</item>
            <pb id="robs170" n="170"/>
            <item>Maj.-Gen. Henry W. Slocum, commanding the Right 
Wing on July 2 and 3.</item>
            <item>Maj.-Gen. Winfield S. Hancock, commanding the Left Center on July 2 and 3.</item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">First Corps  -  Maj.-Gen. John F. Reynolds, Permanent Commander.</hi>
          </p>
          <p>Maj.-Gen. Abner Doubleday, commanding on July 1.</p>
          <p>Maj.-Gen. John Newton, commanding on July 2-3.</p>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>FIRST DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Brig.-Gen. James S. Wadsworth, commanding.</item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Solomon Meredith, 
wounded and succeeded by Col. H. A. Morrow; also wounded 
and succeeded by Col. W. W. Robinson; 2d Wisconsin, Col. 
Lucius Fairchild; 6th Wisconsin, Col R. R.
Dawes; 7th Wisconsin, Col. W. W. Robinson; 24th Michigan, 
Col. H. A. Morrow; 19th Indiana, Col. Samuel Williams.</item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Lysander Cutler, 
commanding; 7th Indiana, Maj. Ira G. Grover; 56th Pennsylvania, 
Col. J. W. Hoffman; 76th New York, Maj. A. J. Grover; 95th New York, 
Col. Geo. H. Biddle; 147th New York, Lieut.-Col. F. C. Miller; 
14th Brooklyn, Col. E. B. Fowler.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>SECOND DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Brigadier-General John C. Robinson, commanding.</item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Gabriel R. Paul, 
commanding; 16th Maine, Col. Chas. W. Tilden; 13th
<pb id="robs171" n="171"/>
Massachusetts, Col. S. H. Leonard; 94th New York, Col. A.
R. Root; 104th New York, Col. Gilbert G. Prey; 107th
Pennsylvania, Col. T. F. McCoy; 11th Pennsylvania, Col. R.
S. Coulter.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>THIRD DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Major-General Abner Doubleday, commanding.</item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Thos. A. Rowley, 
commanding; 121st Pennsylvania, Col. Chapman Biddle; 142d 
Pennsylvania, Col. Robt. P. Cummings; 151st Pennsylvania, 
Lieut.-Col. Geo. F. McFarland; 20th New York, S. M., Col. 
Theodore B. Gates.</item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Colonel Roy Stone, commanding; 
143d Pennsylvania, Col. Edmund L. Dana; 149th Pennsylvania, 
Lieut.-Col. Walton Dwight; 150th Pennsylvania, Col. Langhorne Wistar.</item>
            <item>Third Brigade  -  Brigadier-General George J. Stannard; 
12th Vermont, Col. Asa P. Blount; 13th Vermont, Col. Francis 
V. Randall; 14th Vermont, Col. W. T. Nichols; 15th Vermont, Col. 
Redfield Proctor; 16th Vermont, Col. W. G. Veazey.</item>
            <item>Artillery Brigade  -  Colonel Chas. S. Wainwright; 2d Maine, 
Capt. Jas. A. Hall; 5th Maine, Capt. G. T. Stevens; Battery B, 
1st Pennsylvania, Capt. J. H. Cooper; Battery B, 4th United States, 
Lieut. James Stewart; Battery L, 1st New York, Capt. J. A. Reynolds.</item>
          </list>
          <pb id="robs172" n="172"/>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">Second Corps  -  Major-General Winfield S. Hancock, 
Commanding.</hi>
          </p>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>FIRST DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Brigadier-General John C. Caldwell.</item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Colonel Edward E. Cross, 
commanding; 5th New Hampshire, Col. E. E. Cross; 61st 
New York, Lieut.-Col. Oscar K. Broady; 81st Pennsylvania, 
Col. H. Boyd McKeen; 148th Pennsylvania, Lieut.-Col. Robert McFarland.</item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Colonel Patrick Kelly, commanding; 
28th Massachusetts, Col. Richard Byrnes; 63d New York, Lieut.-Col. 
R. C. Bentley; 69th New York, Captain Maroney; 88th New York, Col. 
Patrick Kelley; 116th Pennsylvania, Maj. St. C. A. Mulholland.</item>
            <item>Third Brigade  -  Brigadier-General S. K. Zook; 52d New York,
 Lieut.-Col. Charles G. Freudenberg; 57th New York, Lieut.-Col. A. B. 
Chapman; 66th New York, Col. Orlando W. Morris; 140th Pennsylvania, 
Col. Richard P. Roberts.</item>
            <item>Fourth Brigade  -  Colonel John R. Brooke, commanding; 
27th Connecticut, Lieut.-Col. Henry C. Merwin; 64th New York, 
Col. Daniel G. Bingham; 53d Pennsylvania, Lieut.-Col. Richard 
McMichael; 145th Pennsylvania, Col. H. L. Brown; 2d Delaware, 
Col. Wm. P. Bailey.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>SECOND DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Brigadier-General John Gibbon, commander.</item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Brigadier-General William Harrow; 
19th Maine, Col. F. E. Heath; 15th Massachusetts,
<pb id="robs173" n="173"/>
Col. Geo. H. Ward; 82d New York, Col. Henry W. Huston; 
1st Minnesota, Col. William Colvil.</item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Alexander S. 
Webb; 69th Pennsylvania, Col. Dennis O. Kane; 71st Pennsylvania, 
Lieut.-Col. R. Penn Smith; 72d Pennsylvania, Col. D. W. C. Baxter; 
106th Pennsylvania, Lieut.-Col. Theodore Hesser.</item>
            <item>Third Brigade  -  Colonel Norman J. Hall, commanding; 
19th Massachusetts, Col. Arthur P. Devereux; 20th Massachusetts, 
Col. Paul J. Revere; 42d New York, Col. J. E. Mallon; 59th New York, 
Lieut.-Col. Max A. Thoman; 7th
Michigan, Col. N. J. Hall. Unattached  -  The Andrew Sharpshooters.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>THIRD DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Brigadier-General Alexander Hays, commanding.</item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Colonel Samuel S. Carroll, commanding; 
4th Ohio, Lieut.-Col. James H. Godman; 8th Ohio, Lieut.-Col. Franklin 
Sawyer; 14th Indiana, Col. John Coons; 7th West Virginia, Col. Joseph Snyder. </item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Colonel Thos. A. Smyth, commanding; 14th 
Connecticut, Maj. J. T. Ellis; 10th New York, Maj. J. F. Hopper; 
108th New York, Col. C. J. Powers; 12th New Jersey, Maj. J. T. Hill; 
1st Delaware, Lieut.-Col. Edward P. Harris.</item>
            <item>Third Brigade  -  Colonel Geo. L. Willard, commanding; 
39th New York, Lieut.-Col. Jas. G. Hughes; 111th New York, 
Col. Clinton D. McDougall; 125th New York, Lieut.-Col. L. Crandall; 
126th New York, Col. E. Sherrell.</item>
            <pb id="robs174" n="174"/>
            <item>Artillery Brigade  -  Captain J. G. Hazzard, commanding; 
Battery B, 1st New York, Capt. Jas. McK. Rorty; Battery B, 1st Rhode 
Island, Lieut. T. Frederick Brown; Battery A, 1st Rhode Island, 
Lieut. Wm. A. Arnold; Battery I, 1st United States, Lieut. G. A. Woodruff; 
Battery A, 4th United States, Lieut. A. H. Cushing<corr>.</corr>
</item>
            <item>Cavalry Squadron  -  Captain Riley Johnson, 
commanding; Companies D and K, 6th New York.</item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">Third Corps  -  Major-General Daniel E. Sickles.</hi>
          </p>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>FIRST DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Major-General David B. Birney.</item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Brigadier-General C. K. Graham; 
57th Pennsylvania, Col. Peter Sides; 63d Pennsylvania, Lieut.-Col. 
John A. Danks; 68th Pennsylvania, Col. A. H. Tippin; 105th 
Pennsylvania, Col. Calvin A. Craig; 114th Pennsylvania, Lieut.-Col. 
Fred. K Cavada; 141st Pennsylvania, Col. H. J. Madill. (Note. - 
The 2d New Hampshire, 3d Maine, 7th and 8th New Jersey, also 
formed part of Graham line on the 2d.)</item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Brigadier-General J. H. H. Ward; 1st 
United States Sharpshooters, Col. H. Berdan; 4th Maine, 
Col Elijah Walker; 2d United States Sharpshooters, Maj. H. H. 
Stoughton; 3d Maine, Col. M. B. Lakeman; 20th Indiana, Col. 
John Wheeler; 99th Pennsylvania, Major John W. Moore; 86th 
New York Lieut.-Col. Benjamin Higgins; 124th New York, Col.A. Van Horn Ellis. </item>
            <item>Third Brigade  -  Colonel Philip R. DeTrobriand,
<pb id="robs175" n="175"/>
commanding; 3d Michigan, Col. Byron R. Pierce; 5th Michigan,
 Lieut.-Col. John Pulford; 40th New York, Col. Thos. W. Eagan; 
17th Maine, Lieut.-Col. Chas. B. Merrill; 110th Pennsylvania,
 Lieut.-Col. D. M. Jones.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>SECOND DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Brigadier-General Andrew A. Humphreys.</item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Joseph B. Carr; 
1st Massachusetts, Col. N. B. McLaughlin; 11th Massachusetts, 
Lieut.-Col. Porter D. Tripp; 16th Massachusetts, Lieut.-Col. Waldo 
Merriam; 26th Pennsylvania, Capt. Geo. W. Tomlinson; 11th 
New Jersey, Col. Robert McAllister, 84th Pennsylvania
 (not engaged), Lieut.-Col. Milton Opp; 12th New Hampshire, 
Capt. J. F. Langley.</item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Colonel Wm. R. Brewster, 
commanding; 70th New York (1st Excelsior), Maj. Daniel Mahen; 
71st New York (2d Excelsior), Col. Henry L. Potter; 72d New York 
(3d Excelsior), Col. Wm. O. Stevens; 73d New York (4th Excelsior), 
Maj. M. W. Burns; 74th New York (5th Excelsior), Lieut.-Col. Thomas 
Holt; 120th New York, Lieut.-Col. Cornelius D. Westbrook.</item>
            <item>Third Brigade  -  Colonel George C. Burling, 
commanding; 5th New Jersey, Col. W. J. Sewell; 6th New 
Jersey, Lieut.-Col. S. R. Gilkyson; 7th New Jersey, Col. L. R. 
Francine; 8th New Jersey, Col. John Ramsey; 115th Pennsylvania, 
Lieut.-Col. J. P. Dunne; 2d New Hampshire, Col. E. L. Bailey.</item>
            <item>Artillery Brigade  -  Captain Geo. E. Randolph, 
commanding; Battery E, 1st Rhode Island, Lieut. J. K. Bucklyn; 
Battery B, 1st New Jersey, Capt. A. J. Clark; Battery D, 1st New 
Jersey, Capt. Geo. T. Woodbury; Battery K, 4th United States, 
Lieut. F. W. Seeley, Battery D, 1st New York, Capt. Geo. B. 
Winslow; 4th New York, Capt. Jas. E. Smith.</item>
          </list>
          <pb id="robs176" n="176"/>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">Fifth Corps  -  Maj.-Gen. George
Sykes, Commanding.</hi>
          </p>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>FIRST DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Brigadier-General James Barnes, commanding.</item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Colonel W. S. Tilton, commanding; 
18th Massachusetts, Col. Joseph Hayes; 22d Massachusetts, 
Lieut.-Col. Thomas Sherman, Jr.; 118th Pennsylvania, Col. Chas. 
M. Prevost; 1st Michigan, Col. Ira C. Abbott.</item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Colonel J. B. Sweitzer, commanding; 
9th Massachusetts, Col. Patrick R. Guiney; 32d Massachusetts, 
Col. Geo. L. Prescott; 4th Michigan, Col. Hamson H. Jeffords; 
62d Pennsylvania, Lieut.-Col. James C. Hill.</item>
            <item>Third Brigade  -  Colonel Strong Vincent, commanding; 
20th Maine, Col. Joshua L. Chamberlain; 44th New York, 
Col. James C. Rice; 83d Pennsylvania, Maj. Wm. H. Lamont; 
16th Michigan, Lieut.-Col. N. E. Welch.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>SECOND DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Brigadier-General Romayn B. Ayres, commanding. </item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Colonel Hannibal Day, 6th United States
 Infantry, commanding; 3d United States Infantry, Capt. H. W. 
Freedley; 4th United States Infantry, Capt. J. W. Adams; 6th 
United States Infantry, Capt. Levi C. Bootes; 12th United States 
Infantry, Capt. Thomas S. Dunn; 14th United States Infantry, Maj. G. R. Giddings.</item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Colonel Sidney Burbank, 2d 
United States Infantry, commanding; 2d United States Infantry, 
Maj. A. T. Lee; 7th United States Infantry, Capt. D. P. Hancock; 
10th United States Infantry, Capt. William Clinton; 11th United 
States Infantry, Maj. DeL. Floyd Jones; 17th United
States Infantry, Lieut.-Col. Durrell Green.</item>
            <pb id="robs177" n="177"/>
            <item>Third Brigade  -  Brigadier-General S. H. Weed; 140th 
New York, Col. Patrick H. O'Rorcke; 146th New York, Col. Kenner 
Garrard; 91st Pennsylvania, Lieut.-Col. J. H. Sinex; 155th 
Pennsylvania, Lieut.-Col. John H. Cain.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>THIRD DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Brigadier-General S. Wiley Crawford.</item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Colonel William McCandless, commanding; 
1st Pennsylvania Reserves, Col. W. C. Talley; 2d Pennsylvania 
Reserves, Lieut.-Col. George A. Woodward; 6th Pennsylvania 
Reserves, Col. Wellington H. Ent; 11th Pennsylvania Reserves, 
Col. S. M. Jackson; 1st Rifles (Bucktails), Col. Charles J. Taylor.</item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Colonel Joseph W. Fisher, commanding; 
5th Pennsylvania Reserves, Lieut.-Col. George Dare; 9th Pennsylvania 
Reserves, Lieut.-Col. James McK. Snodgrass; 10th Pennsylvania 
Reserves, Col. A. J. Warner; 12th Pennsylvania Reserves, 
Col. M. D. Hardin.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>ARTILLERY BRIGADE.</head>
            <item>Captain A. P. Martin, commanding.</item>
            <item>Battery D  -  5th United States, Lieut. Charles E. Hazlett.</item>
            <item>Battery I  -  5th United States, Lieut. Leonard Martin.</item>
            <item>Battery C  -  1st New York, Capt. Albert Barnes.</item>
            <item>Battery L  -  1st Ohio, Capt. N. C. Gibbs.</item>
            <item>Battery C  -  Massachusetts, Capt. A. P. Martin.</item>
            <item>Provost Guard  -  Capt. W. H. Ryder; Companies E and D, 12th New York.</item>
          </list>
          <pb id="robs178" n="178"/>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">Sixth Corps  -  Major-General John Sedgwick.</hi>
          </p>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>FIRST DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Brigadier-General H. G. Wright, commanding.</item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Brigadier-General A. T. A. Torbert; 
1st New Jersey, Lieut.-Col. William Henry, Jr., 2d New Jersey, 
Col. Samuel L. Buck; 3d New Jersey,
Col. Henry W. Brown; 15th New Jersey Col Wm. H. Penrose.</item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Brigadier-General J. J. Bartlett; 
5th Maine, Col. Clarke S. Edwards; 121st New York, Col. 
Emory Upton; 95th Pennsylvania, Lieut.-Col.
Edward Carroll; 96th Pennsylvania, Lieut.-Col. Wm. 
H. Lessig.</item>
            <item>Third Brigade  -  Brigadier-General D. A. Russell; 
6th Maine, Col. Hiram Burnham; 49th Pennsylvania, 
Col. Wm. H. Irvin; 119th Pennsylvania, Col. P. C. Ellmaker; 
5th Wisconsin, Col. Thos. S. Allen.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>SECOND DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Brigadier-General A. P. Howe, commanding.</item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Col. L. A. Grant, commanding; 
2d Vermont, Col. J. H. Walbridge; 3d Vermont, Col T. O. Seaver; 
4th Vermont, Col. E. H. Stoughton; 5th Vermont, Lieut.-Col. John R. 
Lewis; 6th Vermont, Lieut.-Col. Elisha L.
Barney.</item>
            <item>Third Brigade  -  Brigadier-General T. A. Neill; 7th Maine, 
Lieut.-Col. Seldon Connor; 49th New York, Col. D. D. Bidwell; 77th 
New York, Col. J. B. McKean; 43d New York, Col. B. F. Baker; 
61st Pennsylvania, Maj. Geo. W. Dawson.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>THIRD DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Brigadier-General Frank Wheaton, commanding.</item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Alexander Shaler;
 65th New York, Col. J. E. Hamblin; 67th New York,
<pb id="robs179" n="179"/>
Col. Nelson Cross; 122d New York, Lieut.-Col. A. W. Dwight; 
23d Pennsylvania, Lieut.-Col. J. F. Glenn; 82d Pennsylvania, 
Col. Isaac Bassett.</item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Col. H. L. Eustis, commanding; 
7th Massachusetts, Lieut.-Col. Franklin P. Harlow; 10th 
Massachusetts, Lieut.-Col. Jefford M. Decker; 37th 
Massachusetts, Col. Oliver Edwards; 2d Rhode Island, 
Col. Horatio Rogers.</item>
            <item>Third Brigade  -  Col. David I. Nevin, 62d New York, 
commanding; 62d New York, Lieut.-Col. Theodore P. Hamilton; 
102d Pennsylvania, Col. John W. Patterson; 93d Pennsylvania, 
Col. Jas. M. McCarter; 98th Pennsylvania,
Maj. John B. Kohler; 139th Pennsylvania, Lieut.-Col. 
Wm. H. Moody.</item>
            <item>Artillery Brigade  -  Col. C. M. Tompkins, commanding; 
Battery A, 1st Massachusetts, Capt. W. H. McCartney; Battery D, 
2d United States, Lieut. E. B. Williston; Battery F, 5th United States,
 Lieut. Leonard Martin; Battery G, 2d United States, Lieut. 
John H. Butler; Battery C, 1st Rhode Island, Capt. Richard Waterman; 
Battery G, 1st Rhode Island, Capt. Geo. W. Adams; 
1st New York, Capt. Andrew Cowan; 3d New York, 
Capt. Wm. A. Harn.</item>
            <item>Cavalry Detachment  -  Capt. Wm. L. Craft, 
commanding; Company H, 1st Pennsylvania; Company L, 
1st New Jersey. </item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">Eleventh Corps  -
Major-General Oliver O. Howard, Commanding.</hi>
          </p>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>FIRST DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Brigadier-General Francis C. Barlow, commanding. </item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Col. Leopold Von Gilsa, commanding; 
41st New York, Lieut.-Col. D. Von Einsiedel; 54th New York, 
Col. Eugene A. Kezley; 68th New York, Col. Gotthilf Bourny 
de Ivernois; 53d Pennsylvania, Col. Charles Glanz.</item>
            <pb id="robs180" n="180"/>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Adelbert 
Ames; 17th Connecticut, Lieut.-Col. Douglass Fowler; 25th 
Ohio, Lieut.-Col. Jeremiah Williams; 75th Ohio, Col A. L. 
Harris; 107th Ohio, Capt. John M. Lutz.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>SECOND DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Brigadier-General A. Von Steinwehr, commanding.</item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Col. Charles R. Coster, 134th 
New York, commanding; 27th Pennsylvania, Lieut.-Col. 
Lorenz. Cantador; 73d Pennsylvania, Capt. Daniel F. 
Kelley; 134th New York, Lieut.-Col. Allan H. Jackson; 
154th New York,
Col. P. H. Jones.</item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Col. Orlando Smith, commanding; 
33d Massachusetts, Lieut.-Col. Adin B. Underwood; 136th 
New York, Col. James Wood, Jr.; 55th Ohio, Col. Chas. B. 
Gambee; 73d Ohio, Lieut.-Col. Richard Long.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>THIRD DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Major-General Carl Schurz, commanding.</item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Brigadier-General A. Von 
Schimmeepfennig, commanding; 45th New York, Col. 
Geo. Von Arnsburg; 157th New York, Col. Philip P. 
Brown, Jr.; 74th Pennsylvania, Col. Adolph Von 
Hartung; 61st Ohio,
Col. S. J. McGroarty; 82d Illinois, Col. J. Hecker.</item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Col. Waldimer Kryzanowske,
 commanding; 58th New York, Lieut.-Col. August Otto; 
119th New York, Col. John T. Lockman; 75th Pennsylvania, 
Col. Francis Mahler; 82d Ohio, Col. James S. Robson; 
26th Wisconsin, Col. Wm. H. Jacobs.</item>
            <item>Artillery Brigade  -  Maj. Thos. W. Osburn, commanding; 
Battery I, 1st New York, Capt. Michael Wiedrick; Battery I, 
1st Ohio, Capt. Hubert Dilger; Battery K, 1st Ohio, Capt. 
Lewis Heckman; Battery G, 4th United States, Lieut. Bayard 
Wilkeson; 13th New York, Lieut. William Wheeler.</item>
          </list>
          <pb id="robs181" n="181"/>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">Twelfth Corps  -  Brigadier-General Alpheus S. 
Williams, Commanding.</hi>
          </p>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>FIRST DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Brigadier-General Thomas H. Ruger, commanding. </item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Col. Archibald L. McDougall; 5th 
Connecticut, Col. Warren W. Packer; 20th Connecticut, 
Lieut.-Col. Wm. B. Wooster; 123d New York, Col. A. L. 
McDougall; 145th New York, Col. E. L. Price; 46th 
Pennsylvania, Col. James L. Selfridge; 3d Maryland, 
Col. J. M. Sudsburg.</item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Henry H. 
Lockwood; 150th New York, Col. John H. Ketcham; 
1st Maryland (P. H. B.), Col. Wm. P. Maulsby; 
1st Maryland (E. S.), Col. James Wallace.</item>
            <item>Third Brigade  -  Col. Silas Calgrove, commanding; 
2d Massachusetts, Col. Chas R. Mudge; 107th New York, 
Col. Miron M. Crane; 13th New Jersey, Col. Ezra A. Carman; 
27th Indiana, Lieut.-Col. John R. Fesler; 3d Wisconsin, 
Lieut.-Col. Martin Flood.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>SECOND DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Brigadier-General John W. Geary, commanding.</item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Col. Charles Candy, 66th Ohio, 
commanding; 28th Pennsylvania, Capt. John Flynn; 
117th Pennsylvania, Lieut.-Col. Ario Pardee, Jr.; 5th 
Ohio, Col. John H. Patrick; 7th Ohio, Col. Wm. R. 
Creighton; 28th Ohio, Capt. W. F. Stevens; 66th Ohio, 
Lieut.-Col. Eugene Powell.</item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  1st Col. Geo. A. Cobham; 
2d Brig.-Gen. Thos. L. Kane; 29th Pennsylvania, 
Col. William Rickards; 109th Pennsylvania, Capt. 
Frederick L. Gimber; 111th Pennsylvania, Lieut.-Col. 
Thomas M. Walker.</item>
            <item>Third Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Geo. S. 
Greene; 60th New York, Col. Abel Godard; 78th New York,
<pb id="robs182" n="182"/>
Lieut.-Col. Herbert Von Hammerstein; 102d New York, 
Lieut.-Col. James C. Lane; 137th New York, Col. David 
Ireland; 149th New York, Col. Henry A. Barnum.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>ARTILLERY BRIGADE.</head>
            <item>Lieutenant E. D. Muhlenberg, commanding.</item>
            <item>Battery F, 4th United States, Lieut. S. T. Rugg; 
Battery K, 5th United States, Lieut. D. H. Kinsie; Battery 
M, 1st New York, Lieut. Chas. E. Winegar; Knapp's 
Pennsylvania Battery, Lieut. Charles Atwell. </item>
            <item>Headquarter Guard  -  Battalion, 10th Maine.</item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">Cavalry Corps  -  Major-General Alfred 
Pleasanton, Commanding.</hi>
          </p>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>FIRST DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Brigadier-General John Buford, commanding.</item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Col. William Gamble, 8th Illinois, 
commanding; 8th New York, Col. Benjamin F. Davis; 
8th Illinois, Lieut.-Col. D. R. Clendenin; 2 squadrons 12th 
Illinois, Col. Amass Voss; 3 squadrons 3d Indiana, 
Col. Geo. H. Chapman.</item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Col. Thos. C. Devin, 
6th New York, commanding; 6th New York, Lieut.-CoI. 
Wm. H. Crocker; 9th New York, Col. William Sackett; 17th
Pennsylvania, Col. J. H. Kellogg; 3d Virginia (detachment).</item>
            <item>Reserve Brigade  -  Brigadier-General Wesley 
Merritt; 1st United States, Capt. R. S. C. Lord; 2d United States, 
Capt. T. F. Rodenbough; 5th United States, Capt. 
J. W. Mason; 6th United States, Maj. S. H. Starr, Capt.
G. C. Cram; 6th Pennsylvania, Maj. Jas. H. Hazletine.</item>
          </list>
          <pb id="robs183" n="183"/>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>SECOND DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Brigadier-General D. McM. Gregg, commanding.</item>
            <item>(Headquarter Guard, Company A, 1st Ohio.)</item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Col. J. B. McIntosh, commanding; 
1st New Jersey, Maj. M. H. Beamont; 1st Pennsylvania, 
Col. John P. Taylor; 3d Pennsylvania, Lieut.-Col. Edward S. 
Jones; 1st Maryland, Lieut.-Col. James M. Deems; 
1st Massachusetts, at Headquarters, 6th Corps.</item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Col. Pennock Huey, commanding; 
2d New York, 4th New York, 8th Pennsylvania, 6th Ohio.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>THIRD DIVISION.</head>
            <item>Brigadier-General Judson Kilpatrick, commanding.</item>
            <item>(Headquarter Guard, Company C, 1st Ohio.)</item>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Brigadier-General E. J. Farnsworth; 
5th New York, Maj. John Hammond; 18th Pennsylvania, 
Lieut.-Col. Wm. P. Brinton; 1st Vermont, Col. Edward D. 
Sawyer; 1st West Virginia, Col. H. P. Richmond.</item>
            <item>Second Bridage  -  Brigadier-General Geo. A. 
Custer; 1st Michigan, Col. Chas. H. Town; 5th Michigan, 
Col. Russell A. Alger; 6th Michigan, Col. George Gray; 
7th Michigan, Col. Wm. D. Mann.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>HORSE ARTILLERY.</head>
            <item>First Brigade  -  Capt. John M. Robertson, 
commanding; Batteries B and L, 2d United States, 
Lieut. Edward Heaton; Battery M, 2d United States, 
Lieut. A. C. M. Pennington; Battery E, 4th United States, 
Lieut. S. S. Elder; 6th New York, Lieut. Joseph W. Martin; 
9th Michigan, Capt. J. J. Daniels; Battery C, 3d United 
States, Lieut. Wm. D. Fuller.</item>
            <item>Second Brigade  -  Capt. John C. Tidball, 
commanding; Batteries G and E, 1st United States, Capt. 
A. M. Randal; Battery K, 1st United States, Capt. Wm. M.
<pb id="robs184" n="184"/>
Graham; Battery A, 2d United States, Lieut. John Calef; 
Battery C, 3d United States.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>ARTILLERY RESERVE.</head>
            <item>Brigadier-General R. O. Tyler.</item>
            <item>First Regular Brigade  -  Capt. D. R. Ransom, commanding; 
Battery H, 1st United States, Lieut. C. P. Eakin; Batteries F and K, 
3d United States, Lieut. J. C. Turnbull; Battery C, 4th United States, 
Lieut. Evan Thomas; Battery C, 5th United States, Lieut. G. V. Weier.</item>
            <item>First Voluntary Brigade  -  Lieut.-Col. F. McGilvery, 
commanding; 15th New York, Capt. Patrick Hart; Independent 
Battery, Pennsylvania, Capt. R. B. Ricketts; 5th Massachusetts, 
Capt. C. A. Phillips, 9th Massachusetts,
Capt. John Bigelow.</item>
            <item>Second Volunteer Brigade  -  Capt. E. D. Taft, commanding; 
Batteries B and M, 1st Connecticut, 5th New York, Capt. Elijah D. 
Taft; 2d Connecticut, Lieut. John W. Sterling.</item>
            <item>Third Volunteer Brigade  -  Capt. Jas. F. Huntington, 
commanding; Batteries F and G, 1st Pennsylvania, Capt. R. B. 
Ricketts; Battery H, 1st Ohio, Capt. Jas. F. Huntington; Battery A, 
1st New Hampshire, Capt. F. M. Edgell; Battery C, 1st West 
Virginia, Capt. Wallace Hill.</item>
            <item>Fourth Volunteer Brigade  -  Capt. R. H. Fitzhugh, 
commanding; Battery B, 1st New York, Capt. James McRorty; 
Battery G, 1st New York, Capt. Albert M. Ames; Battery K, 
1st New York (11th Battery attached), Capt. R. H. Fitzhugh; 
Battery A, 1st Maryland, Capt. James H. Rigby; Battery A, 
1st New Jersey, Lieut. Augustin N. Parsons; 6th Maine, 
Lieut. Edwin B. Dow.</item>
            <item>Train Guard  -  Major Charles Ewing, commanding; 
4th New Jersey Infantry.</item>
            <pb id="robs185" n="185"/>
            <item>Headquarter Guard  -  Capt. J. C. Fuller, commanding; 
Battery C, 32d Massachusetts.</item>
          </list>
          <p>
            <hi rend="italics">Detachments at Headquarters, Army of the Potomac, 
During the Battle of Gettysburg, Under Orders of the Provost 
Marshal General:</hi>
          </p>
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Brigadier-General M. R. Patrick, commanding; 93d New York, 
8th United States, 1st Massachusetts Cavalry, 2d Pennsylvania Cavalry, 
Batteries E and I, 6th Pennsylvania Cavalry, Detachment Regular 
Cavalry; United States Engineer Battalion, Capt. Geo. H. Mendill, 
commanding.</item>
            <item>Guards and Orderlies  -  Capt. D. P. Mann, commanding;
Independent Company Oneida Cavalry.</item>
          </list>
          <p>Taking it for granted that the regiments averaged about the 
same number of men in each army, which we can reasonably do, 
perhaps the following lists will better enable the reader to 
comprehend the tremendous force brought to bear against 
each other in that battle:</p>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>ARMY OF NORTHERN VIRGINIA.</head>
            <item>States. .....Infantry Reg'ts. .....Calvary.
.....Artillery. .....Total.</item>
            <item>Alabama,.....13.....  .....2.....15</item>
            <item>South Carolina,.....14.....2.....5.....21</item>
            <item>North Carolina,.....41.....4.....4.....49</item>
            <item>Georgia,.....33.....3.....7.....43</item>
            <item>Florida,.....3.....  .....  .....3</item>
            <item>Louisiana,.....10.....  .....7.....17</item>
            <item>Mississippi,.....11.....  .....1.....12</item>
            <item>Virginia,.....49.....20.....37.....106</item>
            <item>Maryland,.....1.....1.....4.....6</item>
            <item>Arkansas,.....1.....  .....  .....1</item>
            <item>Texas,.....3.....  .....  .....3</item>
            <item>Tennessee,.....3.....  .....  .....3</item>
            <item>.....182.....30.....67.....279</item>
          </list>
          <pb id="robs186" n="186"/>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>IN THE ARMY OF THE POTOMAC, AT GETTYSBURG.</head>
            <item>States.  .....Infantry.  .....Cavalry.  .....Artillery.  .....Total.</item>
            <item>Connecticut,.....5.....  .....3.....8</item>
            <item>Delaware,.....2.....  .....  .....2</item>
            <item>Illinois,.....1.....2.....  .....3</item>
            <item>Indiana,.....5.....1.....  .....6</item>
            <item>Maine,.....10.....1.....3.....14</item>
            <item>Maryland,.....3.....2.....1.....6</item>
            <item>Massachusetts,.....19.....2.....4.....25</item>
            <item>Michigan,.....7.....4.....1.....12</item>
            <item>Minnesota,.....1.....  .....  .....1</item>
            <item>New Jersey,.....12.....1.....2.....15</item>
            <item>New Hampshire,.....3.....  .....1.....4</item>
            <item>New York,.....69.....8.....15.....92</item>
            <item>Ohio, .....13.....1.....4.....18</item>
            <item>Pennsylvania,.....68.....10.....7.....85</item>
            <item>Rhode Island,.....1.....  .....5.....6</item>
            <item>Vermont,.....10.....1.....  .....11</item>
            <item>West Virginia,.....1.....2.....1.....4</item>
            <item>Wisconsin,.....6.....  .....  .....6</item>
            <item>U. S. Regulars,.....13.....4.....25.....42</item>
            <item>.....249.....39.....72.....360</item>
          </list>
          <p>If nothing else can be found in my little book to 
recommend it, these, mostly official, and
 <hi rend="italics">all</hi> as nearly accurate
 as can be gotten after twenty-five
years, ought to give it a place in every house in the 
United States.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>