<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://docsouth.unc.edu/dtds/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % external-entities SYSTEM "./extEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY % internal-entities SYSTEM "./intEntities.dtf">
<!ENTITY smithfp SYSTEM "smithfp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY smithtp SYSTEM "smithtp.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
<!ENTITY smith98 SYSTEM "smith98.jpg" NDATA jpeg>
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="" status="new">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><emph>Biography of Rev. David Smith of the A. M. E. 
Church; Being a Complete History, Embracing over Sixty Years' Labor in the 
Advancement of the Redeemer's Kingdom on Earth.</emph><emph>Including “The 
History of the Origin and Development of Wilberforce University”:</emph>
Electronic Edition.</title>
        <author>Smith, Rev. David, b. 1784</author>
        <author>Payne, Daniel Alexander, 1811-1893</author>
        <funder>Funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities
 supported the electronic publication of this title.</funder>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text scanned (OCR) by</resp>
          <name id="cg">Katherine Anderson and Bethany Ronnberg</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Images scanned by</resp>
          <name>Katherine Anderson</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Text encoded by </resp>
          <name id="ns">Lee Ann Morawski  and Natalia Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>First edition, <date>1999</date></edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent>ca.     250K</extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Academic Affairs Library, UNC-CH</publisher>
        <pubPlace>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, </pubPlace>
        <date>1999.</date>
        <availability status="unknown">
          <p>© This work is the property of the University of North Carolina 
at Chapel Hill. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching 
and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the 
text.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="title page"> Biography of Rev. David Smith, of the A. M. E. 
Church Being a Complete History, Embracing over Sixty Years' Labor in the 
Advancement of the Redeemer's Kingdom on Earth.  Including “The History 
of the Origin and Development of Wilberforce University.”</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent> 135     p., ill.</extent>
          <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>Xenia, O.</pubPlace>
            <publisher>The Xenia Gazette Office</publisher>
            <date>1881</date>
            <authority/>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note anchored="yes">Call number    922.7 S645B (Divinity School Library, 
Duke University)</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The electronic edition is a part of the UNC-CH
digitization project, <hi rend="italics">Documenting the American South.</hi></p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>All footnotes are inserted at the point of reference within paragraphs.
 </p>
        <p>Any hyphens occurring in line breaks have been 
removed, and the trailing part of a word has been joined to 
the preceding line.</p>
        <p>All quotation marks, em dashes  and ampersand have been transcribed as
entity references.</p>
        <p>All double right and left quotation marks are encoded as ” and “
respectively.</p>
        <p>All single right and left quotation marks are encoded as ’ and ‘ respectively.</p>
        <p>All em dashes are encoded as —</p>
        <p>Indentation in lines has not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Running titles have not been preserved.</p>
        <p>Spell-check and verification made against printed text using Author/Editor 
(SoftQuad) and Microsoft Word spell check programs.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy id="lcsh">
          <bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings, </title>
<edition>21st edition, 1998</edition></bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="lcsh">
          <list type="simple">
            <item>Smith, David, b. 1784.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Maryland -- Biography.</item>
            <item>African Americans -- Ohio -- Biography.</item>
            <item>African American clergy -- Biography.</item>
            <item>African Methodist Episcopal Church -- Clergy --
Biography.</item>
            <item>African Methodist Episcopal Church -- History -- 19th
centur</item>
            <item>Freedmen -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Slaves -- Maryland -- Biography.</item>
            <item>Wilberforce University -- History -- 19th century.</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2000-04-07, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Celine Noel and Wanda Gunther </name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> revised TEIHeader and created catalog 
record for the electronic edition.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-11-30, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Natalia Smith, </name>
          <resp>project manager, </resp>
        </respStmt>
        <item>finished TEI-conformant encoding and final proofing.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-11-29, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Lee Ann Morawski</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished TEI/SGML encoding</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>1999-11-19, </date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Katherine Anderson and Bethany Ronnberg</name>
          <resp/>
        </respStmt>
        <item> finished scanning (OCR) and proofing.</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div1 type="frontispiece image">
        <p>
          <figure id="frontis" entity="smithfp">
            <p>[Frontispiece Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="title page image">
        <p>
          <figure id="title" entity="smithtp">
            <p>[Title Page Image]</p>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <titlePage>
        <pb id="dsmith1" n="1"/>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">BIOGRAPHY
<lb/>OF
<lb/>REV. DAVID SMITH,
<lb/>OF THE A. M. E. CHURCH
 <lb/>
BEING A COMPLETE HISTORY, EMBRACING OVER
<lb/>SIXTY YEARS' LABOR IN THE ADVANCEMENT
<lb/>OF THE REDEEMER'S
<lb/>KINGDOM ON EARTH.</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="subtitle">INCLUDING
<lb/><hi rend="ITALICS">“The History of the Origin and Development
<lb/>of Wilberforce University.”</hi></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <docImprint><pubPlace>XENIA, O.:</pubPlace>
<publisher>PRINTED AT THE XENIA GAZETTE OFFICE.</publisher>
<docDate>1881.</docDate></docImprint>
      </titlePage>
      <div1 type="contents">
        <pb id="dsmith3" n="3"/>
        <head>CONTENTS</head>
        <list type="simple">
          <item>I. Introduction . . . . . . <ref target="dsmith9" targOrder="U">9</ref></item>
          <item>II. My Redemption . . . . . . <ref target="dsmith13" targOrder="U">13</ref></item>
          <item>III. My Connection with Sharp-street Colored <lb/>
Methodist Church . . . . . . <ref target="dsmith15" targOrder="U">15</ref></item>
          <item>IV. My Life as an Exhorter in the M. E.<lb/>
Church . . . . . .<ref target="dsmith18" targOrder="U">18</ref></item>
          <item>V. My Labors outside of Baltimore . . . . . . <ref target="dsmith21" targOrder="U">21</ref></item>
          <item>VI. My Connection with the A. M. E.<lb/>
Church . . . . . . <ref target="dsmith25" targOrder="U">25</ref></item>
          <item>VII. The Union Formed by the Philadelphia,<lb/>
Baltimore and Show Hill <lb/>Churches . . . . . . <ref target="dsmith31" targOrder="U">31</ref></item>
          <item>VIII. My Ordination to the Order of Deacon<lb/>
and Elder . . . . . . <ref target="dsmith39" targOrder="U">39</ref></item>
          <item>IX. My Labors near Pittsburg . . . . . . <ref target="dsmith55" targOrder="U">55</ref></item>
          <item>X. My Labors in Ohio . . . . . . <ref target="dsmith69" targOrder="U">69</ref></item>
          <item>XI. My First Appointment in Ohio . . . . . . <ref target="dsmith74" targOrder="U">74</ref></item>
          <item>XII. My General Labors . . . . . . <ref target="dsmith82" targOrder="U">82</ref></item>
          <item>XIII. The Return to my Labors in Ohio . . . . . . <ref target="dsmith86" targOrder="U">86</ref></item>
          <item>WILBERFORCE UNIVERSITY . . . . . . <ref target="dsmith99" targOrder="U">99</ref></item>
          <item>Miscellaneous Remarks . . . . . . <ref target="dsmith133" targOrder="U">133</ref></item>
        </list>
      </div1>
      <pb id="dsmith5" n="5"/>
      <div1 type="preface">
        <head>PREFACE.</head>
        <p>The idea of writing and giving the Church and
community the advantage of my experience and
such facts as came under my personal observation
during the many years of labor I have spent in
the A. M. E. Church, has occupied my attention
for years. In the sun-set of my days upon earth 
I am seriously impressed with the duty of publishing 
my life in the form of a history that generations yet 
unborn might know that David Smith lived and labored for the
advancement of the Redeemer's Kingdom on earth, and
that my life was spent as a sacrifice (according
to my limited ability) to better the condition of
<pb id="dsmith6" n="6"/>
my fellow-man. Just before the civil war I undertook
the task of having my life published. I had
it all prepared for the <hi rend="italics">press</hi> and placed in the
hands of a white brother to have it published.
This dear brother was then in the M. E. Book
Concern at Cincinnati, and when I heard from
him, he informed me the manuscript was misplaced.
I then became very much discouraged
and gave up the notion of any further attempt of
publishing my life, until last fall, September 1880,
at the session of the Ohio Annual Conference,
which met in Columbus, Ohio, on the 13th of
September, 1880. In the evening, the Semi-<sic corr="Centenary">Centinary</sic>
Celebration of the Ohio Conference was 
held in St. Paul's A. M. E. church, Columbus, O.
I was called upon to say something in regard to
my connection with the A. M. E. Church and my
labors in the Ohio Annual Conference. I had
stated imperfectly some of my labors in the Church,
and after the Conference closed its session, the
<pb id="dsmith7" n="7"/>
young pastor, Rev. John Coleman, who was appointed
to the Xenia station by Bishop James A.
Shorter, called upon me and stated to me how
much he was interested in my remarks. He said
he thought the Church and community ought to
have the advantage of my history before I departed
this life. I carefully considered the matter,
and finally concluded I would publish my biography
if he would assist me in its preparation. He
agreed and inside of four months I present this
imperfect little book.</p>
        <p>I hope it may be interesting, useful, and find
favor in the eyes of the Church and community,
as one of the last acts of my life on earth. And
when my body sleeps in the silent grave and my
spirit is at rest, I trust this book may speak for me.</p>
        <signed>THE AUTHOR.</signed>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div1 type="text">
        <pb id="dsmith9" n="9"/>
        <head>THE BIOGRAPHY<lb/>
OF THE<lb/>
<hi rend="italics">Rev. David Smith.</hi></head>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
          <p>I was born March 10th, 1784, nine miles from Baltimore,
Baltimore county, Maryland; on Major Rutter's farm. I was
sold from this place to a Spanish Consul, by the name of
John Burnibue. I lived with Mr. Burnibue until I was eight or
nine years of age. The family were all Roman Catholics
except Mr. Burnibue's wife's sister, whose name was
Matilda White. She was a young lady possessed of fine
feelings and great sympathy. The family of Mrs. Burnibue
was in humble circumstances in life. Miss Matilda White
obtained the position of house-keeper for Mr. Burnibue;
she had the entire care of the household affairs, and thereby
releasing Mrs. Burnibue of the house duties and domestic
cares, thus allowing her
<pb id="dsmith10" n="10"/>
to become the equal companion of Mr. Burnibue
and his associates. I was entrusted entirely to the
care of Miss Matilda White, and her fine feelings
and great sympathy always kept her above prejudice
and partiality, hence she treated me as
kindly as she did the rest of the family.</p>
          <p>The Catholics were then, as they are now, very
strict and devoted to their religious faith. One of
the rules of the family was that I should attend
the Catholic church with the children of the
family; this we did whenever the weather and
health <sic corr="permitted">permited</sic>—there was no excuse for us children.
I remember the method by which we were
punished for our misbehavior, it was after this
manner:</p>
          <p>She seldom ever whipped us, but would shut us
up in the closet and tell us how the Saviour was
displeased with our bad conduct, and thus make
us feel very penitent for our sins.</p>
          <p>While I was attending the Catholic church I
was very much charmed with the organ and the
the delightful music rendered Sabbath after Sabbath,
and from that day until now, I have ever
been a lover of music, although I am not talented
in this useful and interesting art.</p>
          <p>Now, I wish to mention an important fact connected
with my liberation. Miss Matilda White
<pb id="dsmith11" n="11"/>
was uncommonly poor, and at the time of the rebuilding
of the Episcopal church in Charles
street, Baltimore, Parson Ben (so called by the
community in general at that time) instituted a
lottery for the benefit of the Church. Miss Matilda
White, thinking a great deal of me, gave me
five dollars with which to purchase a ticket for her.
She drew $12,000 with it, and for me, her luck
was my temporal salvation, as you shall soon see.
Shortly after Miss Matilda drew this fortune, I
embraced the Christian religion; then I began to
labor under many difficulties from the family on
account of my religious profession. No one
knows the bitter feeling a devoted Catholic has
towards a Protestant, but he who has experienced
it as I did in the case under consideration.</p>
          <p>My warm affections, just renewed by the Spirit
of God, inclined me toward the Methodists, but
the very name of a Methodist was obnoxious to a
Roman Catholic, hence my afflictions became sore
and many; it appeared to me that Satan himself
was turned upon me and that I would certainly
be destroyed. All the family became my bitter
oppressors and persecutors, except Miss Matilda
White. Mr. Burnibue was so enraged against me
that he determined to sell me to a Georgian, which
to a poor slave was the worst form of punishment. 
<pb id="dsmith12" n="12"/>
I have never had such feelings before nor
since. I became so disturbed about my situation,
I plead with God day and night, for my deliverance.
I could heartily join the Prophet and say :
“O, that my head were waters and mine eyes a
fountain of tears.” For I thought I certainly
would grieve and cry myself to death. The tears
I shed, flowed so constantly that there were two
briny channels made visible upon my cheeks.
Right here I promised God, if he would interpose
and deliver me from this affliction, I would be an
humble, faithful and obedient servant all the days
of my life. I used as a plea the power he had
exercised in freeing me from sin. I knew very
well, if God was able to deliver me from the corrupt
influence of the world and the power of
Satan, that he was able to deliver me from this
slave-holder. Yet I was like many others, I did not
see by what method he would secure my deliverance.
Still with child-like simplicity I trusted
him, though I did not understand then as I do
now, the sentiment or that good hymn:
<q direct="unspecified"><lg type="verse"><l>“Ye fearful saints, fresh courage take,</l><l>The clouds ye so much dread,</l><l>Are big with mercy and shall break</l><l>In blessings on your head.”</l></lg></q></p>
          <p>I was advertised for sale in the Baltimore
papers, and this kind of statement was made:</p>
          <pb id="dsmith13" n="13"/>
          <p>“No one can buy him but a Georgian.”</p>
          <p>It seemed that nothing would satisfy Mr. Burnibue's
hatred and bitter feeling against me, but
my shipment to Georgia. Still I waited the appointed
time until my deliverer came. The Lord
moved in a mysterious way, his wonders to
perform. I now close this chapter and hasten to
my mysterious redemption.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER II.<lb/>
MY REDEMPTION.</head>
          <p>Miss Matilda White, unbeknown to me, had
skillfully arranged to defeat Mr. John Burnibue's
evil designs, and, therefore, consulted a Georgia
slave-buyer and provided him with the means and
instructed him to buy me for her. Her intention
to set me free was kept a profound secret from
Mr. Burnibue, and, also, from the Georgian; for
if it had been known to either or both, the plan
could not have been worked so successfully as it
was, for Mr. Burnibue would not have permitted
her to buy me; and, just to think, this wise and
blessed woman never even hinted to me her intention
to set me free. This, I regarded as a wise
step in her, for if I had known it, I might have
<pb id="dsmith14" n="14"/>
been overjoyed and revealed her plan and might
have been the means of her being defeated. I
was sold at home between nine and ten o'clock in
the morning (the precise date unknown). As I
came down stairs from Mr. Burnibue's office (his
private office) I met Miss Matilda White, and the
Georgian handed her a bill of sale for me, and
immediately she took me to a lawyer's office (Mr.
Heath's). He wrote my free papers, and, in company
with Miss Matilda White, the lawyer went
to the court-house and had them recorded. This
was on the day I was sold, and I received a copy
of the same.</p>
          <p>I said, now I am free—both soul and body.
My heart was so rejoiced I did not know hardly
what to say, yet I said, “Glory to God in the
highest.” Here, with gratitude and thankfulness,
I made many promises to God which, in the long
line of my life, have been motives to noble enterprises
for God and humanity. I consecrated myself
to God and my whole life to better the condition
of my people. Ever since then, the cause of
the Lord has prospered in the hands of his humble
servant, of which I shall speak more elaborately
in the future.</p>
          <lg>
            <l>“His purposes will ripen fast,</l>
            <l>Unfolding every hour,</l>
            <l>The bud may have a bitter taste,</l>
            <l>But sweet will be the flower.”</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <pb id="dsmith15" n="15"/>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER III.<lb/>
MY CONNECTION WITH SHARP-STREET<lb/>
COLORED METHODIST CHURCH.</head>
          <p>According to the rules and discipline of the
Church, I joined on six month's probation. As
nearly as I can recollect, I was about twelve years
old. The Rev. Nasey Schin was then pastor of
Sharp and Light street Churches, the only colored
Churches in Baltimore at that time. When my
probation was out (the six months) I was then
received into full membership, and very soon after
I requested the Rev. Schin to give me a permit to
hold prayer-meetings in private houses, which he
consented to do.</p>
          <p>I perceived the Lord had found me standing in
the market place idle and said unto me, “Go work
in my vineyard, and whatever is right I will pay
thee.” And, thus being moved by the Spirit of
the Lord, I commenced my labors for the Lord
Jesus. I held prayer-meetings in different parts
of the city, telling my Christian experience and
how God had delivered me from the devil and
slavery.</p>
          <p>A great revival followed my humble efforts, so
much so the people and pastors of Baltimore became
<pb id="dsmith16" n="16"/>
so intensely interested in my success, that I
became a public talk, both from the pulpits and also
in the streets of the city. This deep interest in
me and my success continued for a considerable
while, and both white and colored people became
my friends and had the greatest respect for me.</p>
          <p>But, alas! a cloud of opposition arose. I perceived
that I was not going to have it pleasant all
the while. Soon my own people became jealous
of me and my work, thinking and saying that I
was too young to be allowed to carry on these
meetings; but the white people thought differently,
for many of their servants were professing the
Christian religion at these meetings and, consequently,
made better servants; hence, they spoke
well of me and did all they could to protect and
enhance my efforts.</p>
          <p>At this time there were no licensed preachers
among my people. The highest position to which
the colored ministry attained in the M. E. Church
was to an Exhorter. These were spiritual overseers
of the black sheep of the Redeemer's fold.
Whenever the dark-skinned sheep went astray, the
colored Exhorters reported them to the Quarterly
Conference and the Elders of the M. E. Church,
and the Elders and Conference would deal with
them according to their offense, and would often
<pb id="dsmith17" n="17"/>
turn these colored people out of the Church. The
colored people had several Exhorters in the city of
Baltimore at that time.</p>
          <p>There were Fathers Dublin, John Why, Pikinhill,
Chrisphus, and others; these constituted the
leading Exhorters of Baltimore. At the white
Quarterly Conference, these Exhorters complained
against me. They said I was too fast for a young
man; and these Exhorters could not read, nor could
I, at that time. They acknowledged that I was a
pious young man, but they made this objection:
that I said more about the Scriptures than they,
who were older and much more experienced than
myself. The Conference listened patiently to
their complaints against me. The Elder said he
would attend some of my meetings and see how
I carried them on. This he did unbeknown to me.</p>
          <p>I remember at the last prayer-meeting I held
just before the quarterly meeting, the pastor,
unbeknown to me, brought the Presiding Elder
with him to my meeting. At the ensuing Quarterly
Conference the Presiding Elder stated that
he had visited one of my meetings, and he said I
was doing a good work; and from that time there
was no further dispute about me and my work.
The Quarterly Conference immediately voted me
<pb id="dsmith18" n="18"/>
Exhorter's license. I felt the Lord was fighting
for me while I held my peace. Thus I was promoted
to the rank of an Exhorter in the M. E.
Church.</p>
          <p>“He that waiteth upon the Lord shall renew his
strength; he shall mount up as on the wings of an
eagle.”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER IV.<lb/>
MY LIFE AS AN EXHORTER IN THE M. E.<lb/>
CHURCH.</head>
          <p>I continued to hold meetings in private houses
until I gained the affections of the people at large
—both white and colored—more particularly the
better class of my own people. I will name some
of them: Alexander Murray, John C. Hall,
Charles Hackett, Henry Harden, John Forty,
Edward Walters, Stephen Hill, and many others.
These were my particular friends, and God made
me an agent in bringing many of them to love the
Lord Jesus.</p>
          <p>I organized a band of young men to assist me
with my meetings. Among them were the following:
Nathan Peck, Alexander Murray, Leben
<pb id="dsmith19" n="19"/>
Lee and David Cornish. These were my faithful
and zealous friends and helpers in the Gospel.
We were, as a general thing, excellent singers.
This drew great crowds of young people and the
better class of the aged. After singing, we would
turn our gathering into prayer-meeting, which
terminated in the conviction and conversion of
souls to God.</p>
          <p>Alexander Murray, like John the Baptist, was
our forerunner. His duty was to prepare the
place of meeting, and every Sunday, after three
o'clock preaching, he would announce the next
place of meeting. These meetings were held
among the best colored families of Baltimore, and
because the best families attended and took part
in these meetings we had excellent order. The
citizens had the highest regard for us. Tongue
can not express the wonderful results which followed
our humble labors in this part of the
Lord's vineyard.</p>
          <p>It will be remembered by the readers, at this
time there were few free colored people in Baltimore,
compared to the great mass of my people
who lived in this great city. There was a large,
and also respectable, portion of my people, who
were nurses, stewards, coachmen and housewaiters.
These were very largely influenced by
<pb id="dsmith20" n="20"/>
their owners, both in sentiment, fashion and expression.</p>
          <p>Such men as Stephen Hill were the exponents
of this class of colored people. His name will
ever be remembered by the good people of Baltimore.
So wonderfully was this great man possessed
with native ability, though he could not
read, he had such a remarkable mind that the oral
instructions his owners gave him, made him one of
the leading spirits among our people in the city of
Baltimore. Brother Hill could see through and
discuss like a learned philosopher nearly any subject,
whether in science, philosophy, religion, or
politics. The reader can not imagine the degree
of native ability possessed by this man. There
were so few men among us who possessed such
talent as did Brother Hill that he was almost unduly
admired and worshiped by our people.
When such men became religious as they did,
their owners became very much interested in me
and did what they could to assist me, for such religious
reformation made this class of men and
women better servants, and by their good behavior
many of them became free. Stephen Hill,
Henry Harden, Leben Lee, and many others were
set free by their owners on account of their good
behavior and industry.</p>
          <pb id="dsmith21" n="21"/>
          <p>The work of the Lord prospered and increased
daily. Souls were added to the Church, such as
will be saved in glory. So successful was our
evangelistic work in the city of Baltimore, Sharp
street church became overflowed with hearers;
hence the people were compelled to build another
church in Old Town. In the next chapter I shall
give some account of our labors outside of Baltimore.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER V.<lb/>
MY LABORS OUTSIDE OF BALTIMORE.</head>
          <p>It was revealed to me by the Spirit of God that
my successful labors in the city of Baltimore had
come to a close; hence, I was impressed to leave
the city and go on the plantations. O, what an
instructive lesson I learned at this point in the
history of my life! The lesson was this: God
will make thee the weakest of his servants whom
he has fashioned and set in their proper places to
work. <hi rend="italics">Awful</hi> agents in his hand for good. “To
everything there is a season.” When God's appointed
seasons for good have passed, the agents
he has employed to work in his vineyard cease to
<pb id="dsmith22" n="22"/>
be affective, however strongly they may exert
themselves. “The Spirit of God worketh in us
to perform the will and pleasure of God and not
our own.”</p>
          <p>I became very much perplexed to know how I
should begin my labors in the field to which I had
been lead, viz: the plantations. What to do I did
not know, but finally it occurred to me, that if I
would present the case to some wealthy friend of
note and obtain his approval, I could possibly
reach the field to which I had been called, and by
some kind of recommendation obtain the favor of
the slave-holders on these plantations. I presented
the matter to Mr. John T. Barr, Esq. He was
one of the largest dry goods merchants in Baltimore
and then kept a wholesale store in Baltimore
street. I had lived with him and he had the
greatest confidence in me.</p>
          <p>I stated to him what had been revealed to me;
he then told me he would prepare for me a recommendation
of character, and said I should have
no trouble in this direction, and immediately he
proceeded to write the recommendation for me.
He went to nearly all the wealthy men of Baltimore
and had them to endorse this commendation
for me. Then I went out among all denominations,
and all were willing to bear what I had to
<pb id="dsmith23" n="23"/>
say about the Lord Jesus. The Lord made our
words like fire and hammer, melting the hearts of
the unconverted and leading them to conform
their <hi rend="italics">lives</hi> in <hi rend="italics">love</hi> and <hi rend="italics">obedience</hi> to God's holy
word. O, how it made my soul rejoice to see so
many converted to the Savior!</p>
          <p>The slave-holders became so favorably impressed
with me and my labors that they would allow
me to hold meetings two or three days on the
plantations at nearly any time I saw fit to do so.
The result was that many of the slaves were converted
to God, and naturally they became better
servants, and afterwards obtained their freedom.
The masters of these slave people would assign
my lodging and fare with the household servants
instead of the field hands. This indicated the
respect they had for me. Many of the masters,
their sons and daughters were convicted and
converted to God; hence they espoused my labors
of <hi rend="italics">love,</hi> and did all they could to assist me in my
arduous duties.</p>
          <p>I remember very distinctly of holding a meeting
on what was then called Manna Hill, on the turnpike
leading to Little York, Pa. The meeting
was held in a school house; we commenced the
service at 11 A.M. The power of the Lord was so
wonderfully poured out upon the assembly, that
<pb id="dsmith24" n="24"/>
the meeting did not break up until 3 P.M. Here I
saw the slaves and their owners singing, shouting
and praising God together. All seemed to be one
in Christ Jesus; there was no distinction as to the
rich or poor, bond or free, but all were melted into
sweet communion with the spirit and united in
Christian fellowship; and to my mind they could
have befittingly sang this blessed hymn:</p>
          <lg>
            <l>“Blest be the dear uniting love</l>
            <l>That will not let us part;</l>
            <l>Our bodies may far off remove,</l>
            <l>We still are one in heart.”</l>
          </lg>
          <p>We had many such meetings in those days. I
could say volumes upon this subject if it were not
for a more important part of my history. I now
leave this present subject to speak of my departure
from the M. E. Church.</p>
          <lg>
            <l>“Farewell, dear friends, I must be gone,</l>
            <l>I have no home or stay with you;</l>
            <l>I take my staff and travel on,</l>
            <l>Till I a better world do view.”</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <pb id="dsmith25" n="25"/>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER VI.<lb/>
MY CONNECTION WITH THE A. M. E.<lb/>
CHURCH.</head>
          <p>Daniel Coker was the leading spiritual overseer in the
Colored M. E. Church of Baltimore. It was his duty to
watch over his colored brethren, take note of their condition
and report to the white Elder; and the Elder's decision in
Church matters was law to the colored brethren. Many of
our people apprehended the wrongness in the manner which
the Presiding Elder would often treat the colored Christian.
They thought it was not a Christian spirit; therefore they
became very much dissatisfied. Time had so altered things
relative to colored preachers, that the M. E. Church now
gave license to colored preachers, but these were only local.</p>
          <p>The following are some of these preachers: Rev. Daniel
Coker was the leading spirit, and the first licentiate in the
city of Baltimore. Afterward the Rev. Daniel Moore, John
Mingo, and two other Exhorters—the Rev. Jos. Touny and
another whose name I cannot call now; these brethren came
from Eastern Shore to the city. They were men possessing
much talent and exercised themselves
<pb id="dsmith26" n="26"/>
in Sharp-street church. These brethren became very
popular in their Church; so much so, that the local preachers
(white) became jealous of them, for they received all the
appointments in the colored churches. At this point began
the bone of contention between the white and colored
Methodists. The contention continued until the leading
colored brethren and sisters of Baltimore organized a
separate and distinct body of Methodists, which resulted in
the organization of an A. M. E. Church in Baltimore.</p>
          <p>The Rev. Daniel Coker consulted the local preachers
(colored) and the Exhorters from Eastern Shore as to
how it would do for them to be 
to themselves—a separate and distinct body of 
Methodists. These brethren opposed the suggestion,
but the Rev. Daniel Coker continued to discuss
the subject in such a way as not to allow them to take
advantage of him and report him to the white Elders. He
continued for some time in this way, until all hope of getting
them to agree with him was lost. He then left them and
called together John C. Hall, Charles Hackett, Alexander
Murray, Nathan Peck, Leben Lee, James Touston, Charles
Pierce, Richard Williams, Henry Harden, Stephen Hill (the
wonderful man of whom I spoke in Chapter IV), David
Smith,
<pb id="dsmith27" n="27"/>
N. T. Hammond and Faton Blake. All were pledged not to
reveal the object of this council, for we were afraid of the
opposite party, and that the white Elders would get into
the secrets of our meeting and defeat our purposes; hence,
the business was kept a profound secret.</p>
          <p>We met weekly for a considerable while, instructed by
Daniel Coker. Stephen Hill was our great lawyer. He
continued to discuss the advantage of forming a distinct
connection of Methodists, and we were all converted and
sanctified to this end. I say sanctified, because not a man of
us ever went back to the M. E. Church. To our great
surprise, the Rev. Daniel Coker informed us, at one of our
meetings, that there was a great disturbance in Philadelphia
between the Rev. Richard Allen and some of the white
Elders of the M. E. Church. The trouble arose, it seems,
from this: The appointing power gave the colored people a
minister (white) who was not faithful to his duties. The
colored people became very much dissatisfied and began to
murmur and neglect their Church obligations. The white
Elder became much displeased at the conduct of the
members, so much so that he threatened to turn them out of
the Church as disorderly members, whereupon the members
of the Church became
<pb id="dsmith28" n="28"/>
enraged and entered a protest against the retention and
support of the appointed pastor.</p>
          <p>The Rev. Richard Allen was the leading spirit in the great
colored congregation of Philadelphia. He claimed the colored
people built the church and, therefore, had a right to it aside
from the appointed Elder. The Elder contending on the other
hand that the property had been made over to the Bishop
and Conference and, hence, it belonged to the M. E.
Connection. Revs. Daniel Coker and Richard Allen communicated
with each other upon the subject of coming out
from the M. E. Church and forming a separate and distinct
body of colored Methodists. The particulars were kept a
secret between the Reverends Coker and Allen. Daniel Coker
informed us at one of our club meetings, in Baltimore, that it
was the intention of Rev. Allen and his congregation to come
out from the M. E. Connection in the city of Philadelphia.</p>
          <p>He obtained our promise at that meeting to come out
from the M. E. Connection in Baltimore—and out we came.
A great number of brethren and sisters came out with us.
Rev. Daniel Coker rented a Presbyterian church in Old
Town, so that that part of the congregation which came
out from Sharp-street church might
<pb id="dsmith29" n="29"/>
have a place in which to worship. And the following
Tuesday or Wednesday evening, we formed seven or eight
classes. By Sabbath, Daniel Coker and others had agreed to
buy a large church (in what was then called Fish street) for
twelve thousand dollars—paying one thousand dollars cash,
or before we got possession.</p>
          <p>About this time Rev. Richard Allen and others were in
great trouble about their Christian rights. The white Elder
tried to force himself on them as their pastor. He made an
appointment to preach for the colored people one Sabbath,
at 3 o'clock P.M. When the time arrived, he came and
brought other ministers of the M. E. Church with him. The
church was filled and all the aisles were crowded, so much
so the ministers and pastors were unable to reach the pulpit;
and aside from the crowd there were brethren appointed
by the dissatisfied part of the congregation to prevent the
pastor from preaching that afternoon. The Rev. Richard
Allen and others were assigned this duty.</p>
          <p>[I do not defend or praise such conduct, but simply
relate it as it is, and leave the readers to exercise their own
judgment.]</p>
          <p>The Rev. Tapseco (colored) was preaching when the
white Elder and his associates came,
<pb id="dsmith30" n="30"/>
and when the Elder found he would not be permitted to
preach for his colored brethren that afternoon, he said to
the ministers who accompanied him: “Bear witness; this
man has taken my appointment.” They then departed much
displeased.</p>
          <p>On the following Monday, the Rev. Richard Allen called
upon Mr. Paul Brown, one of the most eminent lawyers in
Philadelphia, and consulted him about the Church and her
troubles, and finally this counsel drew up a supplement
which he (Allen) and his congregation—the dissatisfied part
of his members—were to sign. The lawyer advised the Rev.
Allen to convey this document to Harrisburg and present it
to the Legislature, praying the right of church property
situate in the city of Philadelphia, which property they (the
colored people) had purchased with their own means. The
Rev. Allen was to remain in Harrisburg until special
legislation decided the matter. This he did. The Legislature
granted the colored people the church property in the city
of Philadelphia. The Rev. Richard Allen had nearly sixteen
hundred members belonging to his congregation at the time,
and when the news reached us at Philadelphia, there was a
wonderful shout among this long oppressed people.
<pb id="dsmith31" n="31"/>
Then was it that the Rev. Richard Allen became so
deeply seated in the hearts of his people,
and this Christian hero remained the loved and admired
until his death.</p>
          <p>Baltimore was out from the M. E. Church three weeks
before the Rev. Richard Allen and his congregation came out
in the city of Philadelphia.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER VII.
<lb/>THE UNION FORMED BY THE PHILADELPHIA,
<lb/>BALTIMORE AND SHOW HILL
<lb/>CHURCHES.</head>
          <p>The representatives of these three Churches met in
Philadelphia. Daniel and Admiral Coker and Stephen Hill
represented Baltimore, and Show Hill Church was
represented by preacher Chaney. The Church at
Philadelphia was represented by Rev. Richard Allen, and his
associates were the Rev. Tapseco and a school-master, who
had control of the colored school in Philadelphia at the time.
These noble hearted men were zealously affected and moved
to organize a plan which would be the means of
accomplishing the good
<pb id="dsmith32" n="32"/>
and glorious end sought, to-wit:—the elevation and education
of a despised and oppressed race, not only in civil, but also
in religious freedom. “Lord lay not this sin to their charge.”</p>
          <p>These Churches formed a Christian Confederation, and
from that meeting the Confederation of the Churches
appointed a Convention to meet in Philadelphia the
following spring. No one can imagine with what enthusiasm
the colored people of these two great cities were filled, over
these encouraging prospects. The Convention was called in
order to form an African Connection and adopt a discipline,
and hymn books; and to make all necessary regulations for
the existence of a great connection. I can not give the names
of all the delegates appointed from the different Churches,
but I can give the names of some, as I had the honor of being
a delegate from Baltimore: The Rev. Daniel Coker, Mr.
Stephen Hill, John C. Hall, Henry Harden, Nathan Peck,
David Smith, and others, were also delegates. The
Convention met as it was appointed, and formed a union of
the Churches and established the intended Connection.</p>
          <p>The next year a Conference was appointed to meet in the
city of Philadelphia. The year rolled on and the Conference
finally met as it was appointed. 
<pb id="dsmith33" n="33"/>
The meeting was held in the Rev. Richard Allen's
parlor, in Pine street, and there the Conference transacted its
important business, and then adjourned. The next
Conference of the African M. E. Connection, met the
following spring in the city of Baltimore, Md. The
Conference convened in a private house. This was the
second Conference of the A. M. E. Connection that year—the
first being held in Philadelphia, we moved in the spring to
Baltimore and held the second. Mr. Solomon Doubton, who
was then a prominent citizen of Baltimore, opened the doors
of his home to accommodate the members of the Conference.
He lived at that time in Spring street. At this Conference the
Rev. Richard Allen was appointed to the pastoral charge of
Bethel Church, Philadelphia; the Rev. Daniel Coker to
Bethel Church, Baltimore, and the Rev. Chaney to the charge
of Show Hill Church. The Conference was held again in
Philadelphia, but I did not attend that session of the
Conference. The minutes will show that Rev. Richard Allen
was ordained Bishop at this session of the A. M. E.
Connection. The Rev. Daniel Coker was elected Bishop in
the morning, but there was so much dissatisfaction among
the people, that the election of Daniel Coker was rescinded, and
<pb id="dsmith34" n="34"/>
Richard Allen was elected and ordained, April 9th, 1816, in
his stead. The objection to the election and ordination of the
Rev. Daniel Coker seems to have been on account of his
color. He being nearly white, the people said they could not
have an <hi rend="italics">African Connection</hi> with a man as light as Daniel
Coker at its head; therefore, the Rev. Richard Allen was
their choice. He was ordained Bishop by Bishop White, a
white bishop, who was then an active Bishop of the
Episcopal Church, assisted by Absalom Jones, an Episcopal
Elder then stationed in Philadelphia; and, I suppose, others
also took part in the ordination of Mr. Allen.</p>
          <p>The people every where seemed to be satisfied with this
remarkable event, but alas! it was the destruction of Daniel
Coker, and it pains me to make mention of this fact in my
history.</p>
          <p>The next Conference was held in Baltimore, and from this
Conference, Daniel Coker was appointed again to Bethel
charge, Baltimore, and also to lay out the Baltimore Circuit,
which he did, and very successfully too, for Daniel Coker, I
may say justly, was an exception, so far as his wit, talent
and education were concerned. He was born in the pine
regions of Baltimore county, Md., my native county and
state. He ran away
<pb id="dsmith35" n="35"/>
when but a small boy, and went to New York, where he
received a liberal education. Here he remained until he grew
up to manhood. He then embraced the Christian religion,
joined the Methodist Church and obtained license to preach
in the Church. About the time this young man grew up, the
colored people in Baltimore petitioned the wealthy (white)
people to grant them a school, that they might educate their
children. This was in opposition to the laws of the state,
but however the wealthy people assumed the
responsibility and granted the request, giving the free
colored people a school.</p>
          <p>When the colored people ascertained that they could
have schools, by the consent of the wealthy white people
of Baltimore, they sent to New York to obtain the services
of Rev. Daniel Coker and another man by the name of
Collins, as teachers of the schools. The Rev. Daniel Coker
came, but before he took charge of the school he informed
some of his friends that he had run away from the state
when quite a boy, and had since resided in New York;
therefore he could not appear in public until they bought
him. After hearing this the young men of Baltimore raised
the money and entered into an arrangement with a Quaker
by the name of Ticin, to “buy Mr.
<pb id="dsmith36" n="36"/>
Coker running,” which was done. These men then entered
upon their duties as teachers in the city of Baltimore, and
the schools prospered by their teaching and management, to
a great extent. Mr. Collins was a great singer, and
established the first choir in Sharp-street M. E. Church.
The introduction of sacred music at this early date in the
city of Baltimore accounts, possibly for the love of singing,
&amp;c., of which the Baltimoreans are so noted.</p>
          <p>The talent Coker exercised, not only in the school house,
but in the pulpit as well, rendered him very influential
among the people in Baltimore, both white and colored. The
whites who favored colonization to Liberia, thought the
Rev. Daniel Coker was too intelligent to remain in this
country. They said he should go to Africa where his talent
could be exercised in the interest of his race. Mr. Coker was
very much opposed to this Society and its intention, but the
members of the Society continued to hold out inducements
to him, promising if he would consent to go, he should be
made President of the Republic of Liberia. Rev. Daniel
Coker met with some misfortunes in the city of Baltimore
and finally he consented to accept the offer; he went to
Liberia, became President, and, I am told, held this office
with credit until the day of his death. </p>
          <pb id="dsmith37" n="37"/>
          <p>After the Rev. Daniel Coker joined the Colonization
Society, and was made President of the Republic of Liberia,
the Baltimore (or Maryland) Conference, which convened
in the spring, took into consideration the Harrisburg circuit,
and the preachers agreed to keep up the preaching places
which the Rev. Daniel Coker had laid out. The following are
some of the preaching places: Little York, Pennsylvania;
Wrightville, on the Susquehanna river, Columbia,
Lancaster, Harrisburg, Carlisle, Shippingburg,
Chambersburg, Greencastle, Hagarstown, Funcktown, and
Fredericktown.</p>
          <p>This circuit was more particularly kept up by Shadrick
Bassett and myself. We traveled this circuit afoot, and had
our appointments arranged for every two weeks. Great
revivals followed from point to point. “The people were
willing in the day of God's power.” Scores were brought
into the Church by our humble efforts. The white as well as
the colored people were so much taken up with us that they
would contribute very liberally to the support of colored churches.</p>
          <p>One thing that assisted us very much in gaining friends
and obtaining means to assist in building churches was the
manner in which the Rev. Daniel Coker had began to lay
out the circuit.
<pb id="dsmith38" n="38"/>
He went to the wealthy white people and obtained their
consent to act as Trustees of the colored churches; and
when I came on the circuit I presented to these wealthy
people the recommendation which I had obtained of Mr.
John T. Barr, Esq., of Baltimore, hence, they were more
particularly interested in me, notwithstanding Bro. Bassett
was the best speaker. Bro. Bassett thought it would be best
for me to collect the means to buy lots and build churches,
which I did there very successfully, and soon were seen the
temples of God lifting their towering heads nearly all over
the circuit.</p>
          <p>The Rev. Henry Harden was appointed to hold our
quarterly meetings.</p>
          <p>The Church had so developed by this time that Bishop
Allen had ordained five of his local preachers. Some were
Deacons and some were Elders. Among them was the Rev.
Henry Harden. You can not imagine what wonderful times
we had at these quarterly meetings.</p>
          <p>In those days when it was announced that a colored
Elder was to hold a quarterly meeting, the people (white
and colored) would come in the towns and villages from all
parts of the country in great crowds. These rustic people
were not ashamed to come to these meetings in road wagons
<pb id="dsmith39" n="39"/>
or in any possible way they could make it convenient
to reach these blessed meetings. Often the meetings would
begin on Saturday and not end before Monday
or Tuesday evening at sunset. We would go out about
a mile from town and hold what were
called “farewell meetings.” 
Many souls were converted at these meetings.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER VIII.
<lb/>MY ORDINATION TO THE ORDER OF
<lb/>DEACON AND ELDER.</head>
          <p>The following year the Conference sat in Baltimore,
brother Bassett and I made our report to
this Conference. The members of this Conference
were highly pleased over the success which
attended our year's labors on the Harrisburgh Circuit.
I was then ordained Deacon and Elder, and
returned to the Harrisburgh Circuit by the appointment
of Bishop Allen. This year I had no
associate to assist me in the Pastoral work of the
Circuit, but I soon found the work was more than
I could faithfully attend, for the Lord began to
pour out his blessings upon the people as he did
the first year, and our number increased daily. I
<pb id="dsmith40" n="40"/>
then wrote Bishop Allen, praying him to send me help;
which he did. The Rev. Bishop Allen sent an elderly man
by the name of Cousin. Brother Cousin was from Virginia;
he brought papers with him, representing them to be from
the hand of the Rev. Richard Allen. These made statements
to this effect:—that the Bishop had given him the over-sight
of the Circuit and that I was to be under him. He was a great
speaker, and entertained and pleased the people very much.
I submitted, thinking his report was true. He had no family,
but I had, and he retained all the money gathered from the
people. I wrote Bishop Allen, stating to him that he had
given Elder Cousin the over-sight of the Circuit, and he kept
all the means, and my family was about to starve. The
Bishop said he did not give Bro. Cousin the over-sight of
the Circuit, and told me to drive him off; but I could not do
this if I wanted to, for brother Cousin had won the
affections of the people, and therefore had the inside track
of me; but at the next Conference he was tried and expelled
for misdemeanor. The same year Elder Cousin and I had
charge of the Harrisburgh Circuit, a trouble occured at East
Point, between the white and colored people, about some
Church property; you can not imagine the excitement
<pb id="dsmith41" n="41"/>
there was at this place. Bishop Allen ordered me to go
there and hold a Quarterly Meeting. I soon found
myself in the midst of this turbulent scene, ready to
do what I could to <sic corr="reconcile">reconsile</sic> these contending
elements. Here (at East Point) I found brother Wm.
Paul Quinn, he was quite young at that time, and a
licensed preacher.</p>
          <p>The Conference year came on, and Bro. Quinn made
all the necessary preparations to meet the Conference
which was to convene in the city of Philadelphia.
There was a man by the name of Rev. Collins,
accompanied and introduced Bro. Quinn to the
Conference. Bro. Collins doubtless is well known by
the old citizens of Pittsburgh, for he afterwards settled
in this smokey city, and became one of the highly
respected citizens of the same.</p>
          <p>From this Conference, Bro. Wm. Paul Quinn was
appointed to lay out a Circuit in Pennsylvania, which
he was very <sic corr="successful">sucessful</sic> in doing. In those days Bro.
Quinn was considered to be a great man, though he
was not very learned, he was both <hi rend="italics">witty and <sic corr="talented">talened</sic>,</hi>
and these endowments enabled him to accomplish
much in the behalf of the Church. His first work in the
A. M. E. Church, in the way of laying out a Circuit,
was mostly in Buck county, Pa. Take notice, Rev<corr sic="missing punctuation">.</corr>
<pb id="dsmith42" n="42"/>
Quinn always claimed to be the first itinerant preacher in
the A. M. E. Church, simply because he traveled his Circuit
on horse-back, but I walked, because I did not understand
how to ride very well. He rode horse-back in laying out his
Circuit. The question as to who was the first itinerant
preacher in the A. M. E. Church, was never settled between
us. At the next Conference, which met in Philadelphia, Rev.
Win. Paul Quinn made a very favorable report, which the
Bishop and Conference received with much joy. The reader
must remember at this stage of development of the Church,
it was our custom to hold two Conferences during the same
year. The first was held in the spring, in Philadelphia, and
this was called the Pennsylvania Conference, after which
Bishop Allen went to the city of Baltimore and held what
was then called the Maryland Conference.</p>
          <p>The Secretaryship, seemed to be the most difficult
position in these Conferences, and why? Simply because
there were so few men of color who could write sufficiently
well as to keep correct minutes. We were often compelled
to select persons as Secretaries of the Conference,
irrespective of their religious or moral condition. Richard
Allen, jr., was our first Secretary, he was
<pb id="dsmith43" n="43"/>
not a religious man, but he was an excellent scribe, and he
filled the position of Secretary for several Conference years.
His office was so important that he would leave
Philadelphia with the Rev. Bishop Allen and come to
Baltimore to act as Secretary of the Maryland Conference.
Richard Allen, jr., remained Secretary of the Connection,
until the Rev. Jacob Matthews joined the A. M. E. Church,
who became Richard Allen's successor, in this position. The
Rev. Jacob Matthews was an M. E. preacher from the city
of New York. He moved to Philadelphia, joined the A. M. E. 
Church, and was stationed at Bethel Church as the
successor of Bishop Allen, after serving his time with this
congregation, Bishop Allen appointed him to Bethel
Church, Baltimore, Md. Rev. Matthews was a fair scribe
and an excellent man, very much beloved by the people. He
filled the office of Secretary for a considerable while. The
Harrisburgh Circuit was then under the jurisdiction of the
Maryland Conference.</p>
          <p>We will now return to the Harrisburgh Circuit. It was at
the session of the Baltimore, following the Philadelphia
Conference which met in the spring (at the time Bro. Quinn
joined), that Bro. Cousin was tried and expelled from the
Conference for misdemeanor. Now the Harrisburgh
<pb id="dsmith44" n="44"/>
Circuit by this time had become so large that it was thought
best by the members of the Conference to divide it, so as to
make Fredricktown a station, this was done, and two
Circuits and one station was made out of what was formerly
called the Harrisburgh Circuit. Then the people of
Fredricktown petitioned Bishop Allen to send me to
Fredricktown as their stationed preacher. This was very
unpleasant to me, for I always had the spirit of an
evangelist. However I remained in this station about three
months. I felt as a bird caged, deprived both of the use of
wings and free air. My habit had been to preach two or
three times a day, and nearly every night to large
congregations composed of white and colored people. To
see the same faces and preach to the same people, night
after night, became a painful affliction to me. I became so
much dissatisfied, I left and went to Washington, D.C. At
that time our people in Washington were very much
opposed to the A. M. E. Church, and declared if any of the
A. M. E. preachers should dare to come to Washington to
establish an A. M. E. Church, they (the people under the
M. E. Connection) would tar and feather them, but like the
great Apostle of the Gentiles, I thought in myself “none of
these things move me,” for it was
<pb id="dsmith45" n="45"/>
my purpose to trust in the living God, who is able to do
more than I could think or ask. Now with unshakened faith
in God, I went to Georgetown, not knowing what would
befall me. My only ambition was to preach the Gospel of
the Son of God, that souls might be saved, and the kingdom
of <sic corr="righteousness">rightousness</sic> established among my people. While
passing through the streets, I met a colored man who was
leader in the Church choir. His congregation was then
building a new church, he asked me if I was not a preacher? I
told him I was; he then requested me to remain and preach
for the congregation that evening. I consented, and preached
for them; we had a wonderful time, eight persons came to the
altar to be prayed for, and two of them came through that
evening, and there was a wonderful shout in the camp. I
wish now to relate a little instance which may be amusing to
the readers:</p>
          <p>One of the leading <sic corr="brethren">breathren</sic> was as happy as he could
well be, and seized me around the neck and said “brother
where did you come from?” I told him I was from
Fredricktown, and that I was a Bethel preacher, of the
Bethel Connection, “put out the lights!” and out the
candles went. He did not only put out the candles, but
drove me out also. One of the brethren got my horse
<pb id="dsmith46" n="46"/>
and commanded me to depart. It was about 12 o'clock in the
night when he brought my horse. This kind of treatment
was a sad affliction to me, for I was a stranger and a <sic corr="pilgrim">pilgram</sic>
in that part of the country. You might imagine my distress,
if you could for a single moment, think of this one fact, 12
<hi rend="italics">o'clock at night, drove out of the church,</hi> unacquainted with
any one, or place where I might find shelter and sympathy.</p>
          <lg>
            <l>“Judge not the Lord by feeble sense,</l>
            <l>But trust him for his Grace,</l>
            <l>Behind a frowning providence, </l>
            <l>He hides a smiling face.”</l>
          </lg>
          <p>However I mounted my horse and inquired of the
watchman the way to Capitol Hill, he gave me the
directions, which I followed very closely. I crossed the
bridge leading from Georgetown to the city of Washington. I
was acquainted with a Bro. by the name of St. Cypian
Beanes who was a noble hearted man and was then in good
circumstances. He lived on Capitol Hill, and my purpose
was to find his comfortable home. I was satisfied if I could
only find him, God would open his heart and he would take
one of God's humble servants and give him shelter. The
watchman directed me to Bro. Beanes' house, and it was
about 2 o'clock when I arrived. This dear
<pb id="dsmith47" n="47"/>
brother received me very kindly. After I had been seated for
a short while I made known to him the object of my visit. He
said my life was not secure, but if God was for me I would
come out more than conqueror. He promised me to do what
he could to assist me in the accomplishment of my
intentions, but advised me to be very cautious in my
operations. I spoke to him of the recommendation which I
had obtained of Mr. John T. Barr, Esq., of Baltimore, Md.
He said it would do very well to show it to the white people,
but that colored people did not stop for this kind of
recommendation. In the midst of this danger I began to study
some plan by which I might succeed in my undertaking. The
thought of appointing a committee of protection presented
itself to me.</p>
          <p>I commenced my work by selecting and appointing the
best men (not Church members) from among those who
were porters and waiters at the Capitol. These were to
protect me in my intended work to establish an A. M. E.
Church in Washington. The first on the committee were
George Hicks, Dora Bowen and William Coster, runners at
the Capitol, and two other names which I can not now
remember. At the War office I appointed Wm. Deacher, Wm.
Warren and others. 
<pb id="dsmith48" n="48"/>
These men had wonderful influence among the colored
people; and what these men said was generally received as
true by the colored people of Washington. The news soon
spread all through Washington that an A. M. E. preacher
was in the city. The city was in great excitement. The
people (colored) who were under the M. E. Church soon
made me leave between two suns. Now, before I left
Washington I obtained a written permission from a 'squire
by the name of Jackson Chambers to preach the following
Sabbath in his rope-walk. Mr. Chambers was an M. E.
preacher (local). Brother Beanes was the chief agent in
obtaining this permit, for he was well acquainted with Mr.
Chambers. I then mounted my horse, crossed the river and
came to a little town, about sixteen miles from Washington
City, and stopped with a tavern-keeper by the name of
George Cole, with whom I became acquainted at the
Baltimore Conference some time before. Mr. Cole was a
brother-in-law to Bro. Beanes, and both were thought much
of by the wealthy whites. I arrived at Mr. Cole's tavern
between 10 and 11 o'clock A.M. The slave-holders generally
assembled here about this time of the day to drink and talk
about their slaves. I was introduced to them by Mr. Cole. They were
<pb id="dsmith49" n="49"/>
all pretty much under the influence of liquor. I immediately
showed them the recommendation I had from Mr. John T.
Barr, of Baltimore. They then and there requested me to
preach, which I did, taking as a text, John, III chapter, 7
verse; subject: “The new birth.” These men were all much
pleased with the discourse.</p>
          <p>On Sabbath, I returned to Washington in company with a
great many colored men, who went to protect me from the
violence which they supposed awaited me in the city. O, just
think, all these were slave men! As we got to the bridge
leading into Washington, we saw a great crowd of people on
the opposite side of the bridge awaiting our arrival. This was
Sabbath morning, and I was on my way to the rope-walk to
fill my appointment at 11 o'clock. We naturally thought
they were there for the purpose of disturbing us. I was then
advised by my protectors to take off my ministerial
costume that I might not be distinguished from the rest of
the company. I took off my costume, and when we came to
the rope-walk we found a great crowd of people—white and
colored—awaiting our arrival, and three constables to prevent
me from preaching; but I had the written agreement
from 'Squire Chambers himself, stating that I was authorized
to preach in his
<pb id="dsmith50" n="50"/>
<hi rend="italics">rope-walk</hi> on Sabbath. The committee of protection,
whom I had appointed before I left Washington for Mr.
Cole's tavern, met me at the rope-walk and showed my
permit to the constables, and insisted on my preaching in
the rope-walk that morning; hence, the constables
abandoned the premises and I was allowed to proceed.</p>
          <p>Among the persons who constituted the committee of
protection which met me at the rope-walk, and perhaps the
most prominent, was Bro. Beanes, with whom I had
stopped when I first <sic corr="went">whent</sic> to Washington. My opening
hymn on this occasion was thus:</p>
          <lg>
            <l>“Thou Judge of quickened dead,</l>
            <l>Before whose bar severe,</l>
            <l>With holy joy or guilty dread, </l>
            <l>We shall soon appear.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Our cautioned souls prepare</l>
            <l>For that tremendous day,</l>
            <l>And fill us now with watchful care, </l>
            <l>And stir us up to pray.”</l>
          </lg>
          <p>I took for my text, John iv: 29: “Come see a man that told
me all things that I ever did. Is not this Christ?” The text is
so familiar to the people, even to this day, when I visit that
great city, Washington, the subject and text is a traditional
talk, for many of the people have the text written in their
Bibles, and I have had to preach
<pb id="dsmith51" n="51"/>
from the same text several times to satisfy them.</p>
          <p>After preaching in the rope-walk that morning,
I told them all about the A. M. E. Connection and
what the African M. E. Church proposed to do.
I then called for joiners, and forty-three came forward
and joined our Connection. We gained a
great victory, and the meeting was long remembered
by all those who were present. Many of
those who joined us were converted that day and
night.</p>
          <p>I did not preach at Jackson Chambers' in the
afternoon, nor at night. Some people might want
to know the reason I did not preach in this 
rope-walk in the afternoon? Simply, because “the
slaying of the Lord were many,” and the people
were crying for mercy in every direction. I then
thought it would be better to wait until night before
I began preaching again. Night came on
and I went to Capitol Hill; the moon was shining
very bright. I took Mr. George Bell's door-step
as my pulpit, and here I stood and proclaimed the
Gospel to dying men and women. After the
meeting was opened I took for my text, Isaiah,
53—1: “Who hath believed our report, and to
whom is the arm of the Lord revealed?” A large
crowd of people attended the meeting that evening.
After preaching I again opened the door of
<pb id="dsmith52" n="52"/>
the Church, and twenty more joined the Connection.
I then requested all the members to meet
me on Monday evening, to be assigned to their
classes. I then called my committee to meet on
Tuesday evening, to take into consideration the
best method of building a church.</p>
          <p>We met, and Mr. George Hicks stated that
there was an old school-house on Capitol Hill that
could be bought for $300, but this school-house
was on leased ground; but, if the house was fixed
up it would make a comfortable place of worship.
We agreed to buy the school-house, and the next
night I made the intention known to the congregation
 (this was on Wednesday evening). I appointed
a meeting again on Thursday evening,
and told the congregation to bring all the money
they could, for I desired to get possession of the
school-house by the next Sabbath; and, on Thursday,
we collected three hundred dollars and
enough over that amount to repair and make the
school-house comfortable for worship the following
Sabbath.</p>
          <p>The colored people under the M. E. Church had
stirred up the people to such an extent that on
the Sabbath, three constables were stationed at
the school-house to prevent us from holding our
meeting. We had the lease for the ground and a
<pb id="dsmith53" n="53"/>
receipt for the money we had paid for the 
school-house. Mr. George Hicks showed these papers
to the constables and they left the premises, and
did not arrest me as the enemies of the A. M. E.
Church had intended. The next thing after we
got possession of the school-house was the breaking
out of a great revival, and the people fell before
the Word of God like grass before a scythe.
Prominent among those who embraced the Christian
religion were Mr. George Hicks, who became
an earnest preacher in the A. M. E. Church, and
George Simms, an Exhorter. I took the Rev.
Bro. Schurman into the A. M. E. Church and
appointed him to Fredericktown to fill out the
Conference year.</p>
          <p>I returned again to Mr. Cole's tavern, and in a
short while established a Church in the neighborhood
—the congregation being composed chiefly
of slave people. The white people thought a
great deal of me because I did not say anything
to their slaves about becoming free from their
earthly masters, but impressed upon them the
necessity of becoming free from the devil. I then
went to Prince George co. and established a
Church of nearly two hundred members. These
three points constituted the circuit of which
Washington was the head. I held a camp meeting 
<pb id="dsmith54" n="54"/>
in Prince George co., and many were converted
to God. The Rev. Jacob Matthews, who
was then stationed in the city of Baltimore, assisted
me in this camp meeting.</p>
          <p>You will remember that I was to preach at
Fredericktown that year, but when I took the
Rev. Schurman in the A. M. E. Connection, I
appointed him to the Fredericktown station, which
he filled with credit and success. Bro. Schurman
had a wonderful revival and many souls were
added to the Church. Now, after the Conference
labors were closed, I returned to the Conference,
which met in the city of Baltimore, and
made the report of my work, and there was great
rejoicing among the Conference members over
my labors.</p>
          <p>I was sent back to Washington the following
year, but I did not remain there; the Rev. Schurman
went in my stead, as there were some family
matters which called me home for a while. I was
then living in Baltimore. When the Rev. Schurman
had gotten as far as Mr. Cole's tavern, he
was arrested and put into jail by the slave-holders,
and the Churches at this place (Mr. Cole's) and
the one at Prince George's were closed against us.
I went back to Washington and continued in that
city from that time until the Church in Washington 
<pb id="dsmith55" n="55"/>
was a station, and I named the church Israel.
After my departure from the city, the members
bought a church under Capitol Hill.</p>
          <p>Now, I leave Washington and turn my attention
to another field of my labor.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER IX.
<lb/>MY LABORS NEAR PITTSBURG.</head>
          <p>The Rev. Jacob Richardson and I concluded to
come to the West and labor in the vineyard of the
Lord. We made Pittsburg, Pa., our objective
point, and soon started for the Smoky City of the
mountains. We arrived in Pittsburg on Sabbath
evening, and there was great excitement over the
arrival of the colored Evangelists. I preached at
night. The following persons were living in
Pittsburg at the time (I mention them because
there are some interesting features connected with
them and our labor in Pittsburg): James and
George Coleman were musicians and Abraham
Lewis was one of their associates; and, while Mr.
Lewis was not a musician and did not play for the
wealthy white people about Pittsburg as James
and George Coleman did, yet he waited at the
<pb id="dsmith56" n="56"/>
entertainments of these wealthy white people.
These persons came to hear us on Sabbath night,
and all three of them were convicted and converted
to God that night. James and George
Coleman became circuit preachers, and were
much beloved by all who knew them, as they did
much valuable work for the A. M. E. Connection,
James, especially; for he became a leading preacher
in the Ohio Conference. Abraham Lewis remained
a local preacher, but was very useful and
highly esteemed by the leading citizens of Pittsburg.
He was truly a light in the Smoky City,
and too much can not be said of him as an exemplary
man. He lived the life of the righteous;
hence, died the death of the same, and to-day,
doubtless, he is enjoying the saint's rest. “There
remaineth therefore a rest to the people of God.”</p>
          <p>I remained in Pittsburg one week, and then
proceeded to Little Washington, Pa. Here I met
with some difficulties. There was a man living
in Little Washington by the name of George
Bowler, who was a barber and a colored man
of considerable influence. He had written to
Bishop Allen, praying him to send a preacher to
Little Washington. When I arrived I found him
in his shop shaving an M. E. preacher, by the
name of Rev. Bear. Mr. Bowler was an Exhorter
<pb id="dsmith57" n="57"/>
in the M. E. Church. The Rev. Bear entered
into a conversation with me (let it be remembered
that all the colored people of Methodist persuasion
belonged to his Church). He said to me in the
presence of Mr. Bowler: “You have compassed
land and water to make proselytes, and you will
make them ten-fold more the children of the
devil.” After hearing this, Mr. Bowler said to
me: “You can't stay in my house.”</p>
          <p>I then left his premises and went into the streets
and inquired for a Presbyterian minister, for I
knew the Presbyterians were kind and endorsed
(as a general thing) religious freedom. I soon
found one of that persuasion by the name of Rev.
Brown. I showed the recommendation I had
obtained of Mr. John T. Barr, Esq., of Baltimore.
I also told him of my intention to gather my people
together, wherever it was practicable, and
form them into a distinct body of Methodists.
He received and treated me very kindly. “If the
Lord is for us, who can be against us?” After
remaining with Mr. Brown that night, I thought
the next morning, when I awoke, that “I must
work while it is called day,” and, “I must work
the work of Him that sent me.” After family
devotion and breakfast was over, I started out in
search of the colored people.</p>
          <pb id="dsmith58" n="58"/>
          <p>I found quite a number of them, but they were afraid (?)
of me. I continued on my mission, and finally I came across
an old colored man by the name of Dawns. He was the
father of the well-known William Dawns, of Cincinnati. This
boy, William, was then going to school in Little
Washington. The young man grew up and moved to
Cincinnati. I recommended him to my Lodge in Philadelphia
to be made one of the first colored Masons west of the
Allegheny mountains. Nearly all the old settlers of
Cincinnati know him well. His widow, Rebecca Dawns, is
still living on West Walnut Hills, Cincinnati.</p>
          <p>I must again return to old Mr. Dawns, of Little
Washington. He owned a beautiful grove, which was
connected with a little homestead. He did not profess to be
a Christian, and I explained to him the history and object of
the A. M. E. Connection. He endorsed my purpose, and
seemed well pleased with the idea of a connection being
controlled entirely by colored people. I prayed him to allow
me to preach in his beautiful grove. He readily consented to
do so, and built a stand and made all the necessary
arrangements for Sabbath afternoon's preaching. The Rev.
Mr. Brown was so much interested in my success that he
had written kind requests to all the pastors of
<pb id="dsmith59" n="59"/>
Washington, Pa., asking them to dispense with their
meetings on Sabbath, in the afternoon, and they (the
pastors) and their congregations turn out
to my meeting. The Baptist preacher consented, but the
Rev. Bear would not listen to it. However, we went on
with our meeting, and it was amusing to see his people
desert their shepherd and come out to see and hear an old
colored preacher. The whole town turned out <hi rend="italics">en masse</hi> to
my meeting, for they had not heard a colored man preach in
this section of the country before. I commenced to preach
between 2 and 3 o'clock P.M., and just as I was about to
close, Jacob Richardson came from Pittsburg, and read the
preface to our discipline.</p>
          <p>I then proceeded to open the doors of the Church, and
forty-eight persons came forward and joined the A. M. E.
Connection. I left one lone colored woman to be seated in
the gallery of Mr. Bear's church. The galleries of the M. E.
Churches were the auditoriums for the Ethiopian brethren
and sisters of that day, and the rule of 
our mother Church was: “Thus far shall thou come and no
farther.” The Rev. Mr. Bear was much displeased with the
movement of his African competitor. He tried to move the
public against me, but failed to succeed. I told him that
these
<pb id="dsmith60" n="60"/>
were my people and I had a right to them; yet this did not
satisfy him.</p>
          <p>The next perplexing thing was the manner of obtaining a
place of worship. I was a Mason and proved to some of the
leading white Masons that I was a true brother. I then told
them my mission, and stated my purpose to gather up my
people and organize them into a distinct body of
Methodists, which was known as the A. M. E. Church, and
that I had no place of worship. They agreed to allow me to
preach in the Masonic Hall until the congregation could
obtain a place of worship. All seemed willing to assist me in
obtaining a suitable place to hold divine services.</p>
          <p>Monday morning I started out among the colored and also
the white people with a subscription paper and got about
nine hundred dollars' subscription. We then bought a double
house from a judge of the Court. If my memory serves me
rightly, I think his name was Beard. He took the value of the
subscription paper as pay for the property. We soon
repaired the house and a revival followed, and soon had the
town in what Mr. Bear would term an excitement. We soon
had a respectable membership and a fine congregation added
to the A. M. E. Connection. I remained in Little Washington
a short while and then departed for Brownville, Pa. </p>
          <pb id="dsmith61" n="61"/>
          <p>I found the colored people here as I did in Washington—
those who were of the Methodist persuasion belonged to
the M. E. Church. My first sermon was preached in the
Friends' church. I remember a Quaker was convicted and
cried for mercy. After this, the leading members of the
Society would not allow me to preach in their church any
more, because they did not believe in that kind of
excitement. However, I continued faithful to my mission,
and my people severed their connection with the M. E.
Church without much trouble on my part—for they were
like ripe fruit, only waiting to be plucked.</p>
          <p>We worshiped in a man's house by the name of Norris,
who was the father of Thomas Norris, of Pittsburg. Bro.
Thomas Norris was quite a boy, going to school, when I
established the Church in Brownsville. I have only to
mention Brother Norris, for the old citizens and preachers
who have visited Pittsburg, remember well his hospitable
disposition and usefulness to the A. M. E. Connection in
this great city. In the case of Father Norris and son, we see
“Hereditable good is like hereditable evil, transmitted from
father to son.” We raised a large subscription in
Brownsville, but did not build a church; for it was built
after my departure.</p>
          <pb id="dsmith62" n="62"/>
          <p>From Brownsville I went to Pike's Run, and took sixty
members in the A. M. E. Church. We worshiped in Mr.
Pointer's house. From Pike's Run, I went to a little town (I
cannot recollect its name at present), I was successful there,
and took thirty members in the Church. These three points
constituted what was afterwards called the Little
Washington Circuit. The following spring, I and my wife
went to the Baltimore Conference. We learned there was a
great trouble in Bethel Church, Philadelphia; however the
trouble did not take a definite form until the meeting of the
Philadelphia Conference. The trustees and officers of Bethel
Church had elected Bishop Allen their pastor for life, at five
hundred dollars per year as a salary. Mr. Allen also held the
following offices in Bethel Church, (remember he was
appointed or elected to these positions before he was
ordained Elder or Bishop), trustee and steward, and after his
ordination, pastor of the Church. After the Rev. Allen
became Bishop, the people became dissatisfied. They
wanted him to resign all the offices in the Church except
that of the Bishoprick. They wanted Bishop Allen and the
Conference to appoint them a pastor yearly, and that the
five hundred dollars they agreed to pay the Bishop for life,
as pastor of the
<pb id="dsmith63" n="63"/>
Church, be paid to the pastors whom the Bishop and
Conference might send from time to time. There was quite a
number of the male members of the Church, who banded
themselves together and drew up a petition, making the
statements (as to his position as an officer of the Church)
and when the Conference met, (the Conference was held in
Bishop Allen's parlor) these men assembled in front of the
Bishop's house, with the petition to present to the Bishop
and Conference, asking Mr. Allen to resign his offices and
relinquish all personal claims previously entered into by
him and the congregation of Bethel Church. The Rev.
Richard Allen refused to allow their petition to be read
before the Conference. This created great dissatisfaction,
both in and out of the Conference. He went further than this
refusal, for at night he read these members out of the
Connection as disorderly members. Some of these members
were well to-do, and they went around on Lumbard street,
in a stone's throw of the Bethel church, and bought a lot, on
which to build an Independent church.</p>
          <p>There was great trouble both in the Church and the
<sic corr="families">familes</sic> of the congregation who belonged to, and attended
the Bethel church. Husband against wife, and <hi rend="italics">vice versa.</hi>
The cloud of discouragement
<pb id="dsmith64" n="64"/>
hovered over the newly organized
Connection, and the Conference was much afflicted. After
the Independent Congregation had put up a building; they
sent for Bishop Allen and desired to harmonize their
differences and they remain in the Connection if possible,
but the Rev. Richard Allen would not consent to their plans,
and furthermore, they differed among themselves, and a
great fight ensued and much blood was shed, but there were
no lives lost. The part of this Independent Congregation
which desired to accept Mr. Allen's plan of harmony, drew
out and went in what was called Hurst street, and built
themselves a Church. One was called <hi rend="italics">Big Wesley</hi> and the
other <hi rend="italics">Little Wesley.</hi> Little Wesley remained Independent
for a considerable while, and finally returned to the A. M. E.
Church. The real cause of so much division among the
colored people after the idea was obtained that they were at
liberty to organize and carry on distinct and seperate
religious bodies, was this:—a great many ambitious men came
to the front to obtain rule and fame. I desire to name a few
of such men: Rev. Thompson, Rush and Wm. Paul Quinn
set up seperate Churches in the city of New York, and Rev.
Peter Spencer, of Wilmington, Delaware, who met in the
Convention
<pb id="dsmith65" n="65"/>
at Philadelphia, when the A. M. E. Church was
organized. We do not wish in mentioning the names of this
class of men, to make the impression that these were men of
no influence and standing in the community in which they
lived; for they were certainly men of means and influence.
Many of then formed seperate bodies, some endured the
march of time, while others faded away. It was with Rev.
Richard Allen, Daniel Coker, Henry Harder, Stephen Hill
and other intelligent colored men, we may attribute the
origin of the <hi rend="italics">idea of Christian equality, freedom and 
self-government</hi> among the colored people of America. The Rev.
Richard Allen and his organization (A. M. E. Church) has
endured the march of time, and perhaps it may be attributed
to this fact—the A. M. E. Church started to catch up with
the times and unfold her Christian character according to the
progress of the present and future generation. The seed of
energy, character and intelligence which was set in motion
by these founders is seen to-day sending a healthy <hi rend="italics">influence</hi>
throughout the length and breath of the A. M. E. Church,
and thus the Church has been throwing off the old forms
and gathering new life and strength, as the years have come
and gone. And now more than a half <sic corr="century">centuary</sic> finds her in
possession
<pb id="dsmith66" n="66"/>
of great institutions of learning, and a publishing
department, Church Organ and an intelligent ministry.
After the Conference was over in Philadelphia, I took a
respite and moved from Baltimore to Philadelphia.</p>
          <p>These Independent members called on me, and desired me
to preach for them as their pastor, but this I refused to do.
They appointed a man from among themselves by the name
of Edward Johnson, he took charge of temporal concerns of
the Church. I want it well understood that I did not take any
part in the troubles between Mr. Allen and his people. My
peculiar disposition was and is to-day, not to be a <sic corr="sectarian;">secterian;</sic>
but having an ardent love for preaching and being possessed
of the missionary spirit, I was moved to go wherever there
was a door opened for the preaching of God's word. I agreed
however to take the Spiritual over-sight of the newly formed
organization.  I labored among <sic corr="them">then</sic> a considerable while; 
they wanted to come under some Connection; therefore 
asked my advice in the matter. I told them they could write to the Zion M. E.
Church, New York, and form a Connection, which they did
by calling a Convention as Mr. Allen and the founders of
the A. M. E. Church. This Connection was afterwards
called the Zion Wesleyan Connection.
<pb id="dsmith67" n="67"/>
The Rev. Mr. Rush was their first superintendent.
He desired me to go to Jersey City, nine miles
from New York; there I built a church and it
became very prosperous. At this time the whites
were mobbing the colored people and burning their
property all over the country. I then went to
Hartford, Connecticut, and established a Society
there; here I became acquainted with Mr. Burch,
who afterwards became a preacher in the A. M. E.
Connection. He is still living and preaching
in the State of Mississippi. I raised a Society in
Hartford, Con., and then went to Bridgeport and
built a church there. I remained in Bridgeport
six months. I then went to New York to see
Mr. Rush, the superintendent of the A. M. E.Z.
Connection, he desired my ordination papers; I
went into his room and he wrote on these papers,
that I was a preacher of the Zion Wesleyan Connection.
I could not write, or read writing; when
I found out what Mr. Rush had done, I determined
to go out of the reach of all of these contending
parties. I concluded to come West, but I did not
make my intention known to any one.</p>
          <p>During the time I was laboring with the Zion Wesleyan
Connection, there arose trouble between Bishop Allen and
Rev. Wm. Paul Quinn, and I am not able to say whether the
Rev. Quinn was
<pb id="dsmith68" n="68"/>
turned out of the Connection, or whether he left
the Bethel Connection. However this may be,
he went to New York and founded a Church with
about one hundred and fifty members; but he did
not succeed well with his enterprise. He requested
me to come and hold Quarterly meeting for
him, and while there the people became very
much attached to me, and wanted me to take
charge of their Church.</p>
          <p>Soon Bishop Allen died, and Bishop Morris
Brown filled his place.</p>
          <p>At a love feast in Philadelphia, Bro. Quinn,
having applied to join the Connection again,
Bishop Brown brought the matter before the
people and they consented to receive him with
this proviso:—that he should go West and speed
the Connection. This he agreed to do, and started
off the next morning, and he as all know, was
quite successful in his labors in the West. I soon
followed him to the far West. I passed through
Pittsburgh to Cincinnati, Ohio. I will speak in
the next chapter of my labor in Ohio. The
Macedonian cry, “come and help,” was heard on
the west side of the Allegheny <sic corr="mountains.">mountians.</sic></p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="dsmith69" n="69"/>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER X.
<lb/>
MY LABORS IN OHIO.</head>
          <p>Elder Quinn was the Presiding Elder over the West.
He met Bishop Morris Brown at Pittsburg, and came
from there to Chillicothe, Ohio. I understand this was
the second session of Conference which met in 1831. I
had just arrived in Cincinnati about the time the
Conference began its session at Chillicothe. I was then
in the midst of a great revival in Cincinnati, and many
souls were brought to Christ. Bishop Brown and Elder
Quinn had written to me, informing me that it was the
Bishop's intention to station Bro. Atchison in
Cincinnati, and desired that I should remain and assist
him in his pastoral duties. I consented, and through
our labors many souls were converted to God. I wish
to mention some important facts connected with the
Rev. Atchison's year's labor in Cincinnati:</p>
          <p>First.—I informed the people of Cincinnati that I was a
Mason, and I called them together and we raised three
hundred dollars in a few days. They immediately
selected a delegation (recommended by myself) and
sent them to the Philadelphia
<pb id="dsmith70" n="70"/>
Lodge (to which I belonged) to be made Masons. Mr.
Anderson was then Master of the Lodge of which I speak.
The delegation returned, bringing Mr. Anderson with them,
and immediately began to make colored Masons in the
West. We soon formed two numbers in the city, and from
this time out, masonry spread among the colored people in
the West like wild-fire. “Behold how great a matter a little
fire kindleth.”</p>
          <p>The colored people being wronged by the white people
of Cincinnati, and having nowhere nor means with which to
bury their dead, I proposed to form a benevolent society
among the colored population of Cincinnati. A great many
joined this society, and each member was to pay 25 cents
per month. We soon gathered considerable means, and the
society was in the act of putting out its money on interest
when I persuaded them to buy a burying ground, which 
they did. This proved a great blessing to the people of 
color in Cincinnati. Then I proceeded to establish a Ladies' 
Court among the Masons' wives and daughters. This society 
spread far and wide in the West, and to-day it is very extensive. 
Many other such societies of the kind have been formed and have 
done great good to my people. I am said to be the father of the
benevolent societies in the West.
<pb id="dsmith71" n="71"/>
I wish to make a short apology, not in the sense
of excusing myself for having set these societies at work in
the West, but I mean my apology in the way of deference
for my conduct in this direction, and at the time I was so
busily engaged in the noble work of organizing and carrying
on benevolent societies. 1st, Societies then, and their use.
2d, Societies now, and their abuses.</p>
          <p>It is a piece of wisdom, as well as it is natural, for the
races and nations of mankind to be united in love and for the
accomplishment of noble objects and enterprises in life.
History proves that the most united race or nation has ever
been the most successful and have accomplished the
greatest good for the world. When I came to the West, and
at the time when I was young and vigorous and in the active
field laboring for God and the good of my people, “The
people were like sheep having no shepherd,” devoured on
every side by the wolves of slavery, prejudice and
ostracism. They were daily destroyed and wasted by mobs,
both in the East and West, North and South. The great need
of my people was “leaders” and “organizers.” These leaders
were so few and the wants of the people so many, that they
were required to perform the religious, political, intellectual
and benevolent duties common to the
<pb id="dsmith72" n="72"/>
race; hence, you can readily see why I was forced to the
duty of organizing and carrying on benevolent associations
among my people at that time and under those
circumstances, and aside from these conditions which force
the religious leaders into so many positions which seem
unbecoming at the present time. The next thought which
presents itself to us is this fact: The existence of the
benevolent societies is justified.</p>
          <p>First —There was no admission to the poor houses for
colored people. They had no where to bury their dead. They
were not admitted to public schools nor churches without
impositions and afflictions; hence it was necessary for the
people to unite and assist each other in these directions. No
reasonable person will condemn these early fathers of the
race.</p>
          <p>Second.—Benevolent Societies of to-day, and their abuses.
While I claim to be the father of Benevolent Societies in the
West, I do not think that there is any just reason for the
existence of so many Benevolent Societies, and the extent to
which they are carried on by their leaders at the
present day. 1st, the necessity for their existence is not
urgent and plausible as it was at the time when I came out
West. All have admission (with few exceptions) to the
public schools, burying
<pb id="dsmith73" n="73"/>
grounds and infirmaries. Again the cities and towns have
their organized committies to see after the poor and supply
them with such things as they really need. Again, it is
claimed that the Churches are vastly injured by these
organizations, &amp;c. I have only this to say among the last
words of this life: If these Societies have become
demoralizing to the Church of God, I say away with them,
and let the present generation have some other institutions
in harmony with the Church of God, and which will meet
the wants of the present age.</p>
          <p>“To everything there is a season, and a time to every
purpose under the heaven.”</p>
          <p>The Church of God is the hope of the world, and in her
triumph and success is found all the best interests and
happiness of mankind. My prayer is that “the Kingdom of
God may come and his will be done on earth, as the angels
do it in heaven.”</p>
          <lg>
            <l>“Hosanna to our Conquering King!</l>
            <l> All hail, incarnated love!</l>
            <l>Ten thousand songs and glories wait</l>
            <l> To crown thy head above.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Thy victories and thy deathless fame,</l>
            <l>Through all the world shall run,</l>
            <l>And everlasting ages sing</l>
            <l>The triumphs thou has won.”</l>
          </lg>
        </div2>
        <pb id="dsmith74" n="74"/>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER XI.
<lb/>
MY FIRST APPOINTMENT IN OHIO.</head>
          <p>I do not recollect where the Conference met following the
session at Chillicothe, 1831. However this may be, at the
session of 1832, I was sent to lay out a circuit beginning at
Hamilton, O. The circuit comprised the following places:</p>
          <p>Hamilton, Mason, Lebanon, Harveysburg and Xenia.
These constituted what was known and called the Hamilton
circuit. I made very little progress either temporal or
spiritual, during the year, a black cloud of wickedness and
ignorance engrossed the minds and hearts of the people.
The whites were very much opposed to the prosperity of
the colored people. The colored people and the
abolitionists were persecuted and driven from their little
homes which they had accumulated by hard labor. Their
churches and houses were stoned and many were compelled
to sell out and go to Canada. This state of things continued
for quite a while. The mean and fiendish treatment the
colored people received from the low class of whites,
encouraged and urged on by the intelligent and wealthy, can
not be described. The
<pb id="dsmith75" n="75"/>
fugitive slave law was in full force, and this hellish
instrument made the low-class of whites companions of
blood hounds and negro hunters. In search for the fleeing
slaves, they would come in our houses at night and
maltreat our wives and daughters, and we had no appeal,
our oaths were useless breath and words spent to no
purpose.</p>
          <p>The Rev. M. M. Clarke, a scholar and the embodiment
of manliness, called a convention, and he and men of like
minds, established schools for the colored children, but
these were all broken up by mob laws. The school houses
were destroyed and the children stoned. After such fearful
destruction of his school enterprise, he joined the traveling
Connection and was stationed in Cincinnati—in this station
he met with great success. From here he went to the State
of Illinois. This eminent and enterprising man soon visited
the continent of Africa.</p>
          <p>I was again stationed in the city of Washington, D. C. He
returned and was much deranged in his mind; this affliction
came from family trouble which he encountered. We did
what we could for him in Washington, and sent him West,
and he became very useful again, and ended his days on
earth while stationed in New Orleans.</p>
          <p>I leave this point at present for fear the torch
<pb id="dsmith76" n="76"/>
of my indignation will be kindled and my manhood
aroused to an unchristian condition. In the <sic corr="original printing error">the</sic> sunset of my
life, when the battle-ax (the ballot) which defends my
manhood is placed at my disposal, I am bound by the
law of self-preservation, to cast it manfully against the
remains of that class who thus wronged and crushed the
people with whom I am identified.</p>
          <p>I now come back to my spiritual labors. The following
year, 1833, I was re-appointed to the Hamilton circuit, and
did much better than I did the first year. I established little
societies in all the places which constituted the Hamilton
circuit, with the exception of Harveysburg. I had what I
considered a successful camp meeting at Harveysburg, but
did not build any church there. When I visited this point I
usually preached in the United Brethren's church, as my
people did not have any place of worship. The Quakers and
the whites in general, were much taken up with me. The
next Conference year the Rev. James Woodson was
appointed to the Hamilton circuit, and I was made his
Presiding Elder. He did great good, temporal and spiritual,
and this year we formed a society in Oxford, and was
<sic corr="successful">succesful</sic> in getting a Church.</p>
          <p>The next year the Bishop saw fit to send me to
<pb id="dsmith77" n="77"/>
Chillicothe. The people were then worshiping in an old
delapidated frame church, but during the year I bought a
lot and paid for it. The people were poor and dilatory,
hence assisted me but little in my Church labors. However
I and some wicked friends with whom I had gotten
acquainted, and who thought a great deal of me, went out
and got the stone, boated them to Chillicothe and laid the
foundation for a new Church; this foundation remained for
ten years without a building. The same year I went to
Bainbridge and collected enough money to build a church
there. Allow me to say that the white friends at this place
were exceedingly liberal. Bro. Samuel Watts was appointed
to the Chillicothe charge and after he received his
appointment I persuaded him to go among the whites and
obtain money enough to build a church, and I remember I
gave him a gold dollar to start the work, he was quite
successful, and built the brick church which the
congregation now occupies.</p>
          <p>My next appointment was to the Columbus charge, by
Bishop Nazrey. It will be remembered by this time we (the
African Methodist) had the following Bishops: Bishop
Morris Brown, Quinn, Payne and Nazrey. I succeeded
the Rev. J. M. Brown. The Church was very much confused
<pb id="dsmith78" n="78"/>
and the officers all scattered, so much so that they would
not meet me when I arrived (trouble too bad to mention) I
went on doing the best I could and there was always a
crowd to hear what I had to say. Mr. Jas. Respus was one
of the trustees, but he did not profess faith in the Lord
Jesus. He was in good circumstances and a man of influence,
he and his wife declared they would stand by me. I stopped
with them, and he lifted the collections for me, until I could
get some men in the Church out of whom I might get some
officers. We had a successful revival and many were
converted to God. We soon re-organized the Church and
built a parsonage, by the help of the Lord. The parsonage
was built on the old Church lot. Mr. &amp; Mrs. Respus were
great helpers. He had two teams and agreed to haul the
stone to Capitol Square. I drove one of these teams for my
board that Conference year. As Conference came on the
people spoke very strongly of petitioning for my return,
but I heard of it and told them from the pulpit that I would
not come back the next year. Bishop Nazrey was on his way
to Detroit, Michigan, to hold Conference, and unbeknown
to me, the people wrote him to stop in Columbus as they
wished to have an interview with him upon the subject of
sending me back to Columbus, but I would not consent.</p>
          <pb id="dsmith79" n="79"/>
          <p>From the Detroit Conference, 1858, I was sent
to Allegheny, Penn.  There I found an old delapidated
church, with a few poor members who were
very deficient in business, and here wickedness
prevailed to a fearful extent. I did the best I
could, and after much hard labor, we had a 
great revival, collected three hundred dollars from the
white and colored people. At the same time
laboring under a great many disadvantages. We
repaired the church, and matters moved on nicely.
From the next Conference the Bishop appointed
me to the Zanesville charge, and here I found many
fine business and christian men and women. I succeeded
the Rev. A. R. Green, who died at Vicksburg, from the
yellow fever, a few years ago. He was considered at
that time one of our best business men, but was quite
self-willed. When I went to Zanesville, the Rev. A. R. 
Green had an enterprise on foot to obtain a place of
worship. He had gotten the people to subscribe
for this purpose, and it seems he had purchased
two lots with houses on them, and at the same
time he and the trustees held a claim on this
property. The trustees and the former pastor
had the books arranged so we could not understand
them, hence this made a division between the people
and trustees. I went to work and
<pb id="dsmith80" n="80"/>
turned the trustees out of the board, contrary to
the law and discipline of the Church, but it was
the best I could do. They declared war against
me and followed me to the Conference. I am 
sorry to say that the Rev. A. R. Green lead the
trustees in their persecutions against me. At the
Conference they instituted a trial against me, and
proved that I was guilty of mal-administration.
I acknowledged before the Conference that I had
turned out the trustees contrary to the law of the
Church. I was not working for David Smith, but
for God. I did wrong; therefore, I asked the
forgiveness of the Bishop and Conference, and also
the trustees. They readily forgave me, and the
Conference restored the trustees to their office
again.</p>
          <p>I then went to Bishop Nazrey and prayed him
to send the Rev. James A. Shorter to the Zanesville
charge, which he did, for Bishop Nazrey had
the utmost confidence in me. I knew full well 
that the Rev. James A. Shorter could settle any
difficulty of the kind according to the law and
discipline of the Church. He soon saw the trouble,
settled it and purchased the church I was
trying to buy from the white people. This ended all
the dispute, and the Church sailed on in peace
and harmony. Since that time Zanesville has
<pb id="dsmith81" n="81"/>
been among the leading appointments in the Ohio
Conference. Among the leading intelligent Christian
workers of Zanesville I have only to mention the
following: Bro. Messer, who held many important
positions in the Church at Zanesville; Bro. N. T. Gant, a
wealthy citizen and member of the A. M. E. Church, did
much toward building up this important charge. I might
mention many other noble-hearted Christian men and
women who did much to make the A. M. E. Church what
it is in the city of Zanesville.</p>
          <p>This charge has been blessed with some of the best
and most intelligent pastors of the Ohio Conference,
among whom were the Reverends A. R. Green, David
Smith, J. A. Shorter (now Bishop), S. H. Thompson, A.
A. Whiteman, G. H. Graham and Dr. John G. Mitchell.
These men have done much to inspire this
congregation to noble deeds. “Like priests; like
people.”</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="dsmith82" n="82"/>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER XII.
<lb/>
MY GENERAL LABORS.</head>
          <p>I wish to pause for a while with my labors in Ohio and
speak briefly of some of my general labors, which have
important connections with something I shall say in the
future.</p>
          <div3 type="subchapter">
            <head>HOW AFRICAN METHODISM WAS FIRST 
<lb/>INTRODUCED IN KENTUCKY.</head>
            <p>I went to New Orleans and remained there six months.
On my return I stopped in the city of Louisville, Ky. Here
I saw a lady that suited my fancy, and I therefore married
her, (my third wife). She was Sonney Lewis' widow. The
M. E. preacher who had charge of the colored and white
Methodists of Louisville knew me in Baltimore, and was
acquainted with the nature and object of the African M. E.
Church. He persuaded me not to say anything about the A.
M. E. Church, as it was very dangerous at that time for any
one to advocate the principles of Christian manhood which
the A. M. E. Church held and taught her adherents. There
was a man by the name of Rev. James Harper who was
<pb id="dsmith83" n="83"/>
pastor at Lexington about the time I stopped in the city.
He knew me years before, and was not upon very good
terms with me. He incited the people against me and the 
A. M. E. Church, calling us abolitionists. The white 
preacher of Louisville persuaded me to take charge of 
the Centre-street Church, and another little Church which 
belonged to a man by the name of Washington Spradley.
I consented, but did not join them.</p>
            <p>That year I became acquainted with a great many of the
white preachers and citizens of Louisville, and they had 
great confidence in me. That year I had wonderful success 
in Louisville. After my year was out I bought property and 
moved over to Jeffersonville, Ind., and raised a Society there. 
I also went back (now and then) to Louisville and preached 
in my wife's mother's house and raised a society under the
auspices of the A. M. E. Church. There was a man by the
name of Smith who agreed, if I could preach for the little
society in Louisville, he would pay my traveling expenses
to and from the city. The little society in Louisville soon 
bought a lot. I then <sic corr="laid">layed</sic> out the Jefferson circuit, comprising
New Albany, Charleston and Jeffersonville. We
built churches in New Albany and Jeffersonville. 
I found out where the Rev. William Paul Quinn
<pb id="dsmith84" n="84"/>
was (he was not then Bishop), and wrote to him to
come to Jeffersonville. He came, bringing the Rev.
George Johnson with him. He was Elder Quinn's
secretary. I stated to him what I had done, and he then
called a Quarterly Conference in Jeffersonville and
appointed the Rev. George Johnson to Louisville,
where he put up a little frame building on the lot they
bought in the city. This little society multiplied and
finally built “Quinn's Chapel.” He met with
considerable difficulty. We appointed Bro. George
Johnson's father to the Jeffersonville circuit, and my
house was headquarters.</p>
            <p>I had brought Major Wilkerson from New Orleans
with me and introduced him to the Ohio Conference
which met at Cincinnati. When the Conference met in
Cincinnati, William Paul Quinn was Presiding Elder.
He gave the Rev. Wilkerson charge of a circuit in
Indiana, and made me Presiding Elder over Rev.
George Johnson, his Father, and the Rev. Wilkerson.</p>
            <p>The following year the General Conference met in
Pittsburg, Pa., 1844. At this General Conference the
Rev. William Paul Quinn was made Bishop. I
prepared to go, but did not, for some reason best
known to myself. The following year the newly-made
Bishop organized the Indiana
<pb id="dsmith85" n="85"/>
Conference, and appointed Vincennes, on the Wabash
river, as the place of meeting. During this year I found the
Rev. Willis R. Revels, with whom I became acquainted in
Connecticut. He was in a very low condition, but he
prepared and went with me to the Conference. He afterward
became an eminent preacher in the A. M. E. Church, and
died at his home in Indianapolis, an honored member of the
Indiana Conference.</p>
            <p>I moved from Jeffersonville to Cincinnati. I took what was
called a ministerial respite, and retained this relation several
years. I will now return to my labors in Ohio. During the
years of general labor I became acquainted and was generally
known throughout the West. My acquaintance and labors
introduced me as an African Methodist, and the people of
the then Western States became friends to the A. M E.
Church; hence the seed of African Methodism, wafted from
the East to the West by a few sacrificing missionaries, grew
and spread into the plant of African Methodism, until to-day 
she claims her thousands of noble-hearted Christians in
the Middle and Western States. The noted name of the once
Bishop William Paul Quinn has only to be mentioned, and
the impulse of gratefulness echoes from the Pacific to the
summit of the Allegheny
<pb id="dsmith86" n="86"/>
mountains. I am generally called by the Western brethren
Father Smith, of Ohio.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="chapter">
          <head>CHAPTER XIII.
<lb/>
THE RETURN TO MY LABORS IN OHIO.</head>
          <p>When my respite was out in Cincinnati I was again
appointed to the Hamilton circuit. The following brethren
had charge of the circuit from the time I laid out the circuit
until I returned to it the second time: Reverends Newson,
Wells, Jessie, Devine, Rice and Daniel Winslow. These
brethren made a considerable improvement in the condition
of the circuit during their time. Just before Bro. Winslow left
the circuit I held a camp meeting for him at Mason, and it
was at this meeting that Bishop William Paul Quinn was
stabbed by some ruffian, but we are glad to say it was only
a flesh wound. He instituted a law suit, but it did not
amount to anything. He then went back to Philadelphia to
show the public what he suffered for his people in the
West, and the people had great sympathy for him.</p>
          <p>The next Conference year after this camp meeting, I
followed Brother Winslow on the Hamilton
<pb id="dsmith87" n="87"/>
circuit. I had a pleasant time, but little was done in the way
of building churches. Wesley Roberts negotiated (upon his
own responsibility) with a man by the name of Rader to
build a brick church in the lower part of Xenia. Mr. Rader
put up the walls and put the roof on the building and Bro.
Roberts became security for the money. This was toward
the end of Conference year. The circuit was so large that I
could not remain in Xenia long enough to do much in the
way of assisting the people to collect money to meet their
payment. At the session of the ensuing Conference I
advised the Conference to make Xenia a station, and that I
would go and be their pastor and trust God for my pay. “It
may not be my way or time, but in his way and time the
Lord will provide.”</p>
          <p>The Conference divided the Hamilton circuit and made
Xenia a station and returned me as the pastor. I had only
eight members, and nowhere to stay but at Brother Wesley
Roberts' house. The church had no floor in it, and I went to
work, got boards and put a floor in the church. The people
did not know anything about festivals. I went to
Cincinnati, and got some of the sisters out of our Church to
purchase such things as I needed for the occasion, and two
of them came
<pb id="dsmith88" n="88"/>
with me and assisted in carrying on the enterprise. We
realized a considerable amount of money to pay off our
debt, for we had two festivals almost in succession. There
were two things which made its successful in this
enterprise:</p>
          <p>First.—The people had a mind to work for those who were
members of the Church; were possessed of zeal and
magnanimity of heart and unanimity of purpose which aided
them to succeed; hence, they accomplished the work their
hands found to do. The work of building the church by the
eight members (assisted by the liberal-hearted community)
and this remarkable festival or festivals stands among the
greatest achievements of the A. M. E. Church in the city of
Xenia. Although the A. M. E. Church in Xenia has been
afflicted by a “split,” yet she has gathered and retained a fair
proportion of the intelligent and wealthy citizens of our
city, and bids fair to be among the prominent appointments
of the Ohio Conference.</p>
          <p>Soon after our festivals the news came that a railroad was to be
laid between Xenia and Dayton, and that it would take a part off
of our church lot. The people became very much dissatisfied and
discouraged, but, before the Conference year was up, I had
contracted for the church where we
<pb id="dsmith89" n="89"/>
now worship. We contracted for the same with a man by the
name of Barr for $1,200, and out of said amount Mr. Rader
was to be paid the balance due him for building the little
brick church, and at the same time Mr. Barr was to take the
NOTE we (the Church) held against the Railroad Company
who had bought our little church. By this time my year was
out.</p>
          <p>The next Conference year the Bishop appointed the Rev.
Jeremiah Bowman to the Xenia station. I was one of the
trustees of the Church in Xenia. I felt it my duty to guard
the interest of the Church I had labored so hard to obtain,
therefore I took a respite and came home to see after
matters. There was some informality in the notes given Mr.
Barr, and the Church had seven hundred dollars more to pay
than she had agreed to. The people were very much
dissatisfied with Mr. Bowman, for he was very disagreeable.
He had everything his own way, and went to work and
seated the Church, called the Quarterly Conference. He
appointed me Steward, and said the books, papers and
money of the Church should be put in my hands. I held my
peace, as there was much confusion.</p>
          <p>As soon as he got the church seated he sent for Bishop
Quinn and had the church consecrated,
<pb id="dsmith90" n="90"/>
and took up a collection of $18 or $20, which was
placed in my hands. I carried the money out
home (I was then living at Wilberforce). He
came the next morning and demanded the papers
and money to show them to the Bishop (as he
told me). I refused, and he became angry and
fell out with me. He came in the afternoon
(Monday) and said the Bishop was going away
on Tuesday and wanted to see the papers before
he departed. I gave him the papers and books,
but not the money. I gave the money to one of
the Stewards, Bro. Joseph Garrett, who lives in
Toledo. Tuesday morning, I came to Xenia,
saw Bishop Quinn, and stated to him what Bro.
Bowman had said. He knew nothing of it, but
said he wanted his expenses paid. The entire
year was one of trouble until the ensuing 
Conference. The next Conference was held in Xenia,
1856, Bishop D. A. Payne, presiding. I brought
a charge against Bro. Bowman for the manner
with which he had treated the people. Bro. Bowman 
brought a charge against me for interfering
with his charge. The Bishop stated that it was
necessary to try the charge against me first. The
committee decided that I was not guilty of interfering 
with Bro. Bowman's charge. Then they
proceeded with the charge against Bro. Bowman.
<pb id="dsmith91" n="91"/>
With this we leave the matter, saying none but God knows
the trouble the Church and Conference had with Bro.
Bowman.</p>
          <p>From the Xenia Conference I was appointed to the Troy
and Piqua circuit, succeeding the Rev. H. A. Jackson. The
cloud of trouble had turned into sunshine, and we had a
glorious time that year. After I served the Troy circuit one
year, Bishop Payne insisted that I should go to Washington,
D. C., as the people wanted me there very much. It had been
about forty years since I had established the Church in
Washington; hence, they wanted me to return, which I did.
This was in 1859 or 1860. I took charge of Israel Church
and had the oversight of the Church on the Island. There
seemed to be a strange feeling come over the people on my
return which I can not describe. There never was a time
when there seemed to be more union among the people than
at that time, though it was war times.</p>
          <p>I became acquainted with Mr. Lovejoy, who was a
member of Congress at the time. He, his wife and associates
would attend my Church. Mr. Lovejoy often preached for
me, and he and his associates and their wives contributed
largely to my support. The wives of this class of men (for
they were abolitionists of the deepest dye)
<pb id="dsmith92" n="92"/>
have given me many a five-dollar gold piece, and they would
tell me all about the efforts they were then putting forth to
make the District free. I could not keep it, but would often
tell my old brethren and sisters. They often begged me not
to say anything about it, for fear the white people would
get hold of it and maltreat them. Mr. Lovejoy said to me: “I
will let you know when the effort for the liberation of the
District is completed, and I want you to have a jollification
meeting in your Church.”</p>
          <p>This, I did. I was the first to publish it through
Washington and Georgetown. We had a wonderful
jollification meeting at which many of the Senators and their
wives were present. I preached from the following words:
“Greater is he that is for us than he that is against us.” O,
such a shout of joy as we had in and out of the church. It
can not be described. At night I tried to preach but failed,
for such was the joy of the people. During the year I built a
church in Good Hope and had a large society. The
Government took it for the use of the soldiers, but paid us
well for its use. We took the money, paid for the church and
everything seemed to go on gloriously and prosperously.</p>
          <p>The martial law of Washington became such
<pb id="dsmith93" n="93"/>
that no persons were allowed to leave the city; (I remained
in Washington during the war) I went to President Lincoln
and told him I wanted to go home to see my wife. He said
to me, “Father Smith, I can not give you a permit to go
home.” On the day I reached Xenia, Ohio, peace was
declared, and Oh, what rejoicing there was in the city over
the Union victory, tongue can not express it. I remained
home until the Ohio Conference met in Delaware. I was
then appointed by Bishop Quinn, to Kentucky as a
Missionary. The purpose was to get together all the
Churches which belonged to my people, or as many as I
possibly could. I succeeded in adding the following
Churches to the A. M. E. Church: St. Paul's Church,
Lexington, Ky., and I appointed the Rev. G. H. Shaffer as
pastor, and one at Georgetown which I had charge of; and
one at Nicholasville; and another at Harrodsburg. Rev. R.
Craig had the pastoral charge of the Harrodsburg. To the
Church at Frankfort, I appointed the Rev. W. H. Brown,
who was then a student at Wilberforce. To the Church at
Cynthiana, Rev. J. Francis. I do not recollect whom I
appointed to Danville. The Conference met in Chillicothe in
1866, and I brought my brethren to Conference from
Kentucky to be ordained, which was done, and they
<pb id="dsmith94" n="94"/>
were sent to enlarge the <sic corr="ministerial">ministeral</sic> ranks of the
A. M. E. Church, and now the little Kentucky
field has so enlarged in the last ten years, she has
become a <sic corr="separate">seperate</sic> Conference in our Connection,
known as the “Kentucky Conference of the A. M. E. 
Church,” and now has between fifty and 
sixty regular appointments, with five or six thousand 
members. At the last session, September,
1880, this Conference was divided, and now there
are two Conferences in the State of Kentucky.
Glory to God for the wonderful success that the
humble labors of his servant have accomplished
in that field and part of his vineyard.</p>
          <lg>
            <l>“This work, to thee, God, in faith we lay,</l>
            <l>This work, Lord, to thee we raise;</l>
            <l>Thine eye be opened night and day,</l>
            <l>To guard this work of prayer and praise.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Upon this work heavenly peace,</l>
            <l>And holy love, and concord dwell,</l>
            <l>Here give the burdened conscience ease.</l>
            <l>And the wounded spirit heal.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>But will, indeed, Jehovah deign,</l>
            <l>Here to abide no transient guest,</l>
            <l>Here will our great Redeemer reign,</l>
            <l>And here the Holy Spirit rest.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Never let thy glory hence depart;</l>
            <l>Yet choose not, Lord, this shrine alone,</l>
            <l>Thy Spirit dwell in every heart,</l>
            <l>In every bosom fix thy throne.”</l>
          </lg>
          <pb id="dsmith95" n="95"/>
          <p>My next appointment was to Urbana station. I was
appointed to the charge by Bishop Payne, 1873, to fill out
the incomplete year of the Rev. J.W. Steward. We succeeded
in taking in eighty-three new members, and raised seven
hundred dollars to pay on Church debts, &amp;c. The Bishop
returned me to the Urbana station from Conference.
Everything went on nicely for a while, then one of the
officers became dissatisfied, saying I was too old, and used
his influence in the official board against me, until he got his
associates dissatisfied. He and the other official members
told me at an official meeting, “that they had nothing against
me, only that I was too old to entertain the congregation,” (I
mean the young folks). I want you to mark, this fact—these
young people had come in the Church under my
administration. I think the real cause was this: They wanted
a young preacher.</p>
          <p>I made it a practice to carry the young preachers, &amp;c.,
when I went to Urbana on Sabbath, and these fathers in the
Church, appreciating young men, were moved to this unjust
complaint against me. I have always made it a rule of my
life, never to stay with a people that did not want me. I
therefore told them to write a statement to that effect, and
that I would convey it to Bishop
<pb id="dsmith96" n="96"/>
Payne. I did so, and the Bishop moved me immediately.
This ended my labors in Urbana.</p>
          <p>The next appointment I received was to the Troy and
Piqua circuit. I met with little success at this point, yet I
succeeded in keeping the Church together, and I also
collected some money to assist in enlarging the Church. 
I gave fifty dollars for that purpose. The Church was 
remodeled after my Conference year was up.</p>
          <p>The next Conference met in Portsmouth. I located at this
Conference: From then until the writing of this book I have
been going through the Connection, assisting the brethren
and anxiously watching the success of the A. M. E.
Connection.</p>
          <p>Now, at the close of nearly a century of years, I stand, as
it were, up in the dome of African Methodism. My ears are
saluted with the noise of a mighty Christian army of the
sable sons that have arisen out of the waters of Africa—an
army comprising fifteen hundred traveling preachers, three
hundred and thirty-six thousand members, and one
publishing house, situated at 631 Pine street, Philadelphia.
At this publication department the great organ of the A.M.
E. Church is printed,—“The Christian Recorder”—, which is
the exponent and battle-axe of the race, exposing
<pb id="dsmith97" n="97"/>
corruption in Church and State and defending
the Christian manhood of the race. We have two
foreign missionaries—one stationed in Hayti and
the other in Africa.</p>
          <p>I wish to speak of the last great department of
the A. M. E. Church that has arisen since she
started—the <hi rend="italics">Christian lighthouse</hi> of the A. M. E.
Church—viz: Wilberforce University.  Why do
I speak so particularly and emphasize so strongly
upon this department of the Church? Simply,
because the future developments of our beloved
Church lay in the education and character of her
<hi rend="italics">ministerial rank, for as the preachers are so will
the people be.</hi> The cause must produce <hi rend="italics">like effect.</hi>
A wise and holy ministry will create and develop
a wise and holy Church. As we look through
the window of prophecy we read these sentences:
“For the earth shall fill with the knowledge of
God as the waters cover the sea.”—Heb. 2-14.
To show what progress we are making toward a
Holy ministry and Christian education, I refer the
readers to the History of Wilberforce as carefully
prepared and published by Rt. Rev. D. A. Payne,
D. D.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="illustration">
        <pb id="dsmith98" n="98"/>
        <p>
          <figure id="ill1" entity="smith98">
            <p>[Illustration]</p>
            <p/>
          </figure>
        </p>
      </div1>
      <div1 type="text">
        <pb id="dsmith99" n="99"/>
        <head>CHAPTER XIII.
<lb/>
 THE HISTORY
<lb/>
OF THE 
<lb/>
ORIGIN AND DEVELOPMENT
<lb/>
OF 
<lb/>
WILBERFORCE UNIVERSITY</head>
        <docAuthor>BY BISHOP DANIEL A. PAYNE, (<hi rend="italics">Its Former Pres't.</hi>)</docAuthor>
        <div2 type="subchapter">
          <head>WILBERFORCE UNDER THE AUSPICES OF THE
<lb/>
M. E. CHURCH.</head>
          <p>“It was in one of the darkest periods of the Nation's
history, when the Cincinnati Conference of the Methodist
Episcopal Church, moved by the inspiration of Christian
philanthropy, appointed a committee of seven to consider
and report a plan for the improvement of the intellectual
and moral condition of the thirty thousand colored people
of Ohio, and those of other free States, by furnishing them
such facilities of education as had been
<pb id="dsmith100" n="100"/>
generally beyond their reach. This period was that
intervening the passage of the Fugitive Slave Bill and the
breaking out of the civil war. The demon of slavery had
reached the zenith of its power, and was preparing for its
deadly struggle with the genius of liberty. ‘A Brief History
of the Enterprise’ was written by one of its chief actors, and
is too interesting and important a leaf in the history of our
national progress to be abridged. I therefore give it here,
<hi rend="italics">verbatim et literatim.</hi> It is from the pen of Rev. John F.
Wright, D. D.:</p>
          <q direct="unspecified">
            <text>
              <body>
                <div1 type="speech">
                  <p>“ ‘The mission of Methodism, like that of the Gospel, is
to every human being. All classes have engaged her
attention, especially the poor; and the colored people of this
and other lands have shared of her sympathy and labors.
In 1853 some of the ministers and members of the Methodist
Episcopal Church saw and felt the necessity of a more
liberal and concentrated effort to improve the condition and
furnish the <sic corr="facilities">facilitles</sic> of education to the thirty thousand
colored people in Ohio and those of other free States. At the
session of the Cincinnati Conference, held at Hillsboro,
September 28th, 1853, on motion of Rev. A. Lowrey, it
was ordered ‘that a committee of seven be appointed by the
President to inquire and report to the next Conference what
can best be done to promote the welfare of the colored
people among us.’ Bishop Janes appointed the following
that committee, namely: John F. Wright, Augustus Eddy,
A. Lowrey, G. Moody, J. T. Mitchell, William I. Fee,
and Charles Elliott.</p>
                  <pb id="dsmith101" n="101"/>
                  <p>“ ‘A majority of the committee met on the call of the
chairman, at the Methodist Book Concern, on the 9th of
August, 1854, and on a full and free discussion, adopted the
following brief outline of a plan which was judged best
calculated to answer the end had in view, and which the
chairman was requested to elaborate in a report to be
presented to the Conference:</p>
                  <p>“ ‘1. <hi rend="italics">Resolved,</hi> That it is of the greatest importance, both
to the colored and white races in the free States, that all the
colored people should receive at least a good common
school education; and that for this purpose well-qualified
teachers are indispensable.</p>
                  <p>“ ‘2. That the religious instruction of the colored people is
necessary to their elevation as well as their salvation.</p>
                  <p>“ ‘3. That we recommend the establishment of a literary
institution of a high order for the education of the colored
people generally, and for the purpose of preparing teachers
of all grades to labor in the work of educating the colored
people in our country and elsewhere.</p>
                  <p>“ ‘4. That we recommend that an attempt be made, on
the part of the Methodist Episcopal Church, to co-operate
with the African Methodist Episcopal Church in promoting
the intellectual and religious improvement of the colored
people.</p>
                  <p>“ ‘5. That we recommend the appointment of a general
agent to carry out the objects proposed in the foregoing
resolutions, and to labor otherwise for the improvement
of the people of color.</p>
                  <pb id="dsmith102" n="102"/>
                  <p>“ ‘6. That we will furnish all the Conferences in the free
States of the West with a copy of our resolutions, and
respectfully request them to cooperate with us.</p>
                  <p>“ ‘7. That the editor of the Western Christian Advocate be
requested to publish the foregoing resolutions, and call the
attention of the Conferences invited to concur in them, in
such remarks as he may deem proper.</p>
                  <signed>“ ‘JOHN F. WRIGHT, <hi rend="italics">Chairman.</hi>
“ ‘A. LOWREY, <hi rend="italics">Secretary.</hi>
’”</signed>
                </div1>
              </body>
            </text>
          </q>
          <p>Dr. C. Elliott accompanied the publication of these
resolutions with an able editorial.</p>
          <p>The chairman of the committee was directed to
communicate this plan to the several Conferences in the
West for their consideration and concurrence. This was
done, and many of those Conferences took favorable action
on it, which showed that they were not only ready to adopt
the outline of this great movement, but to assist in carrying
it out.</p>
          <p>“The committee, as instructed, made a report to the
Cincinnati Conference, held in the city, September 23,
1854.</p>
          <p>“We have but little space, and can make but a short
extract from this report. It says: “We give no countenance
to any theory which goes to deprive the black man of his
full share in our common humanity, but hail him as a man, a
brother, in accordance with that grand affirmation of the
Bible, which must forever settle the unity of the human race;
that God ‘hath made of one blood all nations of men, for
to dwell on the face of the
<pb id="dsmith103" n="103"/>
earth.’ Hence, we cordially concede our obligation to do
good to the colored race, according to our ability and their
necessity. Here, then, is an extensive field open for
benevolent enterprise, where a part of the large donations of
the rich and the smaller contributions of those of less ability
may advantageously mingle together, and where the
patriot, the statesman, and the philanthropist of every
description may unite in the accomplishment of this noble
work.”</p>
          <p>“Several resolutions were appended to the report. One
recommended the establishment of a literary institution of a
high order for the education of the colored youth; and one
recommended the appointment of a general agent. The
entire report was adopted by the Conference, and John F.
Wright was appointed the agent.</p>
          <p>The general agent, although he had to serve a large district
as presiding elder, labored quite extensively, by
correspondence and otherwise, in the work assigned him,
bearing his own expenses. He succeeded in awakening a
lively interest on the subject, and in attracting the attention
and exciting the hopes of the colored people.</p>
          <p>At the session of the Cincinnati Conference, September
28th, 1855, the committee, consisting of Rev. C. W. Swain,
A. Lowrey, and M. Dustin, to whom was referred the
elevation of the colored people, reported the following 
resolutions, which were adopted by the Conference:</p>
          <p>“<hi rend="italics">Resolved,</hi> That we recommend the appointment of
Rev. John F. Wright as general agent
<pb id="dsmith104" n="104"/>
for this Conference, to take the incipient steps for a College
for the colored people in this State.</p>
          <p>“<hi rend="italics">Resolved,</hi> That our delegates be, and are hereby
instructed, to bring this subject before the next General
Conference for their sanction and assistance.</p>
          <p>“<hi rend="italics">Resolved,</hi> That it be the duty of our general agent to 
co-operate with the African Methodist Episcopal Churches in
promoting Sabbath schools and other educational interests
of the colored people.”</p>
          <p>The Conference associated with their general agent C. W.
Swain, A. Lowery, M. Dustin and M. French, to carry out
the first resolution, having reference to the eligible and
valuable Xenia Springs property, in Greene county, Ohio.</p>
          <p>The general agent and the committee associated with him
held their first meeting at the Methodist Book Concern,
Cincinnati, on the 31st of October, 1855, all present except
Rev. C. W. Swain. John. F. Wright was appointed
Chairman, and M. French, Secretary.</p>
          <p>At this meeting the agent was authorized to commence
negotiating with the owners for the purchase of the Xenia
Springs property, that being preferred by the committee as
the most eligible location for such an institution. The agent
was also authorized to make an offer for the property, and
solicit subscriptions and donations for the object.</p>
          <p>The offer made by the agent in behalf of the committee
was declined, but the negotiations were continued till the
amount of difference between
<pb id="dsmith105" n="105"/>
the parties was reduced to five hundred dollars. At this
point Mrs. Judge McLean exerted her kind influence in 
<sic corr="bring">brining</sic> about a contract for the purchase.</p>
          <p>An offer of $13,500 was made to one of the principal
owners, who laid it before his partner in the East, and as no
answer was returned to the Western owner for a longer time
than was usual, he inferred his friend approved of the sale,
and closed the contract, agreeing to the payments
proposed, and so informed his Eastern partner.</p>
          <p>The former letter had then been received, and he objected
to the terms on which Mr. D. had agreed to sell the
property. He came out in person, and Messrs. Wright and
French, after a long interview, received from him the most
favorable terms on which he would sell, as follows: One-fourth
of $13,500 to be paid down, or a note given, including ten
per cent. interest, at sixty days, with personal endorsers;
the balance in one and two years; notes to be given by the
commissioners of the Conference for the deferred payments,
with approved personal endorsers, and all secured by a
mortgage on the property, six per cent. interest to be paid
semi-annually—allowing us only ten days to consider and
comply with the conditions.</p>
          <p>Messrs. Wright and French soon obtained an interview
with their associates at the General Conference at
Indianapolis, and after a deliberate consultation, they all,
except Rev. C. W. Swain, agreed, in order to secure this
valuable and in every way suitable property for this
benevolent
<pb id="dsmith106" n="106"/>
object, that they would sign notes for the amount, and do
what they could to procure endorsers.</p>
          <p>In the meantime, this philanthropic work had been
presented to the General Conference, and referred to a
committee, consisting of Rev. Cyrus Brooks, Z. Connell,
Moses Hill, H. E. Pilcher, M. Dustin, F. C. Holliday and
R. Boyd. On the 22d of May, 1856, through their chairman,
the committee made their report. It commences with a
history of the movement, and then describes the Xenia
Springs property, including fifty-two acres of ground, with
a large edifice, with numerous rooms, which are well adapted
for the purpose of a boarding-house, school and class-rooms,
chapel, etc.; also several cottages, well adapted to the use
of private families. There are several mineral and other springs
on the premises, the whole having been fitted up for a
fashionable watering place, at a cost of some $50,000. It is
situated in Greene county, Ohio, very near a good turnpike
road, about midway between Cincinnati and Columbus, and
near the railway. It is easy of access, and yet retired, in a
rural, beautiful and healthy region, and in nearly as mild a
climate as can be obtained north of the Ohio river.</p>
          <p>The following resolutions, with the whole report, were
adopted by the Conference with great unanimity, and
without an expressed objection:</p>
          <p>“<hi rend="italics">Resolved,</hi> That in the judgment of this General
Conference, the religious education of the people of color in
our land, will tend most effectually and speedily, under
God, to their elevation in this country, and to prepare the
way for the
<pb id="dsmith107" n="107"/>
restoration of the benighted millions of downtrodden
Africa to the blessings of civilization, science and religion.</p>
          <p>“<hi rend="italics">Resolved,</hi> That we look upon the proposed plan for
the education of the colored youth of our land as of God,
and as promising great good to the people of color among
us, and untold blessings to the land of their ancestors; and
we do most earnestly recommend this noble work to the
sympathy, the prayers, and the generous benefactions of all
who desire the elevation of the entire family of man.</p>
          <p>“<hi rend="italics">Resolved,</hi> That we bespeak for the agents of this
enterprise a cordial reception on the part of all Christians
and philanthropists, hoping that they may be successful,
not only in awakening sympathy and enlisting prayers, but
also in gathering funds to pay for the property purchased,
and to afford a liberal <sic corr="endowment">endownment</sic> of the Institution, so
as to place it on an equal footing with the best institutions
of learning in our country.”</p>
          <p>Messrs. Wright and French with great pleasure,
heard of the favorable action of the General 
Conference, and applied themselves with increased
exertions to comply with the conditions made by
Mr. B., the hardest of which seemed to be to 
procure men from pure philanthropy to endorse their
notes. Yet they found business men who 
determined to take the risk for the sake of advancing
the intellectual and moral improvement of the
most neglected and needy portion of our population.
It was known that another party stood
ready to close the contract with the owners if
<pb id="dsmith108" n="108"/>
they failed, offering $1500 more. They had till Saturday,
the 24th of May, to meet the conditions, and by diligent
and continued efforts the last endorser was obtained, half an
hour before midnight, at which the time allowed expired.
As they are deemed worthy of imperishable honor, we
render the small tribute of here recording their names, with a
clear conviction that their record is on high, and a strong
hope that they will have a brighter and more enduring
reward in the decisions of the great day.</p>
          <p>The names are: Wm. Wood, Alexander Webb, John
Dubois, Morris S. Hopper. The general agent advanced
$376, and for the balance of the cash payment, $3000, a
note was given at sixty days, endorsed by William Wood,
John Elstner, and W. B. Smith &amp; Co.—names never to be
forgotten.</p>
          <p>This enterprise was commenced by faith in that God
who hath respect unto the lowly, and who can control the
hearts of all men, and its friends have cause to thank God
and take courage.</p>
          <p>Immediately after the purchase, the general agent entered
upon his work of soliciting funds to meet the note of $3000
due in sixty days. He collected some in the West, and going
to the East he had some success in New York, Boston,
Providence, Woonsocket, New Bedford, and other places
in New England and New York; and it ought to be said, to
the honor of Dr. W. G. Palmer, that a few days before the
note matured he loaned the agent, on his individual note,
$1000, by which, with other funds, the note was paid.</p>
          <pb id="dsmith109" n="109"/>
          <p>On the 30th day of August, 1856, application
was made in due form, to the authorities of Greene
county, and State of Ohio, for the benefit of the general law
of the State, passed April 9th, 1852; and every requisition
of the law being complied with, the institution was
organized and constituted a body corporate, under the name
of  “The Wilberforce University.” The corporators adopted
articles of association and elected a Board of twenty-three
Trustees. Some changes have taken place in the Board since
its first organization; the present catalogue, however, will
show the names of the members of the Board is it now
exists. At the first meeting John F. Wright, was elected
President of the Board, and M. French, Secretary; and Rev.
Professor F. Merrick was elected President of the
University. There was, however, no demand at that time
for his services at the institution, and the school was
supplied with teachers for the time being, as they were
needed.</p>
          <p>Professor James K. Parker served as Principal
from February, 1857, to July, 1858, and then 
retired with commendation of the Board. Prof.
Merrick having declined serving, on the 30th of
June, 1858, Rev. Richard S. Rust, a distinguished
member of the New Hampshire Conference, was
unanimously elected President of the Institution.
When officially notified of his election, after 
finding he could be released from an important
pastoral charge, he signified his willingness to
accept the appointment, and at the commencement
of the fall term he entered upon his work.
<pb id="dsmith110" n="110"/>
He has shown himself well qualified, and has
been eminently successful in his position. The
number of students has varied from seventy to
one hundred. Many of them are very promising,
and some have made remarkable proficiency in
their studies. Every year the school has been
visited with a gracious revival of religion, and
many of the pupils have been made the happy
subjects of a work of grace which is deemed all
important to their usefulness in life. This benevolent 
scheme is based on the supposition that the
colored man must, for the most part, be the 
educator and elevator of his own race in this
and other lands. Hence, a leading object of the 
institution is to educate and thoroughly train many 
of them for professional teachers, or for any other 
position or pursuit in life to which God, in
His providence, or by his Spirit, may call them. It 
has also been a cherished idea with the founders of 
the Institution that a Theological Department should 
be organized at the earliest period possible, in which 
young men called of God to preach “the unsearchable 
riches of Christ” might receive that aid so essential to 
prepare them for this great work. We are happy to 
learn that several young men have already
entered this department, who give promise of great
usefulness to the Church and the world. Our enterprise has
enlisted the hearts and received the favor of some
distinguished statesmen and other citizens of our common
country, and is designed to unite and engage the efforts of
all Christians and philanthropists. Several of the leading
denominations of Christians
<pb id="dsmith111" n="111"/>
are represented in the Board of Trustees. We have good
reasons to believe this work is of God, that His hand is in
it, and His blessing will be upon it, and, therefore, we hope
for good results.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <head>IMMEDIATE RESULTS.</head>
          <p>The catalogue of 1859—60, shows a roll of 207
students, the majority of whom were the natural
children of Southern and Southwestern planters.
These came from the plantation with nothing
mentally but the ignorance, superstition, and vices
which slavery engenders; but departed with so
much intellectual and moral culture as to be 
qualified to be teachers in several of the Western
States, and, immediately after the over-throw of
slavery, entered their native regions as teachers of
the freedmen.</p>
          <p>A large number were gathered from the free States, and
others from some of the most respectable families in
Pennsylvania, Ohio, Illinois and California. These
derived the greater benefit from the instruction given at
<sic corr="Wilberforce,">Wilberfore,</sic> and were prepared for a higher sphere of
usefulness. Dr. Rust had also formed a class in the Classics
and Mathematics; another in French; and a third had
commenced theological studies, of whom were six young
men, who have since distinguished themselves in the
pastoral and other fields of usefulness, covering politics,
the military service of the United States, and the publishing
department of the African M. E. Church. One of these ran a
short but glorious career as a pastor, and is gone to enjoy
the “Saints' everlasting rest.”</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="dsmith112" n="112"/>
        <div2 type="text">
          <head>WILBERFORCE UNDER THE AUSPICES OF
<lb/>THE A. M. E. CHURCH.</head>
          <p>On the 10th of March, 1863, between 9 and 10 o'clock, P. M., 
one of the Bishops of the A. M. E. Church agreed with
the original Trustees<ref id="ref1" n="1" rend="sc" target="note1" targOrder="U">*</ref><note id="note1" n="1" rend="sc" place="foot" anchored="yes" target="ref1"><p>*The original Trustees consisted of twenty-four persons, four 
of whom were colored.</p></note> of Wilberforce University to
purchase the property for the A. M. E. Church, to be used
as an institution of education for the colored race; which
was, at the time, excluded from all the schools of higher
education, excepting two or three, of which Oberlin was
chief. Their admission into others, if admitted at all, was on
such conditions as few persons of color would accept. This
Bishop associated with himself, Rev. James A. Shorter and
Mr. John G. Mitchell, who was at that time Principal of a
graded school in the city of Cincinnati. These three persons
applied for and obtained a new charter for Wilberforce, in
the name of the A. M. E. Church, according to the general
law of Ohio.</p>
          <p>Under this charter they organized a new Board of
Trustees, and the school was re-opened on the 3d day of 
July, 1863, by Prof. John G. Mitchell. Only six children
were present. They were put upon the study of elementary 
English.</p>
          <p>During the first ten months the school gradually
increased in members and progressed in knowledge.</p>
          <p>Professor Mitchell was aided by his wife, Mrs. Fannie
A. Mitchell.</p>
          <pb id="dsmith113" n="113"/>
          <p>At the opening of the spring of 1864, the
increasing numbers demanded another teacher, and
Miss Esther T. Maltby, of Oberlin, then a teacher
in the schools of the American Missionary Society,
at Portsmouth, Va., was secured as Lady Principal
and Matron.</p>
          <p>She reached Wilberforce with a Greek testament
in her hand. It was her traveling companion
all along the journey from Portsmouth to Xenia.</p>
          <p>This circumstance I am particular to mention,
because the fact furnished us with a key to her
character, as it seemed to have colored her 
life since. She was an excellent Greek and
Latin scholar, a good mathematician, and has no
superior, that I ever saw, as a disciplinarian.
Zealous for the moral purity of the children and
youths committed to her care, she labored day and
night to induce them to be Christians as well as
scholars.</p>
          <p>The ordinary religious services of the Institution
were not sufficient for her; she, therefore, held an
extra prayer meeting every morning, from 8 to 8 1/2
o'clock, in which she read the Holy Scriptures,
exhorted, sang, and prayed with those who were
willing to attend her meetings, and succeeded in
leading many from their vices, to live an upright
life; among whom was a very playful and 
mischievous lad, by the name of Thomas H. Jackson,
who united with the College Church, graduated
from the Theological Department of the University,
filled the chair of Ecclesiastical History, Pastoral
Theology, and Homiletics for two years
<pb id="dsmith114" n="114"/>
at Wilberforce; severed in the pastorate of a large
Church at Columbia, South Carolina, for three
years, and at the last annual meeting of the Trustees
was re-elected to fill the same chair.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <head>THE CATASTROPHE OF 1865.</head>
          <p>Professor Mitchell had been constrained, by the
wants of the school, to go out as a financial agent.
The management of the school was left solely to
Miss Maltby, and, under God, it was increasing
in numbers and popularity.</p>
          <p>The progress of the students was commendable,
and classes were formed in Greek, Latin, and the
lower Mathematics. Everything indicated a 
prosperous future, when suddenly the buildings were
set on fire by incendiaries. Within half an hour
the beautiful edifice was nothing but smouldering
embers. The catastrophe fell upon us like a clap of
thunder in a clear sky.</p>
          <p>It was a time of lamentation for our friends,
and rejoicing for out enemies. Said one of the 
latter, “Now their buildings are burned, there is
no hope for them.” Another said, “I wish lightning
from heaven would burn down Wilberforce.”
This one supposed his impious prayer was more
than answered.</p>
          <p>But we believed and said, “Out of the ashes of
the beautiful frame building a nobler one shall
rise.” Mr. Mitchell had gone to Xenia, with
almost all the students, to witness the celebration
of the fall of Richmond.</p>
          <p>Two obstreperous female students were detained
on the grounds by way of punishment for acts of
<pb id="dsmith115" n="115"/>
disobedience. I was attending Conference at Baltimore, and
Miss Maltby was left alone. No, she was not alone. As
God was with Daniel in the lion's den, and with his three
brethren in the fiery furnace, so was He with her in the
trouble at Wilberforce. Without faltering, one of the
cottages was converted into a school-room, and the
scholars taught therein, till the last of June, which
terminated the academic year; after which,
all the students from abroad went home.</p>
          <p>The majority of the advanced students never
returned, but went to other institutions. Those who
preferred Wilberforce came back the next autumn.
Meanwhile, we began to mature our plans for rebuilding.
The result is before the country. The edifice will be
finished and dedicated next summer, and will be a larger,
finer, and nobler edifice than the former. As respects the
school, it passed through severe trials.</p>
          <p>Miss Maltby's nervous system was so affected
by the catastrophe, that for twelve month's she
was unfit for labor, and never returned. She is
now a missionary in Asia Minor, in the service of
the A. B. C. F. M. Professor Mitchell was compelled 
to be in the field, soliciting funds to aid us
in rebuilding, and, therefore, for a season, the
management of the school fell upon our most 
advanced student, Mr. J. P. Shorter, who acted his
part nobly, until we were able to secure the services 
of competent Professors, who were soon
found in the persons of Professor Theodore E.
Suliot, Professor William Kent, and Miss Sarah J.
Woodson.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="dsmith116" n="116"/>
        <div2 type="text">
          <head>OPENING OF THE DEPARTMENTS.</head>
          <p>The Theological and Classical were opened in the
autumn of 1866; the Scientific in 1857; the Normal in
1872.</p>
          <p>Graduates have gone forth from all these 
Departments, except the Law, and only three from
that have been put upon the study of Law.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="list">
          <list type="simple">
            <head>GRADUATES FROM THE THEOLOGICAL 
<lb/>DEPARTMENT.</head>
            <item>Rev. John F. Janifer, B. D. . . . . 1870</item>
            <item>Rev. Thomas H. Jackson, B. D. . . . . 1870</item>
            <item>Rev. Isaiah H. Welch, B. D. . . . . 1870</item>
            <item>Rev. Benjamin F. Lee, B. D. . . . . 1872</item>
            <item>Rev. George T. Robinson, B, D. . . . . 1872</item>
            <item>Rev. Charles Edward Herbert, B. D. . . . . 1872</item>
            <item>Rev. John W. Beckett, B. D. . . . . 1872</item>
            <item>Rev. Henry A. Knight, B. D. . . . . 1875</item>
            <item>Rev. John Coleman, B. D. . . . . 1875</item>
            <item>Rev. John G. Yeiser, B. D. . . . . 1876</item>
            <item>Rev. George C. Whitfield, B. D. . . . . 1876</item>
          </list>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="list">
          <list type="simple">
            <head>FROM THE CLASSICAL.</head>
            <item>Mr. Joseph P. Shorter, A. B. . . . . 1871</item>
            <item>Mr. Samuel T. Mitchell, A. B. . . . . 1873</item>
            <item>Mr. Alexander Dumas Delany, A. B. . . . . 1873</item>
            <item>Miss Mary E. Davis, A. B. . . . . 1874</item>
            <item>Miss Julia A. Shorter, A. B. . . . . 1873</item>
            <item>Mr. Samuel R. Bailey, A. B. . . . . 1874</item>
            <item>Mr. Andrew T. Bowles, A. B. . . . . 1876</item>
          </list>
        </div2>
        <pb id="dsmith117" n="117"/>
        <div2 type="list">
          <list type="simple">
            <head>FROM THE NORMAL. </head>
            <item>Miss Almira Copeland, B. E. . . . . 1873</item>
            <item>Miss Virginia Copeland, B. E. . . . . 1873</item>
            <item>Miss Maggie E. Crable, B. E. . . . . 1873</item>
            <item>Miss Carrie L. Jenkins, B. E. . . . . 1873</item>
            <item>Miss Ella J. Greene, B. E. . . . . 1873</item>
            <item>Miss Elizabeth W. Baker, B. E. . . . . 1876</item>
          </list>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="list">
          <list type="simple">
            <head>FROM THE SCIENTIFIC DEPARTMENT.</head>
            <item>Miss Lottie P. Harris, B. S. . . . . 1872</item>
            <item>Miss Hallie Q. Brown, B. S. . . . . 1873</item>
            <item>Miss Mary E. Ashe, B. S. . . . . 1873</item>
            <item>Miss Caroline Z. Jenkins, B. S. . . . . 1875</item>
            <item>Miss Zelia R. Ball, B. S. . . . . 1875</item>
          </list>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <head>SUCCESSION OF PRINCIPALS, PROFESSORS AND
<lb/>TEACHERS UNDER THE AUSPICES OF THE
<lb/>CINCINNATI CONFERENCE OF THE METHODIST
<lb/>E. CHURCH.</head>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>I.</head>
            <item>Rev. M. P. Gaddis, Principal; Mrs. M. P. Gaddis,
Assistant, about six months.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>II.</head>
            <item>Professor James K. Parker, Principal; Mrs. James K.
Parker, Matron; Miss Maggie Baker, Teacher of Music;
Miss Mary J. Allen, Teacher of English, about two years.</item>
          </list>
          <list type="simple">
            <head>III.</head>
            <item>Rev. Richard S. Rust, D. D., President (Wesleyan
University,) Professor of Theology and
<pb id="dsmith118" n="118"/>
Mental Science; George W. Mendall, A.M., (Wesleyan
University,) Professor of Languages and Natural Sciences;
Mary J. Allen, (Wesleyan Academy,) Preceptress, Teacher
of French and Mathematics; Sarah J. Woodson
(Oberlin,) Teacher of English Department; Adelaide
Warren (Oberlin,) Teacher of Instrumental and Vocal
Music.</item>
          </list>
          <p>Professor Wendell was succeeded by Professor Pliny S.
Boyd, A. B., Oberlin. Miss Warren was succeeded by
Miss Biffington, New York; and Miss Allen was
succeeded by Miss Isabella Oakley.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <head>SUCCESSION UNDER THE AUSPICES OF THE
<lb/>A. M. E. CHURCH, FROM 1863-65.</head>
          <p>Right Rev. D. A. Payne. D. D., President (Gettysburg Theological 
Seminary,) Professor of Christian Theology, Mental Science, 
and Church Government.</p>
          <p>John G. Mitchell, A.M., (Oberlin,) Professor
of Greek, Latin and Mathematics.</p>
          <p>Miss Esther T. Maltby, A. B., (Oberlin,) Lady
Principal, Matron and Secretary of Faculty.</p>
          <p>Mrs. Fannie A. Mitchell (Oberlin,) Assistant
Teacher and Head of Intermediate Department.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <head>FROM 1866 TO 1868.</head>
          <p>Right Rev. D. A. Payne, D. D., President 
(Gettysburg Theological Seminary.)</p>
          <p>Professor John G. Mitchell, A.M., (Oberlin.)</p>
          <p>Rev. William Kent M. D., (England,) 
Professor of Natural Science.</p>
          <pb id="dsmith119" n="119"/>
          <p>Theodore E. Suloit, A.M., (Edinburgh, Scotland,)
Professor of Latin and French Literature,
and Adjunct Professor of Mathematics.</p>
          <p>Miss Sarah J. Woodson, Oberlin, Preceptress
of English and Latin, and Lady Principal and
Matron.</p>
          <p>Miss Woodson was succeeded by Miss
Josephine Jackson, B. S., Adrian, Michigan.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <head>FROM 1868-1869.</head>
          <p>This year finds Bishop Payne still acting as
President, but not a Professor, the Theological
Department being managed wholly by Rev.
Henry C. Fry, A.M., Oberlin.</p>
          <p>Professor John Smith, Oberlin, succeeded Prof.
Mitchell, and Mrs. Messenger succeeded Miss
Josephine Jackson.</p>
          <p>Rev. Thomas H. Jackson, B. D., Wilberforce
University, Professor of Ecclesiastical History,
Homiletics and Pastoral Theology.</p>
          <p>William B. Adams, Amherst, A.M., Professor
of Greek and Natural Science.</p>
          <p>Right Rev. R. G. Mortimer, Professor of Latin,
Greek, Exegesis, and Adjunct Professor of 
Mathematics.</p>
          <p>Dr. Wilson, Teacher of Hebrew Language
and Hebrew Exegesis.</p>
          <p>Roswell Howard, A.M. B. L., Professor of Law.</p>
          <p>Honorable John Little, Professor of Law.</p>
          <p>Mrs. Alice M. Adams, Holyoke, Lady
Principal, Matron and Teacher of English; who was
succeeded by Miss Emma L. Parker; who was
<pb id="dsmith120" n="120"/>
succeeded by Miss Leonore Congdon. Miss
Parker was of the Wesleyan Female Seminary,
Oxford, Ohio; Miss Congdon, of Oberlin.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <head>1870 TO 1876.</head>
          <p>Bishop Payne is still the President. Professor Jackson
was succeeded by Rev. B. F. Lee, Wilberforce University.</p>
          <p>Benjamin H. Sampson, A.M., Oberlin, succeeded 
Professor Mortimer as Professor of Latin, Greek
and Mathematics, and Secretary of the Faculty.</p>
          <p>Rev. Benjamin F. Lee is in turn succeeded by
Professor Thomas H. Jackson, and Professor Sampson's
chair is now filled by Professor Joseph P. Shorter, the first
graduate from our Classical Department; at the same time
Miss McBride is succeeded by Miss Ella J<corr sic="missing punctuation">.</corr> Greene, in all
things excepting the languages.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <head>OUR METHODS</head>
          <p>In the Classical and Mathematical Department, are the
same as generally obtained in American colleges.</p>
          <p>In the Normal, we have the methods of Oswego. 
In the practicing schools of the Normal Department 
there is nothing peculiar but our manner
of teaching Orthography and Orthœpy; here we
employ analysis, that is to say, immediately after
a pupil has spelled a word, he is required to tell
how many letters, how many vowels, and how
many consonants it contains, then to give the
quality and quantity of every vowel, and to 
<pb id="dsmith121" n="121"/>
distinguish the characteristic of the sub-vocals and the
aspirates.</p>
          <p>We deem this the best method of teaching the art of
spelling, because it is the most thorough;
and also because, when the principle is continually
applied and the habit is formed, in subsequent
life the individual will be satisfied with nothing
short of a thorough knowledge of <hi rend="italics">any object</hi>
which he may take to scrutinize; or any subject
he may begin to investigate.</p>
          <p>In our Theological Department, we employ both the
inductive and deductive methods, allowing the largest
liberty of investigation and of expression; excepting that
which borders upon impiety and blasphemy.</p>
          <p>Our aim is to make Christian scholars, not mere bookworms, 
but workers, <hi rend="italics">educated workers</hi> with God for
man—to effect which we employ not the <sic corr="Classics">Ciassics</sic> and
Mathematics only, but Science and Philosophy also, the
former for their discriminating, polishing and cultivating
influences, the latter for the quickness and exactness which
they impart to the cognitive faculty, and the seed thoughts
which they never fail to sow in the mind. And yet we hold
that the Classics and Mathematics, as Science and
Philosophy, can and must be consecrated to human 
well-being by the teachings, the sentiments, and the spirit of
Jesus.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <head>OUR SOCIAL SURROUNDINGS.</head>
          <p>We are in the midst of a farming region, immediately
encircled by ten families, who are also educating their
children in our school; two of
<pb id="dsmith122" n="122"/>
them were formerly students, who, since they left
us, have been married, and are now in their turn
educating their children in their own Alma Mater.
The influence of the College upon these children
is manifest; not only in their manners, but also in
their talents, for, of 126 to 153 students who have
annually filled our halls during the last four years,
none surpass them in mental powers; very few
equal them in capacity or ability.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <head>THE GROUNDS.</head>
          <p>The real estate of Wilberforce contains 53 acres
of land, finely timbered, and abundantly watered
with mineral springs. The campus embraces
about ten acres—5 in front and 5 in the rear.  It
is traversed by a ravine, which at certain points
becomes so deep as to eclipse the apex of the
cupola, 92 feet high. Its meanderings are east,
southeast by north, flanking and moulding the
rear of the campus into graceful curves and
slopes, producing the form of a miniature table-land,
sharply defined and beautiful. The front is
level, with a slight indenture running southward.
It is shaded by forest trees and a few evergreens.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <head>OUR PROPERTY</head>
          <p>consists of fifty-two acres of undulating land,
which was heavily timbered when we bought it,
in 1863. It is traversed by a deep ravine, through
which a murmuring streamlet meanders winter
and summer. At the time of its purchase, there
were five mineral springs running out of the sides
of this ravine, which are at present reduced to
<pb id="dsmith123" n="123"/>
three, caused by the diminution of the timber, which has
been cut down for fuel and other purposes. On these fifty-two 
acres we have ten buildings, exclusive of a barn and
stable. Nine of these buildings are cottages, erected within
the campus. They are inhabited chiefly by students and
families who came to educate their children under college
restrictions and influences.</p>
          <p>The main edifice is built in the centre of the campus. The
foundations are of solid lime stone. The superstructure is
of red brick, three stories above the basement, and is 44 by
160 feet. It embraces a centre and two wings—the centre is
40 by 52, the wings are 40 by 60. This building contains
eight recitation and one lecture rooms, one art and one
music room, one library, and a large hall, to be fitted up for
a museum. It has also five dormitories, with forty 
bed-rooms, and sleeping accommodations for eighty persons.
The basement contains fifteen rooms, which embrace the
kitchen, pantry, store-rooms, dining-hall, laundry and
sleeping apartments for all connected with the culinary and
laundry work. When the dormitories and cottages are filled,
students often find comfortable accommodations in this
commodious basement.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <head>OUR LIBRARY AND MUSEUM.</head>
          <p>The library contains about 3000 bound volumes and 300
pamphlets. The most of them are useful. Among these are
few books of reference. We have none that can be
considered as rare. Our
<pb id="dsmith124" n="124"/>
museum is so small that we call it nothing more than the
nucleus of a future one.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <head>GRATEFUL RECOLLECTIONS OF BENEVOLENCE.</head>
          <p>Before concluding this historical sketch, it seems proper
to make a grateful record of those who generously aided us
when we most needed their assistance to make our very
existence an unquestionable fact, for at that time some of
our own short sighted people, for whose special benefit we
have always planned and executed, had formally denied it.</p>
          <p>In March, 1863, our friends of the Cincinnati Conference
of the Methodist Episcopal Church sold us the property
for its indebtedness, which was $10,000, and that, too, at
the time when the agent of the State of Ohio stood anxious
to buy it at a much larger price for an asylum, and from
others they could have obtained from one to two-thirds
more than we were able to give. Their liberality placed a
valuable seat of learning, with at least $1000 worth of
furniture, within our reach, and therefore we ought to be
grateful.</p>
          <p>In 1867-68, the Society for the Promotion of Collegiate
and Theological Education at the West aided us in the sum
of $1800. Let it be remembered that we were burnt out in
the spring of 1865. In 1867 we had erected the western
wing of our edifice; but its walls were not only unpictured
and its floors uncarpeted, they were <hi rend="italics">unplastered</hi> and
<hi rend="italics">rough; all around us presented an uninviting aspect.</hi></p>
          <p>At my earnest invitation, the good Secretary,
<pb id="dsmith125" n="125"/>
Dr. Theron Baldwin came—he saw the “appalling obstacles”
which we had to face and overcome. His soul was stirred to
its depths, and his eloquent plea in our behalf induced the
Society to vote us $1800 for the 1867. In 1868-69 they
again voted us $1800. Although the funds of the society did
not enable them to make good the whole of this last vote,
what we did receive was of signal benefit, and we are
therefore thankful.</p>
          <p>The American Unitarian Association aided us from 1868
to 1875, at an average of $500 per annum. The first twelve
months of that time they gave us $800, in all about $4000.
We have received from them, for purely educational
purposes, in the form of lectures on different branches of
natural science, including experimental physics, also
lectures on literature and philosophy. The lectures on
literature were both Biblical and secular. They were
delivered by the scholarly Professors of Antioch, and have
been very serviceable to our graduates, not only in 
stimulating them to deep research, but also in polishing their
style, for which we ought to be grateful.</p>
          <p>To construct our new edifice, Rev. R. S. Rust,
D. D., and Rev. J. F. Wright, D. D., each gave us
$100. For our endowment fund, John Pfaff, Esq.,
of Cincinnati, and P. P. Mast, Esq., of Springfield, 
Ohio, <sic corr="each">esch</sic> has subscribed $500. The latter
is to pay his subscription some time in the coming
summer.</p>
          <p>In 1868 that noble philanthropist, Hon. Gerritt
Smith, sent us $500; the same year the equally
noble Chief Justice Chase induced an English
<pb id="dsmith126" n="126"/>
gentlemen to send us $300; subsequently the
Chief Justice gave us $250, and in his last will 
bequeathed us $10,000. In this last instance he
magnified his greatness in making us, who are the poorest
of God's poor in the United States, the first object of his
considerate benevolence.</p>
          <p>Now, and here, we record the facts that, in 1869, we
received, through General Howard, from the Freedmen's
Bureau, $3000, and in 1870 we received from the same 
Bureau, by special act of Congress, $25,000, for all of which
we ought to be grateful. Total from the Bureau, $28,000. All
this has been spent in building, except $3125, which was
paid to the agent as per centage. Concerning our benefactors,
whose earthly career has been finished, <hi rend="italics">we hope</hi> they may
“be rewarded at the resurrection of the just.” Concerning
those who are still living, <hi rend="italics">we pray</hi> that they and theirs may
never lack a friend nor aid in the time of need or the day of
adversity.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <head>COLLEGE SOCIETIES.</head>
          <p>The “Society of Inquiry on Missions” was organized by
the President, for the purpose of collecting information
concerning Christian Missions from all sources, foreign and
domestic, and to cultivate the spirit of missions in the
Theological students for whose special benefit the
organization was brought into existence. Since then other
persons have been admitted to membership, but the
extension of this privilege to persons not members of the
Theological Department, has, in
<pb id="dsmith127" n="127"/>
some respects, damaged the original character of the
Society.</p>
          <p>The Soldalean Society was organized by the students,
the present Professor Shorter, then a student, being their
leader. It is a debating club. Its design is mutual
improvement in composition, disputation and oratory.</p>
          <p>Outside of the Institution, but connected with it by
bonds of earnest friendship, is the “College Aid Society,”
consisting chiefly of married ladies, and some of the oldest
female students. Its aim is declared in its name. This
Society carne into existence through the wants of the
College, and has rendered signal services to the University
in times of embarrassment.</p>
          <p>“Wilberforce University Endowment Association,”
outside of the Institution, consists chiefly of ministers and
laymen of the Ohio, Pittsburg and Kentucky Conferences,
who are earnest workers in its behalf, and connected with it
by a friendship as sincere is it is earnest. Its object is the
permanent endowment of Professorships and
Scholarships.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <head>BOARDING FACILITIES.</head>
          <p>Students can board in families for $2.00 and $2.50 per
week.</p>
          <p>A Boarding Club, consisting of the students, including
both sexes, is called “The Mutual Relief Association.”
Board is furnished by this club for $1.50 per week. The
<hi rend="italics">initiation</hi> fee is $3.50, including the first week's board,
so that the first month's board will cost a new member $7.50;
<pb id="dsmith128" n="128"/>
after that, only $6.00 per month. It was first 
managed by a Steward, a Secretary, and a Treasurer,
elected among themselves; but at the
end of every year they were involved in debts.
At the end of three years, it was found that their
management was ruinous; since then it has been
gratuitously managed by one of our Professors,
who has not only kept the Club out of debt, but
has had a surplus for it at the end of the college
year. They hire a cook, but take turn to wait
upon themselves at table, and thereby reduce their
expenses to the <hi rend="italics">minimum.</hi> The young men do
the heavier part of the work, the young women
the lighter.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <head>SOURCES OF INCOME AND PRESENT CONDITION.</head>
          <p>As respects endowment of Professorship, we have none.
As respects scholarships, we have an endowment of $2300,
which yields assistance to two students, giving each the
sum of $70.50 annually. Ten thousand dollars of the Avery
estate have been set apart for our benefit, and the interest,
at six per cent. paid over to us semi-annually. Our Church
Treasury yields us an average of $1000 annually; tuition
fees and rents, amounting to about $5000 annually; bonds
in the Western Union Telegraph Company, and the railroad
between Pittsburgh and Cleveland, bequeathed by the late
Chief Justice Chase, amounting to $10,000; but this is at
present not available. Morally and intellectually, I believe
we compare favorably with similar institutions. We have
<sic corr="original printing error">have</sic> a church within the University, by means of which
the moral
<pb id="dsmith129" n="129"/>
and religious character of the students is beneficially
affected, so that many who come to us careless of their
spiritual well being, leave us as earnest Christians. In this
church we have also a well-managed Sunday-school, taught
by the Professors and advanced students.</p>
          <list type="simple">
            <item>In the Normal Department are, 
Juniors, . . . . . 4</item>
            <item>Seniors, . . . . . 1</item>
            <item>Classical</item>
            <item>Sophomores, . . . . . 1</item>
            <item>Juniors, . . . . . 1</item>
            <item>Seniors, . . . . . 1</item>
            <item>Theological</item>
            <item>Freshmen, . . . . . 6</item>
            <item>Sophomores, . . . . . 2</item>
            <item>Seniors, . . . . . 2</item>
            <item>Theo'l Dep't, different stages of prepar'n, . . . . . 20</item>
            <item>Scientific Department, are Sophomores, . . . . . 2</item>
            <item>Juniors, . . . . . 1</item>
            <item>Training School, of different grades, . . . . . 50</item>
            <item>Different stages of English studies, . . . . . 46</item>
            <item>Total, . . . . .  127</item>
          </list>
        </div2>
        <div2 type="text">
          <head>SUMMARY OF RESULTS FROM 1863 TO 1876.</head>
          <p>Fully, to appreciate the results of our efforts, it is
necessary to remember, first, that the 10th of March, 1876,
will be just thirteen years since we purchased the real estate
of Wilberforce University, at a cost of $10,000; and the end
of July, 1876, will be thirteen years from the day when the
school was opened. Secondly, that we had not a dollar
when we made the <hi rend="italics">bid</hi> for the property. Thirdly, that we
opened the school with but six
<pb id="dsmith130" n="130"/>
pupils in Primary English studies, having but one
teacher, and that we were burnt out about two
years after we made the purchase of the property.
Our dormitories, recitation-rooms, library and
chapel were all consumed, and our school almost
broken up. We had to begin anew. Now we
have so far completed our new building that we
shall be able to dedicate it this summer. The
burnt edifice was made of wood, erected on a
slight brick foundation; it was beautiful, but a
light and airy thing. Our present edifice is
heavy brick, on massive stone foundation. The cost, when
completed and furnished, will be about $45,000. Within
thirteen years from the day we opened our Primary English
school, we shall have graduated thirteen young ladies and
sixteen young men. Total, 29.</p>
          <p>All our graduates have engaged in the honorable and
useful employment of the pulpit and the school room.
Three have been elected to fill Professorships in their own
Alma Mater, and one is Principal of Lincoln Institute, a
High and Normal School of the State of Missouri, for the
secondary education of colored youth. In addition to these,
scores of undergraduates have received a partial training
within the past twelve years, who are now employed or
have been employed as teachers and preachers in the
Western and Southern States, but chiefly in the latter.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>CONCERNING THE ELECTION OF TRUSTEES AND
<lb/>FACULTY.</head>
          <p>Inasmuch as Wilberforce is under denominational
<pb id="dsmith131" n="131"/>
auspices, it was deemed prudent at the time of its
organization to have each Annual Conference represented
by two laymen and three clergymen; and, therefore,
inasmuch as there are twenty-three Annual Conferences,
there are also one hundred and fifteen denominational
Trustees, and to these add nine honorary Trustees, and the
six Bishops, who are <hi rend="italics">ex officio</hi> Trustees, and we have the
enormous Board of one hundred and thirty; but <hi rend="italics">practically,</hi>
we have not more than twenty four, the largest number ever
present at an annual meeting. The lesson taught us at the
end of twelve years, is, that there is no need of having more
than one clergyman and one layman to represent an Annual
Conference, who may have alternates; these, with ten or
twelve honorary members and the <hi rend="italics">ex officios,</hi> from whom a
quorum can be convened within three hours' ride of the
University, would be sufficient for all practical purposes.
Our own experience and observation for twenty years furnish
strong objections, also, to the annual election of the Faculty. 
The power and skill requisite to the successful working of a collegiate
institution are attained only by the long experience and
observations of many years, and is too important and
valuable to be set aside for the gratification of the
ambitious and arrogant, or the envious and malicious, as
has sometimes been done. Common sense dictates the
abolition of such a rule and the adoption of a better.</p>
          <p>We will now finish this historical sketch by remarking:—</p>
          <p>The Charter of Wilberforce prohibits all
<pb id="dsmith132" n="132"/>
distinctions based on race or color. Like Christianity, of
which it is an off-spring, its advantages and facilities are
free to all races. Though very poor, young and weak, all the
leading denominations have been represented among its
teachers and its Faculty as well as its Trustees.
Methodists, Baptists, Presbyterians, Congregationalists,
Unitarians and Quakers—even Roman Catholics—have met
here on common grounds.</p>
          <p>To any thinking mind, may be clearly seen that if
without endowment and with very poor facilities, 
so much good has been accomplished as these 
pages make evident, a thousand fold more could be 
effected if amply endowed and ably officered. To 
this end, its real, intelligent and considerate friends 
should wisely plan and diligently execute.</p>
          <signed>DANIEL A. PAYNE,
<lb/><hi rend="italics">Prest. Wilberforce University.</hi></signed>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div1 type="remarks">
        <pb id="dsmith133" n="133"/>
        <head>MISCELLANEOUS REMARKS.<lb/>
ACCOUNT OF MY COMPANIONS AND HOUSEHOLD.</head>
        <p>In the early part of my life (I do not know the date or
how old I was when I married my first wife) I felt that I
needed a companion to assist me in the arduous duties of
life. I therefore courted the affections of Miss Nancy Prout,
the daughter of William Prout, of Baltimore, Md., and the
happy union of husband and wife was soon consummated.
We raised a very large family; unfortunately for us,
however, death visited us quite often. Very soon we were
deprived of nearly all of the children with which we had
been blessed. Out of the twelve children only four lived to
man and womanhood. My eldest daughter, Miss Elizabeth
Smith, married a man of Philadelphia, by the name of James
Gayles. She became very useful in the Church and a great
organizer of benevolent societies. Finally my wife died a
successful Christian death, and I was again left alone to bear
the burdens of life. I was traveling the Harrisburg circuit
when my companion died.</p>
        <p>I remained single two years. I next married a lady of
Pittsburg, Pa., by the name of Miss Hannah Johnson, the
only daughter of Mr. Adam Johnson. We raised
considerable family, but
<pb id="dsmith134" n="134"/>
disease and death deprived me of all my children and wife,
with the exception of one daughter, whose name is Eliza.
She married William Cary, of Virginia. Mr. and Mrs. Cary
have resided in Xenia, Ohio, for years. Mrs. Eliza Cary is
well known in Xenia, and also in the city of Cincinnati, as a
useful Christian woman.</p>
        <p>I married my third wife in Louisville, Ky. She
was the widow of Mr. Sonny Lewis. We then
moved to Ohio, bought a home and settled three miles 
north of Xenia, near Wilberforce University, and here I remained
until the death of my wife (Polly Smith). She suffered for
seven long years, almost an invalid, and finally died a
Christian death. Again I was left alone, a man carrying
nearly a century of years. I then moved to Xenia, and at
the writing of this book I am living with my daughter, Eliza
Cary, and with this only daughter I expect to spend my
last days on earth.</p>
        <p>Some of the reasons which lead me to join the
A. M. E. Church:</p>
        <p>First. I was convinced by Daniel Coker, and
others, that when the A. M. E. Church was 
established she could do more good among my people
than the M. E. Church, and why? Simply on
<pb id="dsmith135" n="135"/>
account of the peculiar adaptation of any race of people to
reach and effect its own people to a greater degree than a
stranger can possibly do.</p>
        <p>Second. The longer I was connected with her the more
plainly I saw the sweeping field she afforded for the
development of Christian manhood.</p>
        <p>Third, There is no bar on account of color; but Virtue,
Qualification and Usefulness were the three steps to the
highest position in the Church. Hence I have devoted
nearly sixty years to the service of my Church.</p>
        <p>I am hers for success and development.</p>
        <signed>DAVID SMITH.</signed>
      </div1>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI.2>